<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Helen Rogers, &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos;: <lb/>Transported Convicts, Former Lives and Previous Offences <lb/>(2015) 1(1): e3 Open Library of Humanities, DOI: http:// <lb/>dx.doi.org/10.16995/olh.27 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>&apos;A Very Fair Statement of His <lb/>Past Life&apos;: Transported Convicts, <lb/>Former Lives and Previous Offences <lb/>Helen Rogers 1 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>1 Liverpool John Moores University, UK <lb/>h.rogers@ljmu.ac.uk <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>As mass digitization brings new opportunities for analysing criminal and <lb/>convict records, this article considers how we can recover the personal his-<lb/>tories of the convicted. It proposes &apos;intimate reading&apos; as a complementary <lb/>approach to large-scale data mining and distant reading methods currently <lb/>used to examine large prison cohorts. Immersive reading, integrating quanti-<lb/>tative and qualitative analysis of multiple sources, permits investigation of <lb/>specific individuals, their interaction with others, and their engagement -<lb/>however unequal -with the record-makers. It helps us detect the agency <lb/>of those who left few traces of personal testimony but whose lives were <lb/>captured in abstract information garnered by officialdom. <lb/>The article focuses on male convicts who served time at Great Yarmouth <lb/>in the 1830s and 1840s and were transported to Van Diemen&apos;s Land where <lb/>arrivals were interrogated on their offending histories, occupations and <lb/>family ties, while their bodies were inspected for distinguishing charac-<lb/>teristics. Comparing convict records with other documentation on their <lb/>former lives allows us to explore what exiles revealed and concealed from <lb/>the authorities about their past. Record linkage on this cohort brings to <lb/>light the under-reporting of prior convictions in convict records by around <lb/>two-thirds and suggests that historians continue to underestimate the <lb/>extent of previous offending among the transported population. Social pro-<lb/>filing of this group exposes patterns in employment, family and social net-<lb/>works that are not so readily apparent when reading fragmentary evidence <lb/>of individual lives. Small-scale data analysis enables us to decode the more <lb/>personal testimony unwittingly preserved by the penal authorities when <lb/>they described convicts&apos; tattoos. The article concludes with an intimate <lb/>reading of the elaborate tattoos of one Yarmouth convict that spectacu-<lb/>larly depicted the man he felt himself to be. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>On arrival in Van Diemen&apos;s Land, before disembarking from the transport ship, con-<lb/>victs were grilled about their sentence, prior convictions and former lives. Stripped <lb/>to the waist, their bodies were scrutinized for distinguishing characteristics such as <lb/>scars and tattoos. The results of this verbal and physical examination were entered in <lb/>the &apos;Black Books&apos;, used to monitor convicts&apos; conduct in the penal colony and identify <lb/>them should they escape. Digitization of these records is being used by the multi-<lb/>disciplinary Founders and Survivors and Digital Panopticon projects to carry out large-<lb/>scale analysis of the effects of transportation and penal discipline on the life courses <lb/>of Tasmania&apos;s convict population and descendants up to 1920. 1 By contrast, in this <lb/>article I trace the past rather than future lives of convicts, focusing on a small sample <lb/>of the 73,000 men, women and children banished to Van Diemen&apos;s Land between <lb/>1803 and 1853, when transportation to the colony was abolished. Using record link-<lb/>age, I compare what male convicts told the authorities about their history with docu-<lb/>mentary evidence of their former lives. Tracing individual histories through multiple <lb/>sources, I investigate what convicts revealed to the penal authorities and what they <lb/>concealed in order to explore how the subjects of penal discipline responded to offi-<lb/>cial bureaucracy and interrogation of their lives. In so doing, I illustrate a method for <lb/>reading fragmentary sources, found in traditional and digital archives, that combines <lb/>qualitative and quantitative analysis. I demonstrate the convict authorities relied on <lb/>prisoners&apos; testimony for a fuller, though often incomplete, picture of their offend-<lb/>ing histories. While this raises important questions for how historians evaluate offi-<lb/>cial data on convicts, I show that convict records, when read in tangent with other <lb/>sources, illuminate unexpected detail on individual lives and general characteristics <lb/>of the convict population. <lb/>The rise of cultural history in recent decades saw a marked shift across historical <lb/>disciplines from quantitative to qualitative methods of reading. Though some schol-<lb/>ars continued to employ data analysis, particularly those working on demography, <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Founders and Survivors: Australian Life Courses in Historical Context, 1803-1920, http:// <lb/>foundersandsurvivors.org/; The Digital Panopticon: The Global Impact of London Punishments, 1780-<lb/>1925, http://www.digitalpanopticon.org/ <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>public institutions like asylums and workhouses, and the criminal justice system, <lb/>many social historians abandoned quantitative methodologies to explore the discur-<lb/>sive construction of the &apos;social&apos;. 2 While historians have studied the emergence of the <lb/>&apos;statistical idea&apos;, for instance, as expressing new forms of scientific knowledge and <lb/>social administration, many lost faith in the results of statistical enquiry to expose <lb/>anything other than the epistemological premises and ideological concerns of the <lb/>record makers. 3 Articles using data analysis to identify cultural habits and patterns <lb/>are rarely found in journals devoted to cultural history or even social history. <lb/>Digitization of archival sources, however, combined with the interactive func-<lb/>tionality of Web 2.0, is encouraging growing numbers of scholars across the humani-<lb/>ties to re-engage with quantitative analysis. Much of this work consists of &apos;text <lb/>mining&apos; large bodies of digitized text, such as the Old Bailey Proceedings and the <lb/>Tasmanian convict records, and the creation and manipulation of &apos;Big Data&apos; using <lb/>computational methodologies and corpus linguistics. 4 Many studies deploy a version <lb/>of the &apos; distant reading&apos; method advocated by Franco Moretti in his attempt to map <lb/>2 For notable examples, compare Joan Wallach Scott&apos;s use of quantitative social history methods (with <lb/>Louise Tilly) in Women, Work and Family (New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1978) with her use <lb/>of discourse theory in Gender and the Politics of History (New York: Columbia University Press, 1988); <lb/>and similarly Patrick Joyce&apos;s, Work, Society and Politics: The Culture of the Factory in Later Victorian <lb/>England (Brighton: Harvester Press, 1980), compared with his many studies tracking the discursive <lb/>formation of &apos;the social&apos;, beginning with Democratic Subjects: the Self and the Social in Nineteenth-<lb/>century England (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1994). <lb/>3 For examples see: Mary Poovey, Making a Social Body: British Cultural Formation 1830-64 (Chicago: <lb/>University of Chicago Press, 1995) and A History of the Modern Fact: Problems of Knowledge in the Sci-<lb/>ences of Wealth and Society (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1998); Tom Crook and Glen O&apos;Hara <lb/>(eds.), Statistics and the Public Sphere: Numbers and the People in Modern Britain, c. 1800-2000 (New <lb/>York: Routledge, 2011). <lb/>4 Tim Hitchcock, Robert Shoemaker, Clive Emsley, Sharon Howard and Jamie McLaughlin, et al., The <lb/>Old Bailey Proceedings Online, 1674-1913 (www.oldbaileyonline.org, version 7.0, 14 July 2015); <lb/>LINC Tasmania, Colonial Tasmanian Family Links Database (http://portal.archives.tas.gov.au/menu. <lb/>aspx?search=8, 14 July 2015). For an overview of the opportunities afforded by digital resources and <lb/>data analysis, see the Digital Forum on &apos;Processing the Past&apos;, Journal of Victorian Culture, 15.2 (2010): <lb/>280-96, ed. by James Mussell: Richard Deswarte, &apos;Growing the &quot;Faith in Numbers&quot;: Quantitative Digital <lb/>Resources and Historical Research in the Twenty-First Century&apos;, 281-286; Alexis Weedon, &apos;Digital <lb/>Resources and Quantitative Research&apos;, 287-291; Michaela Mahlberg, &apos;Corpus Linguistics and the <lb/>Study of Nineteenth-Century Fiction&apos;, 292-298. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>changes in the novel across period, genre and national boundaries. 5 Distant reading <lb/>forsakes &apos; close reading&apos; of individual texts, at least in the preliminary stages of investi-<lb/>gation, in order to track textual changes that allow analysis of continuity and change <lb/>in social and cultural discourses and the material practices underpinning them. <lb/>This return to quantitative analysis has generated some concern, even among <lb/>its advocates in the digital humanities. Tim Hitchcock, of the pioneering Old Bailey <lb/>Online, observes that data mining requires high levels of technical expertise that <lb/>threatens to disengage scholarship from the democratic practice that inspired &apos;his-<lb/>tory from below&apos;. While large-scale analysis of the Old Bailey Proceedings might <lb/>recover the agency of the accused by showing how they helped drive the rise of plea-<lb/>bargaining, for example, distant reading can divert attention from individual experi-<lb/>ence back to the court records that objectified defendants. The distancing effect of <lb/>data mining, intimates Hitchcock, might be alleviated by record linkage. To this end, <lb/>the connected databases London Lives and Connected Histories, offshoots from the <lb/>Old Bailey Online, allow users to piece together evidence of individual lives from dif-<lb/>ferent records. 6 <lb/>Record linkage of this kind requires a different approach to reading data that can <lb/>complement distant reading. I call it &apos;intimate reading&apos;: the scrutiny of records from <lb/>multiple sources that permits an exploration of individuals and groups, their interac-<lb/>tion with others and their engagement -however unequal -with the record-makers <lb/>and keepers. Such reading is necessarily smaller in scope than distant reading, involv-<lb/>ing examination of &apos; deep&apos; rather than &apos;big&apos; data, but its limited focus enables a more <lb/>intensive form of investigation and extensive contextualization. It demands the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>5 Franco Moretti, Graphs, Maps and Trees: Abstract Models for a Literary Theory (London: Verso, 2005). <lb/>See also Bob Nicholson, &apos;Counting Culture; or, How to Read Victorian Newspapers from a Distance&apos;, <lb/>Journal of Victorian Culture 17.2 (2012): 238-46. <lb/>6 Tim Hitchcock and William J. Turkel, &apos;The Old Bailey Proceedings, 1674-1913: Text Mining for Evidence <lb/></listBibl>

			of Court Behaviour&apos;, paper given at IHR Digital History seminar, 16 May 2011; recording and slides <lb/>available <lb/>https://historyspot.org.uk/podcasts/digital-history/text-mining-old-bailey-proceedings; <lb/>Tim Hitchcock, &apos;Academic History Writing and the Headache of Big Data&apos;, http://historyonics.blogs-<lb/>pot.co.uk/2012_01_01_archive.html, 30 January 2012; Connected Histories: British History Sources, <lb/>1500-1900, http://www.connectedhistories.org/; London Lives 1690 to 1800: Crime, Poverty and <lb/>Social Policy in the Metropolis, http://www.londonlives.org/. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>immersive reading practised by micro-historians in recovering the world and mental-<lb/>ity of individuals and communities. 7 Intimate reading requires historians to get our <lb/>hands dirty in the virtual and paper archives and get up close and personal with our <lb/>subjects. By this means, intimate reading can cast light on what Ben Heller calls the <lb/>&apos; dark matter of plebeian and middling knowledge and life&apos;. 8 <lb/>Here, I show how my practice of intimate reading developed out of investigating <lb/>inmates&apos; experiences of imprisonment and their lives before and after committal to <lb/>Great Yarmouth Gaol and House of Correction in the 1830s and 1840s. 9 I begin with <lb/>close reading, the approach I initially used to study interactions between prison-<lb/>ers and their teacher, Sarah Martin, who worked as a voluntary prison visitor from <lb/>1818 till her death in 1843. Focusing on her brief journal entries on her encounters <lb/>with one prisoner, John King, I examine what the teacher thought she knew about <lb/>inmates and what she recognized she could not know with certainty. While Martin&apos;s <lb/>journals illuminate her understanding of her students&apos; lives and characters, they <lb/>offer only snapshots of inmates themselves, refracted through the visitor&apos;s pious <lb/>gaze. From examination of one individual prisoner, therefore, I move outwards to <lb/>reconstruct the experiences of offenders like him. Comparisons are drawn between <lb/>statements made by thirty-four male convicts, formerly imprisoned at Yarmouth, in <lb/>answer to cross-examination by the penal authorities in Van Diemen&apos;s Land com-<lb/>bined with evidence of their lives derived from gaol, census and parish registers. <lb/>Social profiling, based on data analysis of this cohort, is then used to help interpret <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>7 Clifford Geertz, &apos;Thick Description: Toward an Interpretive Theory of Culture&apos;, in The Interpretation <lb/>of Cultures: Selected Essays (New York: Basic Books, 1973), pp. 3-30. My approach to &apos;intimate read-<lb/></listBibl>

			ing&apos; resists the opposition between big data and micro history methodologies drawn by Jo Guldi and <lb/>David Armitage in The History Manifesto (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014). <lb/>8 Ben Heller, review of London Lives 1690-1800 -Crime, Poverty and Social Policy in the Metropolis, <lb/>Reviews in History (no. 1001) URL: http://www.history.ac.uk/reviews/review/1001. Date accessed: 27 <lb/>June 2013. <lb/>9 See: Helen Rogers, &apos;The Way to Jerusalem: Reading, Writing and Reform in an Early Victorian <lb/>Gaol&apos;, Past and Present, no. 205 (2009): 71-104; &apos;&quot;Oh, what beautiful books!&quot; Captivated Reading in <lb/>an Early Victorian Prison&apos;, Victorian Studies 55.1 (Autumn 2012): 57-84; &apos;Singing in Gaol: Christian <lb/>Instruction and Inmate Culture in the Nineteenth Century&apos;, Prison Service Journal 199 (2012): 35-43; <lb/>&apos;Kindness and Reciprocity: Liberated Prisoners and Christian Charity in Early Nineteenth-Century Eng-<lb/>land&apos;, Journal of Social History 47.3 (Spring 2014): 721-45. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>John King&apos;s testimony to his penal interrogators and to conduct an intimate reading <lb/>of his life and passions via the description of his elaborate tattoos. Intimate reading, <lb/>integrating qualitative and quantitative analysis, provides insights into individual <lb/>experiences of criminalization while raising new questions that might be explored <lb/>by larger-scale studies of prison and convict populations. <lb/>I. Close Reading: &apos;I am not here for any thing <lb/>that is a disgrace&apos; <lb/>On 11 November 1839, John King (aged seventeen) and William Tunmore (eighteen), <lb/>were picked up in a hayloft and, deemed by the magistrate to be rogues and vaga-<lb/>bonds intent on stealing, were sentenced summarily to three months hard labour in <lb/>the House of Correction at Great Yarmouth. 10 Three weeks later, Sarah Martin recalled <lb/>&apos;Part of a conversation with John King&apos;, beginning with his protestation at conviction: <lb/>&quot;I am not here for any thing that is a disgrace.[&quot;] What? not a disgrace to be <lb/>committed to a prison? -but I was only in a hay loft -And what for -That <lb/>hay loft has of late been a thief&apos;s house. Who but thieves go there? -I was <lb/>only lying there. What right had you to enter another man&apos;s hay loft? Would <lb/>an honest man have done it. -I did nothing. -What good would it do you <lb/>if you could possibly deceive me? -even then would not God know what <lb/>you are? and would you not know yourself to be what you are? He looked <lb/>disconcerted and agreed to this -He was in the prison before. 11 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>10 Great Yarmouth Gaol Registers, December 1838-December 1850, Norfolk Record Office, Y/L2 9, <lb/>11 November 1839. NRO holds the gaol&apos;s surviving papers. The Gaol Register (hereafter GR) included <lb/>those admitted to the House of Correction, under the same roof as the Gaol. <lb/>11 Sarah Martin, Everyday Book, 3 December 1839. All quotations follow Martin&apos;s punctuation and <lb/></listBibl>

			spelling. Great Yarmouth Museum holds Martin&apos;s surviving Everyday Books, headed: &apos;Prison School <lb/>Journal&apos; (1836-1838); &apos;Sarah Martin&apos;s Memo book, remarks made after departure of prisoners&apos;, <lb/>(7 November 1839-6 April 1840; this Everyday Book includes Martin&apos;s prisoner registers, November <lb/>1839-June 1842); &apos;Copy Books written by prisoners under tuition of Sarah Martin&apos;, (12 April 1840-<lb/>12 August 1840 and 10 April 1841-11 June 1841). Extracts are included in Martin&apos;s posthumous <lb/>memoir, first published 1844. A fuller memoir, probably published in 1847, is available via Google <lb/>Books; Sarah Martin, The Prison Visitor of Great Yarmouth, With Extracts from her Writings and Prison <lb/>Journals (London: Religious Tract Society, n.d.) <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Martin&apos;s surviving Everyday Books detailing lessons with inmates offer a rare oppor-<lb/>tunity to examine reactions to conviction, imprisonment and correction after 1835, <lb/>when prisons were brought under the auspices of the Prison Inspectorate, charged <lb/>with systematizing penal discipline in England and Wales. 12 Following lessons, Mar-<lb/>tin hastily jotted down interactions and exchanges between prisoners and herself <lb/>that she believed illustrated improvement or deterioration in conduct and charac-<lb/>ter. Sometimes, as in her entry on John King, the teacher transcribed their words, <lb/>albeit in abbreviated form. Thus, at the very moment that the Prison Inspectorate <lb/>was implementing policies designed to prevent communication between prisoners <lb/>and subject them to a regime of silence, Martin&apos;s journals captured snatches of their <lb/>voices. How might we interpret this evidence and what, if anything, might it tell us <lb/>about the experience and mentality of the convicted? <lb/>The copious writings of prison reformers and the wealth of data amassed by the <lb/>authorities on the convicted have been read as constituting the discursive power of <lb/>disciplinary regimes. Much attention has been paid to how the idea of the &apos; offender&apos; <lb/>was constructed by penal discourses and how, from the 1840s, biographical data <lb/>on prisoners was used to profile and police individual offenders and criminal types. <lb/>Nevertheless, most scholars have been sceptical about whether these discourses tell <lb/>us much about the individual subjectivities of the convicted, concluding that official <lb/>records document what the powerful saw or understood, reflecting and reinforcing <lb/>their preoccupations and prejudices. Viewed this way, it is not John King who speaks <lb/>to us through Martin&apos;s journal but the teacher or, as post-structuralists would have <lb/>it, the discourse of moral correction. 13 <lb/>12 U. R. Q. Henriques, &apos;The Rise and Decline of the Separate System of Prison Discipline&apos;, Past and Pre-<lb/>sent (1972), 54:1, pp. 61-93; Seán McConville, A History of English Prison Administration. Volume 1. <lb/>1750-1877 (London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1981); Randall McGowen, &apos;The Well-Ordered Prison: <lb/>England, 1780-1865&apos;, The Oxford History of the Prison: the Practice of Punishment in Western Society, <lb/>ed. by Norval Morris and David J. Rothman (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1995), pp. 71-99; <lb/>Miles Ogborn, &apos;Discipline, Government and Law: Separate Confinement in the Prisons of England <lb/>and Wales, 1830-1877&apos;, Transactions of the Institute of British Geographers, New Series, 1:3 (1995), <lb/>pp. 295-311. <lb/>13 See, for instance, Marie-Christine Leps, Apprehending the Criminal: The Production of Deviance in <lb/>Nineteenth-Century Discourse (Durham: Duke University Press, 1992); Randall McGowen, &apos;Power and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the following discussion I highlight two problems with this approach. First, <lb/>it overplays the rigour of the information procedures deployed by governing bodies, <lb/>institutions and agents like Martin, and their confidence in the data they collected <lb/>and what it could tell them. Second, in focusing attention on inmates as objects of <lb/>regulatory knowledge, we reaffirm the power of the institution and can miss the <lb/>possibility of investigating the lived experience of those who came in contact with <lb/>it. We cannot begin to comprehend the operation and effects of penal discourses on <lb/>prisoners if we do not also try to go beyond them, to explore the lives and worlds of <lb/>the convicted, and to detect what the record keepers did not, or could not, see. <lb/>Martin&apos;s note on her encounter with King, for example, might seem to confirm <lb/>her authority as teacher and spiritual guide and the legitimacy of the legal system <lb/>that prosecuted him. It does not reveal the circumstances that prompted his defi-<lb/>ant protestation -&apos;I am not here for any thing that is a disgrace&apos; -but recounts <lb/>the teacher&apos;s apparent success in bringing about his submission; &apos;He looked dis-<lb/>concerted and agreed to this&apos;. While Martin&apos;s entries in the coming weeks recorded <lb/>her answers to complaints by his cellmates over the justice of their confinement <lb/>and their opposition to biblical instruction, King appears to have knuckled down to <lb/>learning and within a fortnight could read words of three letters. 14 Nevertheless, she <lb/>doubted his improvement in character; after all, as she remarked tersely, &apos;He was in <lb/>the prison before.&apos; <lb/>Far from Martin&apos;s journals demonstrating the discursive power of the prison <lb/>or the moral regime she managed within it, her need to document the reactions <lb/>of scholars betrays awareness of her limited influence over them. Unlike God, who, <lb/>she believed, could see into their souls, the teacher might be deceived. She must <lb/>judge them by their actions as well as words. Their conduct, too, was difficult to <lb/>interpret. On discharge, King and his cellmates asked for copies of the scriptural <lb/>verses they had learned so they might show them to their friends outside the gaol. <lb/>Humanity, or Foucault among the Historians&apos;, Reassessing Foucault: Power, Medicine and the Body, ed. <lb/>by Colin Jones and Roy Porter (London: Routledge, 1994), pp. 91-112. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 Everyday Book 11-13, 16 December, 1839. <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>The teacher gave each a book, covered in brown paper, containing two or three <lb/>hand-written verses, but how confident could she be that their request indicated the <lb/>beginnings of conversion rather than attempts to curry her favour? 15 <lb/>Thus, record-keeping was important to Martin: when inmates left, the teacher <lb/>tabulated in her register what she had discovered of them and &apos; observed&apos; their char-<lb/>acter so she could judge if they deserved further assistance and remember them if <lb/>they returned to gaol. Hence, she recorded John King&apos;s age and sentence, his religion <lb/>(Church of England), that he could neither read nor write, having &apos;no capacity&apos;, but <lb/>that he had now learned &apos;by memory&apos;; &apos;See Everyday Book&apos;, she added, in case she <lb/>needed future reference. Martin was typically cautious in her assessment of the lad: <lb/>&apos;Former character and habits low -temper good -Always wears a silly smile. very <lb/>ignorant -willing and desirous of being instructed and diligent but fails from want <lb/>of capacity. capable of great deceit.&apos; 16 Martin&apos;s ambivalence and uncertainty towards <lb/>the prisoner reflected what she had learned about him but also what she thought she <lb/>knew of the hundreds of inmates who had passed through her gaol classes. <lb/>John King&apos;s words, transcribed and mediated by Martin, do not give us direct <lb/>access to what the prisoner felt and thought: under interrogation was he defen-<lb/>sive, compliant, cheeky, defiant? Inmate voices were caught only momentarily in <lb/>the teacher&apos;s journals and reach us distorted through her words. More often, she <lb/>reported what she told prisoners and so, for us, they are seen -like John King&apos;s &apos;silly <lb/>smile&apos; -but not heard. While close reading, the dominant method used in recent <lb/>socio-cultural history, may illuminate Sarah Martin&apos;s motivation and perspective, it <lb/>is of limited use in examining the self-perception of her scholars. But perhaps their <lb/>actions can speak in place of their words, as Martin herself intimated? Or, if their <lb/>actions do not speak for them, might they speak of their world? Her prison scholars <lb/>were all captured elsewhere -in the gaol registers, census returns, and parish records. <lb/>Occasionally, even their &apos;voices&apos; can be heard. What happens if we orchestrate these <lb/>voices? Can they get us any closer to comprehending John King&apos;s encounter with the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>15 Everyday Book, 20 December 1839. <lb/>16 Everyday Book, 16 and 20 December 1839; Martin&apos;s Register, 1839, no. 19. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>law and the prison visitor, even to what made him smile? To begin, let us turn to one <lb/>occasion when convicts were compelled to speak. <lb/>II. Forced Migration, Forced Narration? <lb/>By the 1830s and 1840s, gaol and hulk records on individual offenders accompanied all <lb/>convicts to the penal colonies but only in Van Diemen&apos;s Land were arrivals interrogated <lb/>systematically about their criminal history and former life. As late as 1827, Governor <lb/>Arthur complained the colony received no documentation about convicts&apos; offences, <lb/>conduct in custody or prior associations. 17 Consequently, he instigated requirements <lb/>that Surgeon-Superintendents, charged with the instruction as well as the physical wel-<lb/>fare of exiles aboard ship, provide on arrival in Hobart a &apos;hulk list&apos; containing: <lb/>the name, the number, the age, the birth-place, the crime, the period of con-<lb/>viction, when and where the sentence, whether married or single, whether <lb/>he can read or write, or whether he can only read, or whether he can do <lb/>neither, where taught, his trade, the character he brought from the gaoler, <lb/>the character from the hulk, the alleged qualifications, what he is able to do <lb/>and then his behaviour on board the transport. 18 <lb/>This information formed the basis of each convict&apos;s indent. It was presented to <lb/>the Muster Master, responsible for their assignment, who boarded the ship with <lb/>17 P. R. Eldershaw, Public Records of Tasmania. Section Three. Convict Department (1965; Hobart: Archives <lb/>Office of Tasmania, 2003), p. 6. <lb/>18 Governor Arthur, 27 June 1837, Report for the Select Committee on Transportation (1837), p. 279ff, cited <lb/>by Eldershaw, ibid, p. 6. All the information gathering proposed by Arthur was incorporated into the <lb/>cross-examination procedure, except for the question &apos;where taught&apos;. The chaplain Thomas Hay Forster <lb/>spent a week cross-examining 500 convicts aboard the Anson when it sailed from Plymouth in 1844, <lb/>carrying Henry Coppin from Yarmouth; see An Account of a Voyage in a Convict Ship, with Notes of the <lb/>First Itinerating Missionary in Tasmania (London: The Society for the Propagation of the Gospel, March, <lb/>1847), http://anglicanhistory.org/aus/spg23.html. For the role of surgeon-chaplains on convict ships, <lb/>see: Charles Bateson, The Convict Ships, 1787-1868 (1959; Glasgow: Brown, Son &amp; Ferguson, 1985); <lb/>Rosalind Crone, &apos;Attempts to (Re)shape Common Reading Habits: Bible Reading on the Nineteenth-<lb/>century Convict Ship,&apos; A Return to the Common Reader: Print Culture and the Novel, 1850-1900, ed. by <lb/>Beth Palmer and Adelene Buckland (Farnham: 2011), pp. 103-20; Katherine Foxall, Health, Medicine <lb/>and the Sea: Australian Voyages, c. 1815-1860 (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2012). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>the Principal Superintendent of Convicts to make a &apos;minute examination&apos; of each <lb/>prisoner, with piles of paperwork to hand. For Arthur, interrogation would fill the <lb/>gaps in official documentation and impress on convicts the all-seeing power of <lb/>&apos;the System&apos;. Faced by an apparently knowledgeable investigator, such display of <lb/>evidence and forensic inspection, the convict, concluded Arthur, would be awed <lb/>into truthfulness: <lb/>The man perceives at once that the officer who is examining him does know <lb/>something of his history; and not being quite conscious how much of it is <lb/>known, he reveals, I should think, generally a very fair statement of his past <lb/>life, apprehensive of being detected in stating what is untrue.&apos; 19 <lb/>Reputedly, convicts were indeed overwhelmed by the panopticon gaze of the Princi-<lb/>ple Superintendent who, they said, could recall every prisoner by name and ship and <lb/>&apos;never forgets anything&apos;. 20 <lb/>Cognisant of its omissions and reliance on prisoner confession, Arthur&apos;s record-<lb/>keeping system seems to bear out Michel Foucault&apos;s premise that modern forms of <lb/>surveillance function as &apos; a network of relations from top to bottom, but also to a <lb/>certain extent from bottom to top and laterally&apos;. 21 Yet, the role of offenders in the <lb/>production of criminal records has rarely been probed. By the time they arrived in <lb/>Van Diemen&apos;s Land, most convicts will have become accustomed to cross-exam-<lb/>ination as they made their way from bench to prison to hulk to ship. Ten of the <lb/>Yarmouth convicts, including John King, had been incarcerated on at least one occa-<lb/>sion precisely for failing &apos;to give a proper account&apos; of themselves when picked up as a <lb/>&apos;rogue and vagabond&apos;, acting suspiciously. Others will have been quizzed about their <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>19 Cited by Eldershaw, Public Records of Tasmania, p. 7. <lb/>20 Linus Miller, Notes of an Exile to Van Diemen&apos;s Land (1846; New York: Johnson Imprints, 1962), pp. <lb/>285-6, cited by Cassandra Pybus, &apos;The d-Yankee quill-driver&apos;, in Chain Letters, p. 21. For Miller&apos;s <lb/>description of his interrogation aboard the hulk and convict ship in his highly politicized account of <lb/>his transportation for taking part in the &apos;Patriot War&apos; in Upper Canada, 1838-9, see ibid pp. 17-21. <lb/>21 Michel Foucault, Discipline and Punish: The Birth of the Prison (1975, trans. Alan Sheridan) (Harmonds-<lb/>worth: Penguin, 1991), p. 176. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>circumstances and rights of settlement when they applied to the Poor Law guardians <lb/>for parish relief. 22 Some were at home in 1841 when the census enumerator required <lb/>residents to provide their age, occupation and native place. 23 Used to reeling off <lb/>an account of themselves, what did convicts admit to the authorities and, equally <lb/>important, what did they omit? Was Arthur right to assume they would be inclined <lb/>to truthfulness? Did any seize the opportunity to enhance their prospects in a new <lb/>land by reconstructing their past? <lb/>There has been considerable debate over the value and interpretation of data based <lb/>on information supplied by prisoners. According to V. A. C. Gatrell and T. B. Hadden, evi-<lb/>dence of their offences, ages, literacy levels and occupations garnered by the Prison and <lb/>Police Returns &apos;is probably the least reliable material in the official statistical records&apos;. 24 <lb/>In view of contemporary complaints that offenders lied about their age, employment, <lb/>schooling and religion to mitigate their sentence or treatment in gaol, J. J. Tobias <lb/>speculated that prisoners were &apos;incurable romancers&apos;. 25 More credence has been given <lb/>to the value of convict indents but they have been the source of radically different <lb/>interpretations of Australia&apos;s penal population. The first studies employing large-scale <lb/>examination of indents to determine convicts&apos; prior offending rates concluded in the <lb/>mid-twentieth century that, contrary to popular mythology, exiles were rarely starv-<lb/>ing poachers or &apos;Village Hambdens&apos;. Most convicts were not first-time offenders, they <lb/>argued, and many came from what contemporaries termed the &apos; criminal class&apos;. 26 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>22 Carolyn Steedman writes suggestively about settlement examinations as exercises in &apos; enforced nar-<lb/>ration&apos; by the labouring poor, and their productive role in developing ideas of (auto)biography and <lb/>&apos; character&apos;. Significantly, settlement cases were adjudicated by magistrates; see Steedman, &apos;The Magis-<lb/>trates&apos;, Dust (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2001), pp. 38-65. <lb/>23 Edward Higgs, Making Sense of the Census Revisited: Census Records for England and Wales 1801-1901. <lb/>A Handbook for Historical Researchers (London: Institute of Historical Research, 2005); Paul Dobraszc-<lb/>zyk, &apos;&quot;Give in your account&quot;: Using and Abusing Victorian Census Forms&apos;, Journal of Victorian Culture <lb/>14.1 (2009), 1-25. <lb/>24 V. A. C. Gatrell and T. B. Hadden, &apos;Criminal Statistics and their Interpretation&apos;, in Nineteenth-Century <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Society: Essays in the Use of Quantitative Methods for the Study of Social Data (Cambridge: Cambridge <lb/>University Press, 1972), pp. 336-396 (p. 379). <lb/>25 J. J. Tobias, Crime and Industrial Society in the Nineteenth Century (Oxford: B.T. Batsford, 1967), <lb/>pp. 14-21 (p. 19). <lb/>26 L. L. Robson, The Convict Settlers of Australia: An Enquiry into the Origin and Character of the Convicts <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Challenging this iconoclastic revisionism, data analysis by economic historians in <lb/>the 1980s barely looked at prior convictions and instead honed in on information relat-<lb/>ing to convicts&apos; occupations, skills and labour power. 27 The exiles, they contended, were <lb/>best seen as &apos;forced migrants&apos; and &apos; convict workers&apos; whose profile correlated closely <lb/>with that of the British labouring classes from whose ranks they were mainly drawn <lb/>rather than from an imagined criminal residuum. In the most recent study to estimate <lb/>prior offending rates, Alison Alexander, project manager for &apos;Founders and Survivors&apos;, <lb/>endorses the argument made by the Convict Workers team that the majority of Van <lb/>Diemen&apos;s Land convicts had been &apos; ordinary working-class people&apos; in that about 75% <lb/>had been in employment but supplemented meagre earnings by resorting to petty <lb/>theft. Around a quarter, nevertheless, had been habitual offenders, she estimates, with <lb/>about 15% having regularly engaged in theft alongside casual labour while perhaps <lb/>10% had been professional thieves. Alexander&apos;s assessment is based on information <lb/>listed in the indents of 5048 men and women, supplied by the authorities and by con-<lb/>victs themselves but is not, unlike the analysis below, correlated with gaol admissions. 28 <lb/>Recently, attention has turned not just to the imaginary of nineteenth-century <lb/>observers but to cultural narratives deployed by the convicted in their keepsakes and <lb/>tattoos, stories and memoirs. 29 Far from dismissing offenders as &apos;incurable romancers&apos;, <lb/>Transported to New South Wales and Van Diemen&apos;s Land 1787-1852 (Melbourne: Melbourne Univer-<lb/>sity Press, 1965); A. G. L. Shaw, Convicts and the Colonies: A Study of Penal Transportation from Great <lb/>Britain and Ireland to Australia and Other Parts of the British Empire (1966; Irish Historical Press, <lb/>1998). <lb/>27 Stephen Nicholas, (ed.), Convict Workers: Reinterpreting Australia&apos;s Past (Cambridge: Cambridge Uni-<lb/>versity Press, 1988). <lb/>28 Alison Alexander, Tasmania&apos;s Convicts: How Felons Built a Free Society (Crows Nest, NSW: Allen &amp; <lb/>Unwin, 2010, enlarged edition), p. 30. <lb/>29 David Kent and Norma Townshend (eds) Joseph Mason: Assigned Convict, 1831-1837 (Carlton South, <lb/>Vic.: Melbourne University Press, 1996); Ian Duffield and James Bradley (eds.), Representing Convicts: <lb/>New Perspectives on Forced Convict Labour Migration (Leicester: Leicester University Press, 1997); Paul <lb/>Donnelly, &apos;&quot;When This You See Remember Me&quot;: Convict Love Tokens and Related Keepsakes&apos;, Australa-<lb/>sian Victorian Studies Journal 3.1 (1997): 22-37; Michele Field and Timothy Millett (eds.), Convict Love <lb/>Tokens: The Leaden Hearts the Convicts Left Behind (South Australia: Wakefield Press, 1998); Hamish <lb/>Maxwell-Stewart and Ian Duffield, &apos;Skin Deep Devotions: Religious Tattoos and Convict Transporta-<lb/>tion to Australia&apos; in Written on the Body: The Tattoo in European and American History, ed. by Jane <lb/>Caplan (London: Reaktion Books, 2000), pp. 118-35; Lucy Frost and Hamish Maxwell-Stewart (eds.), <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>historians have begun to show how romancing itself might constitute a form of evi-<lb/>dence which illuminates the cultural strategies prisoners used to convey, interpret <lb/>and trade on their past. 30 Ian Duffield, for example, has viewed the records of convict <lb/>interrogation on arrival in Van Diemen&apos;s Land as &apos;forced narratives&apos; that, nonethe-<lb/>less, contain arresting first-person voices. In a close reading of statements made by <lb/>four black convicts, he argues their answers to cross-examination should be read as <lb/>&apos;high-density micro-narrative[s]&apos; in which the voice of the colonized subject intrudes <lb/>spectacularly into the state record. Alexander Simpson, court martialled in 1832 for <lb/>his part in the Jamaican slave uprising, declared his offence as &apos;Mutiny &amp; exciting <lb/>the Slaves to Rebellion. I was a slave myself.&apos; Such &apos;powerfully dramatic &quot;action narra-<lb/>tives&quot;&apos;, contends Duffield, wrest our attention from the colonial &apos; eye&apos;, with its power <lb/>of surveillance over the prisoner, to the autobiographical &apos;I&apos; of the convicted. They <lb/>remind us that the penal gaze was not omnipotent for its record-keeping depended <lb/>on convicts&apos; own voices that sometimes challenged the system that imprisoned them. <lb/>&apos;[I]n these brief, supercharged tales&apos;, concludes Duffield, &apos;the convicts&apos; agendas are <lb/>not effectively hijacked by the agendas of the Convict Department record-keeping: <lb/>convict voices are vividly if briefly audible.&apos; 31 <lb/>The convict &apos;I&apos;, however, was rarely documented as assertively as Alexander <lb/>Simpson&apos;s defiant declaration, &apos;I was a slave myself&apos;. Usually the first-person pronoun <lb/>was expunged from the record and the convict&apos;s identity reduced to his crimes and util-<lb/>ity to the colonial labour force, as when the clerk entered John King as &apos;Fisherman&apos; and <lb/>noted his stated offence, &apos;Stealing 2 stone 11 of old canvass pr [prosecutor] Cullenthorpe <lb/>of Yarmouth&apos;. 32 In order to recover King&apos;s statement as an &apos; action narrative&apos;, and those <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Chain Letters: Narrating Convict Lives (Melbourne: Melbourne University Press, 2001); Rogers, &apos;The <lb/>Way to Jerusalem&apos;. <lb/>30 Compare, for example, Smith&apos;s sceptical interrogation of the claims made by a returned convict with <lb/>Beier&apos;s cultural analysis of the man&apos;s story-telling patter: F. B. Smith, &apos;Mayhew&apos;s Convict&apos;, Victorian Studies, <lb/>22 (Summer 1979): 431-48; and A. L. Beier, &apos;Identity, Language, and Resistance in the Making of the Vic-<lb/>torian &quot;Criminal Class&quot;: Mayhew&apos;s Convict Revisited&apos;, Journal of British Studies, 44 (July 2005): 499-515. <lb/>31 Ian Duffield, &apos;&quot;Stated This Offence&quot;: High Density Convict Micro-Narratives&apos;, Chain Letters, pp. 119-35: <lb/>pp. 120, 122, 134-5. <lb/>32 Most of the Van Diemen&apos;s Land records are held at the State Archives of Tasmania, Hobart, and many <lb/>are searchable online at http://portal.archives.tas.gov.au/menu.aspx?search=11. These include the <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the vast majority interrogated by the Superintendent of Convicts, we need to return <lb/>to the scenes of their &apos; crimes&apos; and the circumstances that led to their exile. <lb/>III. Record Linkage and Social Profiling: &apos;Stated <lb/>this Offence&apos; <lb/>In the following examination, I compare the prison and convict records of thirty-four <lb/>men transported to Van Diemen&apos;s Land in the period 1837-1852 who served time <lb/>at Yarmouth Gaol, for summary and indictable offences. 33 Small-scale analysis has <lb/>its own challenges and limitations. Piecing together the offending histories of the <lb/>convicted requires careful detective work if we are to avoid falsely indicting them <lb/>anew. Two John Kings went in and out of Yarmouth Gaol in the early 1840s, for <lb/>example, and another man bearing the same name was transported with John King <lb/>aboard the Surrey. Variations in name and transcription mistakes can lead to a wide <lb/>margin of error so my statistical findings should be read as approximations. How-<lb/>ever, a micro-historical approach combining quantitative and qualitative investiga-<lb/>tion and aided by access databases, enables more extensive contextualization and <lb/>intensive interpretation of historical sources than large-scale studies can undertake. <lb/>Some Yarmouth convicts had entered prison as early as 1834 and all can be tracked <lb/>in the Gaoler&apos;s daily log as well as in the gaol registers. Twenty-nine convicts were <lb/>transported following trial at the Great Yarmouth Quarter Sessions. The remaining <lb/>five passed through the prison but were sentenced in the county town to transporta-<lb/>tion at the Norwich Quarter Sessions or the Norfolk Special Assizes. 34 <lb/>major records on individual convicts -the Conduct Records and Convict Indents -including those on <lb/>John King: John King, 6533, per Surrey (4), 1842, extra identifier 2, [database no. 40331], CON33/1/27, <lb/>CON14/1/13. Where both records are available, they are given in the order of Conduct Record fol-<lb/>lowed by Convict Indent. For some convicts there is no indent but details about their occupation and <lb/>physical characteristics etc. are found in the Appropriation Lists or Description Lists. These will follow <lb/>the hyperlink to the Conduct Record. Convicts&apos; names are followed by their police number, ship, and <lb/>year of arrival. For using convict records see Susan Hood, Transcribing Tasmanian Convict Records (Port <lb/>Arthur: Port Arthur Historic Site Management Authority, 2003). Detailed, though partial, transcrip-<lb/>tions can be searched at http://foundersandsurvivors.org/. <lb/>33 Only two were sentenced to transportation after 1845 and by 1852 most had reached, or were reach-<lb/>ing, the end of their sentence. <lb/>34 The online database England &amp; Wales, Criminal Registers, 1791-1892 (Provo, UT, USA: Ancestry.com <lb/>Operations Inc, 2009) was searched for evidence of convictions outside Yarmouth. These registers <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Five women admitted to Yarmouth Gaol in the same period were sent to Van <lb/>Diemen&apos;s Land, four of whom were sentenced by the town&apos;s magistrates. Tried at the <lb/>Norfolk County Assizes, which heard all capital offences, Charlotte Yaxley pleaded <lb/>not guilty to murdering her step-daughter. She was the only Yarmouth convict to <lb/>protest against her conviction when stating her offence in Van Diemen&apos;s Land: &apos;I am <lb/>innocent&apos;. 35 All the other exiles were convicted of theft and their profiles correspond <lb/>with the similar number sent from the East Anglian port to other penal colonies in <lb/>the same years. I exclude women from this analysis, however, because their offend-<lb/>ing histories were very different to the men&apos;s. Between them, the women had been <lb/>convicted of seven offences (only two had known prior convictions) and, in common <lb/>with other female prisoners in the gaol, they had a much lower committal rate than <lb/>the males. <lb/>All but two of the male Yarmouth exiles arrived in Van Diemen&apos;s Land after <lb/>the transition in 1839 from the Assignment to the Probation system, when penal <lb/>bureaucracy approached its apogee. 36 Comparison of gaol registers and convict <lb/>records confirms Governor Arthur&apos;s concerns about the reliability and leakage of <lb/>the official documentation trail that continued into the Probation era. 37 In 1844, for <lb/>example, the Gaoler testified at the Norwich Assizes to the prior convictions of three <lb/>former inmates, all under twenty years old, tried for stealing money from a public <lb/>house: Robert Harrod had eleven committals at Yarmouth, William Jenkins three and <lb/>Joshua Artis nine. Yet, the Gaoler&apos;s information did not reach the hulk authority, <lb/>recorded only indictments and miss any summary convictions convicts had received elsewhere. <lb/>35 Charlotte Yaxley, 17, per Garland Grove (1), 1841, Conduct Record CON40/1/10, Description List <lb/>CON19/1/3. For cross-examination of women at Hobart, see Lucy Frost, Abandoned Women: Scottish <lb/>Convicts Exiled Beyond the Seas (London: Allen &amp; Unwin, 2012), pp. 26-9. Only 11% of women aboard <lb/>the Australasia in 1849 had been charged with more than two previous offences while over a half had <lb/>only one or no prior convictions; see Trudy Mae Cowley, A Drift of &apos;Derwent Ducks&apos;: Lives of the 200 <lb/>Female Irish Convicts Transported on the Australasia from Dublin to Hobart in 1849 (Hobart: Research <lb/>Tasmania, 2005), pp. 11-12. <lb/>36 Ian Brand, The Convict Probation System: Van Diemen&apos;s Land 1839-1854 (Hobart: Blubber Head Press, <lb/>1990). <lb/>37 Errors will have been inevitable in a bureaucratic exercise on such a scale. Sentenced at Walsingham, <lb/>William Hurn per Neptune 1, 1837 and William Barnes per Asia 5, 1840 were wrongly entered as tried <lb/>at Great Yarmouth; see England &amp; Wales Criminal Registers, 7 July 1837 and 10 January 1840. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>which reported that Harrod and Artis had one previous conviction and Jenkins <lb/>&apos;2 or 3&apos;, presumably offences committed at Norwich. 38 Neither did the Gaoler&apos;s report <lb/>of their conduct under his watch reach the convict authority. Harrod was disciplined <lb/>seven times in Yarmouth Gaol while Jenkins and Artis, at eighteen times apiece, were <lb/>among the most frequently punished inmates for run-of-the-mill infractions: fight-<lb/>ing, singing, shouting, swearing, communicating with female prisoners and so on. 39 <lb/>When the Gaoler&apos;s report was forwarded, it usually tallied with his record of the <lb/>prisoner&apos;s conduct in gaol, but in only nineteen out of thirty-four cases did his assess-<lb/>ment reach Van Diemen&apos;s Land. <lb/>The Gaol Report usually recorded the Gaoler&apos;s numerical estimate of the con-<lb/>victs&apos; prior committals at Yarmouth, regardless of whether they had been acquitted, <lb/>and included the offence for which they were transported. According to his reports, <lb/>the nineteen convicts had served 56 imprisonments between them, giving an aver-<lb/>age offending rate of 2.95. In fact, the thirty-four convicts had served 129 prior <lb/>imprisonments at Yarmouth, averaging 3.82 each. If we add to these committals <lb/>the offences that led to their transportation, as well as a further 29 offences com-<lb/>mitted elsewhere, only two of which they omitted, we have a total of 194 offences <lb/>and an overall committal rate of 5.71 each. By contrast, if we calculated the average <lb/>number of prior committals solely on the Gaoler&apos;s Reports, we would have a figure <lb/>of 1.65 per convict, an under-reporting of repeat offending by around two-thirds. <lb/>Only three of the thirty-four convicts were positively identified by the Gaoler <lb/>as first-time offenders but, in their statements, two of these acknowledged prior <lb/>offences committed elsewhere while the third had been imprisoned twice at <lb/>Yarmouth as a refractory pauper. 40 No information was sent about seven con-<lb/></body>

			<listBibl>38 Gaol Keeper&apos;s Journal, January 1841-December 1845 (Y/L2 48), 20 December 1844; Robert Harrod, <lb/>15914, per Theresa, 1845, CON33/1/67, CON14/1/29; Joshua Artis, 15826, ditto, William Jenkins, <lb/>15933, ditto. <lb/>39 Gaol Keeper&apos;s Journals, January 1836-December 1840 (Y/L2, 47) and January 1841-December 1845 <lb/>(Y/L2 48), passim. <lb/>40 John Cooper, 14708, per William Jardine (1), 1844, CON33/1/62, CON14/1/30; Edmund Bowles, <lb/>13829, per Barossa (2), 1844, CON33/1/59, CON14/1/8; William Alexander, 18277, per Mayda, 1846, <lb/>CON33/1/79, CON17/1/2, p. 154, off Norfolk Island per Pestongee Bomangee May 1847. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>victs. Six of these men had previous committals at Yarmouth while four of them <lb/>owned up to former convictions in their statements. The one convict who had no <lb/>offending history was a Sheffield cutler on the tramp, sentenced to transportation <lb/>for street robbery committed in Yarmouth with two other itinerants. 41 If, as many <lb/>itinerants will have done, he concealed his identity and previous convictions from <lb/>the authorities (he claimed to have no relatives) he has also concealed himself <lb/>from the historian and his record cannot be confirmed. <lb/>With at most one first-time male offender transported from Yarmouth, the <lb/>gaol committal rates raise questions about the conclusions of earlier large-scale <lb/>examinations of convict records, such as the assertion in Convict Workers that two-<lb/>thirds of exiles were first-time offenders. 42 They also suggest the possibility that L. <lb/>L. Robson&apos;s long-contested claim that &apos;[c]ertainly one-half, and probably two-thirds, <lb/>had formerly been punished&apos; may have been a conservative estimate. 43 However, <lb/>committal rates do not take us much closer to understanding how the convicted <lb/>viewed their offences. Some imprisonments were for very short periods -a day <lb/>or two on Further Examination or a week or two on Remand that did not lead to <lb/>conviction and which, understandably, many convicts did not acknowledge. If we <lb/>exclude these short stays and six acquittals from our analysis, we have a figure of <lb/>91 convictions of which the convicts admitted 45 and omitted 46 when stating <lb/>their former crimes. 44 With the offences committed outside Yarmouth and those for <lb/>which they were sentenced to transportation, in all they acknowledged 122 crimes, <lb/>averaging 3.59 offences each. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>41 John Morgan, 15291, per George Seymour, 1845, CON33/1/64, p. 15291, CON14/1/26, Description <lb/>List, CON18/1/44. <lb/>42 Based on indents for New South Wales 1817-1840, Nicholas and Shergold, found a recidivist rate of <lb/>39%; see Stephen Nicholas and Peter R. Shergold, &apos;Unshackling the Past&apos; in Convict Workers: Reinter-<lb/>preting Australia&apos;s Past, ed. Stephen Nicholas (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1988), pp. 3-13 <lb/>(p. 7). Using a sample of 4000 indents, Shaw found 45% of convicts sent to Van Diemen&apos;s Land (1830-<lb/>1840) had prior convictions; see Nicholas and Shergold, &apos;Convicts as Migrants, ibid, pp. 43-61 (p. 46). <lb/>43 Robson&apos;s calculation was based on a 5% sampling of male convict records for Van Deimen&apos;s Land and <lb/>New South Wales; see Convict Settlers, pp. 9, 36-7, 176-9. <lb/>44 This figure includes very short imprisonments and acquittals for offences that convicts acknowledged. <lb/>Like the Gaoler, some convicts may have reported their committals rather than convictions. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Of the prior offences they admitted, the Yarmouth exiles were most likely to <lb/>acknowledge convictions for theft. They admitted to 33 (73.33%) of these offences, <lb/>even some that were trivial (Samuel Iverson, who seems to have had a sweet tooth, <lb/>confessed to serving one day for peppermint and two acquittals for sugar) and to us <lb/>earned grossly excessive sentences (George Mills&apos;s six-month sentence for stealing <lb/>apples). 45 In total, the transportees declared six out of eight convictions for pilfering <lb/>food and all five for stealing clothes. Their readiness to admit to theft suggests that <lb/>most accepted the illegality of crimes against property ownership, an acceptance <lb/>borne out by the fact that, when free, some would take to court those who stole from <lb/>them, as did considerable numbers of former convicts. Robert Harrod arrived in Van <lb/>Diemen&apos;s Land with a string of thirteen convictions going back to the age of twelve <lb/>of which over half involved theft (though he conceded only one), but he would bring <lb/>at least two prosecutions when manager of a hotel and store. 46 <lb/>Much of the thieving by Yarmouth offenders appears to have been opportun-<lb/>istic and connected with their occupation, like the work-based appropriation that <lb/>characterized much of the crime committed by the labouring poor elsewhere. 47 <lb/>Samuel Wells worked for a brewer and was transported for stealing a peck of barley. <lb/>Seven years previously he had served three months for robbing a plank, an offence <lb/>he declared along with stealing a fender, a charge for which he was acquitted. 48 The <lb/>sawyer Isaac Gowing was transported for stealing a plane; he admitted his one prior <lb/>conviction of thieving wood the previous year. 49 The Yarmouth transportees declared <lb/>six of the eight clearly occupation-related thefts of which formerly they had been <lb/>convicted. Partnerships in crime were also connected to occupation. Two young men <lb/>transported for life for horse-thieving may have met through working as boatmen, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>45 Samuel Iverson, 16449, per Marion (2), 1845, CON33/1/70, CON14/1/31; George Mills, 8782, per <lb/>Duchess of Northumberland, 1843, CON33/1/36, CON14/1/19. <lb/>46 Mercury (Hobart), 12 July 1861, p. 2 and 8 December 1865, p. 2; Trove National Library of Australia, <lb/>Historical Newspapers, http://trove.nla.gov.au/ <lb/>47 For work-based appropriation, see Barry S. Godfrey, David J. Cox, and Stephen D. Farrall, Criminal <lb/>Lives: Family Life, Employment and Offending (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2007), 78-105, 172-3. <lb/>48 Samuel Wells, 8882, per Duchess of Northumberland (1), CON33/1/36, CON14/1/19. <lb/>49 Isaac Gowing, 8005, per Triton, 1842, CON33/1/33, CON14/1/15. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>though when they were first committed together for being idle and disorderly, the <lb/>youngest was only thirteen. He admitted that offence (10 days and 2 months) and <lb/>twelve months for housebreaking but the older boy admitted only one prior convic-<lb/>tion of twelve months for stealing a watch. 50 <lb/>Others were more selective in their recall. Thomas Mapes was committed nine <lb/>times at Yarmouth. He pleaded not guilty to stealing three cheeses with a compan-<lb/>ion, a cheesemonger, but was sentenced to six months. In his statement he admitted <lb/>taking cheese and receiving ten days for an assault. In fact, by paying fines he avoided <lb/>imprisonments for two assaults, one against a policeman, but served one month <lb/>for an assault on another constable. He overlooked these and other committals, <lb/>including two months for vagrancy and suspicion of robbery. 51 By contrast, William <lb/>Chapman admitted six imprisonments for &apos; disorderly conduct&apos;, without specifying he <lb/>had been charged three times with beating policemen, nor for bathing in the river at <lb/>an improper time. An apprentice shoemaker, he admitted stealing ladies&apos; shoes with <lb/>two other boys, one of whom acknowledged the same offence in his statement. 52 <lb/>The Yarmouth convicts were less ready, therefore, to acknowledge violent crime <lb/>than property offences. In general, assaults were prosecuted much less frequently <lb/>and severely than property-based offences and often imprisonment could be avoided <lb/>by paying a fine. Six men had convictions relating to assault (five of these on women, <lb/>five on policemen) but only three owned up to any history of violence. James Brown <lb/>alluded in veiled terms to two such commitments: &apos;two months for a row&apos; (with his <lb/>father) and six months for &apos;breach of peace&apos; (an assault on Elizabeth Barber). 53 Both <lb/>offences must have been vicious to incur such long sentences. For other convicts, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>50 Lewis Goodwin, 1264, per Blenheim (1), 1837, CON31/1/3, Appropriation List, CON27/1/7; John <lb/>Bowles, 2635, ditto. <lb/>51 GR, 13 March 1837; 30 March 1837; 19 April 1837; 29 September 1840, 9 August 1841; 13 August <lb/>1842; 9 August 1843; 29 November 1844; 27 October 1845; Thomas Mapes, 18874, per Palmyra, <lb/>1846, CON33/1/81, CON14/1/36. <lb/>52 GR, 24 April 1838; 7 November 1838; 29 April 1839; 10 August 1840; 4 January 1841; 15 Novem-<lb/>ber 1842; 3 February 1843; William Chapman, 20472, per Mount Stewart Elphinstone (2), 1848, <lb/>CON33/1/89, CON14//38; James Barley, 673, per Hindostan (2), 1841, CON33/1/4, Appropriation <lb/>List, CON27/1/8. <lb/>53 GR, 6 August 1836; 27 October 1836; James Brown, 5709, per Susan (2), 1842, CON33/1/24, <lb/>CON14/1/15. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>omission of their history of assault probably reflects their acceptance of violence as an <lb/>integral and everyday part of the rough-and-ready male culture of the seaport rather <lb/>than any reluctance to declare it or sense of wrong-doing and shame. 54 Sentenced to <lb/>seven years for stealing a silk bag and money, for instance, John Newstead acknowl-<lb/>edged twelve months for a highway robbery committed outside Yarmouth and five <lb/>counts of &apos; drunkenness&apos;, probably connected with his four convictions for assault at <lb/>Yarmouth, one on a policeman and three on women, one of whom was probably his <lb/>girlfriend since her name was tattooed on his arm. Neither did Newstead disclose <lb/>committals for stealing a pair of boots and being a refractory pauper. 55 <lb/>Of the men&apos;s 129 commitments at Yarmouth, only 19 (14.73%) led to an appear-<lb/>ance at the Quarter Session; the remaining 111 cases (86.05%) were heard summarily <lb/>by the magistrates. 56 Many of these were for misdemeanours ranging from vagrancy, <lb/>being idle and disorderly or a suspicious character, to removing soil, sand or dirt <lb/>without license. William Copping confessed to breaking out of the workhouse five <lb/>times, though none of the three convicts who served time at Yarmouth as refrac-<lb/>tory paupers owned up to their offence against the parish. 57 Thomas Tripp admitted <lb/>two counts of suspicion but not the three weeks spent for being a rogue and vaga-<lb/>bond who &apos; did wilfully expose his person, he being entirely naked&apos;. 58 However, 42 <lb/>of the Yarmouth men&apos;s former convictions were for misdemeanours to which they <lb/>admitted 25, a surprisingly high number (59.52%). These included the boys William <lb/>Jenkins, sent down for twelve months for &apos;setting boats adrift&apos;, and Thomas Bowles, a <lb/>week each for breaking windows and being absent from his work. 59 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>54 Martin J. Wiener, Men of Blood: Violence, Manliness and Criminal Justice in Victorian England (Cam-<lb/>bridge: Cambridge University Press, 2004); Clive Emsley, Hard Men: Violence in England since 1750 <lb/>(London: Hambledon, 2005). <lb/>55 GR, 13 May 1842; 21 May 1842; 1 September 1842; 19 November 1842; 24 April 1843; 3 January <lb/>1846; 30 June 1846; John Newstead, 21025, per Ratcliffe (2), 1848, CON33/1/91, CON14/1/40. <lb/>56 On the rise of summary jurisdiction, see Peter King, Crime, Justice and Discretion in England, 1740-<lb/>1820 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000), 82-125. <lb/>57 William Copping, 3589, per Barossa (1), 1842, CON33/1/16, CON14/1/12. <lb/>58 GR, 9 January 1839; 6 February 1839; 5 March 1842; 18 May 1842; Thomas Tripp, 12997, per Lady <lb/>Franklin, 1844, CON33/1/55, p. 12997, CON17/1/1, p. 16. <lb/>59 William Jenkins, 15933, per Theresa, CON33/1/67, CON14/1/29; Thomas Bowles, 10001, per Asiatic, <lb/>1843, CON33/1/42, CON14/1/24. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>The scavenger Christopher Riches, however, clearly distinguished between felony <lb/>and misdemeanour; &apos;Denies having been convicted before&apos; states his convict record. <lb/>He was eighteen when sentenced to transportation in 1845 with his brother Isaac <lb/>(seventeen) for stealing four fathoms of rope from a ship, worth 1s 10d. 60 On their <lb/>conviction, the Gaoler, unusually, wrote out their committal history in full, showing <lb/>he was well aware of their record of persistent offending. Yet, though Christopher had <lb/>been committed eleven times and Isaac six, their Gaol Reports list only two convic-<lb/>tions each. 61 While comparison of these records illustrates the gaps in the paper trail, <lb/>it also illuminates the boys&apos; understanding of legality, property and theft. Christopher <lb/>first entered gaol on remand in June 1841 for &apos; digging up and carrying away soil from <lb/>the Denes&apos; and was remanded twice more that year for stealing manure and a basket. <lb/>On other occasions he received a week or a fortnight for removing dirt and ill-using <lb/>a donkey. Many juvenile boys were summarily convicted of gathering dirt -a com-<lb/>mon means of making a little money. For Christopher, however, it was a legitimate <lb/>livelihood -Sarah Martin noted his father was the &apos;Town Scavenger&apos; -at which he <lb/>worked industriously. Ten of his eleven admissions were connected with scavenging. <lb/>His brother Isaac seems to have drawn the same distinction between thieving and <lb/>scavenging. He admitted six months for stealing a watch, seven days for stealing <lb/>money, and seven days for &apos;picking my mothers [sic] pocket&apos; but omitted six months <lb/>for vagrancy with intent to steal wood from a shipyard. Isaac excluded one further <lb/>imprisonment -stealing eggs and knives from a shop -an offence for which both <lb/>brothers were prosecuted but only the younger convicted. Given Isaac&apos;s admission of <lb/>the other thefts, on this occasion he may have been wrongly indicted. <lb/>Isaac&apos;s remand for picking his mother&apos;s pocket alerts us to another aspect of <lb/>the offenders&apos; history that is thrown into relief when we compare the statements <lb/>convicts made about their family and its whereabouts with other records. At least <lb/>five Yarmouth convicts had been committed to gaol by a relative, six if we include <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>60 Christopher Riches, 17981, per Joseph Somes (1), 1846, CON33/1/77, CON14/1/35; Isaac Riches, <lb/>17982, ditto. <lb/>61 Gaol Index and Receiving Book, Y/D 41/28, 12 September 1845. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>William Copping, whose prosecution was instigated by the man who subsequently <lb/>lived with Copping&apos;s wife. James Brown was first committed, aged eighteen, for a <lb/>&apos;row&apos; at the behest of his father. The short, sharp shock of six weeks confinement <lb/>evidently failed for he received three more committals before being sentenced to <lb/>seven years. 62 Likewise, on the complaint of his mother, twelve-year-old Robert <lb/>Harrod spent the first of eleven stints at Yarmouth Gaol for being &apos;idle and disor-<lb/>derly, wandering abroad and absenting himself from home&apos;. 63 His absences may <lb/>have been prompted by tension with his step-father, who Robert omitted from <lb/>the family he listed to the convict authorities. 64 Thomas Bowles was sentenced to <lb/>transportation for stealing £50 from his uncle. 65 His father Edmund had been a <lb/>policeman at Yarmouth and was charged with secreting a watch, property of the <lb/>executors of Thos Bowles. When young Thomas got into trouble with the law, <lb/>Edmund appears to have been absent from home; he was not resident at the 1841 <lb/>Census and in 1844, two years after his son, was transported for street robbery in <lb/>Norwich, committed with a woman who was not his wife, and where he had also <lb/>been convicted of assault. 66 <lb/>While these committals hint at family trouble -relatives are only likely to have <lb/>prosecuted an errant family member after prolonged disruptive behaviour -all five <lb/>gave an accurate account of their kin, as did the large majority of convicts. Other <lb/>evidence on their convict records suggests a kind of atonement on the part of two <lb/>of these men. Isaac Riches&apos;s elaborate tattoos, noted by the convict clerk, depicted <lb/>the parents from whom he had stolen -&apos;MR [Mary Riches] CR [Christopher Riches] <lb/>Man &amp; Woman above elbow&apos; -and probably his companionship with his brother <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>62 Gaol Committal and Discharge Book, 6 August 1836. <lb/>63 Gaol Committal and Discharge Book, 26 September 1837; Sarah Martin&apos;s Register, 1841, no. 53. <lb/>64 1841 Census, HO 107/793/1, 1841 England Census [database on-line] (Provo, UT, USA: Ancestry.com); <lb/>Robert Harrod, 15914, per Theresa, 1845, CON33/1/67, CON14/1/29. <lb/>65 Thomas Bowles, 10001, per Asiatic, 1843, CON33/1/42, CON14/1/24. <lb/>66 GR, 13 May 1842; Edmund Bowles, 13829, per Barossa (2), 1844, CON33/1/59, CON14/1/8; HO <lb/>107/790.2. Thanks to descendants of Thomas and Edmund Bowles whose research led me to <lb/>Edmund&apos;s transportation; http://www.rootschat.com/forum/index.php?PHPSESSID=ej0pkl1bn9ho <lb/>3tlpmgfjaab807&amp;topic=526988. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>with whom he embarked for Van Diemen&apos;s Land -&apos;two men arm in arm&apos;. 67 When first <lb/>admitted to gaol, James Brown was entered in the register as &apos;James Brown, Junior&apos; to <lb/>distinguish him from the father with whom he had been brawling. Brown appears to <lb/>have adopted the patronym for he is named in the convict records as &apos;James Brown, <lb/>the Younger&apos;. He seems to have identified with his father, following in his occupation <lb/>as a bricklayer and proudly displaying the tools of their trade in his tattoos -<lb/>&apos;hammer compasses trowell plumb rule level step level&apos;. 68 <lb/>Most Yarmouth convicts began their offending career in their early teens. 61.02% <lb/>were under eighteen when they committed their pre-transportation offences; as a <lb/>cohort they were younger than the gaol&apos;s repeat offender population, 41% of whom <lb/>were under eighteen in the years 1839-1841. Of the convicts, 32.35 % were still <lb/>under eighteen when sentenced to transportation. Where Robson found half of male <lb/>transportees were under twenty-five on arrival in Australia, nearly three-quarters <lb/>(70.59%) of the Yarmouth convicts fell into this age group. 69 Only five were over 30. <lb/>At fourteen, Henry Coppin was the youngest exile, sentenced in 1841 for stealing an <lb/>oil frock and trousers from a ship. One year earlier, his father William Copping had <lb/>been given seven years for receiving stolen goods. Five times confined as a refractory <lb/>pauper, William seems not to have been able to fulfil the two main paternal duties <lb/>of providing for and protecting his children and it is likely that, with his departure, <lb/>Henry went off the rails. 70 Probably Henry was estranged from his mother, for her <lb/>name is not included in his statement though he gave the names of his father and <lb/>siblings. At the 1841 Census, Henry was not at the lodging house in Lowestoft where <lb/>his mother resided with the man who had testified against her husband, and he was <lb/>picked up as a rogue and vagabond prior to his conviction for theft. 71 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>67 Isaac Riches, 17982 per Joseph Somes (1), 1846, CON33/1/77, CON14/1/35; 1841 Census, HO <lb/>107/793/8. <lb/>68 Committal and Discharge Book, 6 Aug. 1836; James Brown the Younger, 5709, Susan, 1842, <lb/>CON33/1/24, CON14/1/15; 1841 Census, HO 107/793/7. <lb/>69 Robson, Convict Settlers, p. 182. <lb/>70 Trev Broughton and Helen Rogers, (eds.) Gender and Fatherhood in the Nineteenth Century (Basing-<lb/>stoke: Palgrave, 2006). <lb/>71 Henry Coppin, 11429, per Anson, 1844, CON33/1/49, CON14/1/25; William Copping, 3589, per <lb/>Barossa (1), 1842, CON33/1/16, CON14/1/12. GR, 21 October 1841; 1841 Census, HO 107/1030/7. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Reconstructing convicts&apos; families by linking their indents with Christening <lb/>records and census returns reveals a startling aspect of their profile. Of the thirty-<lb/>one men whose families can be identified through the indent or the census, sev-<lb/>enteen (54.84%) had lost their father, eighteen if we include the effective death of <lb/>Henry Coppin&apos;s father on his transportation. Twelve had no mother (38.71%) while <lb/>six had neither parent, though only one of these was under twenty. Only ten con-<lb/>victs (32.26%) had both parents living. 72 Record linkage reveals the catastrophic <lb/>effects on some young men of the loss of a parent, and especially the father. In a port <lb/>dominated by male occupations with few employment opportunities for women, the <lb/>death of the male breadwinner could devastate the family economy. On at least two <lb/>occasions William Hickling&apos;s mother had taken her three sons into the workhouse <lb/>and towards the end of her life she would again be a pauper. When William was <lb/>sentenced to transportation for theft in 1841, Maria Hickling and her youngest son <lb/>Robert (seven) were acquitted of receiving stolen goods from him. 73 <lb/>All but two convicts came from Norfolk, one of the most distressed agrarian <lb/>counties in the 1830s and 1840s, while four came from Norwich. 74 The rest were <lb/>born in Great Yarmouth or its immediate vicinity where the mixed economy of the <lb/>port offered more employment opportunities, though much of it casual, and gen-<lb/>erally better wages than the surrounding rural areas. The Gaoler&apos;s records of their <lb/>occupations closely correlate with those on their convict statements and allow us <lb/>to track their progress through the occupational structure of the port. On his first <lb/>admission in 1839, aged fourteen, for stealing poultry, William Hickling was work-<lb/>ing at &apos; a fish office&apos; while on successive visits he was listed as a labourer. On arrival <lb/>72 Based on autobiographical recollections of working-class boyhood in the period 1800-78, Jane <lb/>Humphries finds that by the age of 14, 16% had lost their father, 13% their mother, and 26% <lb/>had survived both parents, rates similar to findings in other studies. While my findings focus on <lb/>slightly older boys and young men, it appears likely that considerably higher rates of orphanage had <lb/>occurred in this cohort than in the wider population. For the difficulties in measuring orphanage <lb/>and the effects of parental mortality on children, see Humphries, Childhood and Child Labour in the <lb/>British Industrial Revolution (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010), pp. 61-72 (p. 65). <lb/>73 3 December 1836 and 14 April 1838, Index of Examined Paupers, 1756-1844 [Y/L16/8]; GR, <lb/>2 December 1841. Few Poor Law records survive for Great Yarmouth so record linkage between <lb/>prison and poor law registers has not been possible. <lb/>74 Anne Digby, Pauper Palaces (London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1978). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>in Van Diemen&apos;s Land, however, William described himself as a fisherman, an occu-<lb/>pation that probably signified the future he had hoped for himself, rather than his <lb/>previous employment. If this is the case, he connected himself with his elder brother <lb/>Matthew, listed as a mariner in the 1841 Census, and the sailor father they had lost. 75 <lb/>Joshua Artis firmly identified himself with his father, a knife-grinder and cutler. We <lb/>can trace Joshua&apos;s progress from &apos; chip boy&apos; in his early admissions to &apos;labourer&apos; in <lb/>later ones. In Van Diemen&apos;s Land he described himself as &apos; an imperfect tailor&apos;, the <lb/>trade he must have begun to learn at the Penitentiary prior to embarkation, but to <lb/>which he proudly added his father&apos;s trade -cutler -the one to which, presumably, <lb/>he always thought he was heading. 76 Fifteen of the twenty-three convicts whose fam-<lb/>ily occupations can be traced claimed their father&apos;s trade or that of an elder brother. <lb/>Some had definitely been employed in their father&apos;s trade, such as the waterman <lb/>Joseph Anderson and watchmaker William Wetherill. For others, their stated occupa-<lb/>tion was a way of connecting themselves to the life they had departed and, in particu-<lb/>lar, their sense of masculine vocation. 77 <lb/>There is only one convict who may have deliberately changed his employment <lb/>status in order to enhance his chances in the penal colony. Henry Simmonds entered <lb/>Yarmouth Gaol as a &apos;hawker of needles&apos;; in Van Diemen&apos;s Land he gave himself the <lb/>more elevated role of coachman and groom. Conceivably he had done this job in the <lb/>past but his claim may have been a white lie for he appears to have told one other. <lb/>Simmonds had been arrested at Yarmouth with his &apos;wife&apos; Anna, who was acquitted of <lb/>street robbery; in Van Diemen&apos;s Land he declared himself single. 78 William Chapman, <lb/>sentenced at the same Sessions as Simmonds, likewise claimed to be single though, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>75 GR, 28 December 1839, 3 June 1840, 2 April 1841, 3 June 1841, 30 October 1841, 28 November 1841, <lb/>28 December 1841. William Hickling, 6511, per Surrey (4), 1842, CON33/1/27, CON14/1/13; 1841 <lb/>Census, HO 107/793/4. <lb/>76 GR, 3 May 1839, 24 May 1839, 6 July 1841, 12 June 1841, 12 June 1842, 19 June 1842, 7 July 1842, 4 <lb/>October 1842, 7 September 1843, Joshua Artis, 15826, per Theresa, 1845, CON33/1/67, CON14/1/29. <lb/>77 Joseph Anderson, 20670, per Bangalore, 1848, CON33/1/90, CON14/1/39; William Wetherill, per <lb/>Tortoise, 1842, Police No. 6511, CON33/1/17, CON14/1/13. <lb/>78 Gaol Receiving Book, 26 January 1843; Henry Simmonds, 15317, per Sir George Seymour, 1845, <lb/>CON33/1/64, p. 15317, CON14/1/26. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>four days after his removal to the Warrior hulk, his &apos;wife&apos; had to be told to leave the <lb/>gaol, having appeared &apos;in a state of angry excitement, using disrespectful language <lb/>towards the Local authorities&apos;. 79 I have not found either Simmonds or Chapman (who <lb/>may have been in common-law unions) in the marriage registers but if these two <lb/>men cast off their marital status -as did some convicts and the spouses they left <lb/>behind -I have found no other evidence of men falsifying their occupational or fam-<lb/>ily circumstances. In the light of their collective profile, therefore, drawn from their <lb/>testimony, what can we make of the statements made by John King when the Surrey <lb/>anchored at Hobart in 1842 and who, early in 1840, had walked out of the prison <lb/>gate, with his booklet of religious verses, covered in brown paper, smiling perhaps? <lb/>IV. Intimate Reading: &apos;I am not married but...&apos; <lb/>John King was sentenced to seven years transportation in December 1841 for steal-<lb/>ing old canvas. His conduct record gives his age as twenty-four but he was only <lb/>twenty. 80 In his statement he declared five previous imprisonments: &apos;2 months for <lb/>shoes; 14 days for lathwood; vagrancy 3 months; for soil 14 days; 3 months for steal-<lb/>ing&apos;. In the &apos;Black Books&apos;, his life was tabulated so the convict authorities might <lb/>better monitor his conduct, exploit his labour and identify him if he absconded. As <lb/>James Bradley and Hamish Maxwell-Stewart caution us, their inspection &apos;served to <lb/>remind convicts of their status as subjected (and subjectified) objects of &quot;panopti-<lb/>con&quot; knowledge, imprisoned by descriptions of their own bodies and regulated by <lb/>the internalisation of this knowledge.&apos; 81 <lb/>Yet, in notating the tattooed markings on convict bodies, the penal clerks <lb/>unwittingly recorded many convicts&apos; own embodied statements. In their highly <lb/>original &apos; quantitative deconstruction&apos; and &apos; qualitative exposition&apos; of the indents of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>79 Gaol Keeper&apos;s Journal, 25 and 29 March 1843; William Chapman, 20472, per Mount Stewart Elphin-<lb/>stone (2), 1848, CON33/1/89, CON14//38. <lb/>80 John King, 6533, per Surrey (4), 1842, extra identifier 2, [database no. 40331], CON33/1/27, <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>CON14/1/13. He was baptized 21 May 1822, St Nicholas Church, Yarmouth; England &amp; Wales Chris-<lb/>tening Records. <lb/>81 Bradley and Maxwell-Stewart, &apos;&quot;Behold the Man&quot;: Power, Observation and the Tattooed Convict&apos;, Jour-<lb/>nal of Australian Studies, 12.1 (Summer 1997), pp. 71-97 (p. 75). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>five thousand tattooed convicts, Bradley and Maxwell-Stewart examine the &apos;margin <lb/>between contending constructions of convict subjectivity&apos;, between the &apos;state record&apos; <lb/>and tattoo descriptions, which suggest &apos; a &quot;popular&quot; counter-narrative of mediation, <lb/>resistance and transcendence.&apos; 82 Their approach offers me a method not only of <lb/>deconstructing the quantitative data on the Yarmouth convicts to explore their col-<lb/>lective experience but also of applying these findings in an intimate reading of John <lb/>King&apos;s tattoos. He had begun to decorate his &apos;pockpitted stout made&apos; body as early <lb/>as 1840, when the Gaoler noted &apos;Several pricked letters and marks on both arms&apos;. 83 <lb/>Professional tattooists and designs did not emerge until the 1860s, so King&apos;s tattoos <lb/>will have been made by himself or by companions. 84 Tattooing was one of the illicit <lb/>activities that went on in the cells, undetected. The Gaoler recorded only three occa-<lb/>sions when he discovered inmates pricking themselves in the years 1836-45. Yet <lb/>he had need to remind prisoners of the ban on tattooing, noting, when he caught <lb/>eighteen-year-old James Thirkettle pricking himself, he &apos;had, as well as the whole of <lb/>the Prisoners, been cautioned in that respect.&apos; 85 Tattooing was a common pastime <lb/>aboard the convict ships and, by the end of his voyage, John King had adorned his <lb/>breast, arms and outer left leg using red dye as well as the more typical black and <lb/>blue. While John King&apos;s body art was probably still work-in-progress, his elaborate <lb/>tattoos spectacularly depicted the man he felt himself to be. <lb/>John King was committed to Yarmouth Gaol on eight occasions and, when <lb/>quizzed by the Principal Superintendent of Convicts at Hobart, did not recall his <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>82 Bradley and Maxwell-Stewart, &apos;&quot;Behold the Man&quot;&apos;, p. 77. See also Maxwell-Stewart and Bradley, &apos;Convict <lb/>Tattoos: Tales of Freedom and Coercion&apos;, in Field and Millett (eds.), Convict Love Tokens, pp. 47-52; <lb/>and David Kent, &apos;Decorative Bodies: The Significance of Convicts&apos; Tattoos&apos;, Journal of Australian Stud-<lb/>ies 53 (1997): 78-88. <lb/>83 The description of his body and tattoos are in the Remarks section of the Conduct Record under the <lb/>data on physical characteristics. For King&apos;s early tattoos, see GR, 10 February 1840. <lb/>84 For the practicalities of amateur tattooing, see Ira Dye, &apos;The Tattoos of Early American Seafarers, <lb/>1796-1818&apos;, in Proceedings of the American Philosophy Society 133.4 (1989): 520-54, especially <lb/>pp. 527-32. Thanks to Matt Lodder for this reference. <lb/>85 Gaol Keeper&apos;s Journal, Jan 1836-Dec 1840 (Y/L2 47, Norfork PRO) and Jan 1841-Dec 1845 (Y/L2 48); <lb/>23 July 1845. See Helen Rogers, &apos;Tattooing in Gaol, Conviction: Stories from a Nineteenth Century <lb/>Prison,&apos; http://convictionblog.com/2013/11/15/tattooing-in-gaol/ <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>earliest confinements in 1836 when he was fourteen, the first just a day for being <lb/>absent from his service -a minor infraction he may have forgotten or considered <lb/>irrelevant. His second was on suspicion of felony with four other juveniles. All were <lb/>released after two days. 86 Each returned to gaol; only one escaped transportation. <lb/>The earliest offence King mentioned in his statement was in 1838, when he was <lb/>apprehended as a vagrant near a timber yard with three planks of lathwood. 87 Like <lb/>many of the companions he met inside and outside prison, he supplemented casual <lb/>earnings by scavenging materials; he admitted &apos;removing soil&apos; and &apos;three months <lb/>stealing&apos; (two shovels obtained by false pretences with Richard Thaxter, also sub-<lb/>sequently transported). 88 Work, play and offending shaded into each other; half of <lb/>King&apos;s offences were committed with others. He was lucky to have avoided transpor-<lb/>tation when convicted alone in 1838, his first time for felony, for &apos;stealing 16 pairs of <lb/>shoes value of ten shillings and fifteen pairs of shoes value of 5s&apos;. 89 In all probability, <lb/>this was the event he wished to remind himself of when he etched the date &apos;APRIL <lb/>1838&apos; on his skin; about 40% of dates in convict tattoos coincide with a conviction. 90 <lb/>Like two-thirds of the Yarmouth exiles who had lost at least one parent, John <lb/>King&apos;s mother had died. He commemorated her name in capitals in his tattoos -<lb/>&apos;SARAH KING&apos; -along with the initials of the family members he gave the Convict <lb/>Superintendent. They can be found in the 1841 Census, living on the beach and <lb/>employed in manual labour connected with the port. King&apos;s father Charles was a <lb/>beachman, his elder brother Charles a twinespinner and sister Sarah a beatster, who <lb/>sewed fishing nets for her living, while Carolyn (fourteen) and Susannah (ten) had <lb/>yet to start work. 91 At Yarmouth, as we have seen, boys tended to follow their father&apos;s <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>86 Gaol Committal and Discharge Book, 10 October 1836 and 20 December 1836. <lb/>87 GR, 9 February 1838. <lb/>88 GR, 5 September 1840; Gaol Committal and Discharge Book, 14 May 1838. Robert Thaxten [Thaxter], <lb/>17789, per Maitland, 1844, CON33/1/76, CON17/1/1, p. 236. <lb/>89 GR, 16 April 1838. <lb/>90 GR, 10 February1840. Bradley and Maxwell Stewart, &apos;&quot;Behold the Man&quot;&apos;, p. 85; Kent, &apos;Decorative <lb/>Bodies&apos;, p. 64. <lb/>91 1841 Census, HO 107/794/1. Names and initials were the most common form of convict tattoo; Kent, <lb/>&apos;Decorative Bodies&apos;, p. 83. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>occupation. As a beachman, Charles King will have combed the shore for drift, <lb/>helped to bring in stranded boats, and loaded and unloaded their cargo -irregular, <lb/>unskilled work that drew many men into pilfering. He appears to have wanted some-<lb/>thing else for his sons. Young Charles was learning a trade -rope making -unlike <lb/>John who, following his absence from service, seems to have lost the apprenticeship <lb/>that, most likely, his father had found him, for he was always listed as a labourer in <lb/>the gaol registers. Perhaps John was no longer welcome at home for he was impris-<lb/>oned three times as a vagrant, the last at the start of 1841 when he was found steal-<lb/>ing bones. 92 <lb/>That summer, King was not with his family when the census was taken. Almost <lb/>certainly he was the John King, aged 20, living with three elderly persons and a <lb/>young woman Mary Bowles, also 20, and a baby, John Bowls [sic]. 93 In the gaol and <lb/>conduct records King was listed as single but, though he was under no compunction <lb/>so to do, he volunteered to the Superintendent of Convicts, &apos;I am not married but <lb/>have lived with Mary Ann Balls and had 2 children by her.&apos; In January 1840, when <lb/>King was serving three months for vagrancy and criminal intent, it is possible that <lb/>his sweetheart was imprisoned too. The factory worker Maria Bowler, aged twenty-<lb/>one and single with one child, was imprisoned for seven days for refractory conduct <lb/>in the workhouse. During her sentence, she was taught by Sarah Martin who noted <lb/>in her journal, &apos;She had been extremely unkind to her baby of 6 months old.&apos; Two <lb/>months later, the teacher visited Maria Bowler in the workhouse, finding the young <lb/>mother &apos;much softened in temper and manner&apos;; an improvement Martin attributed <lb/>to solitary confinement and instruction: &apos;She said she did not like being shut up <lb/>alone and not allowed to speak -if she only sang to her baby. Mrs Shuckford [the <lb/>Gaoler&apos;s wife] sends an order that she should be quiet.&apos; 94 But Maria Bowler was sent <lb/>down again the following year for running away from the workhouse with items <lb/>of clothing. John King was again in prison, serving three months for vagrancy. 95 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>92 GR, 15 January 1841. <lb/>93 1841 Census, HO 107/793/5. <lb/>94 GR, 21 January 1840; Martin, Everyday Book, 30 March 1840. <lb/>95 GR, 27 March 1841 for Maria Bowler; 15 Jan 1841 for John King. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>I cannot establish if Mary Ann Balls, Mary Bowles and Maria Bowler were the same <lb/>woman, as seems likely, nor what happened to King&apos;s lover and their children after <lb/>he was transported. <lb/>&apos;I am not here for any thing that is a disgrace&apos; John King had told his Christian <lb/>teacher when imprisoned for vagrancy in 1839. But vagrancy may well have been <lb/>either cause or effect of the apparent rift from his birth family. Certainly it will have <lb/>prevented him from caring effectively for his young family and Mary Ann Balls. Was <lb/>this in his mind when he admitted to the Superintendent of Convicts, &apos;vagrancy <lb/>3 months&apos;? Mary Ann Balls appears to figure in John King&apos;s tattoos, perhaps with <lb/>her two children if the letter-string &apos;EJMB&apos; refers to their initials. Regardless of his <lb/>inability to meet his manly duty as provider for his family, King&apos;s tattoos conveyed <lb/>the romantic ideals of constancy, companionship and hope. As so often in popu-<lb/>lar culture, these ideals were symbolized by a female figure. Two of King&apos;s tattoos <lb/>depicted loving attachment: &apos;man woman in each hand 2 sprigs&apos;; &apos;sailor &amp; woman <lb/>with cross&apos;. Representations of the sailor&apos;s fond farewell or joyful return to his sweet-<lb/>heart frequently adorned love tokens, illustrated songs and broadsides, and will have <lb/>been especially resonant to men like John King, raised in a seaport, who frequently <lb/>sported them in their tattoos. 96 They remind us that popular culture was often more <lb/>sentimental than bawdy in tone and infused with religious sentiment. 97 While con-<lb/>victs commonly identified with the crucified Christ in their tattoos, however, we can-<lb/>not know if John King&apos;s sailor and woman shouldered the cross together or if she <lb/>bore it alone, just as Mary Ann Balls was left to raise her children on her own. 98 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>96 Field and Millett (eds.), Convict Love Tokens. For examples, many containing images similar to those <lb/>in convict tattoos, see the National Museum of Australia&apos;s online exhibition, &apos;Convict Love Tokens&apos;, <lb/>collected by Timothy Millett, http://love-tokens.nma.gov.au/. <lb/>97 Vic Gammon, Desire, Drink and Death in English Folk and Vernacular Song, 1600-1900 (Aldershot: <lb/>Ashgate, 2008). <lb/>98 At least 150 of 5000 male convicts studied by Bradley and Maxwell-Stewart wore a tattooed cross; <lb/>&apos;&quot;Behold the Man&quot;&apos;, p. 95, no. 54. Crucifixions were adopted by more Catholics than Protestants. <lb/>32.3% of Kent&apos;s sample of male convicts from Ireland sported a cross compared with 8.5% of their <lb/>counterparts from England; see &apos;Decorative Bodies&apos;, pp. 81, 86-7. For the sacred and profane in con-<lb/>vict iconography, see also Maxwell-Stewart and Duffield, &apos;Skin Deep Devotions&apos;, in Caplan (ed.), <lb/>Written on the Body. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Though listed as a labourer in the gaol and census records, King gave his occupa-<lb/>tion as fisherman at Hobart. On his left breast, over his heart, was a barque, possibly <lb/>the Surrey on which he was transported but more likely the ship he had wished to <lb/>join, for he also depicted a mermaid, two anchors and fish, all familiar talismans of <lb/>mariners. Where his father worked on the shoreline, John King looked out to sea. The <lb/>name &apos;ROBERT JACUP&apos; was spelled out, almost certainly the 24 year-old Yarmouth <lb/>shipwright with whom King surely enthused about boats. 99 &apos;RJ.AC.OB&apos; appeared on <lb/>the letter string on King&apos;s outside left leg and there was an &apos;R&apos; between his right <lb/>forefinger and thumb. Robert Jacup was clearly a significant other: mentor, lover, <lb/>partner-in-crime? 100 Perhaps they swapped tattoos. <lb/>Tattooing was an integral part of Yarmouth&apos;s sea-faring culture, as it was of <lb/>life aboard the convict ships. 28 of the 34 men from Yarmouth were tattooed on <lb/>arrival in Van Diemen&apos;s Land (82.35%), far more than the 26% of arrivals from <lb/>Scotland. 101 Like other convict body art, John King&apos;s tattoos drew on symbols of <lb/>male prowess -&apos;man with bow &amp; arrow lion eagle&apos; -but others were more ominous <lb/>in tone. There appears to have been a &apos;Bat &amp; [purse?]&apos; -nocturnal and nefarious <lb/>pursuits? -alongside the note to self -&apos;J.K. prepare to meet thy God&apos;. The words <lb/>echoed the hell-fire-and-brimstone preaching of King&apos;s teacher at Yarmouth Gaol <lb/>but did they signal penitence, fatalism, blasphemy? An intimate reading of his tat-<lb/>toos cannot disclose their full meaning but it can show how John King expressed <lb/>himself through the popular cosmology found in other convict tattoos which mixed <lb/>the sacred and profane, light and dark; &apos;J.K. prepare to meet thy God heart &amp; dart <lb/>flowerpot GK ass manshead&apos;. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>99 1841 Census, HO 107/793/7. <lb/>100 Robert Jacup does not appear in the gaol registers, England &amp; Wales Criminal Registers, or records of <lb/>transportation. <lb/>101 James Bradley and Hamish Maxwell-Stewart, &apos;Embodied Explorations: Investigating Convict Tattoos <lb/>and the Transportation System&apos;, in Duffield and Bradley (eds.), Representing Convicts, p. 187. Their <lb/>findings are for much the same period (1840-53) as here. See also James Bradley, &apos;Body Commodifica-<lb/>tion? Class and Tattoos in Victorian Britain&apos;, in Written on the Body, pp. 136-55. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>V. Conclusion <lb/>Cultural historians have alerted us to the significance of narratives in shaping iden-<lb/>tity but have tended to privilege written texts as the source of such narratives and as <lb/>means to their interpretation. John King&apos;s body art suggests an alternative personal <lb/>history to that contained in the terse statements recorded by the convict authority <lb/>and hints at his inner life as well as the man he chose to display to the world. His <lb/>coded words and symbols speak to us suggestively yet elusively. They do not give us <lb/>access to the &apos;real&apos; John King but, when combined with his penal record and other <lb/>data about his life and social relationships, an intimate reading allows us to do a little <lb/>more than speculate on their meaning. <lb/>Understanding about past lives can be derived not just from the texts that <lb/>produce individuals as &apos;subjects&apos; but from the gaps, overlaps, and tensions within <lb/>and between those records. In his much-cited preface to The Making of the English <lb/>Working Class, Edward Thompson proposed that &apos;if we watch [ . . . ] men over an <lb/>adequate period of social change, we observe patterns in their relationships, their <lb/>ideas, and their institutions.&apos; 102 Thompson dismissed the use of quantitative analysis <lb/>in reconstituting such relationships and yet it can enable us to observe patterns in <lb/>social connections and in people&apos;s behaviour that are not always, nor only, observ-<lb/>able in records of their expression. <lb/>Correlating information on individual offending histories in the convict indents <lb/>with Yarmouth Gaol&apos;s admissions registers reveals official documentation substantially <lb/>under-recorded convicts&apos; previous convictions by about by about two-thirds. This has <lb/>important implications for on-going research on persistent offending. Together, the <lb/>Founders and Survivors and Digital Panopticon projects are reconstructing the life-<lb/>courses of convicts sentenced at the Old Bailey and transported to Van Diemen&apos;s Land, <lb/>unprecedented in scale of investigation and forensic detail. But to capture a fuller <lb/>picture of the petty offending histories typical of most convicts, further research will <lb/>be needed linking convict records to sentencing in the lower courts where the vast <lb/></body>

			<page>102 E. P. Thompson, The Making of the English Working Class (New York: Vintage, 1963), p. 11. <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>majority of cases (around 80% at Yarmouth) were heard. Tracking convicts&apos; life his-<lb/>tories backwards as well as forwards will enable us to root &apos; criminal&apos; behaviour in the <lb/>cultures and economies of particular localities, neighbourhoods and households. This <lb/>may assist us to be more precise about the pressures on individuals and families that <lb/>led to &apos; delinquency&apos;, such as the high levels of orphanage that compounded the pov-<lb/>erty and underemployment experienced by many lads and young men from Yarmouth. <lb/>An immersive, intimate practice of reading, of the kind conducted in this article, <lb/>can help us reconstruct from abstracted data on individuals, garnered by officialdom, <lb/>something of the experience and agency of people living in an actual time and place. <lb/>&apos;What good would it do you if you could possibly deceive me?&apos; asked the Yarmouth <lb/>prison teacher Sarah Martin when she accused John King of being a vagrant and <lb/>thief; &apos; even then would not God know what you are? and would you not know your-<lb/>self to be what you are? He looked disconcerted and agreed to this&apos;. We cannot know <lb/>if John King, or indeed Martin&apos;s other scholars sent to Van Diemen&apos;s Land, inter-<lb/>nalized this judgement of self. But grilled by the Superintendent of Convicts, half <lb/>the Yarmouth men were candid about their offending record, stating most, if not <lb/>all, of their convictions, and especially their longer imprisonments. The other half <lb/>were more selective in their account but only five gave no former offences and all <lb/>admitted the crime which had them transported. In the information they supplied <lb/>about their occupations and families, the Yarmouth convicts were largely credible <lb/>witnesses to their own life histories. When their statements are read alongside other <lb/>records about their lives, we learn some of what Sarah Martin could not know but <lb/>also much that she did: that most had lost parents or become disengaged from their <lb/>family; that regular work and family ties were sources of stability and that lack of <lb/>employment and supervision could undermine those ties; and so too could the lure <lb/>of companionship and conviviality rooted in the masculine, rough-and-ready, com-<lb/>ing-a-going street culture of the seaport. In his vibrant tattoos, John King&apos;s body bore <lb/>that culture&apos;s attractions, its spirit, and its costs: <lb/>Barque on left breast mermaid man woman in each hand 2 sprigs man with <lb/>bow &amp; arrow lion eagle EJMB sun half moon 3 stars heart &amp; darts &amp; several <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rogers: &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos; <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>red marks APRIL 1838 M AM 2 anchors fish ROBERT JACUP on right arm R <lb/>between forefinger &amp; thumb right hand sailor &amp; woman with cross Bat &amp; <lb/>[purse?] JK prepare to meet thy God heart &amp; dart flowerpot GK ass manshead <lb/>SK CK INGWI SARAH KING SH SK on left arm [RJACOB] on outside of left leg <lb/>Competing Interests <lb/>The author declares that they have no competing interests. <lb/>Acknowledgements <lb/>Generous research funding from Liverpool John Moores University and the hospital-<lb/>ity of Clare and Hamish Maxwell-Stewart, Trudy Cowley, Lucy Frost, and Julia Clark <lb/>enabled me to conduct archival research for this article in Tasmania. I would like to <lb/>thank staff at Great Yarmouth Museums, the Norfolk Record Office, and the State <lb/>Archives of Tasmania for assistance in using their collections. Zoe Alker and John <lb/>Herson gave me invaluable support in creating access databases. I am indebted to the <lb/>editor, Melodee Beals, the anonymous readers, Martin Eve, and the following friends <lb/>who responded insightfully to drafts at various stages in this study&apos;s long gestation: <lb/>Zoe Alker, Meg Arnot, Trev Broughton, Thomas Dixon, Barry Godfrey, John Herson, <lb/>Ruth Livesey, Lucinda Matthews-Jones and Hamish Maxwell-Stewart. Thanks also to <lb/>audience feedback on papers given at the Institute of Historical, NAVSA/BAVS/AVSA <lb/>(2013), and the University of Tampere. <lb/></body>

			<front>How to cite this article: Rogers, H 2015 &apos;A Very Fair Statement of His Past Life&apos;: <lb/>Transported Convicts, Former Lives and Previous Offences. Open Library of Humanities, <lb/>1(1): e3, pp. 1-35, DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.16995/olh.27 <lb/>Submitted: 05 October 2015 <lb/>Copyright: © 2015 The Author(s). This is an open-access article distributed under the <lb/>terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License (CC-BY 3.0), which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original author and source are credited. See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/. <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Open Library of Humanities is a peer-reviewed open <lb/>access journal published by Open Library of Humanities. </front>


	</text>
</tei>
