<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory Regime?</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Muhammed Shabir</forename>
          <surname>Korotana</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T09:02:56.827Z">30/01/2026 10:02:56</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1093__slr__hmv019</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2016</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1093/slr/hmv019</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Muhammed Shabir Korotana. (2016). The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory Regime?. Statute Law Review, 37(3), 195-211. DOI: 10.1093/slr/hmv019</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T14:39:30.053316Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-19T14:39:30.053316Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T08:47:26.104Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections 1 Part</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T14:02:56.413Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Done</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T14:02:56.433Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Done</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T14:02:56.445Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Done</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-09T08:12:10.431Z" status="checked" who="#li">
      <desc>Second pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-09T15:40:12.591Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T09:04:01.609Z" status="candidate" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
  <!--bei diesem Texte viele unsicher Passagen durch z.b. die Seitenangaben und Anmerkunegn am Rand -->

    <!-- production credit and numbers on the side irrelevant to the article contents should not be annotated -->
    
			
    <front>Copyedited by: MS <lb/>Statute Law Review, 2015, Vol. 00, No. 00, 1-17 <lb/>doi:10.1093/slr/hmv019 <lb/>The Financial Services (Banking <lb/>Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? <lb/>Muhammed Korotana* <lb/>A BSTR ACT <lb/>The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013 includes the government&apos;s reform <lb/>of the banking industry regarding &apos;ring-fencing&apos; and the &apos;electrification&apos; of the ring-<lb/>fence. The ring-fencing provisions in the Act are based on Sir John Vickers&apos; Report <lb/>and the recommendations from the Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards <lb/>(PCBS). The PCBS argument was that the envisaged &apos;ring-fence&apos; regulation in the <lb/>Bill, based on Sir John Vickers&apos; report, fell short of expectations, and would be easily <lb/>breached by unscrupulous bankers; therefore it recommended that to strengthen it fur-<lb/>ther, the ring-fence should be fortified with more punitive regulatory measures, dubbed <lb/>as &apos;electrifying the ring-fence&apos;. This &apos;electrification&apos; seems to be an innovative idea to <lb/>solve the problems envisaged; however, it is argued that this idea is not without theo-<lb/>retical problems of its own. Also, it is suggested that to solve behavioural and structural <lb/>problems within banking institutions, the Act could have benefited from a regulatory <lb/>regime based on the concept of &apos;whistle-blowers&apos; and economic incentives, also found <lb/>in section 922 of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and the Consumer Protection Act <lb/>(Dodd-Frank Act). <lb/></front>
    
    <body>PA RT 1 <lb/>1. . IN TROD UC TION <lb/>The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013 (Banking Reforms Act) (the Act) <lb/>received Royal Assent on 18 December 2013. The Act implements the final recom-<lb/>mendations of the Independent Commission on Banking (the Commission), set up <lb/>by the government in 2010 to consider structural reform of the banking sector. 1 The <lb/>Act, among others, 2 primarily focuses on the sector&apos;s structural problems, and hence <lb/></body>
    
    <front>* <lb/>Brunel Law School, Brunel University, Uxbridge, UK. <lb/></front>
    
    <listBibl>1 <lb/>Final Report, Recommendations, Independent Commission on Banking, September 2011, http://bankingcommission. <lb/>independent.gov.uk/ <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">2 <lb/>The large UK banking groups are required to hold equity and other regulatory capital to absorb losses. Also, four key areas <lb/>form the focus of the Banking Reforms Act: supervision, culture, competition, and structure. <lb/></note>
    
    1.5 <lb/>AQ2 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>1.20 <lb/>AQ3 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>1.30 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>1.39 <lb/>

			<front>© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@ <lb/>oup.com. <lb/>• 1 <lb/></front>
    
    Copyedited by: MS <lb/>
    
    AQ1 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.10 <lb/>2.15 <lb/>2.20 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>2.30 <lb/>2.35 <lb/>2.40 <lb/>2.45 <lb/>2.46 <lb/>
    
    <page>Page 2 of 17 •</page>
    
    <note place="headnote"> The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? <lb/></note>
        
			<body>recommends structural regulation and a command and control strategy 3 in the form <lb/>of &apos;ring-fencing&apos;-the concept of a firewall between retail, deposit-taking banking, and <lb/>riskier investment banking. This means that retail banking should be separated from <lb/>wholesale or investment banking within a banking group. 4 The Act focuses on the prin-<lb/>ciple that it should be easier and less costly to bring about the resolution of a bank when <lb/>it gets into financial difficulties. This simply means determining which activities of a <lb/>failing bank must be allowed to continue in an orderly manner. This regulatory strategy <lb/>is meant to ensure the continuous provision of a vital service to the economy and the <lb/>customers of a bank. 5 The implicit policy objective is to curtail moral hazard 6 as well as <lb/>the idea that the banks could rely on the implicit guarantees of the government as they <lb/>are seen to be &apos;too big to fail&apos;, 7 and that the government stands as a lender of last resort 8 <lb/>for the failing banks. <lb/>At the Bill 9 stage, the process was joined by the recommendations from the <lb/>Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards (PCBS), 10 dubbed as &apos;electrification&apos; <lb/>of the ring-fence, meaning a further strengthening of the ring-fence mechanism. The <lb/>PCBS published its report on the draft Bank Reform Bill on 11 March 2013, 11 whereby <lb/>it challenged the government&apos;s reform of the banking industry. The PCBS was of the <lb/>opinion that the government&apos;s reform of the banking industry fell short of what was <lb/>required. 12 The PCBS identified a number of challenges that a new structural framework <lb/>(ring-fence) for banks would face. 13 In view of these challenges, the PCBS believed that <lb/>the ring-fencing proposals as they stood in the Bill might &apos;not be sufficient to achieve <lb/>the government&apos;s policy objectives. 14 The PCBS recommended &apos;a series of measures to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>3 <lb/>B Morgan and K Yeung, An Introduction to Law and Regulation (CUP 2007), 80-85; R Baldwin and M Cave, Understanding <lb/>Regulation (2nd edn OUP 2012), 106-107; R Baldwin, &apos;Regulation: After Command and Control&apos;, in K Hawkins (ed.), The <lb/>Human Face of Law (OUP 1997); T Daintith, &apos;The Techniques of Government&apos; in J Jowell and D Oliver (eds.), The Changing <lb/>Constitution (Oxford: Clarendon Press), 209-236; C Veljanovski, &apos;Economic Approaches to Regulation&apos;, in R Baldwin, <lb/>M Cave and M Lodge, The Oxford Handbook of Regulation (OUP 2010), 27-28 and 33-34; see also C Coglianese and E <lb/>Mendelson, &apos;Meta-Regulation and Self-Regulation&apos;, in R Baldwin, M Cave and M Lodge, The Oxford Handbook of Regulation <lb/>(OUP 2010), 146-151. <lb/>4 <lb/>See M Blair, G Waker and R Purves, Financial Services Law (OUP 2014), 648-652. <lb/>5 <lb/>The Government response to the ICB recommendations was published on 19 December 2011; see Cm 8252 Government <lb/>response to the Independent Commission on Banking. Further developed Government proposals were set in the White Paper, <lb/>Cm 8356 Banking reforms: delivering stability and supporting a sustainable economy. <lb/>6 <lb/>R Baldwin and M Cave, (n 1) 20; IG MacNeil, An Introduction to The Law on Financial Investment (Hart 2012), 31-32; see <lb/>generally, G Calabresi, The Cost of Accidents: A Legal and Economic Analysis (New Haven 1970). <lb/>7 <lb/>See generally, E Greene et al., &apos;A Closer Look at &apos; Too big to Fail&apos;: National and International Approaches to Addressing <lb/>the Risk of Large, International Financial Institutions&apos;Capital Markets Law Journal 2(5), 117; AR Sorkin, Too Big to Fail, <lb/>(Harmondsworth: Penguin 2010). <lb/>8 <lb/>TM Humphrey and RE Kelcher, &apos;The Lender of Last Resort: A Historical Perspective&apos; Cato Journal 4, 275; X Freixas, C <lb/>Giannini, G Hoggarth and F Soussa, &apos;Lender of Last Resort -A Review of the Literature&apos;, in C Goodhart and G Illing (eds), <lb/>Financial Crisis, Contagion, and the Lender of the Last Resort (OUP 2002); A Campbell and R Lastra, &apos;Revisiting the Lender <lb/>of Last Resort-The Role of the Bank of England&apos;, in I MacNeil and O&apos;Brien (eds), The Future of Financial Regulation, 2010, <lb/>161-178. <lb/>9 <lb/>The Bill was published on 10 October 2012 in Cm 8453 Sound Banking: Delivering Reform. This was to enable pre-legislative <lb/>scrutiny of the Bill by the PCBS. <lb/>10 <lb/>See PCBS First report (HL98-HC848), Second report (HL 126-HC 1012) and the Final report, Changing Banking for <lb/>Good (HL 27-1-HC 175-1). <lb/>11 <lb/>HL Paper 126 HC 1012. <lb/>12 <lb/>Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards&apos; Final Report (n 11). <lb/>13 <lb/>First Report, paras 63-78, (n 11), and HL Paper 98 of session 1012. <lb/>14 <lb/>First Report, para 94 (n 11). <lb/></listBibl>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>
      
      <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart <lb/>Regulatory Regime?</note>
    
    <page>• Page 3 of 17 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>reinforce the ring-fence in order to increase the prospect of it proving durable in the <lb/>long-run&apos; 15 and &apos;…to create a significant new disincentive for banks seeking over time <lb/>to test the ring-fence with a view to undermining its effectiveness&apos;. 16 <lb/>In this context, the PCBS made two distinct recommendations to be included in <lb/>the Bill in terms of &apos;first and second reserve powers&apos; (electrification provision). These <lb/>two reserve powers, punitive in nature, were meant to deter bankers from unscrupu-<lb/>lously breaching the ring-fence. These recommendations were the specific proposals <lb/>for &apos;electrification&apos; of the ring-fence of banks, implying that banks need to be incen-<lb/>tivized to respect the integrity of the ring-fence. 17 The first recommendation 18 (first <lb/>reserve power) is included in the Act 19 ; however, the second 20 recommendation (sec-<lb/>ond power), which was to exercise full separation across the banking sector as a whole, <lb/>meaning to enforce a complete structural separation across the sector, was ignored by <lb/>parliament. 21 Thus, the Act includes government&apos;s reform of the banking industry in <lb/>respect of &apos;ring-fencing&apos; and &apos;electrification&apos; of ring-fencing, with a watered-down ver-<lb/>sion of electrification. <lb/>The Banking Reforms Act is a unique milestone in the history of banking regula-<lb/>tion in the United Kingdom. The prior banking regulation in the United Kingdom, <lb/>since the hay days of self-regulation, 22 unlike the US regulatory culture, 23 was largely <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>15 <lb/>See Second Report, para 5; also First Report, para 126. The Commission&apos;s report was supported by Sir John Vickers as to <lb/>increasing the durability and permanence of the ring-fence (quoted in Second Report, para 5). <lb/>16 <lb/>See Second Report, para 8. <lb/>17 <lb/>A Tyrie MP said that &apos;[F]or the ring-fence to succeed, banks need to be discouraged from gaming the rules. All history tells <lb/>us they will do this unless incentivised not to&apos;, 21 December 2012, The Telegraph. <lb/>18 <lb/>Second Report, para 10: The first power would &apos;enable the regulator to take steps that could lead to a specific banking group <lb/>affected by the ring-fence being required to divest itself fully of either its ring-fenced or its non-ring-fenced bank. This power <lb/>could thus be exercised in respect of an individual bank (or more than one if necessary) while retaining the benefits across <lb/>the sector as a whole of diversification…&apos; <lb/>Second Report, para 11: An individual banking group could be obliged to full separation of retail and wholesale activities. See, <lb/>how the first reserve power might work, and also several safeguards: &apos; a) A stipulation that the regulator could only commence the <lb/>process if it felt there was a significant risk to the objectives of the ring-fence; b) A provision that the power would not be exercis-<lb/>able before the first independent review of the effectiveness of the ring-fence (an independent review which we discuss in the next <lb/>section of this Report); c) A requirement for the regulator to give a banking group early notice of any intention to use the reserve <lb/>power; d) The appointment of an external reviewer to consider the relationship between the banking group concerned and the <lb/>regulator; e) A right of appeal in relation to the exercise of the power; and f) A Treasury power to override implementation.&apos; <lb/>19 <lb/>See FSMA 2000, section 142. <lb/>20 <lb/>Second Report, para 25: &apos;Alongside our proposal for a group-specific regulatory power to enforce full structural separation, <lb/>we recommended that the independent review should be required to assess the case for a move to full separation across the <lb/>banking sector as a whole&apos;. See also First Report, paras 164, 171. <lb/>21 <lb/>Second Report, paras 25-28. The government rejected the case for a &apos;second reserve power on various grounds: &apos;First, it con-<lb/>tends that passing such legislation would entail the Government pursuing a &apos;different policy&apos; from that contained in the Bill, a <lb/>policy which in the Government&apos;s view would be based on the assumption that the ring-fence might fail, when the Government <lb/>does not itself believe that the ring-fence will fail. Second, the Government argues that &apos;it is not necessary to legislate now for <lb/>a reserve power to abandon ring-fencing at some point in the future&apos;, because this is a decision best made by Government and <lb/>Parliament at the time. Third, it contends that it would be wrong for the final decision on whether to bring in such a radical <lb/>change to be in the hands of the regulator rather than for Government and Parliament.&apos; (Second Report, para 26). <lb/>22 <lb/>Before 1979, with some exceptions, a deposit-taking institution in the United Kingdom did not require any licence or author-<lb/>ization: see Lord Steyn eloquently elaborates this fact in his judgment in Three Rivers District Council and Others v Governor <lb/>and Company of the Bank of England (HL) 18 May 2000, 2000 WL 571203; C Hadjiemmanuil, &apos;The Bank of England and the <lb/>Lessons from Barings: UK Banking Regulation under Parliamentary Scrutiny&apos;, 1 Y.B. Int&apos;l Fin. &amp; Econ. L. 1996, 333. <lb/>23 <lb/>The idea of separation of commercial and invest banking first appeared in National Bank Act of 1866 and it was reintroduced <lb/>in Glass-Steagall Act of 1933 and finally again in Dodd-Frank Act 2010. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    3.5 <lb/>3.10 <lb/>3.15 <lb/>3.20 <lb/>3.25 <lb/>3.30 <lb/>3.35 <lb/>3.40 <lb/>3.45 <lb/>3.46 <lb/>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>

			<page>Page 4 of 17 •</page>
    
    <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? <lb/></note>
    
    4.5 <lb/>4.10 <lb/>4.15 <lb/>4.20 <lb/>4.25 <lb/>4.30 <lb/>4.35 <lb/>4.40 <lb/>4.45 <lb/>4.46 <lb/>
    
    <body>non-structural in nature and did not require the separation of commercial and invest-<lb/>ment banking; the experiment of such structural regulation in the United States can be <lb/>traced back to National Bank Act of 1866. The Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 <lb/>(FSMA) and the regulatory response 24 to the 2007-08 financial crisis in the form of <lb/>the Banking Act 2009 were believed to be insufficient for the regulatory requirements <lb/>of the present times. The Banking Reforms Act, in this sense, ushers in the new era of <lb/>financial regulation and makes a clear-cut watershed in the development of banking <lb/>regulation in the United Kingdom. <lb/>However, this article highlights the theoretical shortcomings of the idea of electrifi-<lb/>cation of the ring-fence and questions its necessity as a corrective regulatory tool. Also, <lb/>it is argued that the emphasis on structural regulation in the context of electrification <lb/>leaves out some of the important behavioural issues. Behavioural regulation 25 is equally <lb/>important as compared to structural regulation, as is manifested across the developed <lb/>world. 26 In this context, the article advocates the usefulness of the concept of &apos;whistle-<lb/>blowers&apos; as an alternative regulatory tool to the costly and disruptive solution of &apos;elec-<lb/>trification of ring-fence&apos;. <lb/>Part 1 deals with the definitional issues of ring-fencing as well as the justification, <lb/>theoretical basis and strategy of regulation in the context of ring-fencing regulation as <lb/>found in the Act. Part 2 deals with the idea of &apos;electrification&apos;. Part 3 deals with the idea <lb/>of &apos;a whistle-blower&apos;. Finally, the article concludes that the idea of &apos;electrification&apos; has <lb/>its own theoretical shortcomings and that the Act should have included the idea of <lb/>&apos;whistle-blower&apos; provisions, incentivizing employees as a major strategy of regulation. <lb/>2. . R ING -FE NC ING A ND THE &apos; ELECTR IFIC ATION&apos; OF <lb/>THE R ING -FENCE <lb/>A. Defining the Ring-Fence <lb/>Ring-fencing is a relatively old concept, which has been used as a trouble-shooter or <lb/>panacea to solve problems in a number of sectors. It has been used as a regulatory solu-<lb/>tion in banking and many other utility sectors; however, since the 2007 financial cri-<lb/>sis, it has been a buzzword for financial regulatory reform across many jurisdictions. <lb/>Perhaps this is the only idea available that has been well tested and immortalized in a <lb/>number of past regulatory reforms. In the context of financial regulation, the idea first <lb/>came to light as a concept in the United States in the National Bank Act of 1866; it <lb/>introduced an idea of partial separation of the banking sector. Then, in the aftermath <lb/>of the Great Depression, the concept of the ring-fence gained further impetus and was <lb/>introduced in the legislative form in the Glass-Steagal Act; this introduced the idea of <lb/>complete structural separation of investment and commercial banking. In the aftermath <lb/>of the 2007-08 financial crises, finally, yet again, ring-fencing took centre stage in the <lb/>Dodd-Frank Act 2010. So, the nature of regulation in this context has long been settled <lb/>in favour of partial or complete separation. The concept of ring-fencing may not sound <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>24 <lb/>CAE Goodhart, The Regulatory Response to the Financial Crisis&apos;, Edward Elgar, 2009. <lb/>25 <lb/>E Avgouleas, &apos;What Future for Disclosure as a Regulatory Technique? Lessons from Behavioural Decision Theory and the <lb/>Global Financial Crisis&apos; in MacNeil and O&apos;Brien (eds) (n 9), 205-225. <lb/>26 <lb/>For example, whistle-blower regulation in Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act and SOX. See <lb/>below Part 2. <lb/></listBibl>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>
      
      <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart <lb/>Regulatory Regime? </note>
    
    <page>• Page 5 of 17 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>an innovative idea; however, its functional application may refute that argument. For <lb/>example, the place and height of the ring-fence in the Banking Reform Act itself, as <lb/>discussed below, is innovative. <lb/>Ring-fencing is a financial regulatory concept when used for financial institutions, <lb/>including banks. In conceptual terms, the ring-fencing primarily means reorganizing <lb/>the allocation of risk 27 optimally for the purpose of reducing the risk that is associated <lb/>with the activities of a company. 28 However, the question is how one can define ring-<lb/>fencing as a financial regulatory concept in a legal sense. It has always been difficult to <lb/>form an abstract definition of a concept which has a number of functional applications, <lb/>let alone in law but in other disciplines as well; therefore the unsurmountable problem <lb/>is &apos;the lack of an agreed-upon methodology on how to…define legal concepts.&apos; 29 Ring-<lb/>fencing is a functional concept rooted in pragmatism with real economic consequences <lb/>and is incapable of normative definition 30 ; the functional approach avoids unwanted <lb/>interpretations. 31 So, the concept of a ring-fence should be defined functionally, taking <lb/>into account all the intended functions of a ring-fence. For example, if the functions <lb/>of the ring-fence are to make a firm&apos;s bankruptcy remote, to help a firm operate on a <lb/>stand-alone basis, to preserve a firm&apos;s business and assets, or to limit a firm&apos;s risky activi-<lb/>ties and investment, then the concept of ring-fencing should be defined accordingly. <lb/>Notwithstanding, in all these cases regulation is used to reallocate the risk optimally for <lb/>the purpose of reducing risk for the companies. <lb/>Because the concept is used in different contexts and scenarios, its definition and <lb/>specific application each time are different. So, each context or scenario produces its <lb/>own &apos;functional definition&apos; by answering a simple question-what is the &apos;function&apos; of a <lb/>particular ring-fencing, and, in other words, what is the function of a particular regula-<lb/>tory reform? What are the objectives that these functions will achieve? So, in a theoreti-<lb/>cal analysis, if the aim of the ring-fence is to achieve stability, the functions or objectives <lb/>of the ring-fence are to achieve that particular aim and the strategies to achieve these <lb/>objectives are the methodologies. 32 <lb/>Thus, one can argue that ring-fencing is a functional financial regulatory concept <lb/>regarding financial institutions, which entails economic consequences. 33 The lack of <lb/>an agreed-upon methodology regarding how to define this legal concept normatively <lb/>causes problems, 34 and it can therefore only be defined in view of its functions. Because <lb/>the concept can only be understood due to its foundation in a common practice in the <lb/>context of banking and finance, ideally that is how this should be defined rather than in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>27 <lb/>See generally J Black. &apos;The Role of Risk in Regulatory Process&apos;, in R Baldwin, M Cave and M Lodge, (n 1) p 302; &apos;The term is <lb/>also used in a regulatory sense to describe a way of managing a corporation where certain parts of the business could be ring <lb/>fenced to ensure that losses in one part did not affect another&apos;, See Financial Times Lexicon. <lb/>28 <lb/>SL Schwarcz, Ring-fencing , 87 S. Cal. L. Rev, (2013), 5. <lb/>29 <lb/>L Kahler, &apos;The Influence of Normative Reasons on the Formation of Legal Concepts&apos; in Concepts in Law 81, 90 ( JC Hage <lb/>and D Pfordten eds., 2009); See also, D Patterson, Dworkin on the &apos;Semantics of Legal Political Concepts,&apos; [2006] Oxford <lb/>Journal of Legal Studies 26, 552, 553 . <lb/>30 <lb/>SL Schwarcz (n 28) p 14; See also, SL Schwarcz, What is Securitisation? And for What Purpose? [2012] The Southern <lb/>California Law Review, 1283, 1289. <lb/>31 <lb/>L Kahler (n 29) 90, &apos;[i]f all concerned people understand concepts A, B and C in a specific way due to their foundation in … <lb/>common practice, it is preferable to use them rather than the more abstract concept of D that contains A, B and C.&apos; <lb/>32 <lb/>SL Schwarcz (n 28) 5-6, 15. <lb/>33 <lb/>Ibid. <lb/>34 <lb/>L Kahler (n 29) 90. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    5.5 <lb/>5.10 <lb/>5.15 <lb/>5.20 <lb/>5.25 <lb/>A 5Q .3 40 <lb/>5.35 <lb/>5.40 <lb/>5.45 <lb/>5.46 <lb/>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>
    
    <page>Page 6 of 17 •</page>
    
    <note place="headnote"> The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory Regime? <lb/></note>

			6.5 <lb/>6.10 <lb/>6.15 <lb/>6.20 <lb/>6.25 <lb/>6.30 <lb/>6.35 <lb/>6.40 <lb/>6.45 <lb/>6.46 <lb/>
    
    <body>a normative sense, which would be a mere abstraction and would lack usefulness. Once <lb/>the functions of the ring-fence have been identified and the concept of ring-fencing has <lb/>adequately been defined from its functional perspective, then and only then should the <lb/>regulation be designed and defined accordingly. <lb/>The Banking Reforms Act adopts the functional definition of the concept of ring-<lb/>fencing; it espouses the idea of ring-fencing of certain activities. 35 The important issues <lb/>relating to the ring-fence are its location and height in a given context to achieve the <lb/>objectives of the legislation. All household and Small and Medium-sized Enterprises <lb/>(SME) deposit-taking and current account provision must take place within the ring-<lb/>fenced bank, and the ring-fenced banks are barred from operating a range of <lb/>wholesale and investment banking activities. A num-ber of provisions in the Act <lb/>relate to the &apos;location&apos; of the ring-fence, about defining, and allowing the government <lb/>to define, concepts and activities, 36 and also determine which activities must or must <lb/>not be carried out within the ring-fenced banks. 37 <lb/>The relevant provision in the Act regarding the &apos;height&apos; of the ring-fence requires the <lb/>regulator to make rules for a ring-fenced bank, ensuring that it can work independently of <lb/>the group and that the ring-fenced banks&apos; core activities are not jeopardized by the acts or <lb/>omissions of other persons; the rules must also cover intra-group exposures, independ-<lb/>ent corporate governance, and payment of dividends. 38 The &apos;electrification&apos; regulation is <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>35 <lb/>Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013, Explanatory Notes: &apos;section 4: Ring-fencing of certain activities <lb/>26 Section 4(1) inserts new Part 9B (ring-fencing) into FSMA. <lb/>27 New section 142A(1) defines &apos;ring-fenced body&apos; for the purposes of FSMA, as any UK institution which carries on at least <lb/>one core activity for which it has been given a Part 4A permission under FSMA. Subsection (2) excludes building societies <lb/>from the definition of &apos;ring-fenced bodies&apos; and gives the Treasury power to exclude other institutions from the definition by <lb/>order. This power will enable the Treasury to provide that only banks above a certain size will be required to be &apos;ring-fenced <lb/>bodies&apos;. Subsection (3) sets out the condition which must be satisfied before the Treasury is able to make such an order: <lb/>the Treasury must be satisfied that excluding the classes of institution in question from the definition of a ring-fenced body <lb/>would not harm the continued provision in the United Kingdom of core services. Subsection (4) requires the Treasury to <lb/>consider the impact the exercise of their powers to exempt certain UK institutions from the definition of &apos;ring-fenced body&apos; <lb/>might have on competition in the provision of core services, and whether any adverse impact might be mitigated. Subsection <lb/>(6) allows the Treasury to set conditions on the grant of an exemption from the definition of a &apos;ring-fenced body&apos;, and subsec-<lb/>tion (7) defines &apos;UK institution&apos; for the purposes of the section. <lb/>28 New section 142B defines &apos;core activity&apos; for the purpose of FSMA. Subsection (2) provides that the regulated activity of <lb/>accepting deposits is to be a core activity, but also gives the Treasury power to provide for exceptions to this, by making an <lb/>order setting out circumstances in which accepting deposits is not to be treated as a core activity. The Treasury therefore have <lb/>power to provide (for example) that accepting deposits of high net-worth individuals, or large corporate entities, is not a core <lb/>activity, so that such deposits may be held in banks which are neither ring-fenced bodies nor exempt under section 142A(2) <lb/>from the obligations that apply to ring-fenced bodies&apos;. See also, Schwarcz (n 10) 5-6, 14-15. <lb/>36 <lb/>The Act also provides the Treasury with a range of delegated powers: (i) Defines a class of institutions which should not be <lb/>regarded as &apos;ring-fenced bodies &apos;even if they otherwise meet the definition (section 142A(2)(b)); (ii) Defines circumstances <lb/>in which accepting deposits is not to be regarded as a &apos;core activity&apos; (section 142B(2)); (iii) Defines circumstances in which <lb/>a regulated activity other than accepting deposits is to be regarded as a &apos;core activity&apos; (section 142B(5)); (iv) Defines circum-<lb/>stances in which dealing in investments as principal is not to be regarded as an &apos;excluded activity&apos; (section 142D(2)); (v) Add <lb/>any other activity to the definition of &apos;excluded activity&apos; (section 142D(4)); (vi) Impose prohibitions on what a &apos;ring-fenced <lb/>body&apos; can do in relation to specific categories of transaction, establishing branches in specific countries, or holding shares in <lb/>companies of a specified type (section 142E). <lb/>37 <lb/>See The Act (inserted provisions in the FSMA 2000 as follows: (i) Defines a &apos;ring-fenced body&apos; as one which conducts &apos;core <lb/>activities&apos; (section142A); (ii) Defines the regulated activity of accepting household and SME deposits as a &apos;core activity&apos; <lb/>(section 142B); (iii) Defines the regulated activity of &apos;dealing in investments as principal&apos; as an &apos;excluded activity&apos; (section <lb/>142D); (iv) Establishes that any &apos;ring-fended body&apos; which carries on an &apos;excluded activity&apos; is in breach of its regulatory <lb/>requirements (section 142G). <lb/>38 <lb/>FSMA, 142H. This is the only section of the Act which refers to the &apos;height&apos; of the ring-fence. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    AQ5 <lb/>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>
      
      <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart <lb/>Regulatory Regime?</note>
    
    <page>• Page 7 of 17 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>designed to prohibit certain kinds of behaviour or demand some positive actions from a <lb/>financial institution. Non-compliance with these regulations results in serious sanctions. <lb/>Arguably, &apos;electrification&apos; of ring-fencing represents &apos;a crucial building block for <lb/>establishing a safer and more secure banking system in the United Kingdom… (which) <lb/>could bring significant benefits for public policy and for banking&apos;. 39 The Prudential <lb/>Regulation Authority&apos;s ( PRA) general objective is to promote the safety and <lb/>soundness of the institutions that it regulates. 40 The general objective is reflected in the <lb/>Act and it reflects the implicit policy objective <lb/>of curtailing the moral hazard. <lb/>B. &apos;Electrification&apos; of the Ring-Fence <lb/>There is a widely held fear that bankers will aim to undermine ring-fencing by getting <lb/>around the new legislation 41 ; this view is based on the theory that private individuals <lb/>will always seek to subvert the workings of regulations to benefit themselves. 42 Without <lb/>a clearly defined ring-fence, there is a risk that bankers will be able to pull the wool <lb/>over the eyes of the regulators. For example, the ring-fencing attempts by the National <lb/>Bank Act of 1866 43 and the Glass-Steagall Act of 1933 44 were frustrated by the banks <lb/>establishing investment affiliates to get around the prohibition, 45 and by intense bank <lb/>lobbying, which paved the way for the repeal of key provisions of the Glass-Steagall <lb/>Act in 1999. 46 Even before the repeal, the ring-fence was seriously weakened by the <lb/>interpretation of the legislation through negotiations between the financial institutions <lb/>and the regulators. 47 In this type of negotiations, the judgment of regulators often ends <lb/>up losing ground in favour of powerful lobbying and interest groups, and the regulation <lb/>often ends up being &apos;captured&apos;. 48 This clearly amounts to subversion of justice. 49 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>39 <lb/>Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards, Second Report, HC (2012-13) p 3 and HL Paper 126 of session 1012. <lb/>[Second Report]. <lb/>40 <lb/>Second Report, paras 29-30. <lb/>41 <lb/>Mervyn King, before Banking Standards Commission, Financial Times, 22/23 November 2012. <lb/>42 <lb/>EL Glaeser and A Shleifer, &apos;The rise of the Regulatory State&apos; [2003] Journal of Economic Literature XLI, 401. <lb/>43 <lb/>The National Bank Act 1864 established the OCC and the federal bank charter; it introduced limitations on bank&apos;s capacity <lb/>to engage in non-banking activities which ring-fenced the banks prior to the US deposit insurance. Before that a number of <lb/>States that had banking charters (e.g. New York) had same type of provisions. <lb/>44 <lb/>The Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act, also known as the Financial Services Modernisation Act of 1999 [enacted on November <lb/>12 1999] repealed part of the Glass-Steagall Act of 1933. The repeal removed barriers in the market among banking, securi-<lb/>ties, and insurance companies that prohibited any one financial institution from acting as any combination of an invest-<lb/>ment bank, a commercial bank and an insurance company. Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act enabled commercial banks, investment <lb/>banks, securities firms, and insurance companies to consolidate under one roof. <lb/>45 <lb/>To get around the ring-fence most banks created affiliates. For example, National City Bank in 1911 and Chase National Bank in 1917, <lb/>both established affiliates that wereable to transact securities business through their &apos;parent&apos; banks prohibited from. National City Bank <lb/>being a New York state charted bank and Chase National Bank being a National Bank were subject to the National Bank Act. <lb/>46 <lb/>See generally, JG Benston, &apos;Is Government Regulation of Banks Necessary?&apos;[2000] Journal of Financial Services Research <lb/>18(2/3), 186. <lb/>47 <lb/>For example, The Glass-Steagall Act was chipped away by a series of administrative developments and rulings which allowed <lb/>commercial banks to indulge in investment activities, see F Tregenna, &apos;The Fat Years: The Structure and Profitability of the <lb/>US Banking Sector in the Pre-Crisis Period&apos; Cambridge Journal of Economics 33(4), 609-632. <lb/>48 <lb/>See &apos;capture&apos; or &apos;special interest&apos; theories of regulation: G Stigler, &apos;Theories of Economic Regulation&apos; [1971] Bell Journal of <lb/>Economics, 3-21; S Peltzman, &apos;Toward a More General Theory of Regulation&apos; [1976] The Journal of Law Economics 19(2), <lb/>211; F McChesney, &apos;Rent Extraction and Rent Creation in the Economic Theory of Regulation&apos; [1987] Journal of Legal <lb/>Studies 16(1), 101. These authors question the motives and capabilities of the regulators. <lb/>49 <lb/>EL Glaeser and A Shleifer, &apos;The Rise of the Regulatory State&apos; Journal of Economic Literature, American Economic Association <lb/>41(2), 401-425, June, 401. <lb/>&gt;</listBibl>
    
   A 7Q .5 6 <lb/>7.10 <lb/>7.15 <lb/>7.20 <lb/>7.25 <lb/>7.30 <lb/>7.35 <lb/>7.40 <lb/>7.45 <lb/>7.46 <lb/>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>

			<page>Page 8 of 17 • </page>
    
    <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? <lb/></note>
    
    8.5 <lb/>AQ7 <lb/>8.10 <lb/>8.15 <lb/>8.20 <lb/>8.25 <lb/>8.30 <lb/>8.35 <lb/>8.40 <lb/>8.45 <lb/>8.46 <lb/>
    
    <body>To deal with the concerns of regulation being captured or frustrated in any way, <lb/>the threat of &apos;electrification&apos; was introduced in the Act. 50 This could be a powerful tool <lb/>in the regulator&apos;s kit to ensure the independence and integrity of a ring-fenced bank. <lb/>However, this will allow different banking models to operate alongside each other; and, <lb/>it does not explain how this would enhance the performance of the institution itself. <lb/>The PRA and Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) are vested with restructuring <lb/>powers; they can require banking groups to restructure their operations where they <lb/>find that a ring-fence is proving to be ineffective. There are four circumstances in <lb/>which group restructuring powers become exercisable. 51 These measures were <lb/>thought to be appropriate in the public interest. 52 <lb/>However, the exercise of the above powers by the PRA and FCA has an inherent <lb/>potential to cause groups to split their commercial (retail) and investment banking <lb/>operations into separate corporate groups. Such a separation is effected by the steps <lb/>that the ring-fenced body may be required to take. 53 FSMA 2000, section 142L, also <lb/>affords for the situation where the PRA or FCA needs to impose a requirement on an <lb/>entity for which it is not the appropriate regulator. 54 <lb/>This plainly punishes an institution which may otherwise be structurally sound; the <lb/>deconstruction of an institution carries disastrous consequences. This kind of extreme <lb/>&apos;boil them in oil&apos; approach to enforcement of regulation entailing high penalties 55 is <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>50 <lb/>See FSMA 2000, section 142. <lb/>51 <lb/>Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013, section 142K Cases in which group restructuring powers become exercisable <lb/>&apos;(1) The appropriate regulator may exercise the group restructuring powers only if it is satisfied that one or more of <lb/>Conditions A to D is met in relation to a ring-fenced body that is a member of a group. (2) Condition A is that the carrying on <lb/>of core activities by the ring-fenced body is being adversely affected by the acts or omissions of other members of its group. <lb/>(3) Condition B is that in carrying on its business the ring-fenced body-(a) is unable to take decisions independently of <lb/>other members of its group, or(b) depends on resources which are provided by a member of its group and which would cease <lb/>to be available in the event of the insolvency of the other member.(4) Condition C is that in the event of the insolvency of <lb/>one or more other members of its group the ring-fenced body would be unable to continue to carry on the core activities <lb/>carried on by it. (5) Condition D is that the ring-fenced body or another member of its group has engaged, or is engaged, <lb/>in conduct which is having, or would apart from this section be likely to have, an adverse effect on the advancement by the <lb/>appropriate regulator-(a) in the case of the PRA, of the objective in section 2B(3)(c), or(b) in the case of the FCA, of the <lb/>continuity objective.&apos; <lb/>52 <lb/>See generally B Morgan and K Yeung (n 4), 17-36; C Sunstein, &apos; After the rights revolution: reconceiving the regulatory <lb/>state (Cambridge (MA): Harvard University Press 1990); T Prosser, Nationalised Industry and Public Control: Legal, <lb/>Constitutional and Public Issues (Oxford: Blackwell 1986); S Croley, &apos;Theories of regulation: Incorporating the administra-<lb/>tive process&apos; [1998] 98 Columbia Law Review 1, 56-65. <lb/>53 <lb/>Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013, section 142L (5) and (6): (5) The steps that the ring-fenced body may be <lb/>required to take are-(a) to dispose of specified property or rights to an outside person; (b) to apply to the court under Part 7 for <lb/>an order sanctioning a ring-fencing transfer scheme relating to the transfer of the whole or part of the business of the ring-fenced <lb/>body to an outside person; (c) otherwise to make arrangements discharging the ring-fenced body from specified liabilities. (6) <lb/>The steps that another authorised person or a qualifying parent undertaking may be required to take are-(a) to dispose of any <lb/>shares in, or securities of, the ring-fenced body to an outside person; (b) to dispose of any interest in any other body corporate that <lb/>is member of the ring-fenced body&apos;s group to an outside person; (c) to dispose of other specified property or rights to an outside <lb/>person; (d) to apply to the court under Part 7 for an order sanctioning a ring-fencing transfer scheme relating to the transfer of the <lb/>whole or part of the business of the authorized person or qualifying parent undertaking to an outside person. <lb/>54 <lb/>See Financial Services (Banking Reform) ACT 2013, Explanatory Notes, no.45, furthermore: &apos;The PRA is given power to <lb/>require the FCA to impose the relevant requirement. The FCA is given an equivalent power where it is the appropriate regula-<lb/>tor, and it wishes to impose a requirement on a PRA-authorised person. The powers set out in this section include a power to <lb/>require a ring-fenced body to make arrangements discharging it from liabilities specified by the regulator (subsection (5)(c)). <lb/>In some cases the regulator may be able to impose the same requirements on authorised persons under sections 55L or 55M. <lb/>Subsection (8) makes it clear that this does not affect the regulator&apos;s use of the group restructuring powers set out in this section.&apos; <lb/>55 <lb/>G Becker, &apos;Crime and punishment: An Economic Approach&apos; [1968] Journal of Political Economy 76(2), 169-217. <lb/></listBibl>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>
      
      <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart <lb/>Regulatory Regime?</note>
    
    <page>• Page 9 of 17 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>rarely workable because there will be a stronger desire for &apos;capture&apos; and subversion of <lb/>justice. 56 <lb/>Besides, the fundamental fault with this reasoning is that it wholly relies on regula-<lb/>tion and shuts the door on criminal and tort law taking effect against the individuals <lb/>who cause the breach of the ring-fence and harm the banking institution; 57 the prin-<lb/>ciples of strict liability, negligence, and fraud can also play important roles. 58 A mix of <lb/>regulation and litigation is needed in the sector. 59 Regulation organizing private litiga-<lb/>tion can be beneficial for financial market development, for example, rules that lower <lb/>the cost of litigation and facilitate litigation. <lb/>The largest banks face the constant threat of being split up if they undermine the <lb/>purpose of the ring-fence and present a risk to the financial system. The threat of being <lb/>broken up is likely to cause regulatory uncertainty and uncertainty for investors and <lb/>make it harder for those banks to raise money, which could then be loaned to businesses. <lb/>The wider theoretical and practical implications are that this element of uncer-<lb/>tainty could contribute to a market failure in a devastating way. 60 For example, if a <lb/>bank is under scrutiny in the context of electrification, news of it being broken up <lb/>could spread panic in the market place among the investors and shareholders, which <lb/>could ultimately cause a run on the bank. So the electrification scrutiny could easily <lb/>itself cause a market failure; any view contradicting this argument is not based on <lb/>any empirical views-they simply amount to personal views and lack theoretical <lb/>depth. 61 <lb/>Also, there is actually a public policy issue here which militates against the &apos;elec-<lb/>trification&apos; power provisions in the Act and deserves attention. The construct of <lb/>the &apos;electrification&apos; powers in the Act allows public policy to be changed by the <lb/>regulators. The fact that, effectively, the electrification provisions would allow the <lb/>regulator to introduce a full separation of retail and investment banking within the <lb/>groups actually amounts to modifying public policy without recourse to parlia-<lb/>ment, and it seems to be unreasonable. Although Parliament can confer legislative <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>56 <lb/>EL Glaeser and A Shleifer (n 49), 403. <lb/>57 <lb/>Ibid (n 49), 404-408; L Friedman, A History of American Law, NY: Simon and Schuster, 1985; RA Posner, &apos;A Theory of <lb/>Negligence&apos; [1972] The Journal of Legal Studies 1(1) , 29-96. <lb/>58 <lb/>EL Glaeser and A Shleifer (n 49), 401-404. <lb/>59 <lb/>M Arnold, &apos;Prosecuting bankers would be a start&apos;, Financial Times, August 4, 2014; J Rakoff (a US district judge): &apos;I suggest <lb/>that the future deterrent value of successfully prosecuting individuals far outweighs the prophylactic benefits of imposing <lb/>internal compliance measures that are often little more than window-dressing&apos; <lb/>60 <lb/>See generally FM Bator, &apos;The Anatomy of Market Failure&apos;, Quarterly Journal of Economics 72, 351-79351; R Cooter, <lb/>&apos;Normative Failures Theory of Law&apos; [1996] Cornell Law Review 82, 947, 949; RO Zerbe Jr and HE McCurdy, &apos;The Failure <lb/>of Market Failure&apos; [1999] Journal of Policy Analysis and Management, 558, 559. <lb/>61 <lb/>See, for example, the oral evidence of Antonio Horta-Osório, Group Chief Executive, Lloyds Banking Group, taken before <lb/>the Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards (Question no. 3421, HC 606-xxx1). He disagreed with the BBA&apos;s <lb/>opposition to electrification. He said: <lb/>&apos;We were not notified about those comments, which I think were made by the CEO of the BBA in his name. I support electri-<lb/>fication, like I supported ring-fencing. As you know, we were the only bank publicly to support ring-fencing. The reason why <lb/>I support your proposal is that, if we think that for society as a whole it is better to have ring-fencing, both from a financial <lb/>stability point of view and from a cultural point of view, I absolutely agree that you should have strong enforcement and <lb/>strong incentives in order for that to happen&apos;, Second Report, para 15; See also both Sir David Walker, Chairman of Barclays <lb/>and Douglas Flint, Executive Chairman of HSBC, also supported the proposal for the first reserve power, the latter saying: <lb/>&apos;In the event that it is judged that participants are circumventing or frustrating the purpose of the ring-fence, it seems to me <lb/>quite reasonable for there to be a sanction.&apos; <lb/></listBibl>
    
    9.5 <lb/>9.10 <lb/>9.15 <lb/>9.20 <lb/>9.25 <lb/>9.30 <lb/>9.35 <lb/>9.40 <lb/>9.45 <lb/>9.46 <lb/>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>

			<page>Page 10 of 17 •</page>
    
    <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? <lb/></note>
    
    10.5 <lb/>10.10 <lb/>10.15 <lb/>10.20 <lb/>10.25 <lb/>10.30 <lb/>10.35 <lb/>10.40 <lb/>10.45 <lb/>10.46 <lb/>
    
    <body>powers on the regulator, it is uncharacteristic that in this case the regulator would <lb/>actually be exercising parliamentary powers, because it is parliament only which <lb/>can make and change public policy. Thus, the provisions on electrification are <lb/>anomalous. <lb/>In this public policy debate, the central question is why ring-fencing (par-<lb/>tial structural separation) was preferable over total separation in the first place? <lb/>Maybe it is designed to enable a non-ring-fenced investment entity in a banking <lb/>group to inject money into a ring-fenced retail institution that got into trouble. <lb/>There must be many other benefits that were envisaged in the choice of partial <lb/>structural separation because it is inconceivable that the preference of partial sep-<lb/>aration happened to come about at the centre stage without any other reasons for <lb/>such public policy. 62 If partial structural separation is removed and replaced with <lb/>full structural separation, what happens to the thinking behind the partial struc-<lb/>tural separation on which the whole structure of public policy was built upon? <lb/>The whole logic of it stands on its head and it remains an unexplained. Besides, <lb/>what is the point of full structural separation? The idea that full separation of <lb/>retail and investment banking would make the financial system safe was unreal-<lb/>istic. This over-interprets the benefits of full separation, and the economy could <lb/>still be blown up by failures of investment banks or the shadow banking sector. 63 <lb/>The benefits of public policy advocating full separation are neither fully analysed <lb/>nor understood. <lb/>Furthermore, the kind of behaviour that will invite the enforcement of electri-<lb/>fication provisions of the Act against a bank could not be regarded as &apos;institutional <lb/>behaviour&apos;; rather, it must be an individual behaviour of the employees. First, it <lb/>is illogical to &apos;punish&apos; the institution for the wrongdoings of a few individuals and <lb/>bring about further structural change; there is no theoretical justification for such <lb/>a reaction. Furthermore no studies have been carried out to inform us or enable <lb/>us to comprehend what the consequences of such a change across the national <lb/>economy would be for wider society and global relationships. To deal with indi-<lb/>vidual behaviour, it may be argued that the specific behavioural regulation should <lb/>suffice, along with the existing common law and company law. 64 The electrifica-<lb/>tion provisions are equivalent to cracking a nut with a sledgehammer. Second, <lb/>structural changes should only be brought about for institutional reasons and not <lb/>otherwise. Thirdly, institutional restructuring must be a public policy issue, with <lb/>the public policy brought about by parliament in the form of legislation; it is not <lb/>something that could or should be changed or implemented by regulators. It may <lb/>be a perfect argument that parliament could delegate regulatory powers to a regu-<lb/>lator; however, these &apos;electrification&apos; powers have gone too far, putting a regulator <lb/>in a position to change a public policy, which is supposed to be the prerogative of <lb/>parliament. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>62 <lb/>EL Glaeser and A Shleifer, (n 49), the authors explain in their &apos;theory of law enforcement,&apos; the reasons for choosing a particu-<lb/>lar type of regulatory regime. <lb/>63 <lb/>P Tucker, &apos;Regulatory Reform, Stability and Central Banking&apos;, Brookings Institution Working Paper, 2014. <lb/>64 <lb/>G Mitchell, &apos;Sanctions for Bank Directors and Ring-Fencing&apos; [2013] Butterworth&apos;s Journal of International Banking and <lb/>Financial Law, 287-289. <lb/></listBibl>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>
      
      <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? </note>
    
    <page>• Page 11 of 17 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>The proposal that there should be an automatic periodic review of the ring-fence <lb/>legislation every 2/3/4 etc. years to make sure that the bankers are not undermining <lb/>the fence would help create a formidable regulatory system instead of merely relying <lb/>on the regulators, which are susceptible to &apos;capture&apos; by special interest groups at a <lb/>serious cost to the rest of society. Automatic revision of this legislation, although a <lb/>rare phenomenon, will be justifiable on the basis of public interest, as financial reg-<lb/>ulation, like the financial industry itself, is a special case. This will also reduce the <lb/>dependence on and concentration of too much power within the hands of regulators, <lb/>and would avoid the risk of capture. Such a two-tier system would guarantee the sta-<lb/>bility of the financial system. <lb/>(C) Regulatory Rationale for the Ring-Fence and the &apos;Electrification&apos; in the Act <lb/>The Banking Reforms Act emerged as a regulatory response to financial market fail-<lb/>ures 65 as a consequence of the 2007-08 financial crisis in the United Kingdom and <lb/>across the world. The theoretical reasons for this Act are rooted in public interest 66 <lb/>and emerged as a regulatory command and control strategy 67 for the financial sector to <lb/>ensure its stability. The fundamental nature of command and control is that it displays <lb/>its influence by imposing standards backed by sanctions. 68 <lb/>The command and control strategy is largely exercised by the FCA and PRA. The <lb/>Act provides the regulators with rule-making powers, which allow them to bring in an <lb/>even more extensive regime of command and control. The legislation would use force <lb/>of law to impose inflexible benchmarks. 69 Politically, this kind of thinking seems astute <lb/>because the government and the regulators are seen here to be acting forcefully and <lb/>taking a clear stand in the aftermath of the financial crisis, by describing some forms of <lb/>institutional behaviour as unacceptable. The public is being assured that the full force <lb/>of the law would be used to protect their interests and in the interest of the financial <lb/>system. <lb/>However, the command and control strategy can only be justified if the critics are <lb/>unable to argue for a better alternative strategy. 70 There are significant inherent prob-<lb/>lems 71 associated with the command and control strategy, such as &apos;capture&apos; 72 and &apos;legal-<lb/>ism&apos;, 73 which the regulation ensuing the Act might face. Strikingly, the Act ignores other <lb/>enforcement strategies such as those based on economic incentives. 74 . Expanded incen-<lb/>tives for whistle-blowers to report suspected violation of a ring-fence could prove a <lb/>better alternative to the electrification idea. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>65 <lb/>See generally FM Bator, &apos;The Anatomy of Market Failure&apos;, Quarterly Journal of Economics 72, 351-79; R Baldwin and M Cave <lb/>(n 4) 9-16. <lb/>66 <lb/>M Feintuck, &apos;Regulatory Rationales Beyond the Economic: In Search of the Public Interest&apos;, in R Baldwin, M Cave and M <lb/>Lodge (n 4) 39-60. <lb/>67 <lb/>R Baldwin, C Cave; B Morgan, K Yeung (n 4). <lb/>68 <lb/>R Baldwin, &apos;Regulation: After Command and Control&apos;, in K. Hawkins (ed.), The Human Face of Law (OUP 1997). <lb/>69 <lb/>B Morgan, K Yeung, See generally the &apos;the role of law&apos; in regulation discussed by the authors, 17-74. <lb/>70 <lb/>Ibid. <lb/>71 <lb/>See generally, RB Stewart, &apos;Regulation on the Crisis of Legalism in the United State&apos;, in T Daintith (ed.), Law as an Investment <lb/>of Economic Policy, Berlin, 1998; E Bardach and R Kagan, Going by the Book: The Problem of Regulatory Unreasonableness <lb/>Philadelphia, 1982; N Gunningham and P Grabosky, Smart Regulation (OUP 1998), 44-45. <lb/>72 <lb/>R Baldwin, M Cave (n 4), 36-37. <lb/>73 <lb/>Ibid 37-38. <lb/>74 <lb/>Ibid 41-44. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    11.5 <lb/>11.10 <lb/>11.15 <lb/>AQ8 <lb/>11.20 <lb/>11.25 <lb/>11.30 <lb/>11.35 <lb/>11.40 <lb/>11.45 <lb/>11.46 <lb/>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>

			<page>Page 12 of 17 •</page>
    
    <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? <lb/></note>
    
    <body>PA RT 2 <lb/></body>
    
   12.5 <lb/>12.10 <lb/>12.15 <lb/>12.20 <lb/>12.25 <lb/>12.30 <lb/>12.35 <lb/>12.40 <lb/>12.45 <lb/>12.46 <lb/>

			<body>3. . A N A LTER N ATIVE TO ELECTR IFIC ATION: E X PA NDED <lb/>INCEN TIVE S FOR WHIS TLE -BLOWER S TO R EPORT SUS PEC TED <lb/>R ING -FENCE VIOL ATION <lb/>Arguably there are some common law alternatives along with or without regulation 75 ; <lb/>the &apos;whistle-blower&apos; concept can prove to be a better, simpler, more efficient, 76 and <lb/>effective alternative to &apos;electrification&apos; of ring-fencing. Whistle-blowing is a term of art; <lb/>it has special meaning in the legal context, as it does in other disciplines; it is a multi-<lb/>disciplinary concept. Hence, it cannot be defined in a normative sense, including all of <lb/>its multidisciplinary characteristics and virtues. In this sense, it is a multi-disciplinary <lb/>and functional concept, which can be defined as a process, and to that end includes at <lb/>least four elements 77 : the whistle-blower, the act of whistle-blowing, the recipient of the <lb/>complaint, and the target organization of the complaint. The act of whistle-blowing on <lb/>an organization is an act of resistance 78 and represents the &apos;voice&apos; of dissidence. 79 The <lb/>act of whistle-blowing has been variously interpreted as providing information about <lb/>the organizational activities that &apos;harm third parties&apos; 80 or &apos;jeopardize the public inter-<lb/>est&apos;. 81 The concerned activity may involve &apos;misconduct, neglect, or irresponsibility&apos;, 82 <lb/>&apos;corrupt, socially harmful, or illegal activity&apos;, 83 or &apos;wasteful activities&apos;. 84 <lb/>The four elements of whistle-blowing on which most authors agree are as follows 85 : <lb/>First, the whistle-blower is or has been a member of the organization 86 ; second, the whis-<lb/>tle-blower is an individual who lacks legitimate authority to change the organization&apos;s <lb/>activities 87 ; third, the whistle-blower can sometimes remain anonymous, although this <lb/>is not without ethical and practical implications 88 ; and fourth, the whistle-blower may <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>75 <lb/>For example, Litigation for breach of contract, breach of fiduciary duty, doctrine of ultra vires and tort litigation for strict <lb/>liability and negligence, see AG Mitchell, &apos;Sanctions for Bank Directors and Ring Fencing&apos; [2013] Butterworth&apos;s Journal of <lb/>International Banking and Financial Law, 288. <lb/>76 <lb/>EL Glaeser and A Shleifer (n 49) 201-204; G Mitchell (99), 287-289. <lb/>77 <lb/>JP Near and MP Miceli, Organisational Dissidence: The Case of Whistle-Blowing, Journal of Business Ethics 4, 1985, 2; cf. <lb/>see PB Jubb, Whistleblowing: A Restrictive Definition and Interpretation, Journal of Business Ethics 21: 83 (1999) the author <lb/>mentions six elements of the proposed definition of whistle-blowing; see also JP Near and MP Miceli, &apos;Whistle-Blowing: <lb/>Myth and Reality&apos; [1996] Journal of Management 22(3), 506, The authors accept three elements of whistle-blowing process. <lb/>78 <lb/>FA Elliston, &apos;Civil Disobedience and Whistle-Blowing: a Comparative Appraisal of Two Forms of Dissident&apos; [1982b] <lb/>Journal of Business Ethics 1, 23-28. <lb/>79 <lb/>AO Hirschman, Exit, Voice, and Loyalty: Responses to Decline in Firms, Organizations, and States (Cambridge, MA: Harvard <lb/>University Press 1970). <lb/>80 <lb/>FA Elliston (78) 23-28. <lb/>81 <lb/>D Farrell and JC Petersen, &apos;Patterns of Political Behaviour in Organisations&apos; [1982] Academy of Management Review 7, <lb/>403-412. <lb/>82 <lb/>D Farrell and JC Petersen, Ibid. <lb/>83 <lb/>IL Janis and L Mann, Decision Making (New York: Free Press 1977). <lb/>84 <lb/>United States Merit Systems Protection Board (USMSPB), Whistle-blowing and the federal employee, U.S. Government <lb/>Printing Office, Washington, DC, 1981. <lb/>85 <lb/>JP Near and MP. Miceli, &apos;Organisational Dissidence: The Case of Whistle-Blowing&apos; [1985] The Journal of Business Ethics <lb/>4(1), 1-16. <lb/>86 <lb/>D Farrell and JC Petersen (n 81) 403-412; IL Janis and L Mann (n 83); United States Merit Systems Protection Board <lb/>(USMSPB), Whistle-blowing and the federal employee, U.S. Government Printing Office, Washington, DC, 1981. <lb/>87 <lb/>FA Elliston &apos;Anonymity and Whistle-Blowing&apos; [1982a] Journal of Business Ethics 1, 167-177; D Weinstein, Bureaucratic <lb/>Opposition (New York: Pergamon Press 1979). <lb/>88 <lb/>FA Elliston (n 78). <lb/></listBibl>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>
      
      <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? </note>
    
    <page>• Page 13 of 17 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>Toccupy a role such as an auditor, ombudsman, or any other overseeing role where he/she <lb/>may be officially required to blow the whistle if he/she observes organizational wrongdo-<lb/>ing. 89 From these four attributes, it may be broadly concluded that the whistle-blower is <lb/>a person, normally an insider, who provides information regarding regulatory violation. 90 <lb/>There is disagreement among authors as to the third element-the nature of the <lb/>person or agency who receives information-in the whistle-blowing process. Some <lb/>authors identify the appropriate recipient of information in the whistle-blowing process <lb/>as an external person or agency to the organization. 91 This amounts to a public com-<lb/>plaint; in their view, internal complaint does not truly represent the whistle-blowing <lb/>process. 92 However, some authors value internal or external complaint equally, as long <lb/>as the internal complaint is also made to someone other than the immediate superior. 93 <lb/>Any organization, public or private, may be made a target of whistle-blowing. By <lb/>encouraging whistle-blowing, the organizations will gain additional information that <lb/>may be used to enhance their operational capabilities. 94 To this end, whistle-blowing <lb/>may be broadly defined as disclosure by the members of an organization of illegal and <lb/>unethical actions by the employers to a person or agency, internal or external which <lb/>can bring about action against the perpetrators of such illegal and unethical activities. 95 <lb/>In the context of the financial sector, the whistle-blower concept has two important <lb/>aspects. First is that a whistle-blower should be rewarded with a substantial bounty for <lb/>providing useful information to the regulators regarding regulatory violations; secondly, <lb/>he/she should be provided with retaliation protection. 96 In the United Kingdom, whis-<lb/>tle-blowing regulation is still in its infancy. The whistle-blowing interest group Public <lb/>Concern at Work (PCaW) set up an independent commission in 2013 to review all <lb/>aspects of whistle-blowing, including legal, governance, and best practice arrangements. <lb/>In November 2014, it published its report, which made a number of recommendations. <lb/>The commission, however, did not make any recommendation for the introduction of <lb/>financial rewards or incentives for whistle-blowing. The commission&apos;s recommendations <lb/>are not specific to any particular sector; rather, they are more general in nature. <lb/>In the United States, the concept was introduced more robustly in the Dodd-Frank <lb/>Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (Dodd-Frank Act), 97 although it was <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>89 <lb/>JP Near and MP Miceli, &apos;Organisational Dissidence&apos; (n 85). <lb/>90 <lb/>Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (Exchange Act) defines a whistle-blower as an individual or group of individuals &apos; who <lb/>provide… information relating to a violation of the securities laws to the Commission, in a manner established, by rule or <lb/>regulation, by the Commission.&apos; See also section 21 F, &apos;Securities Whistle-blower Incentives and Protection&apos;, Dodd-Frank Act <lb/>s 922(a), 124 Stat. at 1841-1842. <lb/>91 <lb/>R Nader, PJ Petkas and K Blackwell (eds.), Whistle-blowing: The report on the conference on professional responsibility, <lb/>Grossman, New York, 1972; D Weinstein (n 87). <lb/>92 <lb/>D Farrell and JC Petersen (n 81), 403-412; IL Janis and L Mann (n 83). <lb/>93 <lb/>FA Elliston (n 87), 167-177; AO Hirschman (n 83). <lb/>94 <lb/>See generally DW Ewing, Do It My Way-Or You&apos;re Fired! (New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons 1983). <lb/>95 <lb/>JP Near and MP. Miceli, &apos;Organisational Dissidence&apos; (n 77), 4. <lb/>96 <lb/>This concept was introduced in SOX 2002, Pub. L. No. 107-204, 116 Stat. 745 (codified in scattered sections of the US <lb/>Code); Also in an enhanced form in Dodd-Frank Act, Pub. L. No. 111-203, S 922, 124 Stat. 1376, 1841-49 (2010) (codi-<lb/>fied at 15 U.S.C. S 78u-6); See R G Vaughn, &apos;America&apos;s First Comprehensive Statute Protecting Corporate Whistle-blowers&apos; <lb/>[2005] Administrative Law Review 57, 1, 4. <lb/>97 <lb/>Pub. L.NO.111-203, 124 Stat. 1376 (2010) (codified in scattered sections of the US Code). Dodd-Frank Act is a vast and <lb/>sweeping overhaul of the US financial and regulatory system, was signed into law on 21 July 2010 by President Barack <lb/>Obama. See D Paletta and A Lucchetti, &apos;Law Remakes U.S. Financial Landscape&apos; [2010] Wall Street Journal, July 16, A1. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    13.5 <lb/>13.10 <lb/>13.15 <lb/>13.20 <lb/>13.25 <lb/>13.30 <lb/>13.35 <lb/>13.40 <lb/>13.45 <lb/>13.46 <lb/>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>

			<page>Page 14 of 17 • </page>
      
      <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? <lb/></note>
      
      14.5 <lb/>14.10 <lb/>14.15 <lb/>14.20 <lb/>14.25 <lb/>14.30 <lb/>14.35 <lb/>14.40 <lb/>14.45 <lb/>14.46 <lb/>
    
    <body>introduced 8 years earlier in Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002 98 (SOX) in a weaker form. <lb/>section 299 of Dodd-Frank expands the incentives for a whistle-blower 99 by obliging <lb/>The Security and Exchange Commission (SEC), by adding a new provision, to &apos;pay an <lb/>award&apos; to whistle-blowers &apos;who voluntarily provide original information to the com-<lb/>mission that led to the successful enforcement of the …action&apos;. 100 Furthermore, in <lb/>protecting whistle-blowers, new section 21 F(h)(1)(A) forbids employers from dis-<lb/>charging, demoting, suspending, threatening, harassing, or in any other way discrimi-<lb/>nating against a whistle-blower &apos;because of any lawful act done by the whistle-blower <lb/>in (i) providing information to the SEC, (ii) helping in any SEC investigation or action <lb/>related to such information, or (iii) &apos;in making disclosures that are required or protected <lb/>under&apos; any securities law, rule, or regulation&apos;. 101 The enforcement of this prohibition was <lb/>further fortified in new section 21 F(h)(1)(B) that creates a private right of action for <lb/>individuals alleging a violation of the anti-retaliation provisions. 102 This enables whis-<lb/>tle-blowers to file a complaint in a district court without first having to exhaust admin-<lb/>istrative options. 103 <lb/>Recently, a sudden increase was revealed in whistle-blowing reports sent to FCA <lb/>following a Freedom of Information request made to the regulator. 104 FCA figures show <lb/>that the regulator launched 254 new cases on the basis of whistle-blowers&apos; informa-<lb/>tion in 2012/13 compared with only 148 cases a year earlier; this is an increase of 72 <lb/>per cent. The concern of the whistle-blower in the suspected market manipulation is <lb/>encouraging. It is easily discernable from this pattern that further encouragement to <lb/>would-be informers, on the basis of reward, would be a successful regulatory strategy. <lb/>Whistle-blowing provisions in the Banking Reform Act would have provided a bet-<lb/>ter solution for the financial market failure and for the improvement of the stability <lb/>of the financial system. A similar provision, as in US legislation, in respect of protec-<lb/>tion against retaliation in the Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act would have <lb/>proved to be the most influential and effective tool for the protection of the ring-fence. <lb/>Furthermore, an even better regulation in this respect would be where retaliation pro-<lb/>tection is available to both those who report information externally to the regulators <lb/>as well as those who report internally to the company (bank) itself. This glaring defi-<lb/>ciency exists in the Dodd-Frank Act, with section 922 retaliation protection only apply-<lb/>ing to those whistle-blowers who report information externally (to SEC), leaving those <lb/>informers who report internally (to the company) either without protection or only <lb/>protected by the weaker protection of SOX. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>98 <lb/>Pub. L. No. 107-204, 116 Stat.745 (codified in scattered sections of the US Code). <lb/>99 <lb/>See B Carton, Pitfalls Emerge in Dodd-Frank Bounty Provision, COMPLIANCE WEEK, September 2010, 1-2.; R Levick, <lb/>A Whole New Ballgame: Dodd-Frank&apos;s Whistle-blower Provisions, FORBES (Nov. 2, 2010, 1;53 PM); RG Vaughn, <lb/>&apos;America&apos;s First Comprehensive Statute Protecting Corporate Whistle-blowers&apos; [2005] Administrative Law Review 57, 1, 4. <lb/>100 <lb/>Dodd-Frank Act S 922(a), 124 Stat. at 1841-1842. <lb/>101 <lb/>Ibid 1845-1846. <lb/>102 <lb/>Ibid 1846. <lb/>103 Dodd-Frank improves regulatory regime regarding &apos;whistleblowing&apos; in a number of way, for example, aggrieved employee <lb/>has more time to file complaint, bring a claim up to 6 years after the has occurred or up to 3 years after becoming aware of <lb/>the claim (provided the claim is brought within 10 years of the violation) (Dodd-Frank Act s 922 (a), 124 Stat. at 1846. In <lb/>contrast SOX requires a complaint to be filed within 180 days of the violation or becoming aware of it (18 USC. S 1514A (b) <lb/>(2)(D) amended by Dodd-Frank Act s 922 (c)(1)(A)(I), 124 Stat. at 1848. <lb/>104 <lb/>Financial Times, 23 December 2013. <lb/></listBibl>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? </note>
      
      <page>• Page 15 of 17 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>Notwithstanding the benefits of external reporting (Dodd-Frank rule), there are <lb/>serious reservations about the regulatory success as far as achieving the aims of the <lb/>regulation. The business and legal communities in the United States, as well as the SEC, <lb/>have acknowledged the potential for the substantial rewards required by the Act to <lb/>undermine internal compliance procedures (e.g. by SOX) by causing a race to the SEC <lb/>for external reporting. 105 The reward and the two-tier nature of the retaliation protec-<lb/>tion, that is, external and internal, both autonomously incentivize external reporting. <lb/>Under Dodd-Frank, a whistle-blower worried about retaliation has an advantage and <lb/>incentive to report directly to SEC as well as internally at the same time, creating a max-<lb/>imum level of protection against retaliation. Any attempt on new legislation regarding <lb/>&apos;whistle-blower provision&apos; incentivizing whistle-blowers to report regulatory violations <lb/>must take into account this flaw in the design of Dodd-Frank and should address both <lb/>provisions embedded in SOX and Dodd-Frank. <lb/>SOX encourages internal reporting anonymously for corporate wrongdoings <lb/>through internal disclosure systems and incorporates anti-retaliation provisions for <lb/>the protection of the whistle-blowers 106 . Section 806 of SOX protects whistle-blowers <lb/>against external reporting to federal regulators, law enforcement agencies, and com-<lb/>mittees of congress or its members. 107 However, it is a far weaker response to deal with <lb/>the problem effectively, because it only protects those whistle-blowers who provide <lb/>the information with a &apos;reasonable belief &apos; that the violation actually occurred. In con-<lb/>trast, the Dodd-Frank offers much more robust protection to the whistle-blower by not <lb/>limiting its protection to a &apos;reasonable belief &apos; that the violation actually occurred 108 . <lb/>However, a serious problem remains in that it extends its protection only to those whis-<lb/>tle-blowers who report externally. <lb/>Comparatively stronger and more robust protection for a whistle-blower against <lb/>retaliation if he/she reports the suspected regulatory violations directly to the regulators <lb/>rather than to the company (bank) would discourage internal reporting, thus weakening <lb/>institutions&apos; internal compliance and reporting procedures and systems. Equally strong <lb/>and robust external (to regulators) and internal (to bank) reporting of regulatory viola-<lb/>tions will play an important role in the early detection and prevention of fraud and other <lb/>regulatory violations. In this context, it is also important that the term &apos;whistle-blower&apos; <lb/>or any other equivalent term is defined broadly to achieve maximum impact, 109 that is, <lb/>should protection only apply to &apos;whistle-blowers&apos; or it should include other reporting <lb/>sources as well. For example, the term &apos;whistle-blower&apos; is defined narrowly by the SEC. 110 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>105 See Proposed Rules for Implementing the Whistle-blower Provisions of Section 21F of the Securities Exchange Act of <lb/>1934, 75 Fed. Reg. 70,488 (proposed Nov.17, 2010) (codified at 17 C.F.R. pts. 240, 249); A letter from the Association of <lb/>Corporate Counsel to Elizabeth M. Murphy, Secretary of Section 1-2 (15 December 2010), available at http://www.sec. <lb/>gov/comments/s7-33-10/s73310-126.pdf; A letter from Bus. Roundtable to Elizabeth M. Murphy, Secretary of Secion 2 <lb/>(17 December 2010) available at http://www.sec.gov/comments/s7-33-10/s73310-142.pdf. <lb/>106 See 15 U.S.C S 78 j-1(m) (4) (B) (2006); See also RM Moberly, &apos;Unfulfilled expectations: An Empirical Analysis of Why <lb/>Sabanes-Oxxley Whistle-blowers Rarely Win&apos; [2007] William and Mary Law Review 49(1), 65, 75. <lb/>107 <lb/>18 U.S.C s 1341, 1343-1344, 1348. <lb/>108 <lb/>18 U.S.C S 1514 A (a) (1). <lb/>109 The prohibition on retaliation found in new section 21 F(h)(1)(A) of the Exchange Act applies only to &apos;whistle-blower&apos;, the <lb/>term is defined narrowly in new section 21F(a)(6) at 1842; it includes only those who provide &apos; information relating to a <lb/>violation of the securities laws to the Commission, in a manner established, by rule or regulation, by the Commission&apos;. <lb/>110 <lb/>Dodd-Frank Act S 922(a), 124 Stat. at 1842. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      15.5 <lb/>15.10 <lb/>15.15 <lb/>15.20 <lb/>15.25 <lb/>15.30 <lb/>15.35 <lb/>15.40 <lb/>15.45 <lb/>15.46 <lb/>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>

			<page>Page 16 of 17 • </page>
      
      <note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime? <lb/></note>
      
     16.5 <lb/>16.10 <lb/>16.15 <lb/>16.20 <lb/>16.25 <lb/>16.30 <lb/>16.35 <lb/>16.40 <lb/>16.45 <lb/>16.46 <lb/>
    
    <body>The system of retaliation protection for a whistle-blower who is reporting inter-<lb/>nally (to company) actually and effectively creates an internal monitoring system. 111 <lb/>Any lack of retaliation protection to a whistle-blower who is reporting internally would <lb/>unfortunately work against the goal of the regulation that is designed in respect of the <lb/>whistle-blowing. To the same extent, Dworkin and Callahan have argued, &apos;[i]f… the <lb/>primary goal of whistle-blowing is reduction of wrongdoing rather than prosecution <lb/>of wrongdoers, and the speed with which problems are addressed is significant, then <lb/>internal whistleblowing should be preferred&apos; to external whistle-blowing. 112 It is fur-<lb/>ther argued that &apos;when the internal/external question is posed in the context of social-<lb/>psychological research generally, and especially when approached from the perspective <lb/>of organizational needs and behaviour, there is little doubt that internal whistle-blow-<lb/>ing is preferable to external reporting&apos;. 113 This view has been endorsed by the major-<lb/>ity of researchers &apos;as the most effective response to organizational wrongdoing&apos; 114 ; the <lb/>research has displayed that the most efficient way of combating occupational fraud is <lb/>a company&apos;s internal system of anonymous reporting. 115 The SEC also agrees with this <lb/>view that &apos;internal compliance and reporting system are essential sources of information <lb/>for companies about misconduct&apos;… if these programmes are not utilized or working, <lb/>our system of securities regulation will be less effective. 116 Therefore, both Dodd-Frank <lb/>and SOX need to be amended to provide equivalent protection for potential whistle-<lb/>blowers, regardless of whether they choose to report externally or internally; and the <lb/>Banking Reforms Act should have followed this approach. <lb/>Thus, to ensure that the bankers do not breach the ring-fence, it is important to have <lb/>a robust and effective whistle-blowing system that protects potential whistle-blowers from <lb/>retaliation and rewards them generously regardless of whether they choose to report inter-<lb/>nally or externally. This is a lesson that can be learnt from the dichotomy of Dodd-Frank and <lb/>SOX. Whistle-blower provision could be the single most important regulation for the pro-<lb/>tection of investors, financial institutions, and the stability of the financial system as a whole. <lb/>Whistle-blowing is a preventive measure, whereas &apos;electrification&apos; is punitive in <lb/>nature-there is no point in dealing with the issue long after the damage has been done <lb/>to the financial system; in such situations, the financial system could even be beyond <lb/>repair before &apos;electrification&apos; comes into play. It is far better to prevent the damage hap-<lb/>pening in the first place. The whistle-blower solution is also cost-effective. <lb/>4. . CONCLUS ION <lb/>The PCBS made an argument during the Bill stage that the &apos;ring-fence&apos; regulation, <lb/>based on Sir John Vickers&apos; report, fell short of expectations, and that it would be easily <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>111 <lb/>See O Lobel, Lawyering Loyalties: Speech Rights and Duties within Twenty-First-Century New Governance&apos; [2009] <lb/>Forbham Law Review 77, 1245, 1251. <lb/>112 <lb/>TM Dworkin and ES Callahan &apos;Internal Whistleblowing: Protecting the Interests of the Employee, the Organisation and <lb/>Society&apos; [1991] American Business Law Journal 29, 267, 306. <lb/>113 <lb/>Ibid p. 299. <lb/>114 Ibid p. 299, N.167. See also, K Rubinstein, &apos;Internal whistleblowing and Sarbanes-Oxley Section 806: Balancing the Interests <lb/>of Employee and Employer&apos; [2007-2008] New York Law School Law Review 52, 637, 650; TM Dworkin, and JP Near, <lb/>&apos;Whistleblowing Statutes: Are They Working?&apos; [1987] American Business Law Journal 241, 242-243. <lb/>115 <lb/>See Association of Certified Fraud Examiners, 2008 Report to the nation on occupation fraud &amp; Abuse 18 (2008). <lb/>116 <lb/>Proposed Rules for Implementing the Whistle-blower provisions of section 21F of the Securities Exchange Act 1934, 75 Fed. <lb/>Reg. 70,496. <lb/></listBibl>

			Copyedited by: MS <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">The Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013: Smart Regulatory <lb/>Regime?</note>
      
      <page>• Page 17 of 17 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>breached by unscrupulous bankers. To deal with the regulation being captured or frus-<lb/>trated in any way, it recommended the threat of &apos;electrification&apos; in the Bill in the form <lb/>of two distinct powers for the regulators, namely the first reserve power and the second <lb/>reserve power. The first power would enable the regulator to take steps that could lead <lb/>to full separation of retail and investment activities within a group. The first reserve <lb/>power made it into the Act, whereas the second power was rejected. <lb/>However, the fact remains that the regulator would be allowed to change legisla-<lb/>tion. It is unreasonable that in this case the regulator would be exercising parliamentary <lb/>powers, because it is parliament alone that can make and change public policy, even if <lb/>parliament were to confer legislative powers on the regulator. <lb/>A better view in this context would be that there should be an automatic periodic <lb/>review of the ring-fence legislation. This would help to create a formidable regulatory <lb/>system instead of merely relying on the regulator, which would always be susceptible <lb/>to &apos;capture&apos; by special interest groups at a serious cost to the rest of the society. Periodic <lb/>revision of this legislation, although a rare phenomenon, is justifiable on the basis of <lb/>public interest and the fact that financial regulation, like the financial sector itself, is a <lb/>special case; regardless, avoidance of market failures and the stability of the financial <lb/>system and consequently the stability of the entire economy should be the focus. <lb/>Furthermore, to ensure that bankers do not breach the ring-fence, it is also impor-<lb/>tant to have a robust and effective whistle-blowing system and economic incentives in <lb/>place, which protect the potential whistle-blowers from retaliation and reward them <lb/>generously, regardless of whether they choose to report internally or externally, as also <lb/>found in section 922 Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act <lb/>(Dodd-Frank Act). This is a lesson that can be learnt from the dichotomy of Dodd-<lb/>Frank and SOX. The whistle-blower provision could be the single most important <lb/>regulation for the protection of investors, financial institutions, and the stability of the <lb/>financial system as a whole. Whistle-blowing is a cost-effective and preventive meas-<lb/>ure, which, if included in such regulation, would certainly enhance the stability of the <lb/>financial system. <lb/></body>
      
     17.5 <lb/>17.10 <lb/>17.15 <lb/>17.20 <lb/>17.25 <lb/>17.30 <lb/>17.35 <lb/>17.40 <lb/>17.45 <lb/>17.46<lb/>


	</text>

</TEI>