<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">The climate-related financial disclosure regulations 2022: A step in the right direction for ESG in the private sector</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Lloyd</forename>
          <surname>Brown</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-08T13:43:54.120Z">1/8/2026 2:43:54 PM</date>
        <title>review </title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1177__14614529221111854</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2022</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1177/14614529221111854</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Lloyd Brown. (2022). The climate-related financial disclosure regulations 2022: A step in the right direction for ESG in the private sector. Environmental Law Review, 24(3), 214-223. DOI: 10.1177/14614529221111854</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T14:43:19.928212Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-19T14:43:19.928212Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-22T16:05:32.083Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Done</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-28T09:10:21.157Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-06T15:29:32.330Z" status="checked" who="#li">
      <desc>Validation completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-08T14:16:13.482Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-08T14:16:13.501Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text>
			<front>1 <lb/>The Climate-related Financial Disclosure Regulations 2022: A step in the <lb/>right direction for ESG in the private sector <lb/>Author Biography <lb/>Dr Lloyd Brown <lb/>Lecturer at the Hilary Rodham Clinton School of Law, Richard Price Building, Swansea <lb/>University, Singleton Park, Swansea, SA2 8PP <lb/>Key words <lb/>Climate change, climate-related risks, ESG, CSR, regulation. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>This legislative note examines the recent regulatory changes that were introduced on 6 April <lb/>2022, and which consequently affect the Companies Act 2006 and the Limited Liability <lb/>Partnerships (Account and Audit) (Application of Companies Act 2006) Regulations 2008. <lb/>The amendments mean that companies and limited liability partnerships (LLPs) that fall <lb/>within the regulations&apos; scope must now disclose their climate change risks and opportunities. <lb/>It is submitted in this work that these amendments are a step in the right direction for <lb/>&quot;environment social governance&quot; (ESG) in the private sector. Indeed, the need to report on <lb/>climate change risk is likely to drive the appetite of affected businesses to develop their ESG <lb/>programs within their overall risk management frameworks. Together with this intrinsic <lb/>impact, the changes are also likely to increase ESG and CSR within the markets more <lb/>broadly. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>This legislative note evaluates the recent changes that have been made to the Companies Act <lb/>2006, 1 and the Limited Liability Partnerships (Account and Audit) (Application of <lb/>Companies Act 2006) Regulations 2008, 2 in respect to the climate change disclosure <lb/>requirements of certain companies and limited liability partnerships (LLPs). The amending <lb/>regulations are, viz: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 Companies Act 2006. <lb/>2 Limited Liability Partnerships (Account and Audit) (Application of Companies Act 2006) <lb/>Regulations 2008 (2008/1911). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>(i) <lb/>the Companies (Strategic Report) (Climate-related Financial Disclosure) <lb/>Regulations 2022 (hereafter, the &quot;Companies Regulations 2022&quot;); 3 and moreover, <lb/>(ii) <lb/>the equivalent amendments which have been made to LLPs pursuant to the <lb/>Limited Liability Partnerships (Climate-related Financial Disclosure) Regulations <lb/>2022 (hereafter, the &quot;LLP Regulations 2022&quot;). 4 <lb/>The regulations at issue were brought into force on 6 April 2022, 5 and the amendments that <lb/>are created apply &apos;in respect of financial years beginning on or after that date.&apos; 6 Together <lb/>with their individual designations, both above-named regulations may be conveniently and <lb/>conjointly referred to as the &quot;Climate-related Financial Disclosure Regulations 2022&quot;, or, <lb/>more simply, as &quot;the regulations&quot;, throughout this note. <lb/>This note is ultimately concerned with this secondary legislation that has been created to <lb/>prompt greater private sector reporting on climate-related risks and opportunities 7 for: <lb/>publicly quoted companies, large private companies, and LLPs. 8 It is hereby argued that their <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>3 Companies (Strategic Report) (Climate-related Financial Disclosure) Regulations 2022 (SI <lb/>2022/31). <lb/>4 Limited Liability Partnerships (Climate-related Financial Disclosure) Regulations 2022 (SI <lb/>2022/46). For a succinct description of these changes, see, &apos;Essential Corporate News -<lb/>week ending January 21, 2022&apos; (Norton Rose Fulbright, January 2022) <lb/>&lt;https://www.nortonrosefulbright.com/en/knowledge/publications/991be932/essential-<lb/>corporate-news-week-ending-january-21-2022&gt; accessed 2 May 2022. <lb/>5 Department for Business, Energy &amp; Industrial Strategy, &apos;Mandatory climate-related <lb/>financial disclosures by publicly quoted companies, large private companies and LLPS: Non-<lb/>binding guidance&apos; (HM Government, February 2022) 6 <lb/>&lt;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_dat <lb/>a/file/1056085/mandatory-climate-related-financial-disclosures-publicly-quoted-private-cos-<lb/>llps.pdf&gt; accessed 2 May 2022. <lb/>6 &apos;Mandatory climate-related financial disclosures for large companies&apos; (Simmons&amp;Simmons, <lb/>23 February 2022) &lt;https://www.simmons-<lb/>simmons.com/en/publications/ckz49qxok1ent0a27fu6c53wd/mandatory-climate-related-<lb/>financial-disclosures-for-large-companies&gt; accessed 2 May 2022. <lb/>7 Above n. 5. <lb/>8 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>enactment is a step in the right direction for &quot;environmental, social, and governance&quot; (ESG) <lb/>programs in the private sector, and for managing the threat of climate change therein. <lb/>Inwardly, further reporting is going to be intrinsically good for ESG considerations and <lb/>programs within the private sector; the principal benefit will certainly stem from the <lb/>increased transparency and accountability that is likely to now be seen through the disclosure <lb/>of climate-related data through reporting streams. Outwardly, of course, increased ESG <lb/>considerations is highly likely to further assist in the greening of the markets and their actors; <lb/>and ultimately, this should assist in the design and percolation of further non-financial <lb/>policies more widely, leading to better &quot;corporate social responsibility&quot; (CSR) initiatives and <lb/>programs. These terms are thoroughly defined, and discussed further, in the section of this <lb/>note which provides the author&apos;s analysis of the impact of the regulations. <lb/>This note is structured simply, and as follows: First, background information is provided on <lb/>what the changes are and why they have been brought into force. Secondly, a detailed <lb/>overview of the 2022 regulations is provided, demonstrating the new legislations&apos; scope and <lb/>requirements. Thirdly, the author goes on to set out their ideas about how the regulations are <lb/>likely to impact the private sector and the markets in respect to ESG and CSR commitments. <lb/>Within this third section, ESG, as a concept, is defined and such programs are considered as <lb/>part of companies and LLPs&apos; &quot;risk management&quot; techniques more generally. Finally, the <lb/>note provides a conclusion to sum up the themes that lie within the work. <lb/>Background <lb/>Given that it has been many years since the Companies Act 2006 was brought into force, it is <lb/>inevitable that some of its sections, and the 2008 Regulations, require updating to better <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>reflect the modern commercial reality of dealing with &quot;non-financial risks&quot;. Whilst in the 21 st <lb/>century the term &quot;non-financial&quot; risks may not be the most helpful, with the differences that <lb/>exist between &quot;financial&quot; and &quot;non-financial&quot; risks becoming increasingly blurred, the term <lb/>is still used here to distinguish the two categories and to reflect the language used within the <lb/>literature. It is acknowledged however that while climate change is a risk that is external <lb/>from, what may be called, the &quot;pure&quot; financial risks (e.g., credit and securities risks), 9 ESG <lb/>issues can nevertheless cause significant financial damage to the private sector. <lb/>The need for such updating of the Companies Act 2006 and the 2008 Regulations is <lb/>illustrated for example, and inter alia, by the need to now comply with the government&apos;s Net <lb/>Zero Strategy and the findings of the Task Force on Climate-related Financial Disclosures <lb/>(TCFD). 10 The TCFD findings are of particular note. It may be suggested indeed that the <lb/>2017 TCFD Report is the fons et origio of the Climate-related Financial Disclosure <lb/>Regulations 2022. The TCFD&apos;s 2017 report warned that, &apos;One of the most significant, and <lb/>perhaps misunderstood, risks that organizations face today relates to climate change.&apos; 11 <lb/>Amongst other things, the Task Force recommended that the &apos;preparers of climate-related <lb/>financial disclosures provide such disclosures in their mainstream (i.e., public) annual <lb/>financial filings.&apos; 12 And the regulations&apos; amendments that have been instigated can be seen <lb/>as an example of putting this recommendation into practice. The importance of the TCFD&apos;s <lb/>report cannot be understated as it has similarly influenced the reporting of &quot;climate change <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>9 L.A. Brown, &apos;Bad debt and green issues: Managing environmental risks in borrowers&apos; <lb/>corporate insolvencies&apos; (2018) 20(3) ELR 137. <lb/>10 Department for Business, Energy &amp; Industrial Strategy, &apos;Net Zero Strategy: Build Back <lb/>Greener&apos; (HM Government, October 2021). <lb/>11 Task Force on Climate-related Financial Disclosures, &apos;Final Report: Recommendations of <lb/>the Task Force on Climate-related Financial Disclosures&apos; (TCFD, June 2017) 3 <lb/>&lt;https://assets.bbhub.io/company/sites/60/2021/10/FINAL-2017-TCFD-Report.pdf&gt; <lb/>accessed 2 May 2022. <lb/>12 Ibid. at (iv). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>risk&quot; in the law governing pension fund trusts, and particularly occupational pension <lb/>schemes. 13 Given its importance in developing climate-related risk appreciation in the <lb/>private sector, the Task Force warns that, &apos;Climate change poses risks to companies, financial <lb/>institutions and individuals alike. Both physical and transition risks could have material <lb/>impacts on the value of companies and their assets&apos;. 14 This is clearly echoed in the guidance <lb/>document which supports, and explains, the regulations (hereafter, &quot;the guidance&quot;). 15 <lb/>Undeniably the guidance is interesting for the fact that it clearly acknowledges the findings of <lb/>the TCFD, 16 which can be viewed as instrumental for the creation and enforcement of the <lb/>regulations. 17 <lb/>Undoubtedly the regulations in question are a part of the larger, and important, trend of <lb/>climate-related reporting requirements that have emerged within the financial markets, and <lb/>within the companies and institutions that operate within those markets. While this increased <lb/>&quot;greening&quot; of the financial markets has made companies and partnerships susceptible to <lb/>&quot;greenwashing&quot; their business activities, 18 it is nonetheless argued here that the regulatory <lb/>amendments are going to be beneficial inwardly and outwardly for affected companies and <lb/>LLPs and the markets more generally. <lb/>The Climate-related Financial Disclosure Regulations 2022 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 Occupational Pension Schemes (Climate Change Governance and Reporting) Regulations <lb/>2021, SI 2021/839. See also, Pension Schemes Act 2021, s 124. <lb/>14 Above n. 5 at 5. <lb/>15 Above n. 7. <lb/>16 Ibid. at 5. <lb/>17 Ibid. <lb/>18 Stephen Morris, &apos;HSBC faces greenwashing accusations from UK advertising watchdog&apos; <lb/>Friday, Financial Times (London, 29 April 2022) &lt;https://www.ft.com/content/6c08ae5f-<lb/>214f-4a5f-801e-6c849a3e517d&gt; accessed 2 May 2022. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>The regulations at issue have been clearly introduced in the above section but are further <lb/>explained here. These regulations were created on 17 January 2022 and brought into force on <lb/>6 April 2022. 19 They apply to the financial years starting on or after the date of their <lb/>enforcement. 20 There are no exemptions for any business that falls within their scope, 21 and <lb/>the Secretary of State must review the provisions &apos;from time to time&apos; 22 and &apos;publish a report <lb/>setting out the conclusions of the review&apos;; 23 this first report is to be published before 6 April <lb/>2027. 24 <lb/>In a document setting out the &quot;roadmap to sustainable investing&quot;, which was also heavily <lb/>influenced by the Task Force&apos;s 2017 report (as above), 25 the Chancellor of the Exchequer, <lb/>Rishi Sunak MP, stated that the government is committed to: <lb/>&apos;Ensuring the financial sector is equipped to play its part is vital. Aligning the <lb/>financial system with a sustainable future will bring real benefits for the environment <lb/>and society. It is an opportunity to boost economic growth, create jobs, and level up <lb/>the UK regions.&apos; 26 <lb/>Thus these regulations have been directly influenced by the government&apos;s desire to &quot;green&quot; <lb/>the financial sector, following its year as the holder of the COP26 Presidency. Moreover, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>19 Above n. 5 at 4. <lb/>20 Companies Regulations 2022, reg. 1(1)-(2). <lb/>21 Above n. 5 at 9. <lb/>22 Companies Regulations 2022, reg 5(1)(a). <lb/>23 Ibid. at reg 5(1)(b). <lb/>24 Ibid. at reg 5(2). <lb/>25 HM Treasury, &apos;Greening Finance: A Roadmap to Sustainable Investing&apos; (HM Government, <lb/>October 2021) &lt;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/greening-finance-a-roadmap-<lb/>to-sustainable-investing&gt; accessed 2 May 2022. <lb/>26 Ibid. at 2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>under the Paris Agreement, the UK government is &apos;bound by international law to act <lb/>consistently with the new global-level aims of limiting global warming well below 2 °C; <lb/>pursuing efforts to 1.5 °C and achieving net zero emissions in the second half of the <lb/>century.&apos; 27 <lb/>Scope <lb/>It is necessary to begin by outlining the scope of the Climate-related Financial Disclosure <lb/>Regulations 2022. Disclosures are to be made in the strategic report at the group level, or at <lb/>the company level where there is no consolidated reporting. 28 Therefore subsidiaries within a <lb/>consolidate group of a UK parent are not required to separately report their climate-related <lb/>risks and opportunities, as these will be made known in the consolidated report. 29 However, <lb/>the &quot;global operations&quot; of companies and LLPs are required to be disclosed in the report, so <lb/>the scope is not only specific to UK operations. 30 <lb/>It is clear from the guidance that the disclosure requirements apply to large companies and <lb/>LLPs. 31 However, that is not too discouraging as supply chains and market forces should <lb/>assist in driving change in small to medium size businesses, too. To briefly expand on this <lb/>point, as large companies must now comply with the legislation that requires climate <lb/>reporting on, inter alia, risks and opportunities and processes, it may be likely that they will <lb/>demand additional compliance from companies that fall within their supply chain but are not <lb/>subject to the new regulatory demands. In accordance with the guidance the categories of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>27 &apos;Explanatory Memorandum on the Paris Agreement&apos; (gov.uk, no date) <lb/>&lt;https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_dat <lb/>a/file/558185/EM_Paris_Ag.pdf&gt; accessed 2 May 2022. <lb/>28 Above n. 5 at 7. <lb/>29 Ibid. <lb/>30 Ibid. <lb/>31 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>companies and LLPs that are subject to the climate disclosures under the regulations include <lb/>the following: <lb/>• All companies that are currently required to produce a non-financial <lb/>information statement, being UK companies that have more than 500 <lb/>employees and have either transferable securities admitted to trading on a UK <lb/>regulated market or are banking companies or insurance companies (Relevant <lb/>Public Interest Entities (PIEs)); <lb/>• UK registered companies with securities admitted to AIM with more than 500 <lb/>employees; <lb/>• UK registered companies not included in the categories above, which have <lb/>more than 500 employees and a turnover of more than £500m; <lb/>• Large LLPs, which are not traded or banking LLPs, and have more than 500 <lb/>employees and a turnover of more than £500m and; <lb/>• Traded or banking LLPs which have more than 500 employees. 32 <lb/>Further information about the guidance&apos;s above summary of affected companies and LLPs <lb/>can be found in regulations 3 and 2 of the Companies&apos; Regulations 2022 and the LLP <lb/>Regulations 2022, respectively. Now that the remit of the legislation has been made known, <lb/>the section below sets out, in greater detail, the reporting requirements that have been brought <lb/>into force under the legislation. <lb/>Disclosure requirements <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>32 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>The new regulations affect existing legislation, as has been already noted. More specifically <lb/>however, amendments are made to sections 414C, 414CA and 414CB of the Companies Act <lb/>2006, 33 and sections Regulations 12A and 12B of the Limited Liability Partnerships <lb/>(Accounts and Audit) (Application of Companies Act 2006) Regulations 2008. 34 The <lb/>guidance states that, &apos;These regulations for companies and LLPs both require climate-related <lb/>financial disclosures to be made against a common list of requirements.&apos; 35 Under regulation <lb/>4 of the Companies Regulations 2022, &apos;The non-financial and sustainability information <lb/>statement must contain the climate-related financial disclosures of the company&apos;. 36 This is <lb/>echoed in regulation 4 of the LLPs Regulations 2022. 37 Indeed, the guidance fleshes out the <lb/>reporting requirements in further detail. It states that, to comply with the new disclosure <lb/>obligations, companies and LLPs must provide the following in their strategic reports: <lb/>(a) a description of the governance arrangements of the company or LLP in relation to <lb/>assessing and managing climate-related risks and opportunities; <lb/>(b) a description of how the company or LLP identifies, assesses, and manages <lb/>climate-related risks and opportunities; <lb/>(c) a description of how processes for identifying, assessing, and managing climate-<lb/>related risks are integrated into the overall risk management process in the company <lb/>or LLP; <lb/>(d) a description of-<lb/>(i) the principal climate-related risks and opportunities arising in connection <lb/>with the operations of the company or LLP, and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>33 Ibid. at 6. <lb/>34 Ibid. <lb/>35 Ibid. at 9. <lb/>36 Companies Regulations 2022, reg. 4. <lb/>37 LLPs Regulations 2022, reg. 4. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>(ii) the time periods by reference to which those risks and opportunities are <lb/>assessed; <lb/>(e) a description of the actual and potential impacts of the principal climate-related <lb/>risks and opportunities on the business model and strategy of the company or LLP; <lb/>(f) an analysis of the resilience of the business model and strategy of the company or <lb/>LLP, taking into consideration of different climate-related scenarios; <lb/>(g) a description of the targets used by the company or LLPs to manage climate-<lb/>related risks and to realise climate-related opportunities and of performance against <lb/>those targets; and <lb/>(h) the key performance indicators used to assess progress against targets used to <lb/>manage climate-related risks and realise climate-related opportunities and a <lb/>description of the calculations on which those key performance indicators are based. 38 <lb/>It is important to note that some of the above information may indeed have been disclosed <lb/>within some companies&apos; annual review documentation before the inception of the legislative <lb/>changes. However, a system that allows companies to drive the degree of the reporting <lb/>inevitably results in inconsistent reporting and differing data. 39 This can be seen by a <lb/>viewpoint that was expressed by the Financial Reporting Council in 2019, namely: <lb/>While different companies will be affected by climate change in different ways, many <lb/>will need to respond to potential increases in cost and/or decreases in revenue… For <lb/>some companies, climate-related issues are material now, with impacts already <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>38 Above n. 5 at 9-10. <lb/>39 Financial Reporting Council, &apos;Climate-related corporate reporting -Where to next?&apos; (FRC, <lb/>October 2019) &lt;https://www.frc.org.uk/getattachment/22ee8a43-e8ca-47be-944b-<lb/>c394ecb3c5dd/Climate-Change-v9.pdf&gt; accessed 24 May 2022 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>disrupting supply chains and changing consumer behaviour. For others, climate-<lb/>related issues are key to longer-term strategic planning decisions. 40 <lb/>The above information needs to be reported in the &quot;Non-Financial and Sustainability <lb/>Information Statement&quot;, and in a manner so that the reader is able to clearly understand the <lb/>climate-related risks and opportunities that are associated with a given company or LLP. 41 <lb/>Additionally, the information must also be &apos;included within the Annual Report and <lb/>Accounts.&apos; 42 It need not take on any particular format or structure, 43 but the level of detail <lb/>that is required should be such that a reader would not have to undertake further research to <lb/>understand the risks and opportunities associated with the company or partnership. 44 Thus <lb/>the information that is necessitated is that which allows and contributes to a person&apos;s <lb/>&apos;understanding of the business.&apos; 45 In this respect company directors, who are the ones that <lb/>now have a legal duty to provide the information in their company&apos;s or LLPs&apos; Annual <lb/>Report, 46 are able to omit any such information that they deem is unnecessary for a person to <lb/>understand the business. 47 <lb/>Perhaps the ability to omit information that is not necessary for a person to understand the <lb/>business may emerge as a potential area of contention in the future, but only time will tell. <lb/>While one can only speculate about this at the time of writing, the author believes that the <lb/>directors&apos; ability to omit information from the information statement and annual report <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>40 Above n. 5 at 3. <lb/>41 Ibid. at 17. <lb/>42 Ibid. <lb/>43 Ibid. at 18. <lb/>44 Ibid. at 17. <lb/>45 Ibid. <lb/>46 Ibid. at 18. <lb/>47 Ibid. at 17. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>should not be too damaging for climate risk reporting. As suggested above, the legislative <lb/>changes state that company reporting should exhibit a level of detail to assist external parties <lb/>from understanding the business, and climate risk and opportunities will inevitably form a <lb/>part of that information. In short, it is unlikely that a company director would be able to <lb/>&quot;cover up&quot; their climate risk and opportunities since these are materially significant to <lb/>understanding the business and will ultimately have to be reported as such. <lb/>Now that the regulations and their guidance have been outlined, the below section discusses <lb/>the impact of the climate-related disclosures on the companies and LLPs that are captured <lb/>within the regulatory framework&apos;s scope. It is also necessary to outline how the amendments <lb/>may benefit the economic markets more generally. <lb/>The impact of the regulations <lb/>Before anything else, it is worthwhile briefly explaining the main differences between ESG <lb/>and CSR. It should be noted that this commentary is primarily concerned with the former <lb/>concept, albeit the latter is still something that needs to be considered in outline. As Cook <lb/>explains, &apos;the major difference between them [ESG and CSR] is that CSR is a business model <lb/>used by individual companies, but ESG is a criterion that investors use to assess a company <lb/>and determine if they are worth investing in.&apos; 48 Gorley confirms Cook&apos;s definition, as <lb/>follows: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>48 James Cook, &apos;What is the difference between ESG and CSR?&apos; (Business Leader, 2 <lb/>September 2021) &lt;https://www.businessleader.co.uk/what-is-the-difference-between-esg-<lb/>and-<lb/>csr/#:~:text=Whilst%20ESG%20and%20CSR%20are,they%20are%20worth%20investing%2 <lb/>0in.&gt; accessed 2 May 2022. Brackets added. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>CSR initiatives are voluntary and tend to focus on improving a company&apos;s <lb/>relationships with external constituencies. For example, CSR managers might <lb/>oversee corporate philanthropy or partnerships with community groups. ESG <lb/>programs are generally implemented as a broader corporate strategy to address <lb/>investor or regulatory demands. ESG practice involves fairly rigorous measuring and <lb/>reporting on environmental, social, and corporate governance activities to understand <lb/>the risks and impacts. 49 <lb/>Subsequent to making the above observation, Gorley thereafter goes on to describe the <lb/>difference between ESG on the one hand and &quot;risk management&quot; techniques on the other. <lb/>And this is pertinent for this analysis also. He explains that: &apos;An ESG program is a form of <lb/>risk management. A wide range of stakeholders -from investors, lenders, and government <lb/>agencies, to communities, customers, employees, and others -is looking at ESG <lb/>performance.&apos; 50 By creating mandatory reporting the regulations will directly impact upon <lb/>the ESG programs of affected entities. This opinion strongly corresponds with Gorley&apos;s <lb/>thoughts, i.e., &apos;An ESG rating and the information used to calculate the score provide <lb/>investors and executives with tools to evaluate a company&apos;s ESG performance and risk <lb/>management.&apos; 51 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>49 A. Gorley, &apos;What is ESG and Why It&apos;s Important for Risk Management&apos; (Sustainalytics, 2 <lb/>March 2022) &lt;https://www.sustainalytics.com/esg-research/resource/corporate-esg-<lb/>blog/what-is-esg-why-important-risk-<lb/>management#:~:text=ESG%20Explained&amp;text=An%20ESG%20program%20is%20a,lookin <lb/>g%20at%20corporate%20ESG%20performance&gt; accessed 2 May 2022. <lb/>50 Ibid. <lb/>51 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>The use of risk management is not new. Environmental risks arguably first came onto the <lb/>agenda of the private sector in the late 1990s and early 2000s. 52 The early environmental <lb/>regulatory frameworks that were enforced primarily created regulatory risks for businesses. 53 <lb/>These new risks greatly encouraged the development of specific &quot;environmental due <lb/>diligence&quot; methods as a means to mitigate the new threats; 54 this can be seen particularly <lb/>clearly in commercial bank lending, where environmental due diligence techniques were <lb/>specifically developed to process loan applications. 55 Hart acknowledges the importance of <lb/>risk management as a tool for adapting to climate-related risks, viz: <lb/>Risk management approaches to climate change have evolved during the past decade <lb/>[his book was published in 2016, it should be noted], with the development of new <lb/>products and structured financial arrangements to manage an expanding array of risks. <lb/>These mechanisms are gaining attention in the international climate negotiations and <lb/>could become an important element of adaptation efforts implemented under the <lb/>UNFCCC. 56 <lb/>Therefore, it is hoped that the regulations will affect companies and LLPs inwardly and <lb/>outwardly. Inwardly, because improved ESG reporting will inevitably reduce the instances <lb/>of the &quot;physical&quot; and &quot;transition&quot; climate change risks that may be incurred. 57 Hart states, <lb/>for example, that, &apos;A warming climate increases the magnitude, impact and complexity of <lb/>various types of risks … As risks become more inter-related, their complexity can undermine <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>52 L. Brown, &apos;Land pollution, environmental risks and bank lending&apos; (2015) 17(4) ELR 237. <lb/>53 Ibid. <lb/>54 Ibid. <lb/>55 Ibid. <lb/>56 C. Hart, Climate Change and the Private Sector (Routledge: London, 2013) at 210. <lb/>Brackets added. <lb/>57 Above n. 5 at 5. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>our ability to accurately assess risks and our potential exposure of them.&apos; 58 And it is clear <lb/>that physical and transitional risks have been a significant driver for the creation of the 2022 <lb/>regulations, given that they are defined in the guidance: <lb/>Physical risks are those arising from the climatic impact of higher average <lb/>temperatures (such as the increased frequency and severity of extreme weather <lb/>events), whilst transition risks are those arising from the changes in technology, <lb/>markets, policy, regulation, and consumer sentiment which will result from our <lb/>transition to net zero. 59 <lb/>As well as inwardly affecting businesses, this legislative note also believes that the changes <lb/>will be outwardly beneficial to the markets. It is submitted that the development of a <lb/>widespread ESG criterion for climate-related risks and opportunities should provide a better <lb/>means of assessing ESG performance. Such a criterion creates a reputational risk for affected <lb/>businesses, as a lower ESG performance rating may act to impede investor confidence, <lb/>amongst other things. Moreover, the need to publicly expose climate change data may lead <lb/>to ignominious vitriol for some, and the threat of this could drive affected businesses to find <lb/>more innovative solutions for dealing with climate change. 60 That said, as well as increasing <lb/>the appetite for ESG within the private sector, it is hoped that the regulations will strengthen <lb/>CSR within the markets more generally. Even though the need to disclose climate change <lb/>risk and opportunities under the respective regulations applies to large businesses, it is also <lb/>likely that small and medium sized businesses will adopt greener initiatives in response to <lb/>supply chains&apos; demands, etc. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>58 Above n. 56 at 210-211. <lb/>59 Above n. 5 at 5. <lb/>60 Above n. 49. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Encouragingly, there is empirical evidence to demonstrate that reporting is an important <lb/>method for making financial institutions and businesses more environmentally astute. For <lb/>instance, very similar reporting requirements have been created for pension fund trusts. 61 In <lb/>fact, the guidance comments on the link that lies between the present regulations and the <lb/>Occupational Pension Scheme (Climate Change Governance and Reporting) Regulations <lb/>2021, which is the statute enforcing climate-related reporting amongst pension funds. 62 It <lb/>states that, &apos;Those large pension schemes are likely to have significant investments in <lb/>companies that are within scope of these regulations. Disclosures provided by companies <lb/>will inform the disclosures of large pension schemes under the pensions legislation.&apos; 63 And <lb/>vice versa. Interestingly, given the case law in this area, 64 the pensions legislation now <lb/>mandates that climate change risk be considered as a &quot;financially material risk&quot; that needs to <lb/>be reported within the pensions&apos; Statement of Investment Principles (SIP). 65 The SIP is not <lb/>too dissimilar to companies&apos; information statements and annual reports. While it is outside <lb/>the scope of this commentary to provide a comparison of these two systems of reporting, it is <lb/>necessary to opine that both operate to disseminate important information to interested <lb/>parties, and this should assist in protecting the environment through sectoral &quot;greening&quot; and <lb/>improved ESG and CSR practices. <lb/>Another interesting observation that may be made is how climate risks and opportunities may <lb/>be treated by pensions, LLPs, and companies. For instance, are these specific risks and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>61 L. Brown, &apos;Towards &quot;Green&quot; Trusteeship: new statutory amendments for occupational <lb/>pension trustees&apos; (2019) 25(10) Trusts &amp; Trustees 978. <lb/>62 Above n. 17. <lb/>63 Above n. 5 at 20. <lb/>64 See, Cowan v Scargill [1985] Ch 270. <lb/>65 Pension Schemes Act 2021, s. 124. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>opportunities, by their very nature, viewed as purely financial risks or purely non-financial <lb/>risks or something of a hybrid? Again, this line of thought may fall outside of the scope of <lb/>this work, but the author wishes to raise it nonetheless to encourage and promote the <lb/>possibility of further research on this matter. While it may be too early to tell how companies <lb/>and LLPs, as a collective, view climate-related risks and opportunities, it is clear that within <lb/>the pension sector climate change has transcended to a type of financially material risk. 66 <lb/>And the above observation may come as a surprise to some given the well-known judgment <lb/>of Sir Robert Megarry VC in Cowan v Scargill [1985], where he stated that the &quot;best <lb/>interests&quot; of beneficiaries are their &quot;best financial interests&quot;. 67 However, in evaluating <lb/>Megarry&apos;s judgment and interpretation of the word &quot;benefit&quot;, it would be entirely wrong to <lb/>suggest that the Vice Chancellor was stipulating that investment opportunities should be <lb/>sequestered into the purely financial and the purely non-financial opportunities. 68 Indeed <lb/>Megarry&apos;s judgment runs much deeper than that, and can be used to propitiate the advocates <lb/>of better ESG governance and reporting. 69 The reason for this is because Megarry <lb/>understood that the word &quot;benefit&quot;, when applied to trusts, is flexible, broad, and elusive. 70 <lb/>As it is with pension funds so to it must be applied to companies and LLPs. It is greatly <lb/>hoped that the regulation&apos;s consolidated approach to reporting risks and opportunities will <lb/>provide greater clarity in the sector, together with assisting in developing the knowledge and <lb/>understanding of how companies and LLPs perceive risks and opportunities more generally. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>66 L. Brown, &apos;Cowan v Scargill and the fiduciary duty of investment: has the nature of the <lb/>investment duty changed and what is currently driving &quot;socially responsible investing&quot; in <lb/>pension schemes?&apos; (2020) 26(8-9) Trust &amp; Trustees 756. <lb/>67 Cowan v Scargill [1985] Ch 270 (Sir Robert Megarry) at 287. <lb/>68 Above n. 66 at 761. <lb/>69 Ibid. <lb/>70 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>A further reason why pensions have been singled out is because of the sector&apos;s significant <lb/>wealth, and ultimately, its ability to affect the markets through their investment policies and <lb/>opportunities. 71 This explains why, in the present regulations, large companies and LLPs <lb/>have been specifically targeted. Interestingly, in recent years, it is evident that pensions have <lb/>divested heavily from fossil fuels, with some having already fully divested from this sector <lb/>on behalf of their beneficiaries. 72 The link between this divestment phenomenon and the new <lb/>climate duties imposed on pension fund trustees and managers remains unclear. However, it <lb/>would not be incorrect to say that the need to report climate-related risks, as a financially <lb/>material risk, is likely to have had some bearing on this investment trend. 73 It may therefore <lb/>be argued that the change of investment appetite amongst pension trustees and managers <lb/>suggests that regulation is impacting on the financial markets&apos; understanding, and approaches <lb/>to, climate change risks and opportunities. It is hoped that the Climate-related Financial <lb/>Disclosure Regulations 2022 will be equally as impactful for companies and LLPs. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In conclusion, this legislative note has set out the changes that have been brought into force <lb/>by the Climate-related Financial Disclosure Regulations 2022. It argues that the changes that <lb/>have been implemented to update the law in respect to companies and LLPs is a positive step <lb/>in the right direction. The note has delineated the scope of the regulatory changes, as well as <lb/>providing an account of the disclosure requirements that are now mandated for certain <lb/>businesses. Together with describing the enforced changes, this note has also provided some <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>71 L. Brown, &apos;The Pension Schemes Act 2021: new duties for trustees and managers of <lb/>pension fund trusts&apos; (2021) 27(9) Trusts &amp; Trustees 880, 884. <lb/>72 P. Collinson, &apos;UK&apos;s biggest pension fund begins fossil fuels divestment&apos; The Guardian <lb/>(London, 29 July 2020) &lt;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2020/jul/29/national-<lb/>employment-savings-trust-uks-biggest-pension-fund-divests-from-fossil-fuels&gt; accessed 2 <lb/>May 2022. <lb/>73 Above n. 71. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>analysis of their possible impact, looking both inwardly and outwardly. Inwardly, businesses <lb/>will unavoidably be moved by the need to react to the regulations, and this should, in turn, <lb/>lead to greater ESG considerations within the private sector. That said, the exact risk <lb/>management processes that will be created in the light of the amending regulations falls <lb/>outside the scope of this piece of work and may be left for further research. Additionally, <lb/>there is likely to also be outward effects of the need to report climate change risks and <lb/>opportunities more greatly. Reporting will inevitably create reputational risks for businesses, <lb/>and a failure to meet the ESG criterion may lead to, inter alia, increased public scrutiny and a <lb/>lack of investor confidence, with this legislative comment noting empirical evidence of the <lb/>possible link between reporting and greater ESG consideration, through the amendments that <lb/>have been made to occupational pension schemes. <lb/></body>    
    
    <div type="annex">Word Count: 4,725 (inc. footnotes) <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="conflict">Declaration of conflicting interests <lb/>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, <lb/>and/or publication of this article. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="funding"> Funding <lb/>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of <lb/>this article. <lb/></div>

			<page>20 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>