<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Shifting Priorities: Are Attitudes Changing at the International Criminal Court about Trials in absentia?</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Caleb H.</forename>
          <surname>Wheeler</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="sandfort">Johanna Sandfort</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T09:09:15.543Z">30/01/2026 10:09:15</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1163__15718123-bja10036</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2021</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1163/15718123-bja10036</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Caleb H. Wheeler. (2021). Shifting Priorities: Are Attitudes Changing at the International Criminal Court about Trials in absentia?. International Criminal Law Review, 21(1), 97-125. DOI: 10.1163/15718123-bja10036</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T14:41:10.149272Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-19T14:41:10.149272Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-29T12:09:43.347Z" status="draft" who="#sandfort">
      <desc>Corrections_completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-30T14:06:25.781Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_FinalSchulze</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T09:01:23.287Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-21T15:35:19.580Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T09:24:00.500Z" status="candidate" who="#cboulanger">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ORCA -Online Research @ <lb/>Cardiff <lb/>This is an Open Access document downloaded from ORCA, Cardiff University&apos;s institutional <lb/>repository:https://orca.cardiff.ac.uk/id/eprint/146902/ <lb/>This is the author&apos;s version of a work that was submitted to / accepted for publication. <lb/>Citation for final published version: <lb/>Wheeler, Caleb H. 2021. Shifting priorities: are attitudes changing at the international criminal court about <lb/>trials in absentia? International Criminal Law Review 21 (1) , pp. 97-125. 10.1163/15718123-bja10036 <lb/>Publishers page: https://doi.org/10.1163/15718123-bja10036 <lb/>Please note: <lb/>Changes made as a result of publishing processes such as copy-editing, formatting and page numbers may <lb/>not be reflected in this version. For the definitive version of this publication, please refer to the published <lb/>source. You are advised to consult the publisher&apos;s version if you wish to cite this paper. <lb/>This version is being made available in accordance with publisher policies. See <lb/>http://orca.cf.ac.uk/policies.html for usage policies. Copyright and moral rights for publications made <lb/>available in ORCA are retained by the copyright holders. <lb/>1 <lb/></front>

			<body>1 <lb/>Introduction <lb/>A recent decision in the Gbagbo and Blé Goudé case (&apos;Gbagbo et al. case&apos;) at <lb/>the International Criminal Court (&apos;ICC&apos;) raised the possibility of a shift away from the <lb/>Court&apos;s long-standing practice of only holding trial in the presence of the accused. <lb/>The final paragraphs of the 28 May 2020 Appeals Chamber decision asserts that any <lb/>future trial proceedings in the Gbagbo et al. case may be held in the absence of Mr. <lb/>Gbagbo and Mr. Blé Goudé should they be released from custody and then later fail <lb/>to appear for trial. This assertion runs counter to the past practice of the Court and, if <lb/>followed, could pave the way for the ICC to conduct trials in absentia. While the <lb/>decision offers little support for its position, it does assert that such a practice is <lb/>compatible with the Rome Statute, existing international practice and general <lb/>principles of law. <lb/>The accused&apos;s right to be present during trial is an important component of the <lb/>human right to a fair trial. The International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights <lb/>was the first international treaty to recognise the right to be present; it has since been <lb/>included in the foundational documents of every modern international criminal justice <lb/>institution as well as a number of regional human rights conventions. 1 The accused&apos;s <lb/>presence during trial ensures that he or she has the opportunity to participate and <lb/>understand the proceedings against them, particularly during the presentation and <lb/>examination of the evidence. 2 It is also thought that an accused who is present during <lb/>their trial can better exercise a number of other fair trial rights, including: assisting in <lb/>the preparation and presentation of their defence; consulting with and selecting their <lb/>own counsel; confronting the witnesses or the evidence presented against them; and <lb/>testifying on their own behalf. 3 It can be much more difficult for the accused to <lb/>exercise these rights when trial is held in absentia, potentially threatening the overall <lb/>fairness of the proceedings. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (adopted 16 December 1966, entered into force <lb/>23 March 1976) 999 UNTS 171. <lb/>2 Sarah J. Summers, Fair Trials: The European Criminal Procedure Tradition and the European Court <lb/>of Human Rights (Hart Publishing, Oxford, 2007), p. 117; Fawzia Cassim, &apos;The Accused&apos;s Right to be <lb/>Present: A Key to Meaningful Participation in the Criminal Process&apos; 38 Comparative and International <lb/>Law Journal of South Africa (2005) 285, 285-286. <lb/>3 Daryl A. Mundis, &apos;Current Developments: Improving the Operation and Functioning of the <lb/>International Criminal Tribunals&apos; 94 American Journal of International Law (2000) 759, 761. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>This article examines the Appeals Chamber&apos;s decision in an effort to <lb/>determine whether it is correct in finding that trials in absentia can be held at the ICC. <lb/>It does this in three parts. First, it examines the Appeals Chamber&apos;s interpretation of <lb/>Article 63(1) of the Rome Statute and compares that understanding of the Statute to <lb/>the existing jurisprudence on this issue. Second, it considers the past practice of <lb/>international criminal justice institutions when determining whether it is appropriate <lb/>to try an accused in their absence and whether the procedure suggested in this <lb/>decision comports with that past practice. Finally, it conducts an analysis of national <lb/>law on the issue of whether it is appropriate to try an absconding accused and whether <lb/>it is possible to identify a general principle of law with regard to the issue. The article <lb/>concludes that the Appeals Chamber&apos;s decision is incorrect to the extent that it <lb/>suggests that trial in absentia is currently permissible at the ICC. The article finds that <lb/>the Appeals Chamber&apos;s interpretation of the Statute is dubious and that the procedure <lb/>currently employed at the ICC does not fully accord with past international practice or <lb/>domestic law. Should the ICC wish to permit trials in absentia, certain changes would <lb/>have to be made to the Statute and Rules of Procedure and Evidence to comply with <lb/>the accused&apos;s right to be present at trial. <lb/>1.1 <lb/>The Appeals Chamber&apos;s Decision <lb/>On 28 May 2020, the Appeals Chamber issued a decision in the on-going <lb/>Gbagbo et al. case (&apos;Gbagbo Appeals Decision&apos;). 4 The primarily purpose of the <lb/>decision was two-fold: to deny Mr. Gbagbo&apos;s request for reconsideration of a decision <lb/>relating to an earlier appeal filed by the Prosecution, and to review the conditions of <lb/>release imposed on the acquitted defendants. In that context, the Gbagbo Appeals <lb/>decision makes several assertions about the accused&apos;s right to be present at trial and <lb/>how it should be understood in conjunction with the law relevant at the ICC. First, it <lb/>suggests that there is nothing in the Statute, if &apos;properly understood&apos;, to prevent the <lb/>Court from proceeding with the trial of an accused who is willfully absent. 5 Second, it <lb/>explains that in its view &apos;the aim&apos; of Article 63(1) of the Statute is to protect an <lb/>accused who wishes to attend their trial, but who is unable to do so through no fault of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>4 ICC, Prosecutor v. Gbagbo et al., No ICC-02/11-01/15, Appeals Chamber, Public Redacted Decision <lb/>on Counsel for Mr Gbagbo&apos;s Request for Reconsideration of the &apos;Judgment on the Prosecutor&apos;s Appeal <lb/>Against the Oral Decision of Trial Chamber I pursuant to Article 81(c)(i) of the Statute&apos; and on the <lb/>Review of Condition on the Release of Mr Gbagbo and Mr Blé Goudé, 28 May 2020. <lb/>5 Ibid., para. 70. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>their own. 6 In the opinion of the Appeals Chamber, that goal is perverted when an <lb/>accused prevents trial from being conducted at all by refusing to appear. 7 Third, the <lb/>Appeals Chamber claims its position is supported by &apos;general principles of law&apos; <lb/>derived from international and domestic law. 8 To better understand this decision it is <lb/>necessary to examine how Article 63(1) has been understood in the past and to <lb/>determine how international and domestic courts have treated the right to be present at <lb/>trial. <lb/>2 <lb/>The Proper Interpretation of Article 63(1) <lb/>The section of the Gbagbo Appeals Decision addressing trial in absentia is <lb/>relatively brief, making it necessary to refer to other similar decisions to gain a better <lb/>understanding of its basis. The author of the Gbagbo Appeals Decision, Judge Chile <lb/>Eboe-Osuji has played a role in most of the ICC&apos;s earlier rulings in favour of holding <lb/>trials in absentia. Judge Eboe-Osuji joined majority opinions of the Trial Chambers in <lb/>Prosecutor v. Ruto et al. (&apos;Ruto Trial Chamber Decision&apos;) and Prosecutor v. Kenyatta <lb/>(&apos;Kenyatta Trial Chamber Decision&apos;) and later wrote a dissenting opinion following a <lb/>Motion for Reconsideration in the Kenyatta case (&apos;Kenyatta Dissent&apos;), all of which <lb/>advocated for trials in absentia under some circumstances. Therefore, a combined <lb/>reading of these decisions is instructive as better contextualises the arguments being <lb/>advanced by the Appeals Chamber in the Gbagbo Appeals Decision. <lb/>In the Gbagbo Appeals Decision, the Appeals Chamber raises the idea that the <lb/>Statute, &apos;if properly understood&apos;, does not prevent the ICC from conducting trial in <lb/>absentia. 9 This is a recurring theme in the decisions on this issue, and one that the <lb/>Ruto Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta Dissent elaborate on. Both of these <lb/>earlier decisions attempt to discern the &apos;plain meaning&apos; of Article 63(1), finding that it <lb/>only imposes a duty on the accused to be present during trial and does require the <lb/>Court to only hold trial in the presence of the accused. 10 This interpretation is justified <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>6 Ibid., para. 69. <lb/>7 Ibid. <lb/>8 Ibid., para. 70. <lb/>9 Gbagbo Appeals Decision, supra note 4, para. 70. <lb/>10 ICC, Prosecutor v. Uhuru Kenyatta, No. ICC-01/09-02/11, Trial Chamber, Dissenting Opinion of <lb/>Judge Eboe-Osuji to Decision on the Prosecution&apos;s Motion for Reconsideration of the Decision <lb/>Excusing Mr. Kenyatta from Continuous Presence at Trial, 26 November 2013, paras. 72 (&apos;Kenyatta <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>on the basis that the Statute&apos;s drafters would have used different language in Article <lb/>63(1) if they had wished to specifically prohibit trial from taking place in the <lb/>accused&apos;s absence. 11 In fact, the Ruto Trial Chamber Decision takes the position that <lb/>Article 63(1) is not concerned with the rights of the accused at all, but only exists to <lb/>impose a duty on the accused so that the Trial Chamber may &apos;maintain judicial <lb/>control over&apos; him or her. 12 Any right to be present the accused may possess can be <lb/>found in Article 67(1)(d), which identifies the accused&apos;s presence at trial as one of the <lb/>minimum guarantees to which she or he is entitled. 13 Accordingly, the function of <lb/>Article 67(1)(d) is to ensure that an accused is not prevented from attending trial if <lb/>they should so desire. 14 <lb/>It must be noted that the &apos;proper interpretation&apos; of the Statute described in the <lb/>Gbagbo Appeals decision does not fully accord with the &apos;plain meaning&apos; of the <lb/>Statute identified in the Ruto Trial Chamber Decision or the Kenyatta dissent. The <lb/>implication in the Gbagbo Appeals decision is that the purpose of Article 63(1) is to <lb/>render illegal any trial that takes place in the absence of an accused who wants to be <lb/>present during trial but is unable to attend through no fault of their own. 15 This <lb/>interpretation suggests that Article 63(1) is concerned, at least in part, with both the <lb/>accused&apos;s right and duty to be present at trial. That interpretation differs from the Ruto <lb/>Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta dissent. Both of these decisions take the <lb/>position that Article 63(1) is only concerned with the accused&apos;s duty to be present. 16 It <lb/>would therefore appear that the Gbagbo Appeals Decision does not entirely <lb/>harmonise with these two earlier decisions when interpreting Article 63(1). <lb/>This discrepancy in how Article 63(1) has been interpreted in these decisions <lb/>may largely be a matter of semantics as the Gbagbo Appeals decision, the Ruto Trial <lb/>Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta dissent all suggest that the accused has both a <lb/>right and a duty to be present at trial regardless of the statutory basis for that <lb/>inference. This is relatively non-controversial. A more contentious issue arises when <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Dissent&apos;); ICC, Prosecutor v. Ruto et al., No. ICC-01/09-01/11, Trial Chamber, Decision on Mr Ruto&apos;s <lb/>Request for Excusal from Continuous Presence at Trial, 18 June 2013, paras. 43 (&apos;Ruto Trial Chamber <lb/>Decision&apos;). <lb/>11 Ibid. <lb/>12 Ruto Trial Chamber Decision, supra note 10, para. 53. <lb/>13 Ibid, paras. 77, 80; see also Art. 67(1)(d) of The Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court <lb/>(&apos;ICC Statute&apos;). <lb/>14 Kenyatta Dissent, supra note 10, para. 80. <lb/>15 Gbagbo Appeals Decision, supra note 4, para. 69. <lb/>16 Kenyatta Dissent, supra note 10, para. 80; Ruto Trial Chamber Decision, supra note 10, paras. 39-<lb/>40. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>one considers how the Court may proceed when the accused voluntarily does not <lb/>appear for trial. The Ruto Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta take the position <lb/>that Article 63(1) gives the Court an &apos;unquestionable statutory basis&apos; to require the <lb/>accused&apos;s attendance at trial and that their failure to appear can result in the forfeiture <lb/>of the right to be present. 17 This forfeiture of the right allows the Court to hold a trial <lb/>in absentia &apos;unconstrained by the elements that must be present in order to find <lb/>waiver.&apos; 18 It is through this interpretation of the Statute that those advocating in <lb/>favour of trials in absentia have justified their position. <lb/>This understanding of Article 63(1) has not been widely embraced. In fact, a <lb/>variety of Judges at the ICC have expressed a multitude of opinions about how to <lb/>properly interpret Article 63(1). In Ruto et al., a majority of the Appeals Chamber <lb/>attributed a different meaning to Article 63(1) when it overruled the Ruto Trial <lb/>Chamber Decision. There, the Appeals Chamber found that the Article&apos;s inclusion in <lb/>the Statute, was meant: <lb/>[T]o reinforce the right of the accused to be present at his or her trial and…to <lb/>preclude any interpretation of the Statute that would allow the Court to <lb/>proceed in the accused&apos;s absence based on a finding that the accused had <lb/>implicitly waived his or her right to be present by absconding or failing to <lb/>appear for trial. 19 <lb/>In so finding, the Appeals Chamber essentially ascribed two purposes to the Article. <lb/>The first is meant to reinforce the accused&apos;s right to be present at trial. The second <lb/>acts to prevent a finding that the Court can proceed in the accused&apos;s absence on the <lb/>basis of an implied waiver of that right. This ruling would appear to refute the <lb/>interpretation of Article 63(1) advocated in the Gbagbo Appeals Decision, the Ruto <lb/>Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta Dissent. <lb/>In truth, neither of the purposes identified in the Ruto Appeals Decision <lb/>directly contradicts the interpretation of Article 63(1) set out in the Gbagbo Appeals <lb/>Decision, the Ruto Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta Dissent. Both of these <lb/>approaches to Article 63(1) stand for the proposition that the accused has a right to be <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>17 Kenyatta Dissent, supra note 10, para. 79; Ruto Trial Chamber Decision, supra note 10, para. 42. <lb/>18 Kenyatta Dissent, supra note 10, para. 79. <lb/>19 ICC, Prosecutor v. Ruto et al., No. ICC-01/09-01/11, Appeals Chamber, Judgment on the appeal of <lb/>the Prosecutor against the decision of Trial Chamber V(a) of 18 June 2013 entitled &quot;Decision on Mr <lb/>Ruto&apos;s Request for Excusal from Continuous Presence at Trial&quot;, 25 October 2013, para. 54 (&apos;Ruto <lb/>Appeals Decision&apos;). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>present at trial. They also accept that an absent accused should not be found to have <lb/>implicitly waived their right to be present. The difference between the interpretations <lb/>can be found in the conclusions drawn from these seemingly compatible findings. <lb/>Where the Gbagbo Appeals Decision, the Ruto Trial Chamber Decision and the <lb/>Kenyatta Dissent determine that Article 63(1) permits the Court to hold trials in <lb/>absentia on the basis of forfeiture, therefore dispensing with the need to find an <lb/>implied waiver, the implication of the Appeals Chamber&apos;s opinion is that the article <lb/>was included in the Statute for the specific purpose of precluding the possibility of <lb/>trials in absentia. 20 Therefore, while some of the reasoning may be the same, the <lb/>outcome is entirely different. <lb/>Judge Kourula and Judge Ušaka also argue in favour of a different <lb/>interpretation of Article 63(1) from that contained in the Gbagbo Appeals Decision, <lb/>the Ruto Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta Dissent. In their Joint Separate <lb/>Opinion to the Ruto et al. Appeals decision, Judge Kourula and Judge Ušaka assert <lb/>that the Trial Chamber has a duty to ensure that trial takes place in the presence of the <lb/>accused. 21 This stands in direct opposition to the belief expressed in the Gbagbo <lb/>Appeals Decision, the Ruto Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta Dissent that the <lb/>only duty described in the article is the one placed on the accused. Judge Kourula and <lb/>Judge Ušaka go on to state that the ordinary meaning of Article 63(1) demonstrates <lb/>that trial must take place in the presence of the accused. 22 They do concede that some <lb/>absences from trial are permissible, but only those that are so inconsequential that <lb/>they do not violate the fundamental requirement that the accused be present. 23 If one <lb/>were to follow this approach, a trial conducted entirely in the absence of the accused <lb/>would far exceed the type of de minimis absences permitted by the Statute. This <lb/>directly conflicts with the plain meaning ascribed to the Statute in the in the Gbagbo <lb/>Appeals Decision, the Ruto Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta Dissent. <lb/>Two other judges have also addressed this issue, albeit in less detail. Judge <lb/>Carbuccia found in her dissenting opinion to the Trial Chamber&apos;s original decision in <lb/>Ruto et al. that Article 63(1) clearly rules out proceeding in the accused&apos;s absence in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>20 Ibid., para. 53. <lb/>21 ICC, Prosecutor v. Ruto et al., No. ICC-01/09-01/11, Appeals Chamber, Joint Separate Opinion of <lb/>Erkki Kourula and Anita Ušaka to the Judgment on the appeal of the Prosecutor against the decision of <lb/>Trial Chamber V(a) of 18 June 2013 entitled &quot;Decision on Mr Ruto&apos;s Request for Excusal from <lb/>Continuous Presence at Trial&quot;, 25 October 2013, para. 5. <lb/>22 Ibid., para. 10. <lb/>23 Ibid., para. 3. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>any circumstances other than those found in Article 63(2). 24 Additionally, Judge <lb/>Ozaki wrote in her partially dissenting opinion to the Trial Chamber&apos;s original <lb/>Kenyatta decision that the ordinary meaning of Article 63(1) imposes a duty on the <lb/>accused to be present during trial. 25 However, she goes on to state that the Court also <lb/>has a corresponding duty to only conduct trial when the accused is present. 26 The <lb/>ordinary meaning of Article 63(1), as understood by Judge Ozaki, is that the <lb/>accused&apos;s presence is a requirement of trial necessitating that the accused be <lb/>continuously and physically present. 27 <lb/>The wide range of different meanings ascribed to Article 63(1) suggests that <lb/>the plain meaning of the article remains ambiguous. This does not mean that the <lb/>interpretations set out in the decisions penned by Judge Eboe-Osuji are wrong; it is <lb/>certainly possible that those decisions represent the correct understanding of the <lb/>Statute. It does mean, however, that the matter is not as clear as the Gbagbo Appeals <lb/>Decision, the Ruto Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta Dissent suggest. Rather <lb/>than engage with the contrary jurisprudence and commentary on this issue in an effort <lb/>to alleviate this ambiguity, the decisions choose to ignore it and instead try to bolster <lb/>their arguments through reliance on an alleged general principle of law. Whether that <lb/>general principle of law is as indisputable as suggested is also open to interpretation. <lb/>3 <lb/>Trial in absentia as a General Principle of (International) Law <lb/>In addition to suggesting that the Statute does not prevent the ICC from <lb/>proceeding in the absence of a willfully absent accused, the Gbagbo Appeals <lb/>Chamber also found that there is no general principle of law that would prevent it <lb/>from holding trials under those circumstances. 28 The ICC&apos;s Statute allows the Court to <lb/>be guided by general principles of law under certain circumstances. Article 21(1) of <lb/>the Rome Statute identifies the three different types of law that the ICC can apply <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>24 ICC, Prosecutor v. Ruto et al., No. ICC-01/09-01/11, Trial Chamber, Dissenting Opinion of Judge <lb/>Herrera Carbuccia to the Public Decision on Mr Ruto&apos;s Request for Excusal from Continuous Presence <lb/>at Trial, 13 June 2013, para. 5. <lb/>25 ICC, Prosecutor v. Kenyatta, No. ICC-01/09-02/11, Trial Chamber, Partial Dissenting Opinion of <lb/>Judge Ozaki to the Public Decision on Defence Request for Conditional Excusal from Continuous <lb/>Presence at Trial, 18 October 2013), para. 7. <lb/>26 Ibid. <lb/>27 Ibid., paras. 9-10. <lb/>28 Gbagbo Appeals Decision, supra note 4, para. 70. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>when reaching decisions and the hierarchy amongst those three types of law. 29 At the <lb/>top of the pyramid are laws purposefully devised for the Court, including the Statute, <lb/>the Elements of Crimes and the Rules of Procedure and Evidence. Second on the list <lb/>are different types of international law, with applicable treaties and principles and <lb/>rules of international law being explicitly identified. Finally, if recourse to those two <lb/>categories fails, the Court may then consider &apos;general principles of law&apos; derived from <lb/>national laws of legal systems of the world. Reliance on general principles of law is <lb/>only permitted to the extent that those principles are consistent with the first two <lb/>categories of laws identified by the Statute. 30 <lb/>There is an ambiguity in the Rome Statute about whether trial in absentia is <lb/>permitted at the ICC which is evidenced by the different ways in which Article 63(1) <lb/>has been interpreted. Therefore, recourse to the other applicable types of law is <lb/>necessary to resolve this issue. Based on the hierarchy contained in Article 21(1), it is <lb/>necessary to first consider whether it is permissible under international law to try a <lb/>willfully absent accused in absentia. That is because the Statute clearly places <lb/>principles and rules of international law ahead of general principles of law in the <lb/>order of legal sources to be considered by the Court. The Gbagbo Appeals Decision <lb/>cites the jurisprudence of the International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda (&apos;ICTR&apos;), <lb/>the United Nations Human Rights Committee (&apos;UNHRC&apos;) and the European Court of <lb/>Human Rights (&apos;ECtHR&apos;) in support of his proposition that a principle of international <lb/>law exists allowing trial to continue against a willfully absent accused. 31 The relevant <lb/>jurisprudence of each will be considered in turn to determine whether a principle or <lb/>rule of international law exists supporting the Appeals Chamber&apos;s conclusion. <lb/>The Gbagbo Appeals decision specifically identifies the Views expressed by <lb/>the United Nations Human Rights Committee in Mbenge v. Zaire and the holdings of <lb/>the European Court of Human Rights in three different cases as supporting its position <lb/>that trials in absentia are permissible at the ICC. The Appeals Chamber suggests that <lb/>those cases stand for the proposition that there is no &apos;blanket prohibition&apos; against trials <lb/>in absentia so long as certain criteria are met. 32 The Gbagbo Appeals decision <lb/>describes those criteria as follows: 1) the accused has adequate notice of the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>29 ICC Statute, supra note 13, Art. 28. <lb/>30 Ibid., Art. 21(3). <lb/>31 Gbagbo Appeals Decision, supra note 4, para. 70. <lb/>32 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>proceedings; 2) he or she declines to exercise their right to be present, waives that <lb/>right or absconds; and 3) measures are taken to ensure that trial is fair. 33 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>What constitutes adequate notice in international criminal law? <lb/>The first criterion identified in the Gbagbo Appeals decision is that the <lb/>accused has adequate notice of the proceedings against them. The UNHRC wrestled <lb/>with this issue in Mbenge v. Zaire, a matter involving an accused who was twice <lb/>convicted in absentia, and sentenced to death in both instances. 34 He alleged in his <lb/>communication to the UNHRC that in both instances he learned of the proceedings <lb/>through the media and that he was never summoned to appear for trial. 35 In its views, <lb/>the UNHRC found that in absentia proceedings are justified in some instances, but <lb/>that for those proceedings to be valid the accused must be notified about the <lb/>proceedings against them and of the date and place of trial. 36 The Committee <lb/>reinforced the importance of notifying the accused of the date and time of trial in <lb/>Osiyuk v. Belarus, when it determined that the trial court&apos;s failure to inform the <lb/>accused of that information violated the accused&apos;s right to be present. 37 This <lb/>interpretation of the notice requirement is also reinforced by the jurisprudence of the <lb/>ECtHR and the ICTR. In Sibgatullin v. Russia, the ECtHR determined that before a <lb/>court can find a that the accused waived his or her right to be present, it must first <lb/>establish &apos;whether the defendant has had the opportunity to know of the date of the <lb/>hearing and the steps to be taken in order to take part.&apos; 38 Therefore, a review of the <lb/>relevant international law would suggest that, to the extent that there is a principle of <lb/>international law permitting trials in absentia, it requires that the accused have notice <lb/>not only of the existence of the proceedings, but that they are also informed of the <lb/>date and location of trial so that they can exercise the right to be present. <lb/>The requirement that the accused be told not only that proceedings have been <lb/>instituted against them, but also the date and location of trial, goes beyond the <lb/>obligations of the appropriate notice requirement identified in the Gbagbo Appeals <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>33 Ibid. <lb/>34 UNHRC, Mbenge v. Zaire, Comm. No. 16/1977, Views, 25 March 1983, paras. 1.2-2.2. <lb/>35 Ibid., para. 2.2. <lb/>36 Ibid., para. 14.1. <lb/>37 UNHRC, Osiyuk v. Belarus, Comm. No. 1311/2004, Views, 30 July 2009, para. 8.3; see also United <lb/>Nations Human Rights Committee, &apos;General Comment No 32: Right of Equality Before Courts and <lb/>Tribunals and to Fair Trial&apos; (CCPR/C/GC/32), para. 36. <lb/>38 ECtHR, Sibgatullin v. Russia, App. No. 32165/02, Judgment, 14 September 2009, para. 46. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>decision. This distinction is significant because it appears the Appeals Chamber <lb/>applies the wrong notice standard in its decision. The Appeals Chamber asserts that <lb/>because both Mr. Gbagbo and Mr. Blé Goudé have previously appeared before the <lb/>Court, they have received proper notice sufficient to allow the Court to proceed in <lb/>their absence if either fails to attend any future trial hearings. 39 This conclusion is <lb/>based on the fact that both men made an initial appearance before the Court, thus <lb/>satisfying the requirements of Article 60 of the Statute. 40 However, the notice <lb/>requirement contained in Article 60 is not as extensive as what is required by the <lb/>UNHRC, the ECtHR and the ICTR. <lb/>Article 60 only requires that the Pre-Trial Chamber satisfy itself that the <lb/>accused has notice of two things: what crimes are alleged against them and what <lb/>rights they have under the Statute. 41 This falls short of the standard identified by the <lb/>UNHRC, the ECtHR and the ICTR. Therefore, notice provided in compliance with <lb/>Article 60 is not, by itself, sufficient under international law to allow proceedings to <lb/>take place in absentia. Notice would only be sufficient when the accused is informed <lb/>what they are accused of and when and where they will be tried for those alleged <lb/>crimes. The ICC&apos;s current procedure makes it impossible for an accused to learn all of <lb/>that information during the Article 60 initial proceedings in large part because it is <lb/>fair to early in the process for a trial date to be set. Therefore, that hearing alone can <lb/>never be sufficient to provide an accused with proper notice justifying trial in <lb/>absentia. <lb/>3.2 <lb/>The Accused Declines to Exercise the Right to be Present, Waives the Right <lb/>or Absconds <lb/>In addition to discussing the requisite notice needed before trial can be held in <lb/>absentia, the Gbagbo Appeals decision also identifies three actions that, when <lb/>performed by the accused, permits the ICC to proceed in absentia. They are when an <lb/>accused: 1) waives the right to be present; 2) declines to exercise their right to be <lb/>present; or 3) absconds. 42 Framing this as three different ways an accused can indicate <lb/>that they will not attend trial, with only one explicitly involving waiver, appears to <lb/>suggest that waiver is only one way in which the accused can demonstrate their assent <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>39 Gbagbo Appeals Decision, supra note 4, para. 68. <lb/>40 Ibid. <lb/>41 ICC Statute, supra note 13, Art. 60. <lb/>42 Gbagbo Appeals Decision, supra note 4, para. 70. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>to trial taking place in their absence. In fact, it is more appropriate to see these three <lb/>actions as all being a form of waiver, with the first constituting an explicit waiver and <lb/>the second and third and third representing types of implicit waiver. <lb/>This is confirmed when one compares the three types of absences identified in <lb/>the Gbagbo Appeals decision to the three examples of waiver identified by the <lb/>ECtHR. The three ways the European Court has identified that an accused can <lb/>unequivocally waive the right to be present are: by stating publicly or in writing that <lb/>he or she does not intend to participate in trial; where the evidence unequivocally <lb/>shows that the accused was aware of the charges and still did not appear; or where the <lb/>accused has become aware of the proceedings from unofficial sources and <lb/>intentionally evades an attempted arrest. 43 The first of these describes an explicit <lb/>waiver, the second describes an accused that declines to participate and the third <lb/>depicts an accused who has absconded. The similarities between these examples and <lb/>those provided in the Gbagbo Appeals decision are striking supporting the conclusion <lb/>that all three types of absence are a form of waiver. <lb/>3.2.1 The Accused Waives the Right to be Present <lb/>The first scenario suggested by the Gbagbo Appeals decision whereby a trial <lb/>chamber can proceed against an absent accused arises when the accused waives their <lb/>right to be present. The Rome Statute and the ICC&apos;s Rules of Procedure and Evidence <lb/>both contain indications of when the Court may proceed against the accused on the <lb/>basis of a waiver. The only statutory provision permitting the accused to absent <lb/>themself from trial is found in Article 61. This provision relates exclusively to the <lb/>Confirmation of Charges proceedings held before a Pre-Trial Chamber of the Court. It <lb/>permits the Pre-Trial Chamber to proceed with the Confirmation of Charges hearing <lb/>in the accused&apos;s absence under two circumstances. They are when the accused has: 1) <lb/>waived their right to be present; or 2) fled or otherwise cannot be found and all <lb/>reasonable steps are taken to inform them the hearing is taking place. 44 <lb/>The Statute is silent about what form waiver can take when an accused wishes <lb/>to allow the Confirmation of Charges Hearing to proceed in absentia. However, <lb/>Article 61(2)(a) is made operative by Rule 124 of the Rules of Procedure and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>43 ECtHR, Shkalla v. Albania, App. No. 26866/05, Judgment, 10 August 2011, para. 70; citing ECtHR, <lb/>Iavarazzo v. Italy, App. No. 50489/99, Judgment, 4 December 2001. <lb/>44 ICC Statute, supra note 13, Art. 61; the second of these two clauses relates to an absconding <lb/>accused, which is discussed in detail in section 3.2.3. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Evidence, which requires the accused seeking to absent themself from the hearing to <lb/>submit a written request for permission to be allowed to waive his or her right to be <lb/>present. 45 Under the rule, the Pre-Trial Chamber can elect to conduct consultations <lb/>with the parties and waiver will be only be granted if the Pre-Trial Chamber is <lb/>satisfied that the accused understands his or her right to be present and the <lb/>consequences of waiving that right. 46 This procedure has been used by the Court in <lb/>the past and in each instance it was determined that the accused was aware of their <lb/>rights and the consequences of waiving them. 47 Proceeding in this way guarantees that <lb/>the accused is aware of what rights they are giving up by choosing not to attend the <lb/>hearing. <lb/>The choice to include this provision at the Confirmation of Charges stage has <lb/>been interpreted as a concession to those national delegations in favour of allowing in <lb/>absentia trials at the ICC. 48 If true, this explanation supports the idea that the drafters <lb/>of the Rome Statute did not intend for trials to be conducted in absentia. Further, the <lb/>inclusion of a waiver procedure in Article 61 applicable only during the Confirmation <lb/>of Charges stage of proceedings suggests that the omission of a similar procedure <lb/>during the trial stage of proceedings was intentional. That the drafters could have <lb/>included a similar rule during trial, and did not, is indicative of the fact that they did <lb/>not believe that trial should be conducted in the accused&apos;s absence. <lb/>The ICC&apos;s Rules of Procedure and Evidence also contain provisions whereby <lb/>the accused can waive their right to be present during trial. Rules 134 ter and 134 <lb/>quater were added to the Rules in 2013 in response to sustained criticism directed at <lb/>the Court for its insistence on the presence of the defendants during trial proceedings <lb/>in the cases arising out of the 2007-08 post-election violence in Kenya. Both Uhuru <lb/>Kenyatta and William Ruto sought to absent themselves from their respective trials <lb/>following their election as president and deputy president in March 2013. During the <lb/>Assembly of State Parties in November 2013, various African nations, including <lb/>Botswana, Republic of Congo, Côte d&apos;Ivoire, the Gambia, Ghana, Namibia, Nigeria, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>45 Rule 124, International Criminal Court Rules of Procedure and Evidence (as amended 2013) (&apos;ICC <lb/>RPE&apos;). <lb/>46 Ibid. <lb/>47 ICC, Prosecutor v. Katanga, ICC-01/04-01/07, Pre-Trial Chamber, Transcript, Confirmation of <lb/>Charges Hearing, 11 July 2008, p. 23, lines 23-25; 24, lines 1-10; ICC, Prosecutor v. Banda and <lb/>Jerbo, ICC-02/05-03/09, Pre-Trial Chamber, Decision on Issues Related to the Hearing on the <lb/>Confirmation of Charges, 17 November 2010, para. 4. <lb/>48 Gregory S. Gordon, &apos;Toward an International Criminal Procedure: Due Process Aspirations and <lb/>Limitations&apos;, 45 Colum J Transnatl L (2007) 635-710, 683. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>South Africa, and Uganda (on behalf of the African Union), raised the issue of <lb/>amending the Rome Statute to provide greater protection for sitting heads of state. 49 <lb/>Several non-African Union states parties, most notably New Zealand, advocated in <lb/>favour of a compromise position. Instead of amending the Statute, which likely would <lb/>have proven to be an arduous process, New Zealand (and several other states) <lb/>suggested amending the Rules of Procedure and Evidence, &apos;that deal with the <lb/>practical problems that can arise where defendants wish to cooperate with the Court, <lb/>but where extraordinary circumstances exist.&apos; 50 As a result, Rules 134 bis, 134 ter and <lb/>134 quater were added to the Rules of Procedure and Evidence. <lb/>Of these new rules, only the latter two deal with waiver of the right to be <lb/>present (Rule 134 bis permits the accused to attend trial through an alternative means, <lb/>i.e. videoconferencing technology). Rule 134 ter authorises the accused to submit a <lb/>written request to the relevant trial chamber asking that they be excused from &apos;part or <lb/>parts&apos; of the trial. 51 Before granting such a request, the trial chamber must find that <lb/>four criteria have been met. They are: 1) exceptional circumstances justify the <lb/>absence(s); 2) alternative measures, such as changing the trial schedule or briefly <lb/>adjourning the trial would be inadequate; 3) the accused explicitly waives their right <lb/>to be present; and 4) the accused&apos;s rights are fully protected in their absence. 52 Rule <lb/>134 quater contains similar provisions, but can only be invoked by an accused <lb/>wishing to absent themself so that they may &apos;fulfill extraordinary public duties at the <lb/>highest national level&apos;. 53 It also does not limit the accused&apos;s possible absence to only <lb/>part or parts of the trial, meaning that the accused could potentially absent themself <lb/>from the entirety of trial. 54 <lb/>It could be argued that both Mr. Gbagbo and Mr. Blé Goudé explicitly waived <lb/>their right to be present permitting trial to take place in their absence should they not <lb/>appear. Both men were required to sign &apos;an undertaking&apos; in which they agreed that <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>49 Statements made by the representatives of Botswana, Republic of Congo, Côte d&apos;Ivoire, the Gambia, <lb/>Ghana, Namibia, Nigeria, South Africa, and Uganda (on behalf of the African Union) during the <lb/>General Debate, 12 Session of the Assembly of States Parties to the Rome Statute of the International <lb/>Criminal Court, 21 November 2013, <lb/>&lt;asp.icccpi.int/en_menus/asp/sessions/general%20debate/Pages/general%20debate%20_%20twelfth% <lb/>20session.aspx&gt;, accessed 13 August 2020. <lb/>50 Statement by the representative of New Zealand, 12 th Session of the Assembly of State Parties to the <lb/>Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court, 21 November 2013, &lt;asp.icccpi.int/iccdocs/ <lb/>asp_docs/ASP12/GenDeba/ICC-ASP12-GenDeba-NZ-ENG.pdf&gt;, accessed on 13 August 2020. <lb/>51 ICC RPE, supra note 45, Rule 134 ter. <lb/>52 Ibid. <lb/>53 ICC RPE, supra note 45, Rule 134 quater. <lb/>54 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>trial could proceed in their absence should they fail to appear. However, close <lb/>examination of the circumstances upon which that &apos;waiver&apos; was obtained indicates <lb/>that it does not meet the minimum safeguards for effective waiver outlined by the <lb/>ECtHR and previously adopted by the International Criminal Court. 55 As the ECtHR <lb/>made clear, the decision to waive the right to be present must be the result of the <lb/>accused&apos;s own free will and not the product of pressure or compulsion. Here, it could <lb/>be argued, that predicating a prisoner&apos;s release from custody on their agreement to <lb/>waive their right to be present at any future trial is the product of pressure or <lb/>compulsion and thus not an expression of the individual&apos;s free will. Thus, any waiver <lb/>made under those conditions would be invalid and could not justify proceeding in the <lb/>accused&apos;s absence. This would mean that the requirements of either Rule 134 ter or <lb/>Rule 134 quater would still need to be complied with before trial could be conducted <lb/>in the absence of Mr. Gbagbo or Mr. Blé Goudé. <lb/>Rules 124, 134 ter and 134 quater only permit the International Criminal <lb/>Court to proceed in the accused&apos;s absence upon the accused&apos;s written request and <lb/>when accompanied by an explicit waiver of their right to be present. None of these <lb/>rules permit the Court to proceed on the basis of an implicit waiver as expressly <lb/>advocated by Judge Eboe-Osuji in his Kenyatta dissent and implicitly asserted by the <lb/>Appeals Chamber in the Gbagbo Appeals decision. Further, there are no other <lb/>provisions in the Statute or the Rules of Procedure and Evidence that permit the Court <lb/>to proceed on the basis of an implied waiver of the right to be present. <lb/>Some might challenge this conclusion based on a superficial reading of Article <lb/>63(2) of the Statute. Article 63(2) states that if the accused &apos;continues to disrupt the <lb/>trial&apos; the Trial Chamber may order the removal of the accused from the courtroom. 56 <lb/>This provision has been described by some as the only exception to the rule that the <lb/>accused must be present during trial at the International Criminal Court. 57 To the <lb/>extent that this is true, it is a type of absence based on an implied waiver of the right <lb/>to be present, as the accused is being excluded on the basis of his actions rather than <lb/>an explicit written or oral statement that they wish to be removed from the courtroom. <lb/>However, Article 63(2), when correctly understood, is not describing a type of <lb/>absence but should instead be construed as establishing an alternative means by which <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>55 Ruto Appeals Decision, supra note 19, para. 51. <lb/>56 ICC Statute, supra note 13, Art. 63(2). <lb/>57 Ruto Trial Chamber Decision, supra note 10, para. 5; Antonio Cassese, International Criminal Law <lb/>(Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2003), p. 402. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>the accused can be present during trial. The article states that when an accused is <lb/>removed from the courtroom the trial chamber must make provision &apos;for him or her to <lb/>observe the trial and instruct counsel from outside the courtroom.&apos; 58 That means that <lb/>the accused is still able to follow the proceedings and participate in trial even if they <lb/>are not physically present in the courtroom. International criminal justice institutions <lb/>have increasingly recognized that the right to be present at trial is met when an <lb/>accused can understand and participate in proceedings regardless of whether they are <lb/>actually physically present in the courtroom. 59 This is in recognition of the fact that so <lb/>long as conditions exist to permit the accused to exercise the right to be present, their <lb/>actual physical location is irrelevant. <lb/>Rule 134 bis supports this understanding of Article 63(2). Rule 134 bis <lb/>permits an accused to request that they be permitted to attend part or parts of trial <lb/>through the use of video technology rather than in-person appearance in the <lb/>courtroom. 60 The rule does not describe an accused who participates in trial in this <lb/>manner as absent, but instead finds that they are &apos;allowed to be present through the <lb/>use of video technology.&apos; 61 This is analogous to the Article 63(2) provision stating <lb/>that when a disruptive accused is removed from the courtroom provisions must be <lb/>made to permit them to observe trial and instruct counsel &apos;through the use of <lb/>communications technology.&apos; 62 To the extent that participation through video <lb/>technology is considered an alternative means of being present, so too should <lb/>participation by communications technology. Understanding the Statute in this way <lb/>also resolves what has been considered a tension in the Statute between the Article 63 <lb/>declaration that &apos;the accused shall be present during trial&apos; and the Article 63(2) <lb/>pronouncement that appears to introduce an exception to that general rule. However, <lb/>if Article 63(2) is read as describing an alternative means of attendance that tension <lb/>disappears. In both instances the accused is present during trial, just not physically <lb/>present, meaning that the different provisions of the Statute remain in harmony. <lb/>While there are some situations in international criminal law where an accused <lb/>may waive the right to be present at trial, they do not all comply with the Rome <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>58 ICC Statute, supra note 13, Art. 63(2). <lb/>59 Caleb H Wheeler, The Right To Be Present At Trial In International Criminal Law (Brill, Leiden, <lb/>2018), p. 234. <lb/>60 ICC RPE, supra note 45, Rule 134 bis. <lb/>61 Ibid. <lb/>62 ICC Statute, supra note 13, Art. 63(2). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Statute. The ICC&apos;s Statute and the Rules of Procedure and Evidence are quite clear <lb/>that waiver of the right to be present must be explicit and should generally be in <lb/>writing. There is no provision in either the Statute or the Rules of Procedure and <lb/>Evidence to suggest that waiver can be implied. Portions of the trial may proceed in <lb/>the accused&apos;s absence, but only when accompanied by an explicit waiver of the right <lb/>to be present that is freely given and free from compulsion. Therefore, the suggestion <lb/>in the concluding paragraphs of the Gbagbo Appeals decision that any future trial <lb/>proceedings may be held in the absence of Mr. Gbagbo or Mr. Blé Goudé should they <lb/>fail to appear is unsupported by the Statute and rules governing the Court. As a result, <lb/>the Appeals Chamber&apos;s decision is overly broad and fails to properly account for the <lb/>unique structure of the ICC. <lb/>3.2.2 Declining to exercise the right to be present <lb/>As a preliminary matter, it is necessary to make clear that there is a difference <lb/>between an accused who does not attend trial and one who declines to attend or <lb/>refuses to attend. To not attend is objective, it simply means that the trial is taking <lb/>place and the accused is not there. To decline to attend or to refuse to attend is <lb/>subjective, it involves an accused who has notice of the proceedings and who decides, <lb/>for whatever reason, that they do not wish to be present during trial. It is only really in <lb/>the latter situation that an accused can be seen as waiving their right to be present. <lb/>The ECtHR has explained in a number of decisions that the right to be present may be <lb/>waived either explicitly or implicitly, however for the waiver to be valid it must be <lb/>unequivocal. 63 An accused who does not attend trial, without some indication as to <lb/>why they did not attend, cannot be seen as waiving the right to be present because it is <lb/>impossible for the trying court to find that the decision not to appear is unequivocal. <lb/>The jurisprudence of the ICTR, the International Criminal Tribunal for the <lb/>former Yugoslavia (&apos;ICTY&apos;) and the Special Court for Sierra Leone (&apos;SCSL&apos;) <lb/>supports the conclusion that an accused who declines to exercise the right to be <lb/>present is implicitly waiving that right. The ICTR&apos;s Appeals Chamber makes this <lb/>clear in its Appeals Judgment in Prosecutor v. Nahimana. The Gbagbo Appeals <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>63 ECtHR, Sejdovic v. Italy, App. No. 56581/00, Judgment, 1 March 2006, para. 86; ECtHR, Poitrimol <lb/>v. France, Judgment, App. No. 14032/88, 23 November 1993, para. 31; ECtHR, Kwiatkowska v. Italy, <lb/>52868/99, Judgment, 30 November 2000; ECtHR, Shkalla v. Albania, App. No. 26866/05, Judgment, <lb/>10 August 2011, para. 70; citing ECtHR, T. v. Italy, App. No. 14104/88, Judgment, 12 October 1992, <lb/>para. 28. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>decision relies on the Nahimana decision for the proposition that, &apos;it is not <lb/>impermissible to proceed with a trial in the absence of an accused who knowingly <lb/>refuses to be present&apos; during their trial. 64 What the Gbagbo Appeals decision fails to <lb/>mention is that the Nahimana decision was justified on the basis that the defendant&apos;s <lb/>refusal to appear constituted an implicit waiver of the right to be present. 65 The <lb/>ICTR&apos;s Appeals Chamber went on to find that trials in absentia are permissible so <lb/>long as the accused exercises a free, unequivocal and knowledgeable waiver of the <lb/>right to be present. 66 In this instance, the defendant&apos;s refusal to appear constituted <lb/>such a waiver and that the Trial Chamber did not act in error by proceeding in his <lb/>absence. 67 <lb/>The ICTY also found that an accused&apos;s refusal to attend trial should be treated <lb/>as an implicit waiver of the right to be present. In the Čelibicí Camp case, the ICTY&apos;s <lb/>Trial Chamber drew a direct link between the accused&apos;s decision not to attend trial <lb/>and waiver. In reference to one of the defendants, Zdravko Mucić, who refused to <lb/>appear for trial, it stated, &apos;[i]f he wants to stay away, he has to forgo his rights -he <lb/>has to waive his right to be present.&apos; 68 The SCSL also found that the refusal to appear <lb/>and waiver were linked. Charles Taylor regularly absented himself from his trial, <lb/>although he did not always explicitly waive his right to be present. On those occasions <lb/>when he did not, the SCSL interpreted his refusal to appear as a waiver of the right to <lb/>be present. 69 On this basis, and despite the fact it is listed separately from waiver in <lb/>the Gbagbo Appeals decision, the decision not to attend should be understood as a <lb/>type of implicit waiver subject to the same rules as other forms of waiver. <lb/>If a refusal to attend is to be considered an implied form of waiver, as it <lb/>appears it must be under international law, it is necessary to guarantee that the <lb/>accused has all of the information necessary to make an informed decision not to <lb/>appear. As previously discussed, that includes knowing not only the nature of the <lb/>charges alleged, but also the date and location of trial. The Gbagbo Appeals decision <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>64 Gbagbo Appeals Decision, supra note 4, para. 70. <lb/>65 ICTR, Prosecutor v. Nahimana et al., Case No. ICTR-99-52-A, Appeals Chamber, Judgement, 28 <lb/>November 2007, para. 116. <lb/>66 Ibid., para. 109. <lb/>67 Ibid., para. 116. <lb/>68 ICTY, Prosecutor v. Delalić et al., Case No. IT-96-21, Trial Chamber, Trial Transcript, 16 April <lb/>1998, p. 11262, lines 2-3. <lb/>69 SCSL, Prosecutor v. Taylor, Case No. SCSL-03-01-T, Trial Chamber, Trial Transcript, 4 June 2007, <lb/>p. 258, lines 28-29; p. 259, line 1; p. 267, lines 4-16; SCSL, Prosecutor v. Taylor, Case No. SCSL-03-<lb/>01-T, Trial Chamber, Trial Transcript, 25 June 2007, p. 342, lines 13-19. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>makes no mention of any need to inform the accused of the date and location of trial <lb/>before proceeding against them. Instead, it relies on the fact that Mr. Gbagbo and Mr. <lb/>Blé Goudé had been made sufficiently aware of the proceedings as a result of their <lb/>previous appearances before the Court. That approach does not comport with <lb/>international law and therefore it cannot form a permissible basis for proceeding in <lb/>absentia at the ICC. Ensuring that the accused is informed of the date and location of <lb/>trial could cure this problem as it would then allow the accused to make an informed <lb/>decision a out whether they wish to attend their trial. This does not, of course, avoid <lb/>the problem that there does not appear to be any legal basis for finding that an <lb/>accused at the ICC may implicitly waive their right to be present at trial. <lb/>3.2.3 When an accused absconds <lb/>The Gbagbo Appeals decision also indicates that a trial chamber can hold a <lb/>trial in absentia when the accused absconds. In international criminal law, an <lb/>absconding accused is generally one who has been subject to the control of the court, <lb/>has been released, usually on bail, and then fails to appear before the court at the <lb/>appointed date and time. 70 Because being in the custody of the court, and then being <lb/>released, is a prerequisite to absconding, it is reasonable to surmise that an accused <lb/>who absconds is aware of the charges against him or her. This knowledge, and the <lb/>accused&apos;s subsequent failure to appear, acts as an implicit waiver of the right to be <lb/>present and an absconding accused may be tried in absentia. 71 <lb/>The Rome Statute contains a provision under which the ICC can proceed <lb/>against an absconding accused, however it only applies to the Confirmation of <lb/>Charges proceedings and not to trial. 72 Article 61(2)(b) of the Statute allows the Pre-<lb/>Trial Chamber to hold the Confirmation of Charges hearing in the accused&apos;s absence <lb/>when they have &apos;fled or cannot be found and all reasonable steps&apos; have been taken to <lb/>secure their appearance. 73 The Court has yet to elaborate on what the phrase &apos;all <lb/>reasonable steps&apos; means in the context of Article 61(2)(b). Despite this, the wording <lb/>of this subsection is important for another reason. It states that all reasonable steps <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>70 William A. Schabas, &apos;In Absentia Proceedings Before International Criminal Courts&apos;, in Göran <lb/>Sluiter and Sergey Vasiliev (eds.), International Criminal Procedure: Towards a Coherent Body of <lb/>Law (CMP Publishing, London, 2009), p. 378. <lb/>71 Cassese, supra note 57, p. 402. <lb/>72 ICC Statute, supra note 13, Art. 61(2)(b). <lb/>73 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>must be taken to accomplish three different goals. First, they must be taken to secure <lb/>the accused&apos;s appearance before the Court. Second, all reasonable steps have to be <lb/>taken to inform the accused of the charges against them. Finally, it is also necessary to <lb/>take all reasonable steps to inform the suspect that a hearing is going to be held. The <lb/>third part directly relates to the importance of informing the accused of the date and <lb/>location of the trial. <lb/>The reason all reasonable steps must be taken to accomplish these three <lb/>purposes is to guarantee that the accused has all of the information necessary to allow <lb/>them to participate in the hearing and still chooses not to do so. It is meant to <lb/>eliminate the possibility that the accused&apos;s non-appearance resulted from anything <lb/>other than their decision not to attend. There is no point in taking all reasonable steps <lb/>to inform someone that a hearing is going to be held against them if they are not <lb/>simultaneously informed about when and where they can participate in that <lb/>proceeding. The existence of the hearing has no meaning to the accused if their <lb/>participation is impossible because they do not know how to appear. Therefore, it is <lb/>implicit in Article 61(2)(b) that the accused be told when and where the hearing will <lb/>take place. <lb/>There is no corresponding provision in the Rome Statute permitting a trial <lb/>chamber to try the accused in absentia. Further, it is far from certain that a general <lb/>principle of international law exists permitting the trial of an absent accused to <lb/>continue. The Statutes and Rules of Procedure and Evidence of the different <lb/>international and internationalised criminal justice institutions are largely silent as to <lb/>whether a trial in absentia can be conducted when the accused has absconded. The <lb/>International Law Commission and the Preparatory Committee responsible for <lb/>developing a draft statute for the ICC both considered including a provision in the <lb/>Statute allowing trial to continue when the accused absconded or refused to appear at <lb/>trial. 74 In the end, no such rule was included in the Rome Statute. This lack of <lb/>authority leads to the conclusion that there is no general principle of international law <lb/>permitting the ICC to proceed against an absconding accused. <lb/>It may, however, be possible to extrapolate a general principle of law based on <lb/>domestic law in favour of trying an absconding accused. A general principle of law <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>74 &apos;Report of the Preparatory Committee on the Establishment of an International Criminal Court&apos;, as <lb/>reported in M. Cherif Bassiouni, The Legislative History of the International Criminal Court: An <lb/>Article-By-Article Evolution of the Statute, vol. 2 (Transnational Publishers, Inc., Ardsley, 2005), pp. <lb/>455-57. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>can be found by surveying domestic legal systems finding one of two things: that <lb/>most or all nations of the world follow the same approach to the legal issue or that it <lb/>is a principle common to all of the major legal systems. 75 While a study examining <lb/>how every legal system addresses this issue would be an overwhelming undertaking, a <lb/>review of a sample of relevant domestic law is instructive. Attention has largely been <lb/>paid to how common law countries approach this issue as most civil law countries <lb/>take a much more permissive attitude towards trial in absentia and do not prohibit <lb/>trying an absconding accused. <lb/>The United States&apos; federal court system only allows trials in absentia in very <lb/>limited circumstances. One of the few exceptions, found in Rule 43(c) of the United <lb/>States&apos; Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, permits courts to depart from the general <lb/>requirement that the accused be present for all stages of the proceedings when the <lb/>accused absconds from trial. 76 An absence occurring under these circumstances is <lb/>considered an implicit waiver of the right to be present, an approach confirmed by the <lb/>United States Supreme Court in Crosby v. The United States. 77 <lb/>The British House of Lords has taken an even more permissive approach when <lb/>deciding the law of England and Wales as to this issue. Historically, English and <lb/>Welsh courts rejected trials in absentia when the accused stands accused of a felony. 78 <lb/>That position began to change during the course of the 20 th century and now it is <lb/>accepted that the trial court may conduct trial against an absent accused when they <lb/>deliberately absent themselves from trial. 79 That being said, it is implicit in the <lb/>opinions of several of the law lords sitting in R v. Jones (Anthony William) that the <lb/>accused must be aware of the date and time of trial before it can be found that they <lb/>chose not to attend or were indifferent to the consequences of their non-appearance. 80 <lb/>There are also a number of other common law countries that follow a similar <lb/>procedure. The Code of Criminal Procedure in Bangladesh authorises courts to try an <lb/>absconding accused in absentia. 81 However, before they can proceed in that manner, <lb/>they must make an effort to notify the accused through the media that proceedings <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>75 ICTY, Prosecutor v. Tadić, Case No. IT-94-1-A, Appeals Chamber, Appeals Judgement, 15 July <lb/>1999, para. 225. <lb/>76 Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, United States of America (2017), rule 43(c). <lb/>77 Crosby v. The United States, 506 U.S. 255, 261 (1993). <lb/>78 William Blackstone, Blackstone&apos;s Commentaries on the Laws of England, Book IV, Chapter 24. <lb/>79 R. v. Jones (Anthony William), [2002] UKHL 5 [HL]; (Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, 2015), p. 335; R. <lb/>v. Leigh James O&apos;Hare, [2006] EWCA Crim 471. <lb/>80 R. v. Jones, supra note 79, paras. 12, 22. <lb/>81 Bangladesh Code of Criminal Procedure of 1898, section 339B. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>have been instituted against them and directing them to attend trial. 82 The court is <lb/>only required to take these steps if the accused has not yet appeared before it, in the <lb/>case of an accused that has made a preliminary appearance trial in absentia may be <lb/>held without first trying to notify the accused. 83 Further, Kenya&apos;s Criminal Procedure <lb/>Code allows trial to continue in absentia in some circumstances if the accused fails to <lb/>appear following an adjournment. 84 However, this provision is only applicable when <lb/>the accused does not stand accused of a felony. 85 When the accused faces felony <lb/>charges the evidence must be taken in the presence of the accused. 86 <lb/>In the past, Kenyan law contained a provision permitting magistrates to record <lb/>the deposition testimony of witnesses against an absconding accused, but that <lb/>provision has since been repealed. 87 This practice is still followed in some countries <lb/>and represents an intermediary position between suspending trial as a result of the <lb/>accused&apos;s absence and conducting trials in absentia. The Pakistani Code of Criminal <lb/>Procedure authorises courts to record evidence in the form of deposition testimony <lb/>against absconding accused that can later be given in evidence should the accused <lb/>come under the jurisdiction of the court. 88 India also permits the taking of deposition <lb/>testimony that can later be used against an absconding accused. 89 <lb/>This procedure has an analog in international criminal law. The Rules of <lb/>Procedure and Evidence at both the ICTY and ICTR contained a provision permitting <lb/>the Tribunals to hear witness testimony against an absent accused. The wording of <lb/>Rule 61 is similar in both sets of rules and its effect is identical. Rule 61 states that <lb/>when the whereabouts of the accused are unknown, and &apos;all reasonable steps&apos; have <lb/>been taken to locate the accused, the tribunal can order the Prosecutor to submit the <lb/>indictment against the absent accused to the relevant Trial Chamber in open court. 90 <lb/>After such an order is made, the Prosecutor must submit the indictment to the Trial <lb/>Chamber at which point the Prosecutor may examine witnesses whose statements <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>82 Ibid. <lb/>83 Ibid. <lb/>84 Kenya Code of Criminal Procedure (revised edition 2012), section 206. <lb/>85 Ibid. <lb/>86 Ibid., section 194. <lb/>87 Douglas Brown, Criminal Procedure in Uganda and Kenya (Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, 1965), p. <lb/>47; see also Kenya Code of Criminal Procedure, supra note 84, section 153. <lb/>88 Pakistan Code of Criminal Procedure (1898, as amended by Act 2 of 1997), Art. 512. <lb/>89 India Code of Criminal Procedure (1973), Art. 299(1). <lb/>90 Rule 61(a), ICTY Rules of Procedure and Evidence (as amended 8 July 2015); Rule 61(a), ICTR <lb/>Rules of Procedure and Evidence (as amended 13 May 2015). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>were provided to the judge who confirmed the indictment against the accused. 91 <lb/>Based on that evidence, the Trial Chamber may reach a determination that there are <lb/>reasonable grounds to believe that the accused committed the alleged crimes. 92 <lb/>While there is no real prohibition against trying an absconding accused in <lb/>most civil law countries, there are some prominent examples of states that do not <lb/>permit trials in absentia, but that do allow trial to continue if the accused absconds <lb/>after the beginning of proceedings. The German Code of Criminal Procedure permits <lb/>trial to continue against an absconding accused when: 1) the trial court has already <lb/>examined the accused; and 2) the court does not think the outcome of the trial is <lb/>dependent on the continuing presence of the accused. 93 Turkey follows a somewhat <lb/>similar procedure in its Penal Procedure Code. It allows trial to continue in the <lb/>accused&apos;s absence if the accused escapes from the courtroom during trial, but only if <lb/>he or she has already been questioned during the proceedings and the court <lb/>determines that his or her presence is no longer necessary. 94 In Turkey, trial can also <lb/>be conducted in the absence of an accused who has not testified so long as sufficient <lb/>evidence exists to sustain a judgment other than conviction. 95 <lb/>Finally, there are also some examples of states that do not appear to allow in <lb/>absentia proceedings against absconding accused, or only permit it under very limited <lb/>circumstances. The Nigerian Criminal Procedure Act states that all accused must be <lb/>physically present in the courtroom during the entirety of trial. 96 The only exception <lb/>to this requirement is that trial may continue in the absence of a disruptive accused. 97 <lb/>There is no provision authorising the continuance of trial in the absence of an <lb/>absconding accused. This is confirmed in the Administration of Criminal Justice Act, <lb/>2015, which reiterates the general rule that trial must be held in the presence of the <lb/>accused. 98 It also does not contain an exception allowing trial to continue in the <lb/>absence of an absconding accused. South Africa follows the same procedure by <lb/>making it a requirement that all criminal trials must take place in the accused&apos;s <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>91 Rule 61(b), ICTY Rules of Procedure and Evidence (as amended 8 July 2015); Rule 61(b), ICTR <lb/>Rules of Procedure and Evidence (as amended 13 May 2015). <lb/>92 Rule 61(c), ICTY Rules of Procedure and Evidence (as amended 8 July 2015); Rule 61(c), ICTR <lb/>Rules of Procedure and Evidence (as amended 13 May 2015). <lb/>93 The German Code of Criminal Procedure (as amended 23 April 2014), section 231(2). <lb/>94 Code of Criminal Procedure, Turkey (2009), Art. 194. <lb/>95 Ibid., p. 193. <lb/>96 Nigeria Criminal Procedure Act (1990), Art. 210. <lb/>97 Ibid. <lb/>98 Nigeria Administration of Criminal Justice Act (2015), Section 266. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>presence. 99 The South African Criminal Procedure Act does contain an exception <lb/>permitting a trial court to proceed against an absconding accused. This exception is <lb/>quite narrow, it is only applicable when the trial involves multiple defendants and it <lb/>requires a finding that the proceedings cannot be postponed without causing undue <lb/>prejudice, embarrassment or inconvenience to the other accused, the prosecution or <lb/>the prospective witnesses. 100 <lb/>While these are only a handful of examples, it is illustrative of the variety of <lb/>different practices that abound with regard to whether trial can continue against an <lb/>absconding accused. Contrary to the inference suggested by the Gbagbo Appeals <lb/>decision, state practice with regard to this issue is far from uniform, making it <lb/>impossible to conclude that a general principle of law exists. Even if it were possible <lb/>to conclude that such a principle does exist, some commentators have expressed <lb/>unease with applying national approaches to trying absconding accused to <lb/>international criminal law proceedings. A particular concern is that proceeding under <lb/>these circumstances could create a negative public perception about the fairness of <lb/>international criminal trials, which could, in turn, threaten the overall legitimacy of <lb/>international criminal justice institutions. 101 This lack of uniformity of approaches to <lb/>the issue of how to treat an absconding accused, combined with the potential harm <lb/>such a proceeding might cause, militates against finding the existence of the general <lb/>principle of law proposed in the Gbagbo Appeals decision. <lb/>3.2.4 Forfeiture of the right to be present as a basis for conducting trial in absentia <lb/>Although not specifically raised in the Gbagbo Appeals decision, the Ruto <lb/>Trial Chamber Decision and the Kenyatta Dissent have previously taken the position <lb/>that trials in absentia are permissible on the basis that the accused&apos;s failure to appear <lb/>constitutes a forfeiture of their right to be present. 102 In essence, Article 63(1) of the <lb/>Rome Statute is seen as imposing a duty on the accused requiring them to appear for <lb/>trial. If the accused fails to appear at trial in compliance with that obligation her or she <lb/>has forfeited the right to be present and the trial chamber may conduct a trial in <lb/>absentia. The trial chamber need not consider why the accused did not appear, or <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>99 South Africa Criminal Procedure Act 51 of 1977, Art. 158. <lb/>100 Ibid., Art. 159(2)(b). <lb/>101 Cassese, supra note 57, p. 404. <lb/>102 Kenyatta Dissent, supra note 10, para. 79; Ruto Trial Chamber Decision, supra note 10, para. 42. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>whether the accused was aware of the consequences of their non-appearance as they <lb/>would in the case of a waiver. 103 That is because a finding of forfeiture is <lb/>&apos;unconstrained by the elements that must be present in order to find waiver&apos;. 104 <lb/>Forfeiture is seen as being distinct from waiver, largely as a result of how each <lb/>becomes operative. 105 While both waiver and forfeiture involve the holder of a right <lb/>relinquishing that right, the way in which the right is repudiated is different. When a <lb/>court finds that a right has been waived it must conclude that the holder of the right <lb/>made a conscious decision to waive the right, that they understood what the right <lb/>protects and the consequences that would result from waiving it. 106 Forfeiture, <lb/>conversely, occurs by operation of law without accounting for the accused&apos;s state of <lb/>mind. 107 <lb/>There are two possible bases for finding that an accused has forfeited their <lb/>right to be present at trial. The first reason is when the accused intentionally interferes <lb/>with the proper administration of justice. The proper administration of justice is often <lb/>cited as one of the key reasons why courts should require the accused&apos;s attendance <lb/>during trial. Under this approach, interruptions to the administration of justice can <lb/>result in forfeiture of the right to be present, which in turn can be punished by <lb/>proceeding in the accused&apos;s absence. 108 Forfeiture under these circumstances is <lb/>considered an appropriate sanction for an accused who fails to comply with the duty <lb/>to present at trial. <lb/>The relationship between the proper administration of justice and trials in <lb/>absentia is based on a comment made by the UNHRC. In its Views in Mbenge v. <lb/>Zaire, the UNHRC states that in absentia proceedings &apos;are in some circumstances… <lb/>permissible in the interest of the proper administration of justice.&apos; 109 Although the <lb/>UNHRC only identified one such circumstance, that implicitly involves the waiver of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>103 Kenyatta Dissent, supra note 10, para. 79. <lb/>104 Ibid. <lb/>105 Martin Böse, &apos;Harmonizing Procedural Rights Indirectly: The Framework Decision on Trials in <lb/>Absentia&apos;, 37 N.C. JIL &amp; Comm. Reg. (2011) 489-510, 500; Christoph J.M. Safferling, International <lb/>Criminal Procedure (Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2012), p. 400. <lb/>106 Peter Westen, &apos;Away from Waiver: A Rationale for the Forfeiture of Constitutional Rights in <lb/>Criminal Procedure&apos;, 75 Michigan LR (1977) 1214-1261, 1214, 1235-37. <lb/>107 Ibid. <lb/>108 Mbenge, supra note 34, para. 9.1; Niccolò Pons, &apos;Some Remarks on in Absentia Proceedings before <lb/>the Special Tribunal for Lebanon in Case of a State&apos;s Failure or Refusal to Hand over the Accused&apos;, 8 <lb/>JICJ (2010) 1307-1321, 1309; Paola Gaeta, &apos;Trial in Absentia Before the Special Tribunal for <lb/>Lebanon&apos;, in Amal Alamuddin, Nidal Nabil Jurdi and David Tolbert (eds.), The Special Tribunal for <lb/>Lebanon: Law and Practice (Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2014), p. 237. <lb/>109 Mbenge, supra note 34, para. 14.1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>the right to be present, the use of the plural form of &apos;circumstance&apos; indicates that there <lb/>are other, unenumerated situations, in which the proper administration of justice <lb/>permits courts and tribunals to proceed in the absence of the accused. 110 It has been <lb/>left to individual courts and tribunals to conclude when those circumstances arise. <lb/>The SCSL has a fairly extensive record of considering the relationship <lb/>between the proper administration of justice and the right to be present. In Prosecutor <lb/>v. Sesay et al., the SCSL&apos;s Trial Chamber observed that criminal law does not allow <lb/>an absent or disruptive accused &apos;to impede the administration of justice or frustrate <lb/>the ends of justice.&apos; 111 This ruling was in response to Defendant Augustine Gbao&apos;s <lb/>refusal to attend any further hearings because he did not recognise the legitimacy of <lb/>the SCSL. 112 To halt trial under these circumstances would have been &apos;tantamount to <lb/>judicial abdication of the principle of legality and a capitulation to a frustration of the <lb/>ends of justice without justification.&apos; 113 The SCSL echoed this sentiment in <lb/>Prosecutor v. Norman et al. when it found that it is not &apos;in the interests of justice to <lb/>allow the Accused&apos;s deliberate absence from the courtroom to interrupt the trial&apos; and <lb/>that any deliberate absence &apos;will certainly undermine the integrity of the trial and will <lb/>not be in the interests of justice.&apos; 114 <lb/>The Appeals Chamber of the ICTY also identified the proper administration of <lb/>justice as a reason to continue trial in the accused&apos;s absence. Its general position was <lb/>that trials in absentia were impermissible before the Tribunal, even when the accused <lb/>waives their right to be present. 115 That being said, the Appeals Chamber identified <lb/>an exception to that basic rule whereby it could conduct in absentia proceedings in <lb/>matters involving the secondary jurisdiction of the Tribunal. It justified holding these <lb/>proceedings in absentia on the basis that those matters involved &apos;obstructing the <lb/>administration of justice.&apos; 116 It can be inferred from this ruling that in absentia trials <lb/>are justified in all instances where the accused is seen as obstructing the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>110 Ibid. <lb/>111 SCSL, Prosecutor v. Sesay et al., Case No. SCSL-04-15-T, Trial Chamber, Ruling on the Issue of <lb/>the Refusal of the Third Accused, Augustine Gbao, to Attend Hearing of the Special Court of Sierra <lb/>Leone on 7 July 2004 and Succeeding Days, 12 July 2004, para. 8. <lb/>112 Ibid., para. 2. <lb/>113 Ibid., para. 8. <lb/>114 SCSL, Prosecutor v. Norman et al., Case No. SCSL-04-14-PT, Trial Chamber, Ruling on the Issue <lb/>of Non-Appearance of the First Accused, Samuel Hinga Norman, The Second Accused, Moinina <lb/>Fofana and the Third Accused, Allieu Kondewa at the Trial Proceedings, 1 October 2004, para. 22. <lb/>115 ICTY, Prosecutor v. Blaškić, Case No. IT-95-14-AR108bis, Appeals Chamber, Judgement on the <lb/>Request of the Republic of Croatia For Review of the Decision of Trial Chamber II of 18 July 1997, 29 <lb/>October 1997, para. 59. <lb/>116 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>administration of justice. From that, it follows that the Tribunal does not consider it to <lb/>be an obstruction of justice when the accused is absent from trial when being tried for <lb/>primary jurisdiction crimes. <lb/>Ultimately, the trouble with using violations of the proper administration of <lb/>justice as a justification for trying an accused in absentia is that the term lacks a set <lb/>meaning in the international law context. 117 Because it lacks a clear definition it <lb/>means that in absentia trials could be conducted under any circumstances so long as <lb/>they can brought under the ambit of &apos;proper administration of justice.&apos; 118 This grants <lb/>the trial chamber a tremendous amount of discretion to determine whether something <lb/>comports with the proper administration of justice. This, in turn, can make the trial <lb/>court&apos;s decisions appear rather arbitrary, which could have an effect on how the ICC <lb/>is perceived. Therefore, should the ICC wish to use the proper administration of <lb/>justice as a reason to proceed against an absent accused, it should make every effort to <lb/>identify what that phrase means so as to ensure full confidence in its future decisions. <lb/>The second justification for finding that the accused forfeited their right to be <lb/>present is through the application of the proportionality principle as used by the ad <lb/>hoc tribunals. The proportionality principle in this context stands for the proposition <lb/>that any infringement on the accused&apos;s right to be present &apos;must be in service of a <lb/>sufficiently important objective&apos; and that it must not impair the right to be present any <lb/>more than necessary to accomplish that objective. 119 While neither tribunal had the <lb/>opportunity to apply the principle to an absconding accused, the ICTR did use it in <lb/>several other instances involving the right to be present. <lb/>In Prosecutor v. Zigiranyirazo, Trial Chamber III was confronted with a <lb/>witness who, out of fear for his safety, refused to travel to Arusha to testify during the <lb/>trial. 120 In an effort to find a way to facilitate his testimony, the Trial Chamber <lb/>ordered that arrangements be made for him to testify in The Hague with all of the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>117 Nina Jørgensen, &apos;The Right of the Accused to Self-Representation Before International Criminal <lb/>Tribunals&apos; 98 American Journal of International Law (2004) 711, 722. <lb/>118 Pons, supra note 108, p. 1318. <lb/>119 ICTR, Zigiranyirazo v. Prosecutor, Case No. ICTR-2001-73-AR73, Appeals Chamber, Decision on <lb/>Interlocutory Appeal, 30 October 2006), para. 14; ICTY, Prosecutor v. Milošević, Case No. IT-02-54-<lb/>AR73.7, Appeals Chamber, Decision on Interlocutory Appeal of the Trial Chamber&apos;s Decision on the <lb/>Assignment of Defence Counsel, 1 November 2004, para. 17; see also Yvonne McDermott, &apos;Trial <lb/>Process: General Duty to Ensure the Integrity of the Proceedings&apos;, in Göran Sluiter, Håkan Friman, <lb/>Suzannah Linton, Sergey Vasiliev, Salvatore Zappalà (eds.), International Criminal Procedure: <lb/>Principles and Rules (Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2013), p. 753. <lb/>120 ICTR, Prosecutor v. Zigiranyirazo, Case No. ICTR-2001-73-T, Appeals Chamber, Decision on <lb/>Defence and Prosecution Motions Related to Witness ADE, 31 January 2006, para. 34. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>parties present. 121 The defendant was then denied entry to the Netherlands and, <lb/>instead of postponing the witness&apos;s testimony until another solution could be found, <lb/>the Trial Chamber allowed the witness to testify outside of the defendant&apos;s physical <lb/>presence. 122 The defendant then challenged that decision on the basis that his right to <lb/>be present had been violated. 123 The Appeals Chamber agreed with him, and by <lb/>applying the proportionality principle, found that although the right to be present is <lb/>not absolute it can only be limited when doing so is proportional to the other interest <lb/>being protected. 124 In this instance, the Trial Chamber&apos;s decision was found to be <lb/>disproportional and constituted an unwarranted and unnecessary restriction on the <lb/>defendant&apos;s fair trial rights. 125 <lb/>The ICTR took a somewhat different approach to absences resulting from <lb/>illness. In Prosecutor v. Bagosora et al., Trial Chamber I was confronted with an <lb/>accused who voluntarily absented himself from trial on the basis of two medical <lb/>reports indicating that he was too ill to attend. 126 The Trial Chamber disagreed and <lb/>chose to continue in the accused&apos;s absence as he was not given authorization to miss <lb/>trial. The Trial Chamber reached its decision through the application of the <lb/>proportionality principle. It concluded that there had been no violation of the <lb/>accused&apos;s right to be present on the grounds that the potential loss of testimony that <lb/>could result if trial was postponed outweighed the remote possibility that the accused <lb/>would be prejudiced if those witnesses were examined in his absence. 127 The Appeals <lb/>Chamber agreed and found that the accused&apos;s unauthorised absence constituted a <lb/>forfeiture of his right to be present at trial. 128 What apparently distinguishes these two <lb/>decisions is the degree to which the accused&apos;s decision not to appear was voluntary. <lb/>Trials in absentia are often used to condemn what is perceived as the <lb/>accused&apos;s &apos;bad faith conduct&apos; of not attending trial when ordered to do so and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>121 Ibid. <lb/>122 ICTR, Prosecutor v. Zigiranyirazo, Case No. ICTR-2001-73-T, Appeals Chamber, Decision on <lb/>Interlocutory Appeal, 30 October 2006, para. 5. <lb/>123 Ibid., para. 7. <lb/>124 Ibid., paras. 17-21. <lb/>125 Ibid., para. 22. <lb/>126 ICTR, Prosecutor v. Bagosora et al., Case No. ICTR-98-41, Trial Chamber, Decision on <lb/>Nsengiyumva Motions to Call Doctors and Recall Eight Witnesses, 19 April 2007, paras. 5, 7. <lb/>127 ICTR, Prosecutor v. Bagosora et al., Case No. ICTR-98-41, Trial Chamber, Judgement and <lb/>Sentence, 18 December 2008, para. 131. <lb/>128 ICTR, Prosecutor v. Bagosora et al., Case No. ICTR-98-41-A, Trial Chamber, Judgement, 14 <lb/>December 2011, para. 48. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>consequently disrupting the smooth progress of trial. 129 This is reflected in both of the <lb/>justifications underpinning forfeiture as a reason to proceed against an absent <lb/>accused. What constitutes bad faith conduct is open to interpretation and is many <lb/>times dependent on the context in which the behaviour is being exhibited. However, it <lb/>can generally be observed that trial courts make a distinction between what they <lb/>consider to be voluntary absences on the part of the accused and absences that are not <lb/>the product of their own volition. 130 This can sometimes be a crude distinction, but it <lb/>reinforces how important it is that the accused has all of the information necessary to <lb/>make an informed decision about whether or not they wish to appear. To the extent <lb/>that forfeiture is justified on the basis that the accused&apos;s absence is the result of a <lb/>voluntary decision not to appear, then it is imperative that they know not only what <lb/>they have been charged with, but also when, where and how they can appear. <lb/>While some may see differentiating implied waivers from forfeiture as a <lb/>distinction without a difference, it is necessary to be cautious about the long-term <lb/>impact of such a conclusion. Basing the decision to proceed in the absence of the <lb/>accused on forfeiture rather than waiver fundamentally alters the character of the right <lb/>to be present. It makes it more of a duty imposed on the accused and less of a right <lb/>controlled by them. The failing of forfeiture, and the reason it should be used with <lb/>caution as a justification for proceeding in absentia, is that it does not account for the <lb/>requirement that the accused&apos;s decision not to attend trial must be unequivocal. <lb/>Therefore, it should only be used as the reason for holding a trial in absentia when <lb/>adequate steps are taken to guarantee that the accused&apos;s non-appearance is the result <lb/>of a genuine choice to be absent and is not the action of an inadequately informed <lb/>accused. The approach advocated in the Gbagbo Appeals decision does not mandate <lb/>that the accused have all of the necessary information before they can be tried in <lb/>absentia and as a result forfeiture of the right to be present does not form an adequate <lb/>basis on which to proceed. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>129 Ekaterina Trendafilova, &apos;Fairness and Expeditiousness in the International Criminal Court&apos;s Pre-<lb/>Trial Proceedings&apos;, in Carsten Stahn and Göran Sluiter (eds.), The Emerging Practice of the <lb/>International Criminal Court (Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, Leiden, 2009), p. 449; Gaeta, supra note <lb/>108, p. 237. <lb/>130 Wheeler, supra note 59, p. 198. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>4 <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The Gbagbo Appeals decision proposes what could be a monumental change <lb/>to how trials are conducted at the ICC. Should the Court begin to try the accused in <lb/>absentia it could expedite the trial process and deliver justice to more victims of <lb/>atrocity crimes. Unfortunately, what the Appeals Chamber proposes does not appear <lb/>to comport with either the Statute or international criminal law as a whole. What the <lb/>Appeals Chamber has done is rely on a highly disputed interpretation of the Rome <lb/>Statute and to selectively choose jurisprudence from other courts that appears to <lb/>support its position when viewed from a particular perspective. However, when other <lb/>understandings of the Statute are taken into account and the external law relied on is <lb/>placed back into context, it becomes apparent that what the Court is advocating is not <lb/>countenanced in the Statute nor is it authorised by a principle of law. As it currently <lb/>stands, no legal basis exists permitting a future trial chamber of the ICC to proceed in <lb/>absentia against Mr. Gbagbo or Mr. Blé Goudé. Further, even if the defects in the <lb/>procedure could be cured, primarily by ensuring that the defendants have notice of the <lb/>date and location of trial, there is still significant disagreement about whether the <lb/>Statute can be interpreted in the manner suggested by the Appeals Chamber. These <lb/>obstacles appear too significant to overcome and it is unlikely that trial in absentia <lb/>will become a feature of trials at the ICC. </body>


	</text>

</TEI>