<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Environmental liability under scrutiny: The margins of applying the EU ‘polluter pays’ principle against the owners of the polluted land who did not contribute to the pollution</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Samvel</forename>
          <surname>Varvaštian</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-11T10:21:56.198Z">1/11/2026 11:21:56 AM</date>
        <title>review</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1177__1461452915598430</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2015</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1177/1461452915598430</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Samvel Varvaštian. (2015). Environmental liability under scrutiny: The margins of applying the EU ‘polluter pays’ principle against the owners of the polluted land who did not contribute to the pollution. Environmental Law Review, 17(4), 270-276. DOI: 10.1177/1461452915598430</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T14:42:08.214138Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-19T14:42:08.214138Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-23T13:25:29.150Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-23T13:25:46.781Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Done</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-28T09:28:37.904Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-28T09:29:04.919Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-06T15:30:21.865Z" status="checked" who="#li">
      <desc>Validation completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-11T10:39:23.183Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>S Varvastian, &apos;Environmental Liability Under Scrutiny: The Margins of Applying the EU &quot;Polluter Pays&quot; Principle <lb/>Against the Owners of the Polluted Land Who Did Not Contribute to the Pollution&apos; (2015) 17(4) Environmental <lb/>Law Review 270-276 <lb/>ENVIRONMENTAL LIABILITY UNDER SCRUTINY: THE MARGINS OF APPLYING <lb/>THE EU &apos;POLLUTER PAYS&apos; PRINCIPLE AGAINST THE OWNERS OF THE <lb/>POLLUTED LAND WHO DID NOT CONTRIBUTE TO THE POLLUTION <lb/>Samvel Varvastian <lb/>Case C-534/13 Ministero dell&apos;Ambiente e della Tutela del Territorio e del Mare and Others v <lb/>Fipa Group Srl and Others [2015] (ECJ, 4 March 2015) (Fipa Group and Others). <lb/>Keywords: Directive 2004/35/EC, EU law, &apos;polluter pays&apos; principle, environmental liability, <lb/>pollution, preventive and remedial measures <lb/></front>
    
    <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>The origins of the case Fipa Group and Others date back to the period between the 1960s -1980s, <lb/>when two companies belonging to the industrial group Montedison SpA (now Edison SpA), <lb/>Farmoplant SpA and Cersam Srl, operated an industrial site for the manufacture of insecticides and <lb/>herbicides in a municipality of the Province of Massa Carrara in Tuscany, Italy. 1 As a result of the <lb/>industrial activities, massive contamination of the surrounding land by various chemical substances, <lb/>including dichloroethane and ammonia, occurred. 2 In 1995, the land was partly decontaminated; <lb/>however, the decontamination proved to be inadequate therefore in 1998 the area was proclaimed a <lb/>&apos;site of national interest&apos; under Italian law for the purposes of its rehabilitation. 3 <lb/>In 2006, 2008 and 2011, three different private companies, Tws Automation (engaged in sales of <lb/>electronic devices), Ivan (a real estate agency) and Nasco Srl (engaged in the construction and boat <lb/>repair business) respectively, became the owners of various plots of land on the site. 4 Since the <lb/>contamination took place before the above-mentioned entities acquired their respective land areas <lb/>from Edison SpA, none of them was actually responsible for the pollution caused by the latter. 5 <lb/>However, by administrative acts issued on 18 May 2007 and 16 September and 7 November 2011 <lb/>respectively, the Italian authorities ordered the three companies, as the &apos;guardians of the land&apos;, to <lb/>adopt specific &apos;emergency safety&apos; measures, including the erection of a hydraulic capture barrier in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 Fipa Group and Others, para. 25. <lb/>2 Ibid. <lb/>3 Ibid. <lb/>4 Ibid., at paras 27 and 28. <lb/>5 Opinion of Advocate General Kokott, delivered on 20 November 2014 in Case C-534/13 Fipa Group and Others, para. <lb/>14. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>order to protect the groundwater table and to submit an amendment to a project, dating back to 1995, <lb/>for the rehabilitation of the land. 6 The original owner, Edison SpA, which was clearly indicated as <lb/>the one responsible for the contamination, was also charged with carrying out the same measures. 7 <lb/>The legal background for these decisions was Italy&apos;s Legislative Decree No 152 of 3 April 2006 (the <lb/>Environmental Code), Article 245(2) of which stipulated, inter alia, that <lb/>&apos;Without prejudice to the obligations incumbent upon the person responsible for the potential <lb/>contamination, … the owner or the administrator of the land who finds that the contamination <lb/>threshold concentrations … have been exceeded, or are specifically and genuinely at risk of being <lb/>exceeded, is required to inform accordingly the region, province or municipality with territorial <lb/>competence and to implement preventive measures&apos;. 8 <lb/>LITIGATION BEFORE NATIONAL COURTS <lb/>The three companies brought proceedings to challenge the administrative acts before the Regional <lb/>Administrative Court of Tuscany, relying on the fact that they were not responsible for the pollution <lb/>in the first place. The regional court supported their cause by referring to both national legislation <lb/>and the &apos;polluter pays&apos; principle established in EU law, which it held did not grant the authorities a <lb/>right to impose the measures at issue on entities that were not directly responsible for the <lb/>contamination observed on the site. The Regional Administrative Court therefore annulled the <lb/>administrative acts in question, in three separate judgments. 9 <lb/>The Italian authorities then lodged an appeal against these judgments before the Council of State, <lb/>claiming that a proper interpretation of Italy&apos;s Environmental Code, which takes into account not <lb/>only the &apos;polluter pays&apos; principle, but the precautionary principle as well, did permit them to compel <lb/>the owner of a polluted site to adopt emergency safety measures. 10 <lb/>On hearing the case, the chamber of the Council of State referred a question to the plenary assembly <lb/>of that court, asking whether the &apos;polluter pays&apos; principle grants national authorities the right to <lb/>impose an obligation to implement emergency safety measures on owners of polluted land who <lb/>were not responsible for that pollution or whether, in such circumstances, the owner is bound only <lb/>by the obligations expressly provided for in Article 253 of the Environmental Code. 11 <lb/>Under Article 250 of the Code: 12 <lb/>&apos;if the persons responsible for the contamination do not immediately adopt [measures necessary to <lb/>prevent pollution or restore polluted land] or if they cannot be identified, and if neither the owner nor <lb/>any interested party adopts those measures … [they] shall be implemented on its own initiative by the <lb/>municipality that is territorially competent and, if that municipality does not adopt those measures, by <lb/>the region, in accordance with the order of priority set by the regional plan for the rehabilitation of <lb/>polluted land …&apos; <lb/>However Articles 253(3) and 253(4) of the Code then stipulate that: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>6 See Fipa Group and Others, para. 28. <lb/>7 See Opinion of Advocate General Kokott, para. 15. <lb/>8 See Fipa Group and Others, para. 22. <lb/>9 Ibid., at para. 29. <lb/>10 Ibid., at paras 30 and 31. <lb/>11 Ibid., at para. 32. <lb/>12 Ibid., at para. 23. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>&apos;… the recovery of costs may not be claimed vis-à-vis the owner of the site where that person is in no <lb/>way connected with the pollution or the risk of pollution, except by reasoned decision of the competent <lb/>authority attesting, inter alia, to the impossibility of identifying the person responsible or of bringing an <lb/>action for damages against that person, or to the unsuccessful outcome of such an action.&apos; <lb/>&apos;In any event, owners not responsible for the pollution may be required to reimburse … the costs <lb/>relating to the measures adopted by the competent authority only within the limits of the market value <lb/>of the land, determined after the implementation of those measures. If an owner who is not responsible <lb/>for the pollution has rehabilitated the polluted site on a voluntary basis, that person shall be entitled to <lb/>bring an action for damages against the person responsible for the pollution in respect of costs incurred <lb/>and any additional damage suffered.&apos; 13 <lb/>With regard to the question put forward by the chamber, the plenary assembly noted that Italian <lb/>administrative courts had applied two different approaches in interpreting the above-mentioned <lb/>provisions of the Environmental Code in relation to the obligations of the owner of a contaminated <lb/>site. 14 The first, which is based inter alia on the principles of EU environmental law, namely the <lb/>precautionary principle, the principle that preventive action should be taken and the &apos;polluter pays&apos; <lb/>principle, implies that the owner is under an obligation to adopt emergency safety measures and <lb/>rehabilitation measures even where that owner is not the polluter. 15 The second approach, however, <lb/>stipulates that such owners do not incur any liability and that the authorities are not entitled to <lb/>compel them to adopt such measures. 16 <lb/>For its part, the plenary assembly of the Council of State took the latter view as prevailing in Italian <lb/>administrative case-law. 17 It argued that this approach followed not only from a literal interpretation <lb/>of the Environmental Code and the principles of civil liability, which require a causal link between <lb/>the act and damage, but from the case-law of the European Court of Justice (ECJ) as well, 18 relying <lb/>upon ERG and Others, 19 and ERG and Others and ENI. 20 Consequently, the plenary assembly came <lb/>to a conclusion that the absence of a causal link between the act and damage in cases where the <lb/>owner is not the polluter meant that no fault-based or strict liability could be established in respect <lb/>of such damage. Thus, the liability of such a person would be based solely on their status as owner. 21 <lb/>In these circumstances, the assembly decided to refer the matter to the ECJ and asked whether the <lb/>EU principles of environmental law, envisaged in Article 191(2) of the Treaty on the Functioning of <lb/>the European Union (TFEU) 22 and Directive 2004/35/EC on environmental liability (Environmental <lb/>Liability Directive) 23 , particularly the &apos;polluter pays&apos; principle <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 Ibid., at para. 24. <lb/>14 Ibid., at para. 34. <lb/>15 Ibid., at para. 35. <lb/>16 Ibid. <lb/>17 Ibid. <lb/>18 Ibid., at para. 36. <lb/>19 Case C-378/08 Raffinerie Mediterranee (ERG) SpA, Polimeri Europa SpA and Syndial SpA v Ministero dello Sviluppo <lb/>economico and Others [2010] ECR I-1919. <lb/>20 Joined cases C-379/08 and C-380/08 Raffinerie Mediterranee (ERG) SpA, Polimeri Europa SpA and Syndial SpA v <lb/>Ministero dello Sviluppo economico and Others and ENI SpA v Ministero Ambiente e Tutela del Territorio e del Mare <lb/>and Others [2010] ECR I-2007. <lb/>21 See Fipa Group and Others, para. 36. <lb/>22 Consolidated Version of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (OJ C326/47 26.10.2012). <lb/>23 Directive 2004/35/EC of The European Parliament and of the Council of 21 April 2004 on environmental liability <lb/>with regard to the prevention and remedying of environmental damage (OJ L143/56 30.4.2004). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>&apos;must be interpreted as precluding national legislation …, which, in cases where it is impossible to <lb/>identify the polluter of a plot of land or to have that person adopt remedial measures, does not permit <lb/>the competent authority to require the owner of the land (who is not responsible for the pollution) to <lb/>adopt preventive and remedial measures, that person being required merely to reimburse the costs <lb/>relating to the measures undertaken by the competent authority within the limit of the market value of <lb/>the site, determined after those measures have been carried out.&apos; 24 <lb/>DECISION OF THE ECJ <lb/>Applicability of &apos;Polluter Pays&apos; Principle Under Article 191(2) TFEU <lb/>First of all, the ECJ emphasized that Article 191(2) TFEU, establishing that EU policy on the <lb/>environment &apos;shall aim at a high level of protection&apos; and &apos;shall be based on the precautionary <lb/>principle and on the principles that preventive action should be taken, that environmental damage <lb/>should as a priority be rectified at source and that the polluter should pay&apos;, is essentially a political <lb/>instrument, since it defines the general environmental objectives of the EU to be implemented by the <lb/>EU bodies. 25 Accordingly, the Court stated that since this provision is directed at action at EU level, <lb/>it cannot be relied upon by individuals to challenge the application of national legislation in an area <lb/>for which there is no EU legislation adopted on the basis of Article 192 TFEU. 26 Similarly, it found <lb/>that competent national authorities cannot rely on Article 191(2) TFEU, in the absence of any <lb/>national legal basis, for the purposes of imposing preventive and remedial measures. 27 Therefore, <lb/>the ECJ concluded that the only way to apply the &apos;polluter pays&apos; principle in this particular case was <lb/>through the Environmental Liability Directive. 28 <lb/>Applicability of the Environmental Liability Directive <lb/>The main doubt raised by the ECJ as to the applicability of the Environmental Liability Directive in <lb/>Fipa Group and Others was related to the fact that the contamination in question occurred decades <lb/>before the Directive was adopted, 29 and according to Edison SpA, the polluting activities ceased in <lb/>1988 with partial decontamination of the area in 1995. 30 The Court noted that <lb/>&apos;It follows from the first and second indents of Article 17 of [Environmental Liability Directive], read <lb/>in conjunction with recital 30 thereto, that the directive applies only to damage caused by an emission, <lb/>event or incident which took place on or after 30 April 2007, where the damage derives from activities <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>24 See Fipa Group and Others, paras 37 and 38. <lb/>25 Ibid., at para. 39. This position is well-established in the ECJ case-law: Case C-379/92 Criminal proceedings against <lb/>Matteo Peralta [1994] ECR I-3453, para. 57; Case C-378/08 ERG and Others, para. 45; Joined cases C-379/08 and C-<lb/>380/08 ERG and Others and ENI, para. 38; Order in joined cases C-478/08 and C-479/08 Buzzi Unicem SpA and Others <lb/>v Ministero dello Sviluppo economico and Others and Dow Italia Divisione Commerciale SrI v Ministero Ambiente e <lb/>Tutela deI Territorio e deI Mare and Others [2010] ECR I-0031, para. 35. <lb/>26 See Fipa Group and Others, at para. 40. <lb/>27 Ibid., at para. 41. <lb/>28 Ibid., at para. 42. <lb/>29 Ibid., at paras 44 and 45. <lb/>30 See Opinion of Advocate General Kokott, para. 28. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>which took place on or after that date or from activities which took place before that date, but were not <lb/>brought to completion before that date.&apos; 31 <lb/>Furthermore, the Court stressed that it follows from the scope of the Environmental Liability <lb/>Directive that one of the essential conditions for the application of the liability arrangements laid <lb/>down therein is the identification of an operator who may be deemed responsible.&apos; 32 This stemmed <lb/>from the fact that the Directive applied to environmental damage and damage to protected species <lb/>and natural habitats caused by occupational activities carried out by an operator. 33 <lb/>However, persons other than those defined in Article 2(6), i.e. those who do not carry out an <lb/>occupational activity within the meaning of Article 2(7) of the Environmental Liability Directive, <lb/>fall outside the scope of the Directive. 34 Since the Court accepted that none of the three respondents <lb/>in the present case were engaged in any of the activities listed in Annex III to the Environmental <lb/>Liability Directive, it observed that the only way for them to be held liable under the Directive was <lb/>through fault or negligence, pursuant to Article 3(1)(b). 35 However, for this mechanism to apply, a <lb/>causal link must be established &apos;between the activity of one or more identifiable operators and <lb/>concrete and quantifiable damage, irrespective of the type of pollution at issue&apos;. 36 This rule follows <lb/>from Articles 4(5) and 11(2) of the Environmental Liability Directive read in conjunction with <lb/>recital 13, which require both the identification of the polluter and the establishment of a causal link <lb/>between their activity and the damage in question. In other words, a causal link should be <lb/>established both in case of strict liability and fault-based liability, as provided in Articles 3(1)(a) and <lb/>(b), 37 otherwise, the situation would be regulated solely by national legislation. 38 <lb/>The ECJ concluded that the situation in Fipa Group and Others clearly indicated that no causal link <lb/>existed between the three companies and the contamination in question. The situation was therefore <lb/>governed by national legislation. That national legislation did not permit the competent authority to <lb/>require an owner of land who was not responsible for pollution to adopt preventive and remedial <lb/>measures. That person was merely required to reimburse the costs of the measures undertaken by the <lb/>competent authority. This did not infringe the Environmental Liability Directive, nor the EU <lb/>&apos;polluter pays&apos; principle. 39 <lb/>COMMENTARY <lb/>The case is interesting in a number of ways. First, it is in line with previous ECJ rulings that the <lb/>application of the &apos;polluter pays&apos; principle envisaged in the Treaty on the Functioning of the <lb/>European Union is possible only via the implementation of EU legislation, in this case, the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>31 See Fipa Group and Others, para. 45. <lb/>32 Ibid., at para. 48. <lb/>33 Articles 2(6) and (7) and 3(1) read together with Articles 5, 6, 8 and 11(2) and recitals 2 and 18. <lb/>34 See Fipa Group and Others, para. 52. <lb/>35 Ibid. at para. 53. <lb/>36 Ibid. at para. 54. See also: Case C-378/08 ERG and Others, paras 52 and 53; order in Buzzi Unicem and Others, para. <lb/>45. <lb/>37 See Fipa Group and Others, paras 55 and 56. <lb/>38 Ibid. at para. 59. See also: Case C-378/08 ERG and Others, para. 59; order in Buzzi Unicem and Others, paras 43 and <lb/>48. <lb/>39 See Fipa Group and Others, paras 60 and 63. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Environmental Liability Directive. 40 This renders the application of the principle contingent on the <lb/>application of directives in EU environmental law. <lb/>Second, it raised the question of third-party environmental liability in the absence of a causal link to <lb/>specific environmental pollution. In this particular case, the third party was merely the owner of the <lb/>polluted site and had not been responsible for its damage. Since Article 8(3)(a) and recital 20 of the <lb/>Environmental Liability Directive emphasize that an operator shall not be liable in case of force <lb/>majeure, which implies, inter alia, damage caused by a third party, 41 it is logical that mere owners <lb/>are to be exempted from the liability, should the damage be caused by another entity. Otherwise, <lb/>owners would be liable for any environmental damage to their property arising from the acts of third <lb/>parties, including the deliberate acts of sabotage. 42 This would be beyond the scope of the <lb/>Environmental Liability Directive. 43 <lb/>EU environmental law, at least up to now, has not shown willingness to regulate these particular <lb/>situations, leaving to national law the question of whether owners of polluted land are liable for <lb/>environmental damage, caused by others. Indeed, Article 16(1) of the Environmental Liability <lb/>Directive stipulates that: <lb/>&apos;This Directive shall not prevent Member States from maintaining or adopting more stringent <lb/>provisions in relation to the prevention and remedying of environmental damage, including the <lb/>identification of additional activities to be subject to the prevention and remediation requirements of <lb/>this Directive and the identification of additional responsible parties.&apos; <lb/>This power, however, may not be absolute. According to Advocate General Kokott: <lb/>&apos;[it] is restricted by the objectives of the Environmental Liability Directive, which Member States may <lb/>not undermine. Thus, they would be prohibited from identifying additional responsible parties to <lb/>replace the polluter who was liable under the directive.&apos; 44 <lb/>&apos;The directive contains, at most, an unspoken requirement that Member States oblige such persons to <lb/>allow the necessary measures on their sites and, where necessary, to cooperate in their <lb/>implementation.&apos; 45 <lb/>Therefore, <lb/>&apos;The scope of the &apos;polluter-pays&apos; principle coincides essentially with the restrictions which the <lb/>objectives of the Environmental Liability Directive impose on the application of Article 16. Member <lb/>States may not undermine the &apos;polluter-pays&apos; principle by identifying additional responsible parties as <lb/>well as or instead of the polluters. Thus, additional responsible parties may have only secondary <lb/>liability.&apos; 46 <lb/>Such secondary liability could, for example, include an obligation on site owners to support <lb/>preventive and remedial measures. This would possibly make these measures much more effective <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>40 Article 1 of the Environmental Liability Directive: <lb/>&apos;The purpose of this Directive is to establish a framework of environmental liability based on the &apos;polluter-pays&apos; <lb/>principle, to prevent and remedy environmental damage.&apos; <lb/>41 See Fipa Group and Others, para. 58. <lb/>42 See Opinion of Advocate General Kokott, para. 33. <lb/>43 Ibid., at para. 39. <lb/>44 Ibid., at para. 48. <lb/>45 Ibid., at para. 52. <lb/>46 Ibid., at para. 54. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>due to the owners&apos; better knowledge of the site and be in line with the principle of preventive action <lb/>and the principle that environmental damage should as a priority be rectified at source. However, it <lb/>would by no means imply that the owners should be under obligation to carry out such measures by <lb/>themselves. 47 Furthermore, the comprehensive secondary liability of site owners for environmental <lb/>damage would be in line with the EU objective of achieving a high level of environmental <lb/>protection (Article 191(2) TFEU), yet also be balanced with fundamental economic rights of the <lb/>owners. 48 <lb/>Nevertheless, it seems that such an interpretation of environmental liability, given that it is indeed <lb/>fully substantiated by EU law, does not bode well for the active promotion of environmental <lb/>protection. After all, shifting the responsibility of undertaking preventive and remedial measures <lb/>from the owners to a competent authority, where the owners are unwilling to undertake them <lb/>themselves, is likely to result in a certain delay between the damage occurring and such measures <lb/>being taken. For example, in present case it took years for national environmental authorities to <lb/>address the owners with this matter. Consequently, the land was allowed to remain contaminated for <lb/>much longer than it otherwise could have been. In contrast, the promotion of obligatory immediate <lb/>measures to be taken not only by the operator, but also by owners of polluted sites, would ensure <lb/>that preventive and remedial action takes place as soon as possible, and result in less severe <lb/>environmental deterioration. At this point yet, it should be observed that the notion of balance <lb/>between environmental protection and economic rights, highlighted by the Advocate General, looms <lb/>over contemporary environmental policy. This explains not only the reluctance of some Member <lb/>States to adopt more stringent environmental liability rules, but also cases in which there is a failure <lb/>to comply even with minimal EU environmental standards. 49 <lb/>However, it is still disheartening for the environmentalists that in interpreting the right to identify <lb/>additional responsible parties the Court, unlike the Advocate General, did not go beyond a simple <lb/>statement that such measures should be compatible with EU primary legislation. 50 As the Advocate <lb/>General herself acknowledged, since other EU provisions, such as waste legislation, &apos;may establish <lb/>wider liability on the part of site owners for the rehabilitation of polluted areas than the <lb/>Environmental Liability Directive.&apos; 51 It should therefore not be ruled out that similar obligations <lb/>could be implemented in the future. 52 This would most certainly be welcomed from the point of <lb/>view of enhanced environmental protection. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>As long as the current provisions of the Environmental Liability Directive remain in place, there is <lb/>no obligation upon owners who were not responsible for environmental pollution to adopt <lb/>preventive and remedial measures. National authorities cannot invoke the EU &apos;polluter pays&apos; <lb/>principle in such situations. However, they retain a right to regulate these matters under domestic <lb/>legislation. Pursuant to Article 16 of the Environmental Liability Directive, this allows them to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>47 Ibid., at para. 56. <lb/>48 Ibid., at paras 60 and 61. <lb/>49 See, e.g., Case C-68/11 Commission v Italy [2012] (ECJ, 19 December 2012), para. 40; Case C-404/13 The Queen, on <lb/>the application of ClientEarth v The Secretary of State for the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs [2014] (ECJ, 19 <lb/>November 2014), para. 20. <lb/>50 See Fipa Group and Others, para. 61. <lb/>51 See Opinion of Advocate General Kokott, para. 72. <lb/>52 Ibid., at para. 22. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>adopt more stringent measures with regard to prevention and to remedying environmental damage. <lb/>At the moment, however, the right to identify additional responsible parties, never mind replacing <lb/>those actually responsible, in the national legislation must be regarded with high caution, since such <lb/>policy should be consistent with the objectives of EU primary legislation. </body>


	</text>

</TEI>