<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Our Forgotten Constitutional Guardians: Preserving Respect for the Law</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Brian Christopher</forename>
          <surname>Jones</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T09:04:34.732Z">30/01/2026 10:04:34</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1093__slr__hmz007</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2019</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1093/slr/hmz007</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Brian Christopher Jones. (2019). Our Forgotten Constitutional Guardians: Preserving Respect for the Law. Statute Law Review, 42(1), 1-19. DOI: 10.1093/slr/hmz007</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T14:40:25.119479Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-19T14:40:25.119479Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-29T10:24:23.281Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-08T17:10:12.480Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T09:06:38.697Z" status="candidate" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>This is a repository copy of Our forgotten constitutional guardians: Preserving respect for <lb/>the law. <lb/>White Rose Research Online URL for this paper: <lb/>https://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/155384/ <lb/>Version: Accepted Version <lb/>Article: <lb/>Jones, B.C. orcid.org/0000-0003-2344-976X (2021) Our forgotten constitutional guardians: <lb/>Preserving respect for the law. Statute Law Review, 42 (1). pp. 1-19. ISSN 0144-3593 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/>This is a pre-copyedited, author-produced version of an article accepted for publication in <lb/>Statute Law Review following peer review. The version of record, Brian Christopher Jones, <lb/>Our Forgotten Constitutional Guardians: Preserving Respect for the Law, Statute Law <lb/>Review, hmz007, is available online at: https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007. <lb/>eprints@whiterose.ac.uk <lb/>https://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/ <lb/>Reuse <lb/>Items deposited in White Rose Research Online are protected by copyright, with all rights reserved unless <lb/>indicated otherwise. They may be downloaded and/or printed for private study, or other acts as permitted by <lb/>national copyright laws. The publisher or other rights holders may allow further reproduction and re-use of <lb/>the full text version. This is indicated by the licence information on the White Rose Research Online record <lb/>for the item. <lb/>Takedown <lb/>If you consider content in White Rose Research Online to be in breach of UK law, please notify us by <lb/>emailing eprints@whiterose.ac.uk including the URL of the record and the reason for the withdrawal request. <lb/></titlePage>
	  <front>Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/>1 <lb/>Our Forgotten Constitutional Guardians: <lb/>Preserving Respect for the Law <lb/>Brian Christopher Jones  <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>A focus on back-end constitutional actors remains the norm when we think of typical <lb/>constitutional guardians. This piece challenges that perception, examining the uniquely <lb/>situated UK constitution, with a focus on two significant front-end constitutional <lb/>guardians: bill drafters within the Office of Parliamentary Counsel and senior clerks <lb/>within the House of Commons. These two groups of actors provide a first-and in some <lb/>cases possibly even the last-port of call for assessing the constitutionality of legislation. <lb/>Yet after another period of constitutional change they appear to have been largely <lb/>forgotten in the literature. This is unfortunate, as research interviews with both groups, <lb/>and also with experts of the legislative process, demonstrate that these actors remain <lb/>key players in the UK constitutional system. Furthermore, these two groups are essential <lb/>to upholding our respect for the law, at a time when disenchantment for parliamentary <lb/>democracy appears to be growing. <lb/>Keywords: constitutional guardians, respect for law, legislative process, bill drafting, <lb/>Parliamentary Counsel, House Authorities <lb/></front>
	  
	  <body>When the Great Repeal Bill was announced, 1 a collective sigh of antipathy amongst <lb/>many constitutional watchers emerged. But for some the concern did not revolve around <lb/>repeal of the European Communities Act (ECA) 1972 not being &quot;great&quot;; after forty plus <lb/>years of stormy relations with its European partners, that much was assured. The danger <lb/>was that the sloganeering and propaganda seen throughout the heated referendum <lb/>would now be incorporated into statutory form, through the bill&apos;s short title. Such a <lb/>wantonly symbolic gesture may have poisoned the bill&apos;s parliamentary processes, <lb/>including its debate in both chambers, and probably even influenced the reporting and <lb/>understanding of the legislation outside of Parliament. 2 However eventually the <lb/></body>

			<front> Lecturer, Dundee Law School, University of Dundee. <lb/></front>
	  
	  <listBibl>1 &quot;Brexit: Theresa May to trigger Article 50 by end of March&quot; BBC News (2 October 2016), <lb/>http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-37532364 (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>2 In fact, this label may still be influencing coverage. As of June 2018, Sky was still referring to it as the <lb/>Great Repeal Bill (Faisal Islam, &quot;Brexit moves from procedure to substance&quot; Sky News (21 June 2018, <lb/>https://news.sky.com/story/brexit-moves-from-procedure-to-substance-11411631 <lb/>(Accessed <lb/>15 <lb/>November 2018)). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>government dropped the idea of such a grand label, and changed the title before <lb/>officially submitting the bill to Parliament to: European Union (Withdrawal) Bill. And <lb/>yet, the story of why the government changed their minds remains somewhat of a <lb/>mystery. 3 The significance of this change may be minor for some, but I believe it carries <lb/>more important implications for the UK constitutional system: statutory law is a <lb/>legitimate indicator of state functionality, and if pathologies are present in legislation-<lb/>such as overtly polemical language-then this can be indicative of larger pathologies <lb/>within the state. After all, statutes are one of the only state outputs that are sanctioned <lb/>by both the executive and legislative branches. 4 And when it comes to producing high-<lb/>quality legislation that will enter the statute book, a host of front-end constitutional <lb/>guardians that straddle executive and Parliamentary offices, largely forgotten in the <lb/>traditional constitutional process, are responsible for this task. This paper is about them, <lb/>and especially the key position they play in helping uphold our respect for the law. <lb/>Just as the masses continue to queue at cinemas worldwide for epic superhero battles <lb/>of good versus evil, legal scholarship remains obsessed with classic battles of <lb/>constitutional authority: the legislature versus the judiciary, or the judiciary versus the <lb/>executive. The Miller v Secretary of State case 5 perfectly embodied this enduring desire <lb/>for legal drama, as it received wall-to-wall coverage in newspapers, blogs, classrooms, <lb/>and virtually everywhere else it could have done so. It epitomised the traditional legal <lb/>spectacle: protagonists versus antagonists (contingent on your personal views), key <lb/>players (Gina Miller, Lord Neuberger and Jeremy Wright) and even a host of pre-<lb/>decision drama. 6 And yet, for all the voluminous attention it received, 7 one prominent <lb/>academic has recently characterised it as a &quot;damp squib&quot;, 8 and another argues that <lb/>history may regard Brexit as a constitutional &quot;blip&quot;. 9 And that is only a year and half <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>3 D.A. Green, &quot;Whatever happened to the &apos;Great&apos; Repeal Bill?&quot; Financial Times (21 June 2017), <lb/>https://www.ft.com/content/05253602-ce4a-3f64-8ace-6a6f0387603f (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>Green notes in his article that when he questioned why name would not be used for the short title, they <lb/>responded that, they &quot;can&apos;t use it because it is a parliamentary thing&quot;. <lb/>4 At least, this applies to bills that originate in the government&apos;s legislative programme, and are therefore <lb/>approved at the Cabinet level. Some statutes, of course, may also go on to be approved by the judiciary, <lb/>which would then make three branches sanctioning these important documents. <lb/>5 R (on the application of Miller and another) v Secretary of State for Exiting the European Union, [2017] <lb/>UKSC 5. <lb/>6 No, this is not a reference to the Daily Mail &quot;enemies of the people&quot; headline after the High Court <lb/>decision. Even after that judgment, a speech by Lady Hale caused controversy, as did the Twitter habits <lb/>of Lord Neuberger&apos;s wife. <lb/>7 See, e.g., all the UKCLA Blog entries on the subject here: https://ukconstitutionallaw.org/tag/miller-v-<lb/>secretary-of-state-for-exiting-the-european-union/ (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>8 M. Elliott, &quot;Sovereignty, Primacy and the Common Law Constitution: What has EU Membership <lb/>Taught Us?&quot; Public Law for Everyone (https://publiclawforeveryone.com/2018/07/20/sovereignty-<lb/>primacy-and-the-common-law-constitution-what-has-eu-membership-taught-us/)(Accessed <lb/>15 <lb/>November 2018). <lb/>9 A. Young, Will Brexit change the UK constitution? Hansard Society Blog (7 August 2018) <lb/>https://www.hansardsociety.org.uk/blog/will-brexit-change-the-uk-constitution (Accessed 15 November <lb/>2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>after the judgment was delivered! In reality constitutional authority is more nuanced <lb/>than this, and can be found in some places that constitutional scholars have provided <lb/>cursory attention. Just as the film critic can bring a relatively unknown movie to our <lb/>attention, so should legal scholars be searching beyond legal blockbusters. Although <lb/>the literature has picked up on many topics of constitutional nuance, some things are <lb/>still completely left out of the equation. This paper discusses a couple of these <lb/>&quot;forgotten&quot; constitutional actors. In particular, it focuses on two groups within the <lb/>British constitutional state that believe they are not only constitutional actors, but <lb/>constitutional guardians: the Office of Parliamentary Counsel (OPC) and Parliamentary <lb/>Clerks (in particular those in the Commons Public Bill Office). <lb/>The legal significance and understanding of the Office of Parliamentary Counsel <lb/>within the British system has been marked as lacking. Edward Page noted in 2009 that <lb/>we &quot;know little about the process of drafting primary legislation&quot;, and that the OPC <lb/>itself is &quot;not very well understood&quot;. 10 What was true close to a decade ago is true now: <lb/>a Westlaw journal search identifying &quot;parliamentary counsel&quot; as the subject/keyword <lb/>produced only 17 results over the span of three decades, stretching back to 1988. 11 But <lb/>this dearth of legal scholarship should not cloud one&apos;s judgment regarding the <lb/>significance of the OPC. As Daintith and Page asserted in 1999, &quot;in the absence of a <lb/>higher law by which a sovereign Parliament is bound, the concept of legal policy as <lb/>interpreted by Parliamentary Counsel is as close that our system has traditionally come <lb/>to a check on the &apos;constitutionality&apos; of legislation&quot;. 12 Of course, HRA statements of <lb/>compatibility may now serve this function at the Parliamentary level, 13 and declarations <lb/>of HRA incompatibility can arise in the courts, 14 but these statements and declarations <lb/>are in relation to human rights compatibility, and not necessarily on the <lb/>&quot;constitutionality&quot; of statutes. Nonetheless, as will be seen below, Parliamentary <lb/>Counsel undoubtedly serve a pre-statement function, before bills are even presented to <lb/>Parliament. Daintith and Page go on to note that the importance of Parliamentary <lb/>Counsel as guardian of legal values &quot;reflects their own conception of their role and in <lb/>particular the belief that they owe a responsibility to the law and statute book as well <lb/>as to the minister whose policy they are responsible for translating into statutory <lb/>form&quot;. 15 But some have indicated that this role is changing, and that the OPC is not the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>10 E.C. Page, &quot;Their Word is Law: Parliamentary Counsel and Creative Policy Analysis&quot; (2009) PL 790, <lb/>791. <lb/>11 Search performed on Westlaw UK (15 November 2018). <lb/>12 T. Daintith and A Page, The Executive in the Constitution: Structure, Autonomy and Internal Control <lb/>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1999) 254. <lb/>13 Human Rights Act 1998, s 19. <lb/>14 Human Rights Act 1998, s 4. <lb/>15 Daintith and Page, The Executive in the Constitution: Structure, Autonomy and Internal Control, 256. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>robust check on government that it used to be. Further discussion of the OPC&apos;s role and <lb/>whether or not their role may be changing is discussed below. <lb/>The House Authorities, (in practice a handful of the most senior Clerks) also do not <lb/>receive much attention in the legal literature, although-as will be seen below-their <lb/>influence on the shape of statutory law is also considerable. As Greenberg noted in <lb/>2011, &quot;Many lawyers have never so much heard of the Clerks of Public Bills or the <lb/>other Parliamentary authorities involved in the passage of legislation. Even if they have <lb/>heard of the figures known collectively as the &apos;House Authorities&apos;, most lawyers will <lb/>only have a very shadowy conception of what it is they do&quot;. 16 Although they may not <lb/>have as much input on the final product of legislation, the House Authorities could also <lb/>be considered front-end guardians of the constitution. But they do so in a different way <lb/>from Parliamentary Counsel. This paper focuses on the Public Bill Office, which <lb/>&quot;examines the drafts of Government and private Members&apos; bills to ensure that they <lb/>conform to the rules of the House&quot;. 17 Some things that may arise in their constitutional <lb/>duties include: determining whether the short and long titles of bills are fit for purpose <lb/>(something that played a significant role in Miller 18 ); whether bills with financial <lb/>provisions on spending or taxes require the cover of money resolutions or ways and <lb/>means motions; whether the Queen&apos;s or Prince of Wales&apos;s consent may be required; <lb/>whether or not measures involve a charge on the people; and determining the scope of <lb/>bills, which of course has implications for any amendments during the parliamentary <lb/>process. At times the scope issue can be extremely difficult to determine, but this is one <lb/>of the most important constitutional functions that Clerks carry out, subject ultimately <lb/>to the Speaker&apos;s power to make the final decision on the selection of amendments. <lb/>Taken together, these duties have a large impact on the final form of statutory law, and <lb/>therefore can impact our respect for law. <lb/>A small number of research interviews were performed in connection with this <lb/>article. Participants included lawyers working in the Speaker&apos;s Office or other counsel <lb/>within the Commons, former members of the OPC, the head of the Commons Public <lb/>Bill Office, and three academics who specialise in the study of statutory drafting and <lb/>the legislative process. Material from these interviews is presented throughout the <lb/>article. This piece first discusses the idea of constitutional guardianship generally, <lb/>followed by a section on guardianship in the British context, and on the OPC and House <lb/>Authorities (Commons Public Bill Office) in particular. It then discusses the idea of <lb/>respect for the law and why the substance of statutory law matters, followed by a section <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>16 D. Greenberg, Laying Down the Law: A Discussion of the People, Processes, and Problems that Shape <lb/>Acts of Parliament (London: Sweet &amp; Maxwell, 2011) 83. <lb/>17 House of Commons Information Office, &quot;The Clerk of the House: Factsheet G16&quot; (2006), <lb/>https://www.parliament.uk/documents/commons-information-office/g16.pdf (Accessed 15 November <lb/>2018). <lb/>18 Miller v Secretary of State [2017]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>on whether disrespect for the law is a significant threat. Next, it discusses whether the <lb/>nature and function of the OPC may have recently shifted, potentially putting more <lb/>pressure on other constitutional actors and also potentially impacting the operation of <lb/>the UK constitution. <lb/>1. THE IDEA OF CONSTITUTIONAL GUARDIANSHIP <lb/>The notion of constitutional guardianship is certainly not new, but the popularity of <lb/>employing &quot;constitutional guardian&quot; language has taken hold over the past two or three <lb/>decades. 19 It can now be called a phenomenon, as books, journal articles and even news <lb/>stories throughout numerous jurisdictions regularly employ this phrase. 20 Whether we <lb/>like it or not, the expression appears here to stay. Generally the idea of constitutional <lb/>guardianship sounds like a positive notion, as it conjures up images of citizens and <lb/>others protecting shared fundamental values in the face of those attempting to trample <lb/>them. In reality, however, the phrase is often used by one branch-or specific set of <lb/>constitutional actors-to assert dominance over another branch, thus attempting to <lb/>quell constitutional conflict by appealing to (a sometimes elusive) constitutional <lb/>authority. Additionally, the expression&apos;s use has often been focused on back-end or <lb/>&quot;ultimate&quot; constitutional guardians who usually possess the so-called &quot;final word&quot; <lb/>within a particular jurisdiction, which nowadays throughout most jurisdictions tends to <lb/>be fixated on the courts, as opposed to other constitutional actors. 21 Given that the idea <lb/>of &quot;guardianship&quot; seems here to stay, a more sophisticated understanding of who <lb/>constitutional guardians are and what this job entails is sorely needed. This piece <lb/>attempts to provide a fuller meaning regarding which actors should be included as <lb/>constitutional guardians, and where they are located in the constitutional process. <lb/>Generally, I tend to take a more expansive approach to constitutional guardianship than <lb/>most, believing that almost everyone in a particular democratic citizenry, from judges <lb/>to taxi drivers, could be included as guardians. After all, there is good reason for not <lb/>putting guardianship into a silo, especially if that silo only includes one relatively small <lb/>set of state actors. But most would probably disagree with that sprawling notion of <lb/>guardianship. Even with my expansive view, however, it is acknowledged that some <lb/>constitutional actors possess more power and influence than others. <lb/>Constitutional scholarship&apos;s obsession with back-end or ultimate constitutional <lb/>decision-makers has disregarded those actors that shape the constitution through mostly <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>19 (forthcoming) _________, &quot;Constitutional paternalism: the rise (and problematic) use of constitutional <lb/>&apos;guardian&apos; rhetoric&quot; (2018) 51 NYU Journal of International Law &amp; Politics. <lb/>20 (forthcoming) _________, &quot;Constitutional paternalism: the rise (and problematic) use of constitutional <lb/>&apos;guardian&apos; rhetoric&quot; (2018) 51 NYU Journal of International Law &amp; Politics. <lb/>21 (forthcoming) _________, &quot;Constitutional paternalism: the rise (and problematic) use of constitutional <lb/>&apos;guardian&apos; rhetoric&quot; (2018) 51 NYU Journal of International Law &amp; Politics. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>front-end constitutional decision-making. In some sense this is understandable, as back-<lb/>end constitutional decisions often resemble elaborate dramas that include a plethora of <lb/>high-profile constitutional actors. Given the major players involved, such back-end <lb/>decisions are also likely to receive more press attention. But although these back-end <lb/>constitutional decisions are commonly portrayed as &quot;protecting&quot; and &quot;defending&quot; the <lb/>constitution, they may also change the law, or the protections provided by the <lb/>constitution, more frequently than many realise. 22 If that is the case, it is difficult to <lb/>justify such actions as merely &quot;protecting&quot; or &quot;defending&quot;, as opposed to &quot;amending&quot; <lb/>the law or the constitution. <lb/>As I have demonstrated elsewhere, written constitutions themselves are relatively <lb/>quiet about explicit &quot;guardian&quot; language, especially in prominent sections such as <lb/>preambles, 23 where we would expect to see something such as this mentioned. However <lb/>some democracies do contain formal mechanisms in terms of this language, as <lb/>government officials take oaths to support and defend the constitution. For example, in <lb/>the US all federal officials (both elected and appointed) take an oath to &quot;support and <lb/>defend the Constitution of the United States&quot;. 24 Federal judges take an additional oath <lb/>that requires they will &quot;faithfully and impartially discharge and perform all the duties <lb/>incumbent upon me as [enter job title] under the Constitution and laws of the United <lb/>States&quot;. 25 Thus, within their respective jobs, they are sworn to certain particulars in <lb/>relation to the Constitution. But these oaths are not merely for federal officials or judges; <lb/>even those in the postal service are required to take similar pledges. 26 Also most <lb/>representatives in State legislatures take a similar oath, which usually includes <lb/>upholding both the US and the respective State Constitution. 27 But again, this type of <lb/>oath taking is not exclusive to federal or state elected or appointed officials. Practicing <lb/>attorneys in most States swear an oath to support the US Constitution and also the <lb/>respective State Constitution. 28 And indeed, many city and county employees of their <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>22 As Larry Alexander said in a recent chapter regarding how judicial review can bring about <lb/>constitutional amendment: &quot;the real question is whether the people are actually aware of what is going <lb/>on&quot; (L. Alexander &quot;What are constitutions, and what should (and can) they do?&quot; in E.F. Paul, F.D. Miller <lb/>and J. Paul, What Should Constitutions Do? (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2011) 178). <lb/>23 See, e.g., (forthcoming) _________, &quot;Constitutional paternalism: the rise (and problematic) use of <lb/>constitutional &apos;guardian&apos; rhetoric&quot; (2018) 51 NYU Journal of International Law &amp; Politics. This is true <lb/>even in jurisdictions that possess a dedicated constitutional court. <lb/>24 SCOTUS, <lb/>Text <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>Oaths <lb/>of <lb/>Office <lb/>for <lb/>Supreme <lb/>Court <lb/>Justices, <lb/>https://www.supremecourt.gov/about/oath/textoftheoathsofoffice2009.aspx (Accessed 15 November <lb/>2018). <lb/>25 ibid. <lb/>26 Cornell Law School, Legal Information Institute, 39 U.S. Code § 1011, <lb/>https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/39/1011 (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>27 See, e.g., the oath for officers in Virginia: &quot;I do solemnly swear (or affirm) that I will support the <lb/>Constitution of the United States, and the Constitution of the Commonwealth of Virginia, and that I will <lb/>faithfully and impartially discharge all the duties incumbent upon me as ____________________ <lb/>according to the best of my ability, so help me God&quot;. Virginia Code, Title 49, § 49-1. <lb/>28 See, e.g., the oath for attorneys in the State of New York: &quot;I do solemnly swear (or affirm) that I will <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>respective States, such as police officers, also have to take such an oath. 29 Throughout <lb/>the US, therefore, a wide variety of actors take formal pledges to support, protect or <lb/>defend the US Constitution and sometimes an additional State Constitution. <lb/>Many of the US actors required to take such an oath can be characterised as front-<lb/>end guardians. Elected and appointed officials who work in the legislature or executive <lb/>designing laws or constructing policies could be characterised as such. 30 They draft <lb/>these with the understanding that there is a shared consensus regarding what the <lb/>constitution is and how it operates. And yet, in America it has been repeatedly <lb/>acknowledged that most high-level political issues end up in the courts, and most often <lb/>usually the Supreme Court, which possesses strike down powers regarding the <lb/>constitutionality of legislation. 31 Thus although there are a variety of actors within the <lb/>US who take an oath to support and defend the Constitution, when it comes to ultimate <lb/>constitutional authority, the courts still have the upper-hand. <lb/>(a) Who are the UK&apos;s constitutional guardians? <lb/>The UK&apos;s unique constitutional arrangements provide an interesting challenge <lb/>regarding the idea of constitutional guardianship: who protects and defends the <lb/>constitution when there is no written constitution? Of course, the unwritten nature of <lb/>the UK&apos;s constitution has been blown out of proportion on many occasions. 32 The UK, <lb/>after all, behaves very similarly on a number of indicators to states which employ <lb/>written constitutions, 33 especially when the traditional roles of the branches of <lb/>government (the executive, legislative and judicial) are considered. However when it <lb/>comes to constitutional guardianship, a convincing argument can be put forward that <lb/>the UK behaves quite differently: back-end constitutional actors do not have as much <lb/>influence over the content of the UK&apos;s constitution as they do in other jurisdictions. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>support the constitution of the United States, and the constitution of the State of New York, and that I <lb/>will faithfully discharge the duties of the office of [attorney and counselor-at-law], according to the best <lb/>of my ability&quot;. (Supreme Court of the State of New York, &quot;Orientation to the Profession&quot;, <lb/>http://www.courts.state.ny.us/courts/ad2/forms/law%20guardian%20handbook/orientationtotheprofessi <lb/>onprogrammaterials.pdf (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>29 See, e.g., the oath for police officers in Tulsa, Oklahoma: https://www.tulsapolice.org/join-tpd/oath-<lb/>of-office.aspx (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>30 Those such as police officers, who have law enforcement functions, may be considered back-end <lb/>constitutional actors: even if they do not possess the final word, they also have little influence on those <lb/>designing laws or constructing policies. <lb/>31 Just as Alexis de Tocqueville said, &quot;[s]carcely any political question arises in the United States that is <lb/>not resolved, sooner or later, into a judicial question&quot; (A de Tocqueville, Democracy in America). <lb/>32 See, e.g., when Lord Neuberger, then president of the UK Supreme Court, declared, &quot;[I]t may be said <lb/>with considerable force that we have no constitution as such at all, merely constitutional conventions, <lb/>and that it is as a consequence of this that we have parliamentary sovereignty&quot; (Lord Neuberger, &quot;The <lb/>British and Europe&quot;, Cambridge Freshfields Annual Lecture (12 Feb 2014), para 26 <lb/>https://www.supremecourt.uk/docs/speech-140212.pdf)(Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>33 See, e.g., the Freedom House scores, which include measures on political rights and civil liberties. The <lb/>UK scores 94/100 on this indicator (https://freedomhouse.org/report/freedom-world/2018/united-<lb/>kingdom)(Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>This is because rather than a focus being on a written constitution and the inevitable <lb/>constitutional adjudication surrounding it, the focus is on statutory law, which is where <lb/>a vast bulk of the constitution is located. Statutes are also the primary vehicle used in <lb/>terms of implementing constitutional change. In theory the entirety of statutory law is <lb/>flat (i.e., there are not &quot;constitutional&quot; or &quot;quasi-constitutional&quot; statutes), and any piece <lb/>of statutory law can be repealed or amended through normal parliamentary processes. 34 <lb/>Ordinary statutes passed by the legislature therefore have much more power and <lb/>significance than in jurisdictions which contain a written constitution. Thus, the <lb/>likelihood of guardians outside of the traditional constitutional actors remains a more <lb/>distinct possibility than in other jurisdictions. <lb/>Above we saw how a wide variety of US citizens are subjected to oaths concerning <lb/>aspects of constitutional guardianship. In the UK oaths of office are not focused on a <lb/>written document, but on an entity: the sovereign. 35 MPs, including those in devolved <lb/>territories, 36 take the following oath: <lb/>&quot;I (name of Member) swear by Almighty God that I will be faithful and bear <lb/>true allegiance to Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth, her heirs and successors, <lb/>according to law. So help me God&quot;. 37 <lb/>Judges throughout the UK take a revised version: <lb/>&quot;I, _________ , do swear by Almighty God that I will well and truly serve our <lb/>Sovereign Lady Queen Elizabeth the Second in the office of ________ , and I <lb/>will do right to all manner of people after the laws and usages of this realm, <lb/>without fear or favour, affection or ill will&quot;. 38 <lb/>Neither of these could be said to acknowledge the UK constitution to any significant <lb/>degree, although the rule of law and judicial independence are alluded to. But for the <lb/>most part, they deal with allegiance to the sovereign. Nevertheless, oaths have been <lb/>mentioned as significant in certain contexts. In a 2015 speech in St. Andrews, Lady <lb/>Hale quite prominently referred to it when discussing the UK constitution, declaring, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>34 However the UK courts have challenged this, most prominently in Thoburn v Sunderland City Council <lb/>[2002] EWHC 195 (Admin), where they articulated a number of &quot;constitutional statutes&quot; that can only <lb/>be repealed through explicit wording, rather through any type of implied repeal. <lb/>35 Although, perhaps it could be argued that if the sovereign is the ultimate symbol of the state, then the <lb/>oaths are not necessarily to the sovereign, but to the present unwritten constitution. <lb/>36 As the Scottish Parliament notes: &quot;Any Member who refuses to take the oath or the affirmation will be <lb/>unable to take part in any other proceedings of the Parliament and will not be paid any salary and <lb/>allowances until he or she has done so. If any Member has not taken the oath or affirmation within two <lb/>months of the day of their election they shall cease to be a Member of the Parliament (unless the <lb/>Parliament agrees to extend this period&quot; (http://www.parliament.scot/newsandmediacentre/99397.aspx) <lb/>(Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>37UK <lb/>Parliament, <lb/>&quot;Swearing <lb/>in <lb/>and <lb/>the <lb/>parliamentary <lb/>oath&quot;, <lb/>https://www.parliament.uk/about/how/elections-and-voting/swearingin/ (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>38 Courts and Tribunals Judiciary, &quot;Oaths&quot;, https://www.judiciary.uk/about-the-judiciary/the-judiciary-<lb/>the-government-and-the-constitution/oaths/ (Accessed 15 November 2018). Scottish judges also take <lb/>this <lb/>oath <lb/>(Judiciary <lb/>of <lb/>Scotland, <lb/>&quot;Judicial <lb/>Independence&quot;, <lb/>http://www.scotland-<lb/>judiciary.org.uk/Upload/Documents/JudicialIndependence_2.pdf (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <page>9 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <body>&quot;[t]he rule of law is something more than the mere servant of Parliament. The quid pro <lb/>quo is that we must stay true to our judicial oath, &apos;to do right by all manner of people <lb/>after the laws and usages of this realm, without fear or favour, affection or ill-will&apos;&quot;. 39 <lb/>Thus far from being irrelevant, the oaths do provide some indication for how various <lb/>constitutional actors may undertake their job. Ultimately, however, not much can be <lb/>gleaned from an oath that is concentrated on the sovereign. <lb/>So who are the UK&apos;s constitutional guardians? If we go by the traditional view of <lb/>the constitution which acknowledges Parliament as the highest legal authority, then <lb/>MPs are certainly one important set of guardians, perhaps even the highest. This aligns <lb/>with the view put forward by Dicey, 40 which ultimately sprung from the Glorious <lb/>Revolution and the Bill of Rights 1689. And as we have seen in Miller, 41 when it comes <lb/>to major constitutional change, there is wide consensus that Parliament should be <lb/>involved to at least authorise such change (even if it is not driving it). Within Parliament <lb/>sits the executive, which controls much Parliamentary business and therefore has a <lb/>substantial influence on the UK constitution. Parliament&apos;s legislative programme is <lb/>largely controlled by the Cabinet, which decides what legislation will be put forward in <lb/>each legislative session. 42 Outside Parliament, Cabinet members run the various <lb/>agencies and departments that make up the administrative side of government. The <lb/>judiciary also serves a significant constitutional role, as it has done for centuries. <lb/>Critically, however, judges do not possess statutory strike down powers for primary <lb/>legislation that other supreme and constitutional courts enjoy. Nevertheless, the <lb/>judiciary retains a prominent role within the constitutional structure, and given their <lb/>HRA powers to issue declarations of incompatibility, the courts have taken on a <lb/>noticeably more robust role than previously. 43 The Constitutional Reform Act (CRA) <lb/>2005 furthered this role, creating an official UK Supreme Court whilst also <lb/>acknowledging the principles of rule of law and judicial independence in statutory <lb/>form. 44 Interestingly, however, the CRA 2005 took away any front-end powers that the <lb/>Law Lords (now UKSC justices) previously possessed. Before the Supreme Court was <lb/>established, the Law Lords were part of the House of Lords, and therefore could <lb/>participate and provide input into the legislative process, which at times included non-<lb/></body>

			<listBibl>39 Lady Hale, &quot;The UK Supreme Court in the United Kingdom Constitution&quot; (8 Oct 2015) at 17, <lb/>https://www.supremecourt.uk/docs/speech-151008.pdf (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>40 A.V. Dicey, The Law of the Constitution, edited by JWF Allison (Oxford: Oxford University Press, <lb/>2013). <lb/>41 Miller v Secretary of State [2017]. <lb/>42 Although, it should be noted that Private Members&apos; Bills have at times had a significant impact, and <lb/>that there is also the relatively recent Backbench Business Committee, which has provided more time to <lb/>debates initiated by backbenchers. <lb/>43 See, e.g., R (on the application of Evans) v Attorney General [2015] UKSC 21; R (on the application <lb/>of UNISON) v Lord Chancellor [2017] UKSC 51. <lb/>44 Constitutional Reform Act 2005, Part 1 &amp; Part 2(3). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>controversial commenting on particular bills. 45 Any such influence has now been <lb/>stripped away. 46 But whilst these groups are highly influential on the UK constitution, <lb/>they are not the only actors who could be considered &quot;guardians&quot;. <lb/>Given the UK&apos;s dearth of back-end constitutional protections (as the courts do not <lb/>possess strike-down powers for primary legislation), some view executive power within <lb/>the UK constitution as inherently problematic. The phrase &quot;elective dictatorship&quot; has <lb/>been commonly used in reference to how much power the Government has to pass <lb/>legislation, 47 and Parliament is regularly portrayed as a &quot;rubber stamp&quot; 48 or &quot;weak and <lb/>ineffective&quot;. 49 But these complaints about Parliament and legislation often come from <lb/>those advocating a written constitution or stronger powers for the courts. Indeed, as <lb/>Waldron persuasively argues, legal scholars unjustifiably &quot;paint legislation up in these <lb/>lurid shades in order to lend credibility to judicial review&quot;, and to silence <lb/>embarrassment about its &quot;counter-majoritarian&quot; operation. 50 Some of those myths <lb/>regarding Parliamentary ineptitude were dispelled in a recent book on the Westminster <lb/>legislative process, as Russell and Gover demonstrated that Parliament-not merely the <lb/>Cabinet or Executive-possesses a significant influence on the final form of Acts. 51 But <lb/>their analysis does not contain the whole story. Whilst important, two other groups of <lb/>constitutional actors also play a role here. <lb/>(b) The OPC and House Authorities as constitutional guardians <lb/>Underestimating or neglecting these constitutional actors is a time-honoured legal <lb/>tradition; and given the lack of a written constitution and the resulting power of UK <lb/>statutory law, such neglect just seems downright strange. Given that the OPC drafters <lb/>are working on instructions from departmental lawyers, many may perhaps think that <lb/>drafters are simply translating policy into law. But this notion is far off base. Geoffrey <lb/>Bowman-former First Parliamentary Counsel-noted in 2005: <lb/>&quot;The popular belief is that the drafter&apos;s main function is to turn policy ideas into <lb/>some kind of special statutory language. This is a misconception. The drafter&apos;s <lb/>main and most valuable function is to subject policy ideas to a rigorous <lb/>intellectual analysis. It is no good putting onto the statute book something that <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>45 R. Cornes, &quot;Reforming the House of Lords: the Role of the Law Lords&quot; (1999), UCL Constitution <lb/>Unit, pp 6-9. <lb/>46 However after retirement former UKSC justices can go back and sit in the Lords. <lb/>47 Lord Hailsham coined this phrase in 1976, whilst arguing for a written constitution. <lb/>48 S. Katilowski, &quot;Rubber Stamp or Cockpit? The Impact of Parliament on Government Legislation&quot; <lb/>(2008) 61(4) Parliamentary Affairs 694. <lb/>49 G. Brady, &quot;Parliament is weak and ineffective -it needs to change&quot; The Spectator (20 March 2015), <lb/>https://blogs.spectator.co.uk/2015/03/parliament-is-weak-and-ineffective-it-needs-to-change/ (Accessed <lb/>15 November 2018). <lb/>50 J. Waldron, The Dignity of Legislation (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999) 2. <lb/>51 M. Russell and D. Gover, Legislation at Westminster (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2017). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>simply will not stand up. It has to stand up to scrutiny in Parliament and (once <lb/>enacted) to scrutiny by practitioners and the courts. If the analysis means that the <lb/>ideas collapse, the client will be sent away to think again or might even conclude <lb/>that the particular project should be abandoned&quot;. 52 <lb/>Page also confirmed this scrutiny by the OPC in a 2009 article, acknowledging that, <lb/>&quot;[t]he drafting stage is likely to be the first at which the policy as a whole is subjected <lb/>to a form of rigorous scrutiny, and a scrutiny with a high degree of legitimacy. If a <lb/>drafter says that a policy cannot work it is taken extremely seriously&quot;. 53 But Page goes <lb/>even further: <lb/>&quot;The legal character of its prospective evaluation gives the views of Counsel <lb/>enormous force even on core issues in legislation. It is a force sufficient to <lb/>convince those involved in putting the legislation forward, whether officials or <lb/>politicians, that the basic architecture of what they are proposing needs to be <lb/>changed. It is also a force that routinely leads to such changes, if not invariably <lb/>on the central thrust of the legislation, then on important sections of it: it does not <lb/>appear to be confined to the odd quirky case&quot;. 54 <lb/>Indeed, when it comes to drafters and the policy process, &quot;the only certainty is that the <lb/>hypothesis that drafters consider neither policy nor substance just form has been <lb/>disproven&quot;. 55 These findings further dispel the &quot;elective dictatorship&quot; notion, where the <lb/>Westminster legislative agenda is construed a top-down process through which the <lb/>executive get everything they want. Initial pushback from the OPC may not just lead to <lb/>legislative changes, but could also be a sign that the legislation may experience <lb/>difficulty getting through the parliamentary process, or will run into opposition from <lb/>the courts or practitioners. <lb/>Beyond influencing policy development, Daintith and Page provide a wider <lb/>assertion that OPC drafters are &quot;guardians of values customarily regarded as integral to <lb/>the legal order&quot;, 56 even providing the first check on the &quot;constitutionality&quot; of <lb/>legislation. 57 But even given the wide success of their text, The Executive in the <lb/>Constitution, the implications of this astute assertion has gone virtually ignored-or at <lb/>least not critically examined-in the legal literature. Perhaps some of this neglect is <lb/>because of other changes taking place in the UK constitution, such as the increasing <lb/>importance of Parliamentary select committees, the evolution of the HRA, and an <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>52 G. Bowman, &quot;Why is there a Parliamentary Counsel Office?&quot; (2005) 26(2) Statute Law Review 69, 70. <lb/>53 Page, &quot;Their Word is Law: Parliamentary Counsel and Creative Policy Analysis&quot; (2009) PL 790, 791. <lb/>54 Page, &quot;Their Word is Law: Parliamentary Counsel and Creative Policy Analysis&quot; (2009) PL 790, 810. <lb/>55 C. Stefanou, &quot;Drafters, Drafting and the Policy Process&quot; in C Stefanou and H Xanthaki, Drafting <lb/>Legislation: A Modern Approach (Ashgate Publishing, 2008) 333. <lb/>56 Daintith and Page, The Executive in the Constitution: Structure, Autonomy and Internal Control, 254. <lb/>They note especially values such as: non-retrospection, proper use of delegation and respect for the <lb/>liberties of the subject, amongst others. <lb/>57 Daintith and Page, The Executive in the Constitution: Structure, Autonomy and Internal Control, 154. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>increased assertiveness by the judiciary. Nevertheless, as the UK constitution borders <lb/>on another major change, with Brexit looming in 2019, Daintith and Page&apos;s insightful <lb/>assertion deserves more attention. <lb/>My research interviews confirmed that OPC drafters and House Authorities are <lb/>viewed as constitutional guardians, or at the very least as guardians of the statute book. <lb/>Former First Parliamentary Counsel Stephen Laws said, &quot;It is our job to advise <lb/>[Government] about things that appear unwise, that threaten the system integrity of the <lb/>statute book. We are the experts on producing statute law and that involves being an <lb/>expert in things you can do wrong that create risks for the future&quot;. 58 Former OPC drafter <lb/>Daniel Greenberg asserted, &quot;Definitely…legislative drafters are the frontline of the <lb/>battle to maintain, or indeed impose sometimes, the rule of law&quot;. 59 Clerk of Legislation <lb/>Liam Laurence Smyth agreed, adding that, &quot;a lot of things we do are not subject to legal <lb/>challenge but are entirely internal processes&quot;. 60 Academics were even more assertive <lb/>that these two groups were constitutional guardians. Asked whether this was the case, <lb/>Prof Constantin Stefanou said, &quot;Yes. And in many respects, they are…they do see <lb/>themselves as custodians of the rule of law in general&quot;. 61 He further asserted, &quot;The <lb/>informal interpretation they will give you is as good as that of any judge&quot;. 62 Prof <lb/>Michael Zander replied, &quot;Definitely. Most certainly. Both the officials in Parliament <lb/>and the Parliamentary Counsel very much play that role. They see it as part of their <lb/>role&quot;. 63 Meanwhile, Prof Helen Xanthaki noted, &quot;the drafter must certainly defend the <lb/>constitution by alerting client departments to any unconstitutionality, hidden or <lb/>unhidden&quot;. 64 <lb/>It seems that many of those who have studied or worked inside these two groups <lb/>would agree that OPC drafters and House Authorities play significant constitutional <lb/>roles. The essence of these roles boils down to a front-end form of &quot;constitutionalising&quot; <lb/>bills: without these two groups of constitutional actors deciding that bills are ready to <lb/>be delivered to Parliament, they simply do not move forward. And even during the <lb/>legislative process, many significant decisions are being made as bills are shaped by <lb/>parliamentary processes (i.e., as amendments are proposed and added to legislation). It <lb/>is obvious that some in these two groups see themselves as the frontline in upholding <lb/>constitutional principles such as the rule of law, while others see themselves as <lb/>protectors of the statute book, the UK&apos;s highest form of law. This mind-set is readily <lb/>connected to how both sets of constitutional actors perceive and maintain their <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>58 Interview with S. Laws (London: 19 February 2018). <lb/>59 Interview with D. Greenberg (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>60 Interview with L. Laurence Smyth (London: 19 February 2018). <lb/>61 Interview with C. Stefanou (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>62 Interview with C. Stefanou (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>63 Interview with M. Zander via telephone (28 February 2018). <lb/>64 Interview with H. Xanthaki (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>constitutional duties, and also in how they help preserve a respect for law that is <lb/>increasingly coming under strain. <lb/>2. UPHOLDING OUR RESPECT FOR LAW <lb/>Statutes used to be instruments that only highly specialised professionals would interact <lb/>with. Nowadays, however, a range of individuals interact with statutes on a variety of <lb/>levels. A 2012 joint study by the OPC and National Archives found that the <lb/>legislation.gov.uk website had two million separate visitors per month, and that 60 per <lb/>cent of those were non-lawyers who needed to consult the site for work-related reasons <lb/>(e.g., police officers, local officials or HR professionals). 65 As Prof Xanthaki said <lb/>during our interview, &quot;we know that people in the UK want direct access to legislation&quot;, <lb/>and &quot;we know that [accessibility of legislation] is an aspect of the rule of law&quot;. 66 After <lb/>all, Tom Bingham&apos;s first principle to his conception of the rule of law is that: &quot;The law <lb/>must be accessible and so far as possible intelligible, clear and predictable&quot;. 67 Even if <lb/>vague, these aspirational qualities are important, and form the baseline for a common <lb/>respect for law amongst the citizenry. <lb/>Governments-whether liberal or conservative, coalition or minority-will continue <lb/>to put forward controversial legislation. Given the operation of democracy and the <lb/>inherent battles between government and opposition, many pieces of legislation will <lb/>rub the other side as inherently flawed, unnecessary, or even unlawful. Nevertheless, <lb/>once a bill receives the Royal Assent it is then recognised not merely as government <lb/>policy, but as law. But statutory law-even given its inherently political origins-is <lb/>supposed to be qualitatively different from the political realm. As one interviewee noted, <lb/>&quot;The statute book is thought of as being a sober instrument. Obviously it reflects politics <lb/>in the highest degree… but there is a sense that statute law has to be sober, restrained, <lb/>dignified&quot;. 68 Therefore, whilst reflecting politics, the statute book is also a legal <lb/>instrument, where citizens can find a coherent set of text that is free from political <lb/>sloganizing and partisan language, and contains the necessary qualities that Bingham <lb/>articulates in his rule of law principles. <lb/>Interviewees repeatedly highlighted the importance of statute book neutrality. Daniel <lb/>Greenberg noted, &quot;The traditional answer is that it is a rule of law issue, not about <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>65 A. Bertlin, &quot;What works best for the reader? A study on drafting and presenting legislation&quot; The <lb/>Loophole <lb/>(May <lb/>2014), <lb/>p <lb/>27 <lb/>https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/3269 <lb/>37/Loophole_-_2014-2__2014-05-09_-What_works_best_for_the_reader.pdf (Accessed 15 November <lb/>2018). <lb/>66 Interview with H. Xanthaki (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>67 T. Bingham, The Rule of Law (London: Penguin, 2010) 37. <lb/>68 Interview with M. Zander (28 February 2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>preventing propaganda…It is less about reining the government in from free advertising <lb/>and more about good law&quot;. 69 But what is good law that adheres to rule of law? Former <lb/>First Parliamentary Counsel Stephen Laws provided a possible answer, emphasising, <lb/>&quot;One of the functions of legislation is to produce law people will comply with <lb/>because it has the authority of the law, rather than the authority of the political <lb/>slogan. You fail in that process if you don&apos;t convince people you have created <lb/>something impartial enough to be properly regarded as law rather than a slogan. <lb/>That&apos;s a balance. You want the law to be expressed in a way that gives people <lb/>the message how you want them to behave and why, but you don&apos;t want to be <lb/>polemical about it. That detracts from the dignity of the law, on which it depends <lb/>in order to be respected and complied with&quot;. 70 <lb/>These points are undoubtedly important. A focus on non-polemical or non-sloganistic <lb/>language can help provide legislation with the &quot;dignity&quot; and &quot;authority&quot; needed for <lb/>compliance (i.e., a type of psychological currency), 71 which certainly impacts the <lb/>operation of the rule of law. As Daniel Greenberg quipped during our interview, <lb/>&quot;Ordinary people, in the same way that they like judges to look like judges, like law to <lb/>read like law&quot;. 72 <lb/>In terms of policing polemical statutory language, the presentation and articulation <lb/>of bill titles attracted significant attention. This is understandable, given that the origins <lb/>of my interviews were about the Great Repeal Bill, and also because as opposed to the <lb/>main text of bills, drafting conventions for short and long titles have been established <lb/>throughout the years. 73 It is also significant because statutory titles came under <lb/>consideration in Miller. 74 But even with these drafting conventions in place, head of the <lb/>Public Bill Office Liam Laurence Smyth still admitted, &quot;We are constantly, every week, <lb/>policing non-sloganising titles&quot;. 75 His statement is primarily in reference to bills <lb/>proposed by private members, whose bills are far out-numbered by the Government <lb/>bills, which dominate the parliamentary landscape. 76 This acknowledgement is <lb/>somewhat disconcerting, given the established conventions already in place on these <lb/>matters; although it is acknowledged that backbenchers-just like government-may <lb/>want symbolic political victories, and statutory language may help them achieve that <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>69 Interview with D. Greenberg (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>70 Interview with S. Laws (London: 19 February 2018). <lb/>71 For more on the psychological aspects of statutory law, see: D. Feldman, &quot;Legislation Which Bears <lb/>No Law&quot; (2016) 37(3) Statute Law Review 212. <lb/>72 Interview with D. Greenberg (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>73 Sir M. Jack, Erskine May&apos;s Parliamentary Practice: The Law, Privileges, Proceedings and Usage of <lb/>Parliament (24th Ed.)(London: LexisNexis, 2011) 526. <lb/>74 Miller v Secretary of State [2017]. <lb/>75 Interview with L. Laurence Smyth (London: 19 February 2018). <lb/>76 House of Commons Standing Orders accord private Members Bills thirteen plenary sittings a year, <lb/>all on Fridays. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>goal. Nevertheless, when it comes to government legislation, some saw draftsmen as <lb/>still having the upper-hand in this situation. One interviewee noted that &quot;certainly the <lb/>draftsmen are on top in this situation&quot;, 77 whilst another noted that getting &quot;particular <lb/>words on the face of the Bill…depends on how appropriate they are or how <lb/>accommodating the drafter is&quot;. 78 <lb/>So how is statutory language policed? The answer lies in a familiar-and essential-<lb/>part of the UK constitution: through conversations. Drafters consult with departmental <lb/>lawyers, House Authorities and others to determine what language is appropriate is <lb/>what is not. If there is a significant dispute, then the Attorney General or the House <lb/>Speaker could get involved at some point, but controversies reaching that level are <lb/>unlikely. These everyday conversations about language also help to prevent the <lb/>legislative pathologies present in other jurisdictions. For instance, in the US Congress <lb/>log-rolling and pork-barrel legislation is quite typical. But this is not so in Westminster. <lb/>According to Liam Laurence Smyth, the reason this does not occur is that, &quot;on a very <lb/>mundane daily basis…we have those conversations: what&apos;s the scope of the Bill, what <lb/>amendments are going to be allowed as admissible or not admissible. So it&apos;s connected <lb/>with having a very strong but equally impartial chair in the House of Commons, and <lb/>the tradition in the Lords, of respecting the rules of what&apos;s relevant&quot;. 79 These everyday <lb/>&quot;mundane&quot; conversations are key to upholding the quality of the statute book, and <lb/>subsequently our respect for law. <lb/>3. IS DISRESPECT FOR LEGISLATION A SIGNIFICANT THREAT? <lb/>The turn of the century has brought about some dire warnings regarding the current <lb/>state of legislation, and how it may impact our political and constitutional realities. <lb/>After a couple of conspicuous laws were passed in Australia bearing evocative US-style <lb/>titles, Graeme Orr noted that such practices could &quot;hasten a decline in respect for <lb/>democratic governance&quot;. 80 More recently David Feldman criticises promissory, <lb/>declaratory, aspirational and politically rhetorical statutory language, arguing that <lb/>&quot;[l]egally pointless legislation could debase the psychological currency of legislation <lb/>generally&quot;. 81 Going further, Feldman notes that, &quot;If Acts of Parliament are used to make <lb/>political points, people may start to regard them as just another kind of political rhetoric, <lb/>which can be ignored if one disagrees with it. This may ultimately tend to undermine <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>77 Interview with M. Zander (28 February 2018). <lb/>78 Interview with S. Salimi (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>79 Interview with L. Laurence Smyth (London: 19 February 2018). <lb/>80 G. Orr, &quot;Names without Frontiers&quot; (2001) Statute Law Review 188, at 189. The titles he focused on <lb/>were: &quot;A New Tax System&quot;, &quot;More Jobs, Better Pay&quot;, and &quot;Fair Access and Better Prices for All&quot;. <lb/>81 D. Feldman, &quot;Legislation Which Bears No Law&quot; (2016) 37(3) Statute Law Review 212, 224. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>the psychological commitment to law on the part of subjects&quot;. 82 Daniel Greenberg has <lb/>also been a vocal critic about the current state of UK statutory drafting. Concluding a <lb/>2015 article analysing &quot;dangerous trends&quot; in drafting, Greenberg stresses that these <lb/>&quot;have the potential to diminish significantly from the accountability and effectiveness <lb/>of Parliamentary democracy in the UK&quot;. 83 Taken together, these warnings are not <lb/>constrained to merely a drafting and statutory interpretation context (or even a &quot;legal <lb/>profession&quot; context), and bear significant implications for constitutional democracy <lb/>more generally. This section ties together some of the dangers identified, and also <lb/>recognises further implications for disrespect for legislation. <lb/>Given the current state of many long-enduring constitutional democracies, there are <lb/>strong reasons to take the warnings above seriously. It is true that the quality of <lb/>legislation is often seen as a technical aspect of the rule of law or of parliamentary <lb/>processes. Daniel Greenberg stated in our interview that statutory language laced with <lb/>propaganda or advertising &quot;risks lowering the credibility and respect for the rule of <lb/>law… We learn to be naturally resistant to advertising… Formal and neutral language <lb/>helps to preserve its credibility&quot;. 84 But beyond adding respect and credibility to the rule <lb/>of law, a more significant implication can be identified: ultimately, statutory law is a <lb/>legitimate indicator of how states are operating. If statutes contain obvious <lb/>disorganisation, polemical language, pointless provisions, or other types of pathologies <lb/>(such as log-rolling or pork-barrel legislation), then this is evidence that the state more <lb/>generally is suffering from other ill effects. Further, when it comes to official state <lb/>outputs, statutes are arguably the highest form of interaction between the citizen and <lb/>the state. These documents are often produced and sanctioned by the most accountable <lb/>and responsive branches of government-the executive and the legislature-and <lb/>sometimes may even get further validated by the judiciary. Very few, if any, other state <lb/>documents receive a seal of approval from two branches of government, let alone a <lb/>potential third. Thus when commentators make the connection from pathologies in <lb/>statutory law, to declines in respect for statutory law, and then to a more general <lb/>decrease in respect for democratic governance, it should be taken seriously, and as a <lb/>legitimate warning for not just those in the legal profession, but for the entire citizenry. <lb/>But there are other implications for statutory pathologies that may influence the <lb/>operation of the state. Stephen Laws noted in our interview, &quot;If you pollute the system, <lb/>it becomes less capable of being used for the purposes you want to use it for. If you <lb/>debase the coinage of communication with the courts…you risk creating a sepsis in the <lb/>system that then makes the job much more difficult in future. It is the job of the drafter <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>82 Feldman, &quot;Legislation Which Bears No Law&quot; (2016) 37(3) Statute Law Review 212, 224. <lb/>83 D. Greenberg, &quot;Dangerous trends in modern legislation&quot; (2015) PL 96, 110. <lb/>84 Interview with D. Greenberg (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>to advise on that&quot;. 85 Stephen&apos;s observation is especially critical, as disrespect for <lb/>legislation may also increase conflict between branches. This has been seen in a number <lb/>of jurisdictions in relation to the legislature and the judiciary. Take an example from <lb/>Australia. In 2014, considering a challenge to the Vicious Lawless Association <lb/>Disestablishment (VLAD) Act 2013, the Australian High Court noted the following <lb/>(obiter): <lb/>&quot;The term &apos;vicious lawless association&apos;, which appears in the title to the VLAD <lb/>Act, is not defined and appears nowhere in the body of the Act. It is a piece of <lb/>rhetoric which is at best meaningless and at worst misleads as to the scope and <lb/>substance of the law&quot;. 86 <lb/>The High Court followed this up later in the judgment with another stinging rebuke: <lb/>&quot;The task of those administering and enforcing the relevant provisions is made <lb/>no easier by the fact that the relevant provisions of the VLAD Act hinge on the <lb/>definition of a &apos;vicious lawless associate&apos;. As will shortly be explained, that <lb/>expression is defined in a way that does not depend upon any determination that <lb/>the person concerned is personally &apos;vicious&apos; or generally &apos;lawless&apos;. The <lb/>expression is, therefore, at least inapt. Perhaps it was thought to reflect the stated <lb/>political objective of dealing with &apos;criminal gangs&apos;, but it is an expression which <lb/>is likely to mislead in at least two ways. First, it is an expression which suggests <lb/>a much narrower focus for the Act than its provisions require. Second, it is an <lb/>expression which, at a trial, can only create prejudice and divert attention from <lb/>the issues which a jury would have to decide. The adoption of this manner of <lb/>drafting is antithetical to the proper statement and administration of the criminal <lb/>law&quot;. 87 <lb/>The labels &quot;meaningless&quot;, &quot;inapt&quot;, and &quot;a piece of rhetoric&quot; that is &quot;likely to mislead&quot; <lb/>can only be considered damning indictments regarding failures in drafting. These <lb/>mistakes make the Australian parliamentary counsel look bad, which may influence <lb/>their relationship with the executive. And for the legislators that passed the law, these <lb/>words will certainly cut deep, and will not soften the relationship between the <lb/>legislature and the judiciary. One can only imagine the comments from the judiciary if <lb/>the Great Repeal Bill would have become the Great Repeal Act, especially considering <lb/>that much of what the EU Withdrawal Act does is implement a large swath of EU law <lb/>into UK domestic law. The only Act that it repeals is the European Communities Act <lb/>1972. 88 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>85 Interview with S. Laws (London: 19 February 2018). <lb/>86 Kuczborski <lb/>v <lb/>Queensland <lb/>[2014] <lb/>HCA <lb/>46 <lb/>(14 <lb/>November <lb/>2014), <lb/>http://austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/HCA/2014/46.html, para 14 (Accessed 15 November 2018). <lb/>87 Kuczborski v Queensland [2014] HCA 67. <lb/>88 In this way the EU (Withdrawal) Act is similar to the Abolition of Domestic Rates etc. (Scotland) Act <lb/>1987, which accomplished its title in Section 1, and then went about implementing the poll tax. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Similar judicial comments have been seen in the American context. In US v <lb/>Windsor, 89 largely considered the pre-cursor to Obgerfell v Hodges, 90 SCOTUS justices <lb/>commented on the title of the Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA), which was ultimately <lb/>ruled unconstitutional by the majority of the Supreme Court. 91 The majority found that <lb/>the short title displayed evidence of animus, which was taken into consideration when <lb/>the Act was struck down. And in the case of Shelby County v Holder, 92 which found a <lb/>provision of the landmark Voting Rights Act unconstitutional, the late Justice Scalia <lb/>noted that the name of the law was &quot;wonderful&quot;, adding that not re-enacting the <lb/>legislation would lose votes for some members. 93 Thus, he concluded, the re-<lb/>authorisation of the statute could not be left in the hands of lawmakers. 94 For a sitting <lb/>judge to say that legislators could not be trusted to re-authorise a 1965 statute that they <lb/>had already re-authorised on a number of occasions, simply because the new title-<lb/>which legislators themselves had written and approved of-is beyond merely inter-<lb/>branch disagreement…it is borderline constitutional dysfunction. <lb/>Given the UK&apos;s unique constitutional arrangements, with Parliament considered the <lb/>highest legal authority and statutes as the highest form of law, a decline in respect for <lb/>statutory law could produce more significant effects than in other jurisdictions. <lb/>Significant disrespect could potentially change one or both of those realities. Instead of <lb/>looking to Parliament as the main (and final) law-making authority, people may start <lb/>looking to other constitutional actors-particularly the courts. This is compounded by <lb/>the fact that UK citizens do indeed interact with legislation quite a lot, and that many <lb/>of those doing so are non-lawyers. 95 Thus, disrespect could go beyond the legal <lb/>profession. Additionally, if drafters and House Authorities are frontline constitutional <lb/>guardians in terms of what gets added to legislation-which I certainly believe-further <lb/>disrespect for legislation may not attract the highest-quality draftsmen or clerks <lb/>available, or may send current drafters or clerks towards the exits. After all, no one <lb/>wants to go into a profession that is widely disrespected. <lb/>(a) Change in culture for the Office of Parliamentary Counsel? <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>89 570 U.S. 744 (2013). <lb/>90 576 U.S. ____ (2015). <lb/>91 __________, &quot;SCOTUS Short Title Turmoil: Time for a Congressional Bill Naming Authority&quot; (2013) <lb/>32(1) Yale Law &amp; Policy Review Inter Alia 25. <lb/>92 570 U.S. 2 (2013). <lb/>93 _________, &quot;Personalised Bills as Commemorations: A Problem for House Rules&quot; (2013) 46(9) <lb/>Connecticut Law Review Online 11. <lb/>94 Transcript of Oral Argument at 47-48, Shelby Cnty., 133 S. Ct. 2612 (No. 12-96), available at <lb/>http://www.supremecourt.gov/oral_arguments/argument_transcripts/12-96.pdf (Accessed 15 November <lb/>2018). <lb/>95 Bertlin, &quot;What works best for the reader? A study on drafting and presenting legislation&quot; The Loophole <lb/>(May 2014), 27. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Above I argued that the OPC has served an important constitutional function since its <lb/>inception, but in recent years troubling signs have emerged that the culture within the <lb/>OPC may be changing. If this is the case, then from a practical perspective it is likely <lb/>to affect other constitutional actors, such as the House Authorities, who often interact <lb/>with OPC drafters on statutory drafting matters. But it also may have wider <lb/>constitutional implications. Whilst it has always been the case that drafters within the <lb/>office are instructed by Ministers and departmental lawyers on policy matters, drafters <lb/>have also looked at themselves as the protectors of the statute book, and throughout the <lb/>years have been willing to question and push back against Ministerial demands that <lb/>have gone too far. This seems to have been a strong characteristic of the office <lb/>throughout the years. As Geoffrey Bowman stated in a 2005 article: &quot;We look for <lb/>people who tend to not take things for granted, and who are prepared to question ideas-<lb/>and if need be, to the point of destruction&quot;. 96 This point ties in with those above about <lb/>drafters not being merely translators or technicians, but often affecting the core <lb/>substance of legislation. Greenberg noted in a 2015 article that, &quot;Ministers have always <lb/>inevitably pushed out the boundaries of acceptability in legislative terms, not because <lb/>of dictatorial or authoritarian ambition, but simply because their focus is on what will <lb/>work most pragmatically and effectively; and they have traditionally left it to career <lb/>legal civil servants to be the guardians of what is proper in constitutional terms&quot;. 97 The <lb/>major questions are whether Ministers are still leaving this job to civil servants, and <lb/>also whether civil servants are still up to the job. <lb/>Some of my interviewees indicated that there has been a culture change within the <lb/>OPC. Daniel Greenberg stated in our interview: <lb/>&quot;When I joined Parliamentary Counsel we were told that Ministers were not <lb/>our clients. In so far as we had a client that was Ministerial it was the Attorney-<lb/>General and we could appeal to the Attorney-General if we did not like what <lb/>the Ministers were telling us to do. That changed very dramatically towards <lb/>the end of my time there…I think Ministers are now seen more as clients than <lb/>they were&quot;. 98 <lb/>Other interviewees agreed. Liam Laurence Smyth, a career parliamentarian, said that, <lb/>&quot;These days, Parliamentary Counsel consider themselves bound to represent the <lb/>government&quot;. 99 Greenberg also noted in a 2015 article that &quot;the quality of advice&quot; that <lb/>Ministers receive from drafters had changed, as drafters &quot;no longer appreciate the basic <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>96 Bowman, &quot;Why is there a Parliamentary Counsel Office?&quot; (2005) 26(2) Statute Law Review 69, 73. <lb/>He did add, &quot;Of course, it is not enough to merely destroy bad ideas. The capacity to contribute fresh and <lb/>constructive ideas is also important&quot;. <lb/>97 Greenberg, &quot;Dangerous trends in modern legislation&quot; (2015) PL 96, 103. <lb/>98 Interview with D. Greenberg (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>99 Interview with L. Laurence Smyth (London: 19 February 2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>legal and constitutional concepts&quot;. 100 Academics were a bit more sceptical about such <lb/>a dramatic change taking place within the OPC, and especially how it would affect their <lb/>constitutional role. Prof Xanthaki stated, &quot;I am certain they will express any concerns <lb/>of constitutionality. I am certain that they will do their best to avoid constitutionality <lb/>from taking place. But, at the same time, I know they will bow down to their clients&quot;. 101 <lb/>Another academic, however, was a bit more pointed, &quot;Times have changed. It is not <lb/>because they are weak individuals or they&apos;ve done a deal with a devil. Civil servants <lb/>need different skills. Having managerial skills is not a bad thing…but I don&apos;t think this <lb/>is because there is a general drop in standards or that the wrong people have been <lb/>employed, because they are very high calibre drafters&quot;. 102 Michael Zander noted that <lb/>there had been &quot;some slippage&quot; in recent years, but that still, &quot;I would look to <lb/>Parliamentary Counsel&apos;s office for a measure of control and a sense of responsibility <lb/>about what the statute book should look like&quot;. 103 These latter responses suggest that <lb/>some type of cultural change may have occurred, but that the OPC still adequately <lb/>performs its constitutional duties. <lb/>Indeed, some interviewees pushed back firmly against there being any type of <lb/>culture change within the OPC. Former First Parliamentary Counsel Stephen Laws <lb/>declared, &quot;No. I think that&apos;s wrong. Operating within the system I&apos;ve described where <lb/>they are your client, your job is to do the best you can for them; not to regulate them <lb/>but to advise them fearlessly on risks, while leaving them the decision of whether or <lb/>not they want to take the risk&quot;. 104 This statement asserts that although Ministers and <lb/>departmental lawyers are viewed as &quot;clients&quot;, drafters have a duty to advise them <lb/>&quot;fearlessly&quot; in terms of risks. As has been indicated by others above, this &quot;fearless&quot; <lb/>advice-connected to Bowman&apos;s point regarding questioning ideas to &quot;destruction&quot;-<lb/>would include concerns centred on constitutionality. <lb/>Nevertheless, even slight changes within the OPC on presentational statutory matters <lb/>could affect other constitutional actors, such as those working in the Commons Public <lb/>Bill Office. Any change within the OPC that diminishes that first check on the <lb/>constitutionality of legislation would be highly significant, as it may even lend more <lb/>credence to those who attempt to diminish the value of legislation, and Parliament&apos;s <lb/>influence on it, and reinforce those who label the UK an &quot;elective dictatorship&quot;. <lb/>Ultimately, if there has been a culture change within the OPC, then such a change is <lb/>something legal scholars should be paying attention to, and which is just as <lb/>significant-or perhaps even more so-than blockbuster cases such as Miller. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>100 Greenberg, &quot;Dangerous trends in modern legislation&quot; (2015) PL 96, 103. <lb/>101 Interview with H. Xanthaki (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>102 Interview with C. Stefanou (London: 20 February 2018). <lb/>103 Interview with M. Zander (28 February 2018). <lb/>104 Interview with S. Laws (London: 19 February 2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>4. CONCLUSION <lb/>The implications for this paper, whilst argued from a public law perspective, certainly <lb/>go beyond merely the constitutionality of legislation. The constitutional actors featured <lb/>above impact every type of law, from contract to commercial, from family to criminal. <lb/>No doubt this has been noticed by some writers. 105 As Daniel Greenberg noted in our <lb/>interview, &quot;The reality is that people that draft legislation have an unbelievable amount <lb/>of power&quot;; they could &quot;undermine judicial independence&quot;, &quot;disguise retrospective <lb/>legislation&quot;, or &quot;break lots of constitutional and fundamental legal principles&quot; if they <lb/>wanted to, and perhaps even do so with little notice. 106 But not all drafting errors, even <lb/>significant ones, are going to be brought to the attention of the courts. And even if they <lb/>do receive court attention, the judiciary lacks the power to change them: they can <lb/>critique and interpret, but not compose, legislation. Thus, preserving our respect for law <lb/>largely begins with these front-end constitutional actors. <lb/>Although these &quot;forgotten&quot; constitutional actors do not provide the high-stakes <lb/>drama that many blockbuster legal cases provide, they are integral to the success of our <lb/>legal and constitutional system. Our current conversations about upholding <lb/>constitutionality seem a bit oversimplified: democracy versus rule of law actually has <lb/>much more nuance. Front-end constitutional guardians such as the OPC and House <lb/>Authorities also serve invaluable constitutional functions. The OPC is rightly <lb/>considered by some as the first check on constitutionality, and this should not be <lb/>discounted-even if there has been a slight culture change within the office. <lb/>Additionally, the House Authorities also play a role in terms of assessing <lb/>constitutionality, as they accept and approve various types of legislative language-<lb/>from short and long titles to relevance of amendments-and their role in upholding the <lb/>quality of legislation, and more generally the statute book, should not be discounted. <lb/>In his classic text, The Politics of the Judiciary, John Griffith had this to say about <lb/>defending liberty within the UK: <lb/>&quot;[W]e depend far more on the political climate and on the vigilance of those <lb/>members of society who for a variety of reasons, some political and some <lb/>humanitarian, make it their business to seek to hold public authorities within <lb/>their proper limits. That those limits are also prescribed by law and that judges <lb/>may be asked to maintain them is not without significance. But the judges are <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>105 P. Sales, &quot;The Contribution of Legislative Drafting to the Rule of Law&quot; (2018) 77(3) C.L.J. 630; R. <lb/>Mulheron, &quot;Legislating Dangerously: Bad Samaritans, Good Society, and the Heroism Act 2015&quot; (2017) <lb/>80(1) Modern Law Review 88. <lb/>106 Interview with D. Greenberg (London: 20 February 2018). Mr Greenberg further noted, &quot;On a very, <lb/>very good day, maybe as much as 1% of what you draft will be considered carefully by anybody else&quot;. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Final version of this article is available at the Statute Law Review website: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/slr/hmz007 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>not -as in a different dispensation and under a different social order they might <lb/>be -the strong, natural defenders of liberty&quot;. 107 <lb/>Given recent changes in the UK, with an HRA and a relatively new Supreme Court, <lb/>whether Griffith&apos;s words hold up in relation to defending liberty is debatable. When it <lb/>comes to defending the &quot;constitutionality&quot; of legislation within the UK context, <lb/>however, the statement appears right on point. As Prof Zander noted in our interview, <lb/>&quot;We depend on all sorts of protections, all sorts of safeguards, pressures and <lb/>conventions&quot;, from the OPC to the judiciary, from the media to academia, &quot;[t]here are <lb/>many different ways of helping the constitution&quot;. 108 Indeed, the variety of constitutional <lb/>guardians in the UK is diverse, and that should be recognised, and celebrated. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>107 J.A.G. Griffith, The Politics of the Judiciary (5th ed)(London: Fontana Press, 1997) 342. <lb/>108 Interview with M. Zander (28 February 2018). </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>