<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Minimum Harmonisation after &lt;i&gt;Alemo-Herron&lt;/i&gt;: The Janus Face of EU Fundamental Rights Review</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Marija</forename>
          <surname>Bartl</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Candida</forename>
          <surname>Leone</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T07:12:57.273Z">30/01/2026 08:12:57</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1017__s1574019615000097</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Cambridge University Press (CUP)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2015</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1017/s1574019615000097</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Marija Bartl, Candida Leone. (2015). Minimum Harmonisation after &lt;i&gt;Alemo-Herron&lt;/i&gt;: The Janus Face of EU Fundamental Rights Review. European Constitutional Law Review, 11(1), 140-154. DOI: 10.1017/s1574019615000097</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-01-02T12:32:55.591850Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2026-01-02T12:32:55.591850Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-06T15:27:11.618Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Annotation completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T21:22:19.015Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith second pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T09:03:49.654Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-25T09:27:56.187Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T07:21:42.543Z" status="candidate" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<front>UvA-DARE is a service provided by the library of the University of Amsterdam (https://dare.uva.nl) <lb/>UvA-DARE (Digital Academic Repository) <lb/>Minimum harmonisation after Alemo-Herron: the Janus face of the EU <lb/>fundamental rights review <lb/>Bartl, M.; Leone, C. <lb/>DOI <lb/>10.1017/S1574019615000097 <lb/>Publication date <lb/>2015 <lb/>Document Version <lb/>Final published version <lb/>Published in <lb/>European Constitutional Law Review <lb/>Link to publication <lb/>Citation for published version (APA): <lb/>Bartl, M., &amp; Leone, C. (2015). Minimum harmonisation after Alemo-Herron: the Janus face of <lb/>the EU fundamental rights review. European Constitutional Law Review, 11(1), 140-154. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S1574019615000097 <lb/>General rights <lb/>It is not permitted to download or to forward/distribute the text or part of it without the consent of the author(s) <lb/>and/or copyright holder(s), other than for strictly personal, individual use, unless the work is under an open <lb/>content license (like Creative Commons). <lb/>Disclaimer/Complaints regulations <lb/>If you believe that digital publication of certain material infringes any of your rights or (privacy) interests, please <lb/>let the Library know, stating your reasons. In case of a legitimate complaint, the Library will make the material <lb/>inaccessible and/or remove it from the website. Please Ask the Library: https://uba.uva.nl/en/contact, or a letter <lb/>to: Library of the University of Amsterdam, Secretariat, Singel 425, 1012 WP Amsterdam, The Netherlands. You <lb/>will be contacted as soon as possible. <lb/>Download date:19 Dec 2025 <lb/>http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/>Minimum Harmonisation after Alemo-Herron: <lb/>The Janus Face of EU Fundamental Rights Review <lb/>European Court of Justice, Third Chamber <lb/>Judgment of 18 July 2013, Case C-426/11, Alemo-Herron v <lb/>Parkwood Leisure Ltd <lb/>Marija Bartl &amp; Candida Leone <lb/>While Alemo-Herron v Parkwood Leisure Ltd (case C-426/11) has received much <lb/>criticism in recent months, one fundamental constitutional question has passed by <lb/>unnoticed. In Alemo-Herron, the Court of Justice expanded the scope of EU <lb/>fundamental rights review in the field of minimum harmonisation to include, in <lb/>particular, member states action that goes beyond the EU minimum rules. This <lb/>expansion of EU fundamental rights review is bound to unsettle the division of <lb/>powers both horizontally (between the EU institutions) and vertically (between <lb/>the EU and the member states), and at the same time, perhaps counter-intuitively, <lb/>poses a significant danger for the level of social and environmental protection in <lb/>Europe. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The recent case law of the European Court of Justice (ECJ), including cases such as <lb/>Aziz 1 and Morcillo 2 , are often praised for their social and fundamental rights <lb/>&apos;minded&apos; interpretation of EU law. 3 This mood of optimism renders it all the more <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 ECJ 14 March 2013, Case C-415/11, Mohamed Aziz v Caixa d´Estalvis de Catalunya, <lb/>Tarragona i Manresa. <lb/>2 ECJ 27 July 2014, Case C-169/14, Sanchez Morcillo And Abril Garcia v Banco Bilbao Vizcaya <lb/>Argentaria SA. <lb/>3 C. Mak, &apos;On Beauty and Being Fair -The Interaction of National and Supranational <lb/>Judiciaries in the Development of a European Law on Remedies&apos;, in K. Purnhagen and P. Rott <lb/>(eds.), Varieties of European Economic Law and Regulation (Springer International Publishing 2014) <lb/>p. 823; G. Comparato and H.W. Micklitz, &apos;Regulated Autonomy between Market Freedoms and <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <front>140 <lb/>Case Note <lb/></front>
    
    <note place="footnote">European Constitutional Law Review, 11: 140-154, 2015 <lb/>© 2015 The Authors <lb/>doi:10.1017/S1574019615000097 <lb/></note>

	<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>

			<body>necessary to return to another judgment, Alemo-Herron, which suggests that, to <lb/>the contrary, fundamental rights review may lower the levels of social protection <lb/>in the EU. <lb/>We argue that to submit member states&apos; legislation that goes beyond the EU <lb/>minimum rules to the ECJ&apos;s fundamental rights review will have important <lb/>constitutional, institutional and social consequences. In this vein, given the <lb/>usually &apos;socially minded&apos; or protective logic underpinning the EU minimum <lb/>harmonisation legislation, which leaves an option to member states to offer a more <lb/>favourable protection regime to consumers, workers or the environment, we <lb/>contend that the challenge to these rules, and European interference, will <lb/>predictably come from one corner of the political spectrum. In particular, the <lb/>expansion of the fundamental rights review allows businesses to contest more <lb/>protective labour, consumer or environmental regulations of EU member states on <lb/>the grounds of EU fundamental rights (such as the freedom to conduct business), <lb/>granting the Court a power to lower the level of protection, if that happens to be -<lb/>as in Alemo-Herron -in line with its economic theory. <lb/>Alemo-Herron may also be seen as following a series of ECJ decisions on the <lb/>posting of workers, limiting the discretion of member states to go beyond the level <lb/>of protection established through minimum harmonisation. What is most <lb/>remarkable about Alemo-Herron, however, is that unlike in Laval and related cases, <lb/>the limitation of workers&apos; rights is not offered up on the altar of fundamental <lb/>freedoms but fundamental rights. Claiming to protect the &apos;core&apos; of the freedom to <lb/>conduct business, the Alemo Court 4 could enforce its own interpretation of proper <lb/>economic policies without the need to justify such deregulatory move either by <lb/>internal market exigencies or by an attempt to use established legal interpretation <lb/>instruments. <lb/>This contribution is structured as follows. First, we describe the facts and the <lb/>background of the ECJ&apos;s decision and then briefly discuss the teleological <lb/>interpretation of the Directive on the Transfer of Undertakings, and the new <lb/>purpose (&apos;fair balance&apos;) that the Court has read into this Directive. This discussion <lb/>prepares the ground for the main argument of this contribution, namely, the <lb/>ambivalent fate of minimum harmonisation after Alemo. The social and <lb/>redistributive implications of expanding the Charter&apos;s scope of review become <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Fundamental Rights in the Case Law of the CJEU&apos;, in U. Bernitz et al. (eds.), General Principles of <lb/>EU Law and European Private Law (Kluwer Law International 2013) p. 121. <lb/>4 We will often refer to &apos;the Alemo Court&apos;. While this practice might appear unusual, we aim by it <lb/>to underline, on the one hand, that we hope Alemo will stay a contingency in the ECJ&apos;s case law and <lb/>not become the Court&apos;s standard approach in similar matters; on the other hand, that there is <lb/>something odd to a decision of this importance being swiftly taken by a five-judge chamber, largely <lb/>relying on the (re)interpretation of a previous decision authored by the same rapporteur (see infra for <lb/>the discussion of this older decision). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>141 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Case note: Minimum Harmonisation after Alemo-Herron <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    
			<body>easily discernible once the right to be protected is the &apos;freedom to conduct <lb/>business&apos;. We conclude by asking for whose benefit is the expansion of <lb/>fundamental rights review in the field of minimum harmonisation. <lb/>Facts and background of the case <lb/>The Alemo judgment concerns the interpretation of Directive 2001/23/EC, aimed <lb/>at &apos;safeguarding of employees&apos; rights in the event of transfers of undertakings&apos;. 5 <lb/>The applicants, a Mr. Alemo-Herron and his colleagues, were employed by the <lb/>London Borough of Lewisham. Subsequently, the division in which they worked <lb/>was &apos;privatised&apos;, and their contracts transferred to Parkwood Leisure Ltd., a private <lb/>company (hereafter &apos;Parkwood&apos;). This direct transfer of employees&apos; contractual <lb/>rights and obligations to a new employer is secured under United Kingdom law by <lb/>the Transfer of Undertakings (Protection of Employment) Regulations 2006, <lb/>which implemented the relevant Directive. <lb/>The employment contracts entered into by the applicants contained a term <lb/>stating that, while the employees worked for the London Borough of Lewisham, <lb/>their terms and conditions of employment would be determined &apos;in accordance <lb/>with collective agreements negotiated from time to time by the [NCJ] …, <lb/>supplemented by agreements reached locally through [Lewisham]&apos;s negotiating <lb/>committees.&apos; 6 <lb/>Therefore, the relevant collectively agreed terms had been, prima facie, <lb/>incorporated in the contract, making those terms applicable to the individual <lb/>employment relationship. The body in charge of establishing such terms was the <lb/>National Joint Council (NJC), a negotiation body including representatives from <lb/>local public employers and trade unions. The transferee, a private company, was <lb/>not involved or represented in the negotiations that led to a series of salary <lb/>increases being agreed after Parkwood acquired the business. When Parkwood <lb/>decided not to follow the salary determinations of the NJC, the applicants <lb/>brought proceedings before the Employment Tribunal to have those pay increases <lb/>recognised. <lb/>To decide whether the pay increases negotiated by the NJC were to impact <lb/>the individual employment contracts, the question to be answered by the <lb/>Employment Tribunal was whether the relevant term should be interpreted as <lb/>incorporating into the contract of employment the collective agreement(s) in force <lb/>at the time the transferee acquired the business (the so-called &apos;static&apos; approach) or also <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>5 Council Directive 2001/23/EC of 12 March 2001 on the approximation of the laws of the <lb/>Member States relating to the safeguarding of employees&apos; rights in the event of transfers of <lb/>undertakings, businesses or parts of undertakings or businesses, OJ 2001 L82/16. <lb/>6 Cited from Alemo-Herron, para. 10. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>142 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Marija Bartl &amp; Candida Leone <lb/>EuConst 11 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>agreements which were concluded at a later point in time (the &apos;dynamic&apos; <lb/>approach). Under English law, earlier case law held that once collectively <lb/>bargained terms had been incorporated into an employment contract, they <lb/>became contract terms like any other, and thus were transferred with the contract <lb/>with no need for further adjustments. This interpretation, which incorporated <lb/>common law &apos;contractual orthodoxy&apos; 7 into the system established by the <lb/>Directive, can be labelled as a dynamic approach in that it considers the term <lb/>incorporating external rules to be capable of following a change in the latter rules. <lb/>The opposite or static approach links the term&apos;s effectiveness to the substantive <lb/>content to which it refers, making later alterations of that content incapable of <lb/>affecting the contract. <lb/>The reason why the ECJ was eventually involved in the case is that the effects of <lb/>a transfer of enterprise on existing employment contracts have been the object <lb/>of European harmonisation. The Acquired Rights Directive provided for the <lb/>automatic transfer of the employment contracts, in Article 3 paragraph 1, and the <lb/>limited 8 applicability of collective agreements, which were in force in the unit at <lb/>the time the transfer occurred in Article 3, paragraph 3. <lb/>In its previous Werhof decision, the Court of Justice had ruled that Article 3(1) <lb/>of the Directive <lb/>must be interpreted as not precluding, in a situation where the contract of <lb/>employment refers to a collective agreement binding the transferor, that the <lb/>transferee, who is not party to such an agreement, is not bound by collective <lb/>agreements subsequent to the one which was in force at the time of the transfer of <lb/>the business. 9 <lb/>The issue on which different national courts in the Alemo-Herron case had come to <lb/>disagree was, in essence, the meaning to be given to Werhof: did the fact that a <lb/>&apos;static&apos; approach was allowed merely imply its literal meaning, or should (in this <lb/>case) the courts read the judgment as actually imposing such an approach? <lb/>Prima facie, it might seem hard to justify such purported uncertainty <lb/>in interpretation. The wording of the Court&apos;s conclusion do not seem to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>7 C. Wynn-Evans, &apos;TUPE, Collective Agreements and the Static-Dynamic Debate&apos; [case note <lb/>on Alemo-Herron and Others v Parkwood Leisure Ltd [2010] IRLR 298, CA], 39 ILJ (2010) p. 275 at <lb/>p. 278. <lb/>8 Limited in time, since the concerned agreement remains applicable &apos;until it expires or is <lb/>replaced by a new agreement&apos;. The article also grants member states the option to limit in time this <lb/>&apos;extended applicability&apos; of collective agreements -an option which, in any case, the UK did not make <lb/>use of. <lb/>9 ECJ 9 March 2006, Case C-499/04, Hans Werhof v Freeway Traffic Systems GmbH &amp; Co. KG, <lb/>para. 37, emphasis added. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>143 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Case note: Minimum Harmonisation after Alemo-Herron <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>impose anything. However, the reasoning in the case in question provided a <lb/>possible counter-argument to an otherwise clear interpretation, ventilating the <lb/>possibility that a dynamic interpretation might affect the employer&apos;s negative <lb/>freedom of association. In particular, the Court in Werhof had stated that <lb/>(imposing) a dynamic approach &apos;would mean that future collective agreements <lb/>apply to a transferee who is not party to a collective agreement and that his <lb/>fundamental right not to join an association could be affected&apos;. 10 <lb/>The Court&apos;s reasoning had indeed clouded the compatibility of the &apos;dynamic&apos; <lb/>clauses with EU law, read in light of EU fundamental rights. This is probably the <lb/>reason why the English Court of Appeal had decided to overrule the applicable <lb/>precedent to comply with EU law. The UK Supreme Court was not, however, <lb/>convinced of Werhof&apos;s relevance to the case at hand, since the reference to negative <lb/>freedom of association did not seem to play a role in Alemo. 11 The Supreme Court <lb/>thus asked whether in light of Werhof, the Directive required, allowed or <lb/>prohibited such dynamic clauses. <lb/>At the level of textual interpretation of the Directive, the questions the UK <lb/>Supreme Court posed called for a simple response. The objective of Directive <lb/>2001/23 was &apos;to provide for the protection of employees in the event of a change <lb/>of employer&apos; (recital 7) by setting minimum level of protection, while allowing <lb/>&apos;Member States to apply or introduce laws, regulations or administrative <lb/>provisions which are more favourable to employees&apos; (Article 8). The &apos;dynamic <lb/>interpretation&apos;, according to the ECJ, is an unambiguous instance of such <lb/>heightened employee protection. 12 This response, one may argue, is further <lb/>legitimised by the fact that the Union&apos;s legislature has confirmed the minimum <lb/>harmonisation character of the Directive twice already -in the original Directive <lb/>and in its recodification. <lb/>Yet, the Court of Justice demurred and declared the dynamic clause <lb/>incompatible with Directive 2001/23. Such a conclusion is justified by means of <lb/>two different routes. First, within EU secondary law, the Court reinterpreted the <lb/>telos of the Directive to claim the Directive&apos;s objective is to &apos;ensure a fair balance&apos; <lb/>between competing interests. This balance would be jeopardised if dynamic <lb/>clauses were allowed. Second, the Court considered primary law and concluded <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>10 Werhof, para. 31. <lb/>11 It &apos;had been of relevance [in Werhof] because of the way German employment law deals with <lb/>collective agreements. It was not a concern in this case, because the matter depended entirely on the <lb/>domestic law of contract&apos;, see Parkwood Leisure Ltd v Alemo-Herron and others [2011] UKSC 26, <lb/>para. 47. The UK Supreme Court had already considered that the solution to the case was <lb/>unambiguous, in light of the fact that the precedents on which it was based &apos;amount to no more than <lb/>a conventional application of ordinary principles of contract law to the statutory consequences <lb/>apparently created by regulation 5 of TUPE&apos;. <lb/>12 Alemo-Herron, para. 24. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>144 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Marija Bartl &amp; Candida Leone <lb/>EuConst 11 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>that EU fundamental rights and freedom of contract, in particular, also preclude a <lb/>dynamic interpretation. <lb/>Interpreting the Directive on its own terms: Whose &apos;fair balance&apos;? <lb/>Before we turn to discuss the fate of minimum harmonisation, we will briefly <lb/>examine the Court&apos;s first argument, which allegedly militated against the dynamic <lb/>interpretation. As noted by several observers, 13 the Court of Justice has interpreted <lb/>the purpose of the Directive as establishing a &apos;fair balance&apos; between the rights of <lb/>employers and employees. <lb/>Directive 77/187 [now Directive 2001/23] does not aim solely to safeguard the <lb/>interests of employees in the event of transfer of an undertaking, but seeks to ensure a <lb/>fair balance between the interests of those employees, on the one hand, and those of <lb/>the transferee, on the other. 14 <lb/>Yet the Directive itself, it has been remarked, 15 at no point mentions such a &apos;fair <lb/>balance&apos;. The whole Directive may indeed be seen as the outcome of balancing by <lb/>the legislature. Against the background of an economic reality increasingly <lb/>characterised by mergers and acquisitions, privatisations, out-sourcing and other <lb/>forms of changes in ownership of enterprises, the Directive has established a <lb/>minimum protection for the employees affected. Furthermore, the fact that the <lb/>Directive itself sets a time limit to the applicability of previously agreed collective <lb/>agreements and allows member states to further limit in time such applicability <lb/>(Article 3.3) suggests that employers&apos; interests have also been taken into account. <lb/>The minimum harmonisation clause is also part of the &apos;balancing act&apos; that was <lb/>performed throughout the Directive. <lb/>While finding little support for the new reading of the purpose of the Directive <lb/>(&apos;fair balance&apos;) in the text itself, the Court places great stress on its decision in <lb/>Werhof. Yet at the same time, the Alemo court &apos;adjusts&apos; the Werhof judgment in a <lb/>fundamental manner. In particular, while the Werhof court 16 claims that the <lb/>interests of the transferee &apos;should not be disregarded&apos;, in Alemo these interests must <lb/>be positively protected: [T]he transferee must be in a position to make the adjustments <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 S. Weatherhill, &apos;Use and Abuse of the EU&apos;s Charter of Fundamental Rights: On the Improper <lb/>Veneration of &apos;Freedom of Contract&apos;&apos;, 10 European Review of Contract Law (2014) p. 167; J. Prassl, <lb/>&apos;Freedom of Contract as a General Principle of EU Law? Transfers of Undertakings and the <lb/>Protection of Employer Rights in EU Labour Law Case C-426/11 Alemo-Herron and Others v <lb/>Parkwood Leisure Ltd&apos;, 42 ILJ (2013) p. 434. <lb/>14 Alemo-Herron, para. 25, emphasis added. <lb/>15 For criticism: see Prassl, supra n. 14, and, more generally, Weatherhill, supra n. 14. <lb/>16 At the hand, as was mentioned supra, n. 4, of the same judge rapporteur. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>145 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Case note: Minimum Harmonisation after Alemo-Herron <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>and changes necessary to carry on its operations. 17 These adjustments seem also to <lb/>have a particular content in this specific context: <lb/>Since the transfer is of an undertaking from the public sector to the private sector, the <lb/>continuation of the transferee&apos;s operations will require significant adjustments and <lb/>changes, given the inevitable differences in working conditions that exist between those <lb/>two sectors. 18 <lb/>Therefore, the Alemo Court seems unsatisfied with the &apos;fairness of the balance&apos; set by <lb/>the Directive in its potentially high level of employee protection in the process of <lb/>privatisation. Thus, insofar as they have not explicitly prohibited member states <lb/>imposing the old (public-sector) working conditions on the new (private) employer, <lb/>the drafters of the Directive seem to have failed to understand the &apos;inevitable&apos; <lb/>differences in the operation of public as opposed to private enterprises, which seem <lb/>to automatically require the worsening of the position of employees. This line of <lb/>reasoning of the Court is, incidentally, entirely at odds with its previous case law on <lb/>the Directive on Transfer of Rights, where the ECJ had insisted that the transfer of <lb/>an undertaking is not per se a reason for the change of employment conditions. 19 <lb/>EU fundamental rights as a challenge to minimum harmonisation <lb/>Alemo-Herron has highlighted a fundamental constitutional question, which has <lb/>received scant attention in the debate thus far. Namely, does (and should) the <lb/>action of EU member states that goes beyond the EU minimum rules fall within <lb/>the scope of EU law in the meaning of the Charter and is it thus subject to EU <lb/>fundamental rights review? <lb/>The question of the scope of application of the EU Charter of Fundamental Rights <lb/>is set to play a pivotal role in the European legal discourse in the years to come. EU <lb/>fundamental rights have a specific character. Unlike the Treaty&apos;s four fundamental <lb/>freedoms, whose violation brings a question automatically into the scope of EU law, <lb/>EU fundamental rights -at least in principle -do not have such an effect. Not every <lb/>alleged threat to fundamental rights is of concern to European Union 20 -instead, <lb/>the operation of EU Charter is limited to a certain internal space already covered <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>17 Alemo Herron, para. 25, emphasis added. <lb/>18 Alemo Herron, para. 27, emphasis added. <lb/>19 ECJ 10 February 1988, Case 324/86, Foreningen af Arbejdsledere i Danmark v Daddy&apos;s Dance <lb/>Hall paras. 15 and 17; ECJ 6 November 2003, Case C-4/01, Martin and others v South Bank <lb/>University, para. 40. <lb/>20 Needless to say, we need not mourn the fate of fundamental rights protection in such a case. <lb/>Such protection obviously takes place also outside the &apos;scope&apos; of EU law; it will just be other (national <lb/>and international) institutions to engage in their interpretation and enforcement. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>146 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Marija Bartl &amp; Candida Leone <lb/>EuConst 11 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>by EU law. 21 As Rosas has convincingly put it, in contrast to EU fundamental <lb/>freedoms, EU fundamental rights are meant to apply only when other EU law <lb/>provisions are applicable to the situation. 22 <lb/>The status of minimum harmonisation remains unclear in this regard. <lb/>Minimum harmonisation can be found in several EU fields of law and policy <lb/>such as consumer protection, environmental protection or social protection. 23 <lb/>It has been considered as a preferred regulatory solution to the extent that, as a less <lb/>intrusive intervention into national legal orders, it gives the best expression to the <lb/>principles of subsidiarity and proportionality of EU action. At the same time, <lb/>member states were never free to violate the Treaty freedoms when going beyond <lb/>EU minimum rules. As Craig has succinctly argued, EU minimum harmonisation <lb/>sets the floor, while the Treaty sets the ceiling within which the EU member states <lb/>are free to pursue their own policies. 24 <lb/>The ECJ case law is ambiguous. On the one hand, in one of the few cases in <lb/>which the ECJ addresses the issue squarely, 25 the Court was reluctant to apply the <lb/>principle of proportionality to the more protective measures of the member state <lb/>going beyond the EU minimum, suggesting that this domain falls outside of the <lb/>scope of EU law. 26 On the other hand, in Karner 27 the Court appears to espouse <lb/>the contrary view. In particular, in response to the argument of one of the parties, <lb/>the ECJ discussed the compatibility of a national measure going beyond the EU <lb/>minimum rules with fundamental rights after finding that the measure did not <lb/>violate the fundamental freedoms, which suggests that such measure falls within <lb/>the scope of EU law in the sense of Article 51 of the Charter. While only ancillary <lb/>to the main argument, and applying a very undemanding level of scrutiny, this <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>21 See also ECJ 7 May 2013, Case C-617/10, Åklagaren v Hans Åkerberg Fransson, para. 29. <lb/>22 A. Rosas, &apos;When is the EU Charter of Fundamental Rights Applicable at National Level?&apos;, 19 <lb/>Jurisprudence (2012) p. 1269, &lt;repository.mruni.eu/bitstream/handle/007/10752/101-209-1-SM. <lb/>pdf?sequence=3&gt;, visited 13 January 2015. <lb/>23 J.H. Jans, &apos;Minimum Harmonisation and the Role of the Principle of Proportionality&apos;, in <lb/>M. Führ et al. (eds.), Umweltrecht und Umweltwissenschaft: Festschrift für Eckard Rehbinder (Erich <lb/>Schmidt Verlag 2007) p. 705, &lt;www.user.uni-bremen.de/∼avosetta/janjansarticle1.pdf&gt;, visited <lb/>13 January 2015. <lb/>24 P.P. Craig and G. de Búrca, EU Law: Text, Cases, and Materials (Oxford University Press 2008) <lb/>p. 626. <lb/>25 ECJ 14 April 2005, Case C-6/03, Deponiezweckverband Eiterköpfe v Land Rheinland-Pfalz. <lb/>26 ECJ 14 April 2005, Case C-6/03, Deponiezweckverband Eiterköpfe v Land Rheinland-Pfalz, <lb/>para. 64: &apos;Deponiezweckverband the Community-law principle of proportionality is not applicable so <lb/>far as concerns more stringent protective measures of domestic law adopted by virtue of Article 176 <lb/>EC and going beyond the minimum requirements laid down by a Community directive in the <lb/>sphere of the environment, inasmuch as other provisions of the Treaty are not involved&apos;. <lb/>27 ECJ 25 March 2004, Case C-71/02, Herbert Karner Industrie-Auktionen GmbH v Troostwijk <lb/>GmbH. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>147 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Case note: Minimum Harmonisation after Alemo-Herron <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>

	

			<body>step of the Court has raised the question whether the Court has abandoned its <lb/>previous case law, which sees such measures as falling outside the scope of EU <lb/>law. 28 In Werhof the Court also relied on an argument derived from EU <lb/>fundamental rights. In particular, the Court suggested that requiring the dynamic <lb/>interpretation of the clause may interfere with the freedom of association of a <lb/>trader. This conclusion, however, concerned the review of the European <lb/>&apos;minimum&apos; rule rather than the national &apos;maximum&apos; rule. <lb/>In Alemo-Herron, the Court of Justice does not consider these issues and goes <lb/>directly to review the member state measure on the basis of EU fundamental <lb/>rights. Advocate General Cruz Villalón is, however, somewhat more revealing in <lb/>his reasoning: <lb/>[A]s we know, even where European Union law expressly gives Member States freedom <lb/>of action, this must be exercised in accordance with that law. This obligation naturally <lb/>includes, inter alia, fundamental rights, as expressly provided in Article 51 of the Charter. <lb/>Accordingly, although the United Kingdom may permit the parties[ 29 ] to include <lb/>dynamic clauses referring to collective agreements in their contracts of employment, this <lb/>must not result in conduct contrary to the fundamental rights referred to in the Charter, <lb/>including the freedom to conduct a business mentioned in Article 16. 30 <lb/>It is not self-evident from the Advocate General&apos;s opinion how Article 51 of the <lb/>Charter should &apos;naturally&apos; grant the review of the measures that go beyond <lb/>minimum harmonisation. The Advocate General does not state why a member <lb/>state&apos;s action should fall within the scope of EU law, and indeed it is not obvious <lb/>that this is the case. In the context of measures going beyond the requirements of <lb/>minimum harmonisation the member states do not seem to act as agents of the EU <lb/>in the sense of the Wachauf 31 line of case law: EU law does not require them to act <lb/>at all, nor to act in a specific way. If member states decide to take action, they can <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>28 J. Stuyck, &apos;Case C-71/02, Herbert Karner Industrie-Auktionen GmbH v. Troostwijk GmbH, <lb/>Judgment of the Fifth Chamber of 25 March 2004&apos;, 41 CMLRev (2004) p. 1683; A. Egger, <lb/>&apos;EU-Fundamental Rights in the National Legal Order: The Obligations of Member States <lb/>Revisited&apos;, 25 YEL (2006) p. 513 at p. 515. <lb/>29 Almost incidentally, the Advocate General seized an important point: are member states (not) <lb/>allowed to permit the parties to include dynamic clauses? Does EU freedom of contract require, in <lb/>this case, setting aside the contractual principle of pacta sunt servanda? <lb/>30 Alemo-Herron, Opinion AG Cruz Villalón, para. 47. <lb/>31 ECJ 13 July 1989, Case C-5/88, Hubert Wachauf v Bundesamt für Ernährung und <lb/>Forstwirtschaft. Catherine Barnard, notices how, with reference to the fundamental principles of <lb/>EU law, the case law in turn addressed cases in which the states were implementing EU law <lb/>(Wachauf), derogating from it (ERT) or, more recently, acting within its scope (Annibaldi). What this <lb/>scope is supposed to encompass, however, is precisely the question which appears most relevant here. <lb/>See C. Barnard, EU Employment Law (Oxford University Press 2012) p. 31. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>148 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Marija Bartl &amp; Candida Leone <lb/>EuConst 11 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>do so in the manner that they deem suitable, provided that it does not infringe on <lb/>the EU minimum level of protection or violate the Treaty, i.e. free movement <lb/>provisions. The action of the member states also does not &apos;derogate&apos; from EU law, <lb/>as would be required by the ERT 32 line of cases. On the contrary, national <lb/>measures seem to enrich the original pursuit of EU legislation. 33 <lb/>While the Advocate General fails to provide satisfactory reasons why UK law should <lb/>be submitted to Charter review, the Court does not engage in any justification as to <lb/>why the more protective national measure falls in the scope of EU law -with reference <lb/>to its previous case law or otherwise. The silence of the Court on this constitutional <lb/>question amounts to an attempt to assume a significant power &apos;by stealth&apos;. 34 <lb/>The freedom to contract and the assault on social regulation <lb/>Structurally, the expansion of the scope of EU fundamental rights review to the more <lb/>social regulation enabled by EU minimum harmonisation renders such protective <lb/>measures vulnerable to the Court&apos;s review on the basis of more economically liberal <lb/>fundamental rights. While the challenge to these protective rules will presumably <lb/>come from the side of business, the fundamental right to freedom to conduct <lb/>business -including the freedom of contract -is one of the most likely candidates to <lb/>be invoked and eventually found in need of a (European) safeguard. <lb/>The first two questions that we need to address are whether there is anything <lb/>that makes the application of the freedom to conduct business, and freedom of <lb/>contract in particular, extraordinary in this context. And why, if at all, should we <lb/>be concerned by the resuscitation of this &apos;human right&apos; by the Court of Justice? To <lb/>begin with freedom of contract (and freedom to conduct business) is missing from <lb/>many international human rights instruments -one might add, for good reasons. <lb/>More contingent than its companion -the right to property -freedom of contract <lb/>is tightly linked to the interpretation of the scope of the market in a particular <lb/>community. Its content follows narrowly the community&apos;s understanding of the <lb/>relation between market and society. The dependence of this right on the social, <lb/>political and economic framework in a particular community is so comprehensive, <lb/>that it seems difficult to make a claim that there is any real &apos;essence&apos; to this right -<lb/>beyond, indeed, the requirement that there is a market economy. 35 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>32 ECJ 18 June 1991 Case C-260/89, Elliniki Radiophonia Tileorassi AE (ERT) v. Dimotiki <lb/>Etairia Pliroforissis and Siotirios Kouvelas. <lb/>33 See for instance P.P. Craig and G. de Búrca, supra n. 25, or Egger, supra n. 29. <lb/>34 For a compelling analysis see G. Majone, Dilemmas of European Integration: The Ambiguities and <lb/>Pitfalls of Integration by Stealth (Oxford University Press 2009). <lb/>35 R.L. Hale, &apos;Coercion and Distribution in a Supposedly Non-Coercive State&apos;, 38 Political <lb/>Science Quarterly (1923) p. 470; K. Polanyi, The Great Transformation: The Political and Economic <lb/>Origins of Our Time, 2nd ed. (Beacon Press 2002). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>149 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Case note: Minimum Harmonisation after Alemo-Herron <lb/></note>

			<note place="foornote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>The conceptual emptiness of the freedom to contract (and the freedom to <lb/>conduct business for that matter) is also reflected both in the lack of &apos;a satisfactory <lb/>definition&apos; at the EU level, as the Advocate General notes in his opinion on the <lb/>Alemo-Herron case, as well as in the very broad interference allowed by the very <lb/>case law of the Court of Justice of the EU. 36 Historically, then, freedom of <lb/>contract has been used to argue for a specific kind of market: the &apos;Lochner era&apos; of <lb/>the US Supreme Court is perhaps the most famous example thereof. 37 <lb/>When it comes to its place in the European legal order, strictly speaking, <lb/>freedom of contract is also not among the rights that the Nice Charter protects as <lb/>&apos;fundamental&apos; in Europe, but the Court (and the Commission) considers it to be <lb/>encompassed by the freedom to conduct business. 38 Importantly, even if the <lb/>freedom to conduct business can be found in Title II of the Charter, thus among <lb/>the &apos;hard core&apos; rights, both the wording of the right (&apos;the freedom to conduct <lb/>business […] is recognised&apos;) and the Court&apos;s previous case law suggest that this is a <lb/>&apos;weak&apos; right. 39 The freedom to conduct business has been introduced as a <lb/>&apos;counterweight&apos; to the social rights contained in the Charter&apos;s Chapter IV and the <lb/>Court has recognised its principle-like character, including the openness to large <lb/>interventions in public interest. 40 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>36 P. Oliver, &apos;What Purpose Does Article 16 of the Charter Serve?&apos;, in U. Bernitz et al., General <lb/>Principles of EU Law and European Private Law (Kluwer Law International 2013) p. 281. <lb/>37 H. Gillman, The Constitution Besieged: The Rise and Demise of Lochner Era Police Powers <lb/>Jurisprudence (Duke University Press 1993). <lb/>38 The guidelines can be found online &lt;eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ: <lb/>C:2007:303:0017:0035:en:PDF&gt;, visited 13 January 2015. In particular, freedom of contract is <lb/>said to be based on, inter alia, ECJ 28 June 1978, Case C-151/78 Sukkerfabriken Nykøbing Limiteret <lb/>v Ministry of Agriculture, and ECJ 5 October 1999, Case C-240/97, Spain v Commission. Both cases <lb/>indeed recognised the existence of freedom of contract as something that, broadly speaking, is not to <lb/>be restricted without an appropriate procedure and legal basis, without saying much as to its nature <lb/>or as to what it entails. In addition, Weatherill in his comment argues that the cases fail to tell much <lb/>about the status of freedom to contract in EU law. More generally, Prassl, supra n. 14, p. 442, notes <lb/>how &apos;even proponents of the recognitions and strengthening of freedom of contract as a general <lb/>principle of Union law have noted that the notion does not currently form part of the EU legal <lb/>order&apos;. <lb/>39 X. Groussot et al., &apos;Weak Right, Strong Court -The Freedom to Conduct Business and <lb/>the EU Charter of Fundamental Rights&apos;, Lund University Legal Research Paper Series No 01/2014, <lb/>&lt;papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2428181&gt;, visited 14 January 2015; P. Oliver, <lb/>supra n. 36. <lb/>40 See ECJ 22 January 2013, Case C-283/11, C-283/11, Sky Österreich GmbH v Österreichischer <lb/>Rundfunk, para. 47: &apos;On the basis of [the Court&apos;s] case law and in the light of the wording of Article <lb/>16 of the Charter, which differs from the wording of the other fundamental freedoms laid down in <lb/>Title II thereof, yet is similar to that of certain provisions of Title IV of the Charter, the freedom to <lb/>conduct a business may be subject to a broad range of interventions on the part of public authorities which <lb/>may limit the exercise of economic activity in the public interest&apos;, emphasis added. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>150 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Marija Bartl &amp; Candida Leone <lb/>EuConst 11 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>

	

			<body>In this context Alemo-Herron becomes a game-changing decision for two main <lb/>reasons. First, as noted above, the judgment clearly (though surreptitiously) <lb/>establishes the Court&apos;s power to review on the basis of EU fundamental rights <lb/>more protective measures that go beyond the EU minimum rules. Second, the <lb/>decision demonstrates the kind of dangers that such protective measures face in <lb/>this newly established domain of ECJ&apos;s adjudication. In particular, as the challenge <lb/>to these protective measures is likely to come from more liberal corners, these <lb/>measures become vulnerable to an ideological stance of which the Court&apos;s <lb/>veneration 41 of freedom of contract might be a telling example. It is not <lb/>insignificant to note that the UK&apos;s (mainly) Conservative government has argued <lb/>for the very same result finally reached by the ECJ. 42 <lb/>The technique the Court has used to reach the desired decision has been to <lb/>expand the understanding of what constitutes the &apos;essence&apos; of the freedom of <lb/>contract. In particular, in an important previous decision, Sky Österreich, to which <lb/>the Alemo Court reaches for its justification, the ECJ has considered the &apos;core <lb/>content&apos; of the freedom to conduct business to be violated if and only if something <lb/>&apos;prevents business activity from being carried out as such&apos;. 43 In Alemo-Herron, <lb/>however, that condition seems to be sufficiently fulfilled given the fact that <lb/>Parkwood was denied the legal capacity to make such &apos;adjustment and changes&apos; 44 <lb/>required in the context of privatisation, &apos;given the inevitable differences in working <lb/>conditions that exist between those two sectors.&apos; 45 According to the Court, <lb/>Parkwood could &apos;neither assert its interests effectively in a contractual process&apos; nor <lb/>&apos;negotiate the aspects determining changes in working conditions for its <lb/>employees with a view to its future economic activity&apos;. 46 <lb/>This reasoning of the Court is difficult to sustain on both substantive (private <lb/>law) and procedural (interpretation technique) grounds. Substantively, the <lb/>Court&apos;s reasoning assumes that the National Joint Council was the only context <lb/>in which negotiation could take place. This was, however, hardly the case. First, <lb/>had the dynamic clause been upheld, Parkwood could have re-negotiated 47 its <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>41 Weatherhill, supra n. 14. <lb/>42 Governments&apos; submissions to the ECJ are not publicly available. The fact is mentioned by <lb/>Prassl, supra n. 14, p. 437, who derives it from &lt;blog.rubensteinpublishing.com/dynamic-<lb/>interpretation-of-tupe-precluded/&gt;, visited 13 January 2015. <lb/>43 Sky Österreich, supra n. 40, para. 47. <lb/>44 Alemo-Herron, para. 25. <lb/>45 Alemo-Herron, para. 27. <lb/>46 Alemo-Herron, para. 34. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">47 It might be useful to recall, at this point, that under UK law collective agreements are only <lb/>binding between two parties if and insofar as they have been incorporated in the individual contract <lb/>of which, then, they become a part just as any other set of terms. This implies that the parties are in <lb/>principle free to re-negotiate them at any point in time. <lb/></note>
    
    <page>151 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Case note: Minimum Harmonisation after Alemo-Herron <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>

	

			<body>contractual obligations with its contractual counterparts -the employees. 48 Even <lb/>if the Directive on the Transfer of Undertakings, and the Court&apos;s case law on this <lb/>Directive, restricts the rights of the transferee to change the terms of the <lb/>employment contracts during the transfer, this constraint is surely not unlimited <lb/>in time. 49 Thus, viewed in this light, the struggle underlying the dispute over the <lb/>&apos;dynamic clause&apos; was not whether Parkwood could negotiate the employment <lb/>conditions of its workers, 50 but rather, the question who -Parkwood or its new <lb/>employees -should be in a superior bargaining position after the transfer. Second, <lb/>Parkwood could have used its contractual autonomy when acquiring the <lb/>undertaking, to make sure that the burden it was assuming was duly considered <lb/>in the transfer price of the undertaking itself. 51 That was indeed a major occasion <lb/>for the deployment of freedom of contract in relation to a more equal counter-<lb/>party. 52 <lb/>In terms of legal interpretation, invoking the violation of the &apos;core&apos; of freedom <lb/>of contract 53 has unbound the last constraints on the Court&apos;s reasoning. As we <lb/>have discussed above, on the one hand, the teleological interpretation of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">48 Such a scenario, by the way, would also have given Parkwood&apos;s employees a better chance to <lb/>exercise their freedom of contract in a meaningful way. As an aside, it should be mentioned that the <lb/>company would not have been required to re-negotiate the whole collective agreement, but merely <lb/>the pay increase. <lb/></note>
    
    <listBibl>49 Martin and others, supra n. 20, paras. 42-43. <lb/>50 This reasoning is not affected by the ECJ&apos;s precedents restricting the possibility to agree <lb/>contractual amendments justified by the fact itself of the transfer, such as Daddy&apos;s Dance Hall, supra n. 20, <lb/>D&apos;Urso (ECJ 25 July 1991, C-362/89, Giuseppe d&apos;Urso, Adriana Ventadori a.o. v Ercole Marelli <lb/>Elettromeccanica Generale SpA a.o.), Rask (ECJ 12 November 1992 , C-209/91, Anne Watson Rask and <lb/>Kirsten Christensen v Iss Kantineservice A/S) and Martin, supra, n. 20. The meaning of these decisions <lb/>cannot be possibly stretched to imply that the parties would at this point be able to re-negotiate their <lb/>contracts. The Court&apos;s precedents should rather be understood as aiming to avoid the circumvention of <lb/>the Directive&apos;s by way of contractual arrangements. As highlighted by its Art. 3, the Directive&apos;s effects -<lb/>including those derived from its interpretation -are not meant to last eternally. If the arguments <lb/>brought forward in those cases have any bearing in this context, this should rather work against the <lb/>Court&apos;s assumption that transfers automatically require adapting the applicable working conditions. <lb/>This assumption is not compatible with the courts previous assertion that a transfer alone should not be <lb/>a sufficient ground for changing the terms of employment. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">51 The proceedings offer no evidence as to whether this has (not) happened in practice. <lb/>52 Incidentally, adopting reasoning which is frequently heard from heralds of laissez-faire in the <lb/>domain of consumer contracts, the take-it-or-leave-it nature of a deal is not in itself a reason to <lb/>consider it as less than favourable to the party accepting it. <lb/>53 Violation perpetrated -as ironic as this may sound -through the application of contract law <lb/>orthodoxy and the principle of pacta sunt servanda. However, according to the same principle all the <lb/>other terms in the transferred contract remain applicable. It seems appropriate, therefore, to ask how <lb/>the line is drawn between terms whose preservation jeopardises the &apos;core&apos; of contractual freedom and <lb/>terms which can be safely transferred. This is just another question that the Court leaves <lb/>unaddressed. <lb/></note>
    
    <page>152 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Marija Bartl &amp; Candida Leone <lb/>EuConst 11 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>Directive has been &apos;taken care of&apos; by the reinterpretation of the telos of the <lb/>Directive, which ceased to be the protection of workers (as the text of the Directive <lb/>would suggest), and turned out to be that of pursuing a &apos;fair balance&apos; between <lb/>interests of employers and the employees as understood by the Court. The <lb/>reference to a violation of the &apos;core&apos; of freedom to contract, on the other hand, has <lb/>allowed the Court to avoid the application of &apos;standard&apos; legal tools of <lb/>interpretation of fundamental rights, such as proportionality or balancing the <lb/>rights. Once the &apos;core&apos; of a fundamental right is in danger, the limitations of <lb/>the right stemming from its &apos;social function&apos;, or the margin of appreciation of the <lb/>legislature to regulate it, cease to play a role. <lb/>However, if a particular fundamental right has so little intrinsic essence as the <lb/>freedom of contract does, the mobilisation of constitutional authority of the Court <lb/>seems to be instrumental to pursuing a purely political -or redistributive -aim. <lb/>In other words, given the dependence of the freedom of contract on our <lb/>understanding of what constitutes the &apos;right kind&apos; of market, the reliance on this <lb/>freedom allows the Alemo Court to reshape the (internal) market and newly <lb/>apportion the benefits thereof, on the basis of its own economic and political <lb/>theory. 54 <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>After Alemo-Herron, one has to ask what remains of minimum harmonisation. <lb/>If the ECJ establishes its right to review the member states&apos; action that goes <lb/>beyond the EU minimum rules, this will not only upset the division of powers <lb/>between the EU institutions and between the EU and the member states but also, <lb/>potentially, lead to a lowering of social standards in Europe. <lb/>First, in purely formal terms, the extension of the Charter&apos;s scope to the member <lb/>states&apos; measures that go beyond minimum harmonisation is far from obvious or (as <lb/>the Advocate General suggests) &apos;natural&apos;, since the member states measures that go <lb/>beyond the EU minimum rules do not unambiguously fall into the &apos;scope&apos; of the <lb/>Charter. The member states hardly act as the agents of the EU, and they certainly are <lb/>not derogating from EU law. The case law of the ECJ on this issue is at best <lb/>ambiguous. While the Court has explicitly refused to apply the proportionality <lb/>principle to this area (Deponiezweckverband), it has at other places implicitly <lb/>included these actions in the scope of EU law and &apos;by the way&apos; uttered statements <lb/>supporting its conclusions reached on other grounds (Karner). The result reached in <lb/>Alemo, thus, would have required a completely different level of argumentation. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>54 And as Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr. remarked in his dissenting opinion in Lochner v. New York, <lb/>198 U.S. 45 (1905): &apos;[t]he Fourteenth Amendment does not enact Mr. Herbert Spencer&apos;s Social <lb/>Statics&apos;. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>153 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Case note: Minimum Harmonisation after Alemo-Herron <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">http://journals.cambridge.org <lb/>Downloaded: 03 Sep 2015 <lb/>IP address: 145.18.109.239 <lb/></note>
    
    

			<body>Second, while the expansion of the fundamental rights review institutionally <lb/>empowers the ECJ, it both undermines the capacity of the EU legislature to use <lb/>one subsidiarity-friendly legal technique and submits the EU member states action <lb/>in this area to the ECJ&apos;s discipline. If relying on freedom of contract, this discipline <lb/>will be that of the Court&apos;s preferred economic theory, possibly changing the <lb/>character of the politico-economic compromise reached by the Union&apos;s and <lb/>member state legislatures. <lb/>The final question that we need to ask is: to whose benefit is all this? First of all, <lb/>the more protective national rules will be challenged foremost by those who lose <lb/>from higher protection -i.e. businesses the main agents of EU integration through <lb/>law. 55 Secondly, the readiness of the ECJ to interfere may result from its <lb/>integrationist agenda, 56 when each national measure struck down means also <lb/>a new European fully harmonised rule. Thirdly, the fact that the ECJ is a <lb/>supranational institution of a still predominantly economic entity, strongly <lb/>invested into opening markets, may influence the Court&apos;s ideology -especially if <lb/>that would coincide with the Court&apos;s integrationist objectives. Thus, let us once <lb/>more reiterate the question -if minimum harmonisation is usually about giving <lb/>more protection to workers, consumers or the environment, what will be the <lb/>consequences of the Court tacitly assuming the power to review these political <lb/>choices -in light of what appear to be largely discretionary political standards? <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>55 N. Fligstein and A. Stone Sweet, &apos;Constructing Polities and Markets: An Institutionalist <lb/>Account of European Integration,&apos; 107 American Journal of Sociology (2002) p. 1206. <lb/>56 E. Stein, &apos;Lawyers, Judges, and the Making of a Transnational Constitution&apos;, 75 American <lb/>Journal of International Law (1981) p. 1; A Stone Sweet, The Judicial Construction of Europe (Oxford <lb/>University Press 2004); H. Unberath and A. Johnston, &apos;The Double-Headed Approach of the ECJ <lb/>Concerning Consumer Protection&apos;, 44 CMLRev (2007) p. 1237; A. Vauchez, &apos;Keeping the Dream <lb/>Alive: The European Court of Justice and the Transnational Fabric of Integrationist Jurisprudence, 4 <lb/>European Political Science Review (2012) p. 51. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <page>154 <lb/></page>
    
    <note place="headnote">Marija Bartl &amp; Candida Leone <lb/>EuConst 11 (2015)<lb/></note>


	</text>

</TEI>