<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">China under Western Aggression: Discourse Transformations, Identity Shifts, and National Reconstruction</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Rong</forename>
          <surname>Ma</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-22T21:44:54.399Z">22/12/2025 21:44:54</date>
        <title>Review Luca</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1163__23521341-12340137</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2022</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1163/23521341-12340137</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Rong Ma. (2022). China under Western Aggression: Discourse Transformations, Identity Shifts, and National Reconstruction. Journal of Chinese Humanities, 8(3), 279-302. DOI: 10.1163/23521341-12340137</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-28T13:29:01.232627Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-28T13:29:01.232627Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-06T10:45:17.536Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Version_1</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-11T11:09:26.534Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Final_Final_Version</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-22T15:30:09.625Z" status="checked" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Review Kazuyo</desc>
    </change>	  
    <change when="2025-12-22T21:44:54.399Z" status="approved" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Review Luca</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>© Ma Rong, 2022 | doi:10.1163/23521341-12340137 <lb/>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC BY 4.0 license. <lb/>Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/>brill.com/joch<lb/>China under Western Aggression: Discourse <lb/>Transformations, Identity Shifts, and National <lb/>Reconstruction <lb/>Ma Rong 馬戎 <lb/>Professor of Department of Sociology, Peking University, Beijing, China <lb/>marong@pku.edu.cn <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Following the Opium Wars, traditional notions of China as encompassing &quot;all under <lb/>heaven&quot; (tianxia 天下) and the &quot;Sino-barbarian dichotomy&quot; (huayi 華夷) could <lb/>no longer be sustained. Under the pressure and intimidation of the Great Powers&apos; <lb/>advanced warships and fire power, the Qing government signed the unequal treaties <lb/>and China was forced to adopt Western conceptual reasoning, discursive language, <lb/>and rules of conduct. Western knowledge and lexicon was successively translated into <lb/>Chinese, affecting transformations in local discourse and society. As part of this pro-<lb/>cess, Japanese texts, which contained a great volume of Chinese characters, became <lb/>an important medium for the transmission of Western epistemology. During the first <lb/>Opium War between China and England, the cultural and political hegemony of the <lb/>Great Powers were demonstrated through debates over interpretations of the Chinese <lb/>character yi 夷. During the Late Qing, Chinese intellectuals drew on their foundations <lb/>in traditional Chinese lexicon to understand and adopt the foreign-derived words <lb/>zhongzu 種族 (race) and minzu 民族 (nation). This process reflects both shifts in how <lb/>Chinese people regarded collective identity and the various presumptions underlying <lb/>state-building visions. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>translating discourse -race -nation -collective identity -state-building <lb/></front>
		  
		  <body>Arnold J. Toynbee counts thirty-four civilizations among the many rich, <lb/>resplendent, and long-standing civilizations that have existed from ancient <lb/></body>

			<page>280 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  <body>times to the present.1 Those which have made it into popular discourse include <lb/>the ancient civilizations of Babylon, Egypt, Greece, and Rome; Christian civi-<lb/>lization, Arab civilization, Indian/Hindu civilization, the Sinitic civilization <lb/>of the East Asian mainland, and so forth. Some of these ancient civilizations <lb/>perished amidst competition and confrontation and others were fortunate <lb/>enough to survive. In any case, the survivors underwent massive transforma-<lb/>tions in both form and content, adapting to the ever-changing world order and <lb/>developments abetted by inter-cultural exchanges. The organizing principles <lb/>of political power and society within them were also reformed, sometimes <lb/>even to the point of becoming unrecognizable to their forbears. <lb/>Spurred on by the Renaissance, Reformation, and Enlightenment, the <lb/>Christian states of Western Europe were the first to undergo the transition <lb/>from feudal societies to modern nation-states. Anthony Smith&apos;s idea of a &quot;civic <lb/>model of the nation&quot; came, in fact, from the 17th-to 18th-century Western <lb/>European notion of a &quot;national polity&quot; characterized by a political identity <lb/>founded on civil liberties and a representative government, and boundaries <lb/>defined by shared culture and land.2 The nationalist movements which sub-<lb/>scribed to this pushed to establish new identity formations and bodies of <lb/>national governance. Taking the Peace of Westphalia (1648) as a signal, they <lb/>reshaped the nature of the European nation, rewriting the international order. <lb/>The political transformation undergone by each spurred on transformation <lb/>of their economy. New manufacturing processes were established and pro-<lb/>duction limits removed, leading to rapid developments in Western European <lb/>industry and technology. In the meantime, the social structures, ideology, and <lb/>cultural discourse in European countries were reshaped and updated. Thus, <lb/>one after another, they entered the new age of industrial civilization. <lb/>As European powers strengthened and prospered, they began to set their <lb/>sights on the rest of the world. Faced with their aggression, the fate of native <lb/>sovereignty in the countries of Asia, Africa, and Latin America took each down <lb/>different historical paths. The Ottoman Empire was dissolved. The Mayan and <lb/>Incan civilizations met with destruction and annihilation.3 European colonies <lb/>spread across the globe, bringing about irrevocable changes to the political <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>1 Lu Fanzhi 魯凡之, Zhongguo fazhan yu wenhua jiegou 中國發展與文化結構 (Hong Kong: <lb/>Jixian she, 1998), 26. <lb/>2 The four signs of a &quot;Civil ethnic polity&quot; include: 1. territory forged by historical circumstance; <lb/>2. a unified legal and governmental body; 3. legal and political legal rights; 4. shared culture <lb/>and awareness. See Anthony D. Smith, National Identity (Reno: University of Nevada Press, <lb/>1991), 11. <lb/>3 &quot;… twelve major civilizations, seven of which no longer exist (Mesopotamian, Egyptian, <lb/>Cretan, Classical, Byzantine, Middle American, Andean) and five which do (Chinese, Japanese, <lb/></listBibl>


			<page>281 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
	 <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  <body>and cultural map of the world. In East Asia, neither the Qing government nor <lb/>Japan could avoid the impact of the powerful, expanding colonial domain <lb/>of the west. <lb/>

		 <lb/>Modern China Forced to Adopt Western Conceptual Reasoning, <lb/>Discursive Language, and Rules of Conduct <lb/>

			Out of lands and environments vastly different from those of distant China, <lb/>the European countries developed distinct cultural traditions and political sys-<lb/>tems. From this, arose two contrasting centers of civilization: the Mediterranean <lb/>and East Asia.4 Cultural exchange between China and Europe can be traced <lb/>back to Catholic missionary activities. In 1583, Jesuit missionaries from the <lb/>Vatican such as Matteo Ricci (1552-1610) entered China via Macau. Ricci col-<lb/>laborated with Xu Guangqi 徐光啟 (1562-1633) to translate key texts in science <lb/>and technology such as Euclid&apos;s Jihe yuanben 幾何原本, Celiang fayi 測量法 <lb/>義, and Tongwen suanzhi 同文算指.5 Such translations constituted the first <lb/>systematic introduction of Western astronomy, mathematics, geography, and <lb/>medicine to the Chinese people. From the late Ming (1368-1644) to the late <lb/>Qing (1644-1911), foreign missionaries who lectured on Western civilization <lb/>would translate certain Western terms into Chinese as part of their talks. This <lb/>spurred on both translation activities in China and cultural exchange between <lb/>China and the West. However, the introduction of China to Western political <lb/>thought, social theory, and constitutional law would not occur until around <lb/>1840, the time of the first Opium War. <lb/>Beginning with the first Opium War (1839-1842), the Qing government suf-<lb/>fered defeat after defeat in wars against foreign nations, ceding territory and <lb/>paying indemnities. In its dealings with Western countries, China steadily <lb/>lost the power to self-determine and was forced, instead, to accept Western <lb/>conceptual reasoning, discursive language, and rules of conduct. Facing the <lb/>imminent threat of annihilation, the Chinese people had no choice but to <lb/>abandon traditional notions of China as &quot;all under heaven&quot; (tianxia 天下) as <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Indian, Islamic, and Western).&quot; See Samuel P. Huntington, The Clash of Civilizations and the <lb/>Remaking of World Order (New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1996), 45. <lb/>4 Zhan Zhonghe 湛中和, &quot;Dizhonghai wenhuaquan yu xifang wenming dutexing de genyuan&quot; <lb/>地中海文化圈與西方文明獨特性的根源, Hunan shifan daxue shehui kexue xuebao 湖南 <lb/>師範大學社會科學學報, no. 4 (2010): 128-31. <lb/>5 Xiao Zhiqin 肖志欽 and Xiao Jian&apos;an 肖建安, &quot;Limadou jiqi dui Zhongguo fanyi shi de <lb/>gongxian&quot; 利瑪竇及其對中國翻譯史的貢獻, Loudi shizhuan xuebao 婁底師專學報, <lb/>no. 4 (2003): 33-35. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>282 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			  <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>			
	  <body>well as the ethnic order based on a distinction between the central hua 華 and <lb/>frontier yi 夷 peoples. Instead, they began to adopt European worldviews <lb/>and principles of international relations. <lb/>On the surface, the Great Powers extolled notions of &quot;equality&quot; and &quot;inter-<lb/>national law;&quot; however, following the First Opium War and Second Opium <lb/>War (1856-1860), the conditions under which the Qing government signed the <lb/>peace treaty were completely devoid of &quot;equality&quot; or &quot;parity.&quot; When it came <lb/>to foreign relations with China, the Great Powers consistently interfered in <lb/>affairs concerning China&apos;s frontier regions and affairs between local groups. <lb/>Examples of this include Tsarist Russia recognizing the legitimacy of Yaqub <lb/>Beg&apos;s (1820-1877) rule in Kashgar, Xinjiang in 1872, and Britain forcibly open-<lb/>ing the commercial port of Yadong 亞東, Tibet in 1888. Thus, the Great Powers <lb/>used diplomatic pressure and military threats, and even occasional military <lb/>intervention,6 to undermine the authority of the Chinese central government, <lb/>replacing it, instead, with Western interpretations and language.7 They sought <lb/>to alter the legal statuses of these regions under international law in order <lb/>to stake a claim in Chinese frontier regions as either their colonies or their <lb/>protectorates. <lb/>At the same time, diplomatic envoys, merchants, missionaries, and geogra-<lb/>phers from the Great Powers paid visits to every part of the Chinese frontier <lb/>regions, building churches, organizing socials, opening schools, starting news-<lb/>papers, and even developing writing systems for the oral languages of certain <lb/>ethnic groups.8 These visitors worked to infiltrate every level of frontier society, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>6 It would seem that, after unsuccessful attempts at opening trade routes with Tibet, British <lb/>troops -invaded Tibet in 1903, occupying Lhasa and finally, in 1906, forcing the Qing gov-<lb/>ernment to sign the &quot;Sino-British Convention on British and Tibetan Relations.&quot; See Zhang <lb/>Zhirong 張植榮, Guoji guanxi yu Xizang wenti 國際關係與西藏問題 (Beijing: Lüyou jiaoyu <lb/>chubanshe, 1994), 42-44. <lb/>7 Western ideas of &quot;sovereignty (zhuquan 主權)&quot; and &quot;suzerainty (zongzhuquan 宗主權)&quot; and <lb/>the distinctions between them do not exist in Sinitic traditions. At the Simla Conference <lb/>of 1913, England suggested dividing Tibet into &quot;inner Tibet&quot; (to include Qinghai the Kham <lb/>region) and &quot;outer Tibet&quot; (consisting of Ü-Tsang), with the central Chinese government hold-<lb/>ing suzerainty, but not sovereignty, over the latter. See Zhang Zhirong, Guoji guanxi yu Xizang <lb/>wenti, 62. <lb/>8 From the end of the 19th century to the 1930s, missionaries active in Yunnan, Guizhou, <lb/>and Sichuan provinces preached to ethnic minorities. Around that time, they devised and <lb/>published on several ethnic minority orthographies. The British Methodist missionary Sam <lb/>Pollard devised Old Miao script. The British James O. Fraser of the Inner China Mission <lb/>developed Old Lisu script with Sara Ba Thaw, a preacher of the Karen peoples of Myanmar. <lb/>Missionaries of the American Baptist Mission Society such as Josiah Nelson Cushing and <lb/>O. Hanson devised Singpho writing. Vincent M. Young of the American Baptist Convention <lb/>developed both the Lahu and Wa scripts. Australian missionary Gladstone Porteous devised <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>283 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			  <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>

			<body>meddling in local affairs and inciting inter-ethnic conflict. Western powers <lb/>sought to promote an image of the Qing dynasty as a country of multiple <lb/>nations existing side-by-side. Starting with such labels as &quot;Tibetan nation&quot; <lb/>and &quot;Mongol nation,&quot; Western languages introduced discourses of &quot;nation,&quot; <lb/>&quot;national self-determination,&quot; and &quot;national identification&quot; to the elites of <lb/>the many peoples -namely, the Manchu, Han, Mongol, Hui, and Tibetan -<lb/>in China.9 Slowly but surely, from the concepts and meanings behind these <lb/>new Western-derived labels, would emerge new forms of political and cul-<lb/>tural identity. <lb/>The actions of Western imperialist powers inevitably impacted inter-group <lb/>relations and affected discursive shifts in the various jurisdictions of the Qing <lb/>government. The elites of the various Chinese ethnic groups began to use <lb/>Western discourse to describe not only the world outside of China, but also <lb/>recent Chinese political history as well as shifts within and between Chinese <lb/>ethnic groups across the dynasties. This was the start of a comprehensive dis-<lb/>cursive shift within Chinese society. <lb/>As China endured its passive and humiliating role in foreign diplomatic <lb/>negotiations, its political system based on traditional notions of ruling &quot;all <lb/>under heaven&quot; and identifying according to the so-called &quot;Sino-barbarian dis-<lb/>tinction&quot; (yixia zhibian 夷夏之辨) was replaced by one based on the forcibly <lb/>imported idea of a &quot;nation-state.&quot;10 Chinese people had much to reconsider: <lb/>how to refer to those strange ocean-crossing peoples; how to refer to the sur-<lb/>rounding tributary states of the Qing empire; how to refer, collectively, to the <lb/>subjects of the Qing dynasty; how to refer to those groups governed by <lb/>the Qing government, but with their own administrative bodies as well as eth-<lb/>nic origins, languages, religions, and ways of life that were wholly distinct; and, <lb/>finally, how to maintain or rebuild the political entity known as China?11 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Yi script. See Chen Jianming 陳建明, &quot;Chuanjiaoshi zai xinan shaoshu minzu diqu <lb/>de wenzi chuangzhi huodong&quot; 傳教士在西南少數民族地區的文字創制活動. <lb/>Zongjiaoxue yanjiu 宗教學研究, no. 4 (2010): 142-49. <lb/>9 &quot;Even the terms &apos;Manchu&apos; and &apos;Han&apos; referring to ethnicities is very modern …… it wasn&apos;t <lb/>until the post-1900 hostility broke out between loyalists and revolutionaries that the <lb/>Manchu-Han conflict came to a head. However, the concept of &apos;Han ethnicity&apos; was also <lb/>being re-invented.&quot; See Sun Longji 孫隆基, Lishixue jia de jingxian 歷史學家的經線 <lb/>(Guilin: Guangxi shifan daxue chubanshe, 2004), 17. <lb/>10 &quot;Imperial China … at the end of the Qing dynasty was forced into the straightjacket of a <lb/>&apos;nation-state.&apos;&quot; Sun Longji, Lishixue jia de jingxian, 21. <lb/>11 The Qing government pursued a &quot;diverse empire&quot; where each district administered itself <lb/>via the principle of &quot;governing according to customary practice&quot; (yin su er zhi 因俗而治). <lb/>See Wang Ke 王柯, Zhongguo, cong &quot;tianxia&quot; dao minzu guojia 中國，從 &quot;天下&quot; 到民族 <lb/>國家 (Taipei: Zhengda chubanshe, 2014), 101. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>284 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
	  <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  <body>To begin with, the Qing government officials used terms associated with <lb/>frontier peoples, such as manyi 蠻夷 (barbarians), to refer to Europeans. The <lb/>British, for instance, were called &quot;red haired barbarians&quot; (hongmao yi 紅毛夷 <lb/>or hongmao fan 紅毛番). However, as European nations exerted their power <lb/>in China, &quot;foreign barbarians&quot; (waiyi 外夷) became the neutral &quot;countries&quot; <lb/>(bangguo 邦國). According to Sinitic tradition, diplomatic envoys from for-<lb/>eign countries were usually called &quot;tributary envoys&quot; (gongshi 貢使). However, <lb/>in the case of Europe, that, too, changed to simply &quot;envoy&quot; (gongshi 公使). <lb/>European envoys were permitted to reside in the capital. Instead of adhering <lb/>to the traditional ritual of kowtowing in audience with the emperor, the envoys <lb/>were, at their request, required only to bow respectfully.12 The &quot;tribute address&quot; <lb/>(gongbiao 貢表) which foreign envoys at court had previously had to present <lb/>upon arriving at court was renamed &quot;official document&quot; (guoshu 國書). The <lb/>word for agreements signed with foreign nations changed from mengshu 盟書 <lb/>(alliance pacts) to tiaoyue 條約 (treaties). These gradual shifts in terminology <lb/>signaled a thorough collapse of the traditional Chinese imperial order. <lb/>At the time, Chinese people who remained clear-headed observed that the <lb/>Qing government was losing its authority over frontier lands and peoples to <lb/>Western colonization. They saw how the existing social order and cultural <lb/>logic was being thoroughly overturned, and how the Great Powers would cause <lb/>rifts between different groups within a nation in order to conquer and enslave <lb/>them.13 Those in the know considered how to &quot;defend the race and nation,&quot; <lb/>how, against the tides of discursive shifts, to form their own interpretations of <lb/>the new lexicon.14 Only by doing so could they reestablish a coherent identity <lb/>among China&apos;s people and keep the fragmentation and violence of in-fighting <lb/>from breaking out across China&apos;s vast territory. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>12 Mao Haijian 茅海建, Jindai de chidu: liangci Yapian Zhanzheng junshi yu waijiao 近代的 <lb/>尺度：兩次鴉片戰爭軍事與外交 (Bejiing: Shenghuo dushu xinzhi sanlian shudian, <lb/>2011), 250. <lb/>13 &quot;The British conquest of India was an act of urging Indian people to kill Indian people.&quot; <lb/>See Yang Du 楊度, &quot;&apos;Youxue yibian&apos; xu&quot; &quot;遊學譯編&quot; 敘, in Xinhai geming qianshinian jian <lb/>shi lun xuan ji 辛亥革命前十年間時論選集, ed. Zhang Nan 張柟 and Wang Renzhi <lb/>王忍之 (Beijing: Shenghuo dushu xinzhi sanlian shudian, 1960), 1: 251. <lb/>14 Datongbao 大同報, a newspaper created by Chinese and Manchu bannermen studying <lb/>in Japan, strongly promoted &quot;Equality between Manchu and Han people and unity of <lb/>Manchu, Han, Mongol, Hui, and Tibetan people as citizens of one great nation.&quot; See Huang <lb/>Xingtao 黃興濤, Chongsu Zhonghua: jindai Zhongguo &quot;Zhonghua minzu&quot; guannian <lb/>yanjiu 重塑中華：近代中國 &quot;中華民族&quot; 觀念研究 (Hong Kong: Sanlian shudian, <lb/>2017), 101-2. <lb/></listBibl>

	<page>285 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
	<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>

	<body>2 Translating Terms between Western Languages and Chinese during <lb/>the 19th Century <lb/>Western discourses and concepts that were brought into China by the Great <lb/>Powers in the mid-nineteenth century had only recently emerged and become <lb/>popular in Europe. The seventeenth century Enlightenment advanced innova-<lb/>tion in philosophy, ethics, political science, economics, history, literature, and <lb/>the natural sciences. The subsequent wave of new concepts and related terms <lb/>that were born from new political beliefs, social movements, and develop-<lb/>ments in technology transformed existing words and phrases in the languages <lb/>of European countries. <lb/>The word &quot;nation&quot; serves as an apt example. It stems from the Latin word <lb/>&quot;natio,&quot; which has multiple meanings. According to the earliest and most <lb/>widespread understanding, it &quot;referred to a group of people who share a place <lb/>of birth and are placed in the same category that is larger than a family but <lb/>smaller than a clan; also, a people.&quot;15 French encyclopedists Denis Diderot <lb/>(1713-1784) and Jean le Rond d&apos; Alembert (1717-1783) reframed &quot;nation&quot; as <lb/>&quot;a collective word used to denote a considerable quantity of those people <lb/>who inhabit a certain extend of country defined within certain limits, and <lb/>obeying the same government.&quot;16 The Declaration of the Rights of Man and of <lb/>Citizens of the French Revolution elevated the idea of &quot;nation&quot; to include ideas <lb/>of sovereignty, stating that &quot;the principle of sovereignty resides essentially in <lb/>the nation.&quot; The British historian Eric Hobsbawm (d. 2012) writes that &quot;the <lb/>modern sense of the word is no older than the eighteenth century (…).&quot;17 Elie <lb/>Kedourie (d. 1992) writes on the &quot;doctrine&quot; of European nationalism at that <lb/>time: &quot;(…) that humanity is naturally divided into nations, that nations are <lb/>known by certain characteristics which can be ascertained, and that the only <lb/>legitimate type of government is national self-government.&quot;18 Thus, the central <lb/>position of modern European nationalism is that every nation has the right to <lb/>establish its own government. <lb/>The process by which Western concepts were transmitted to China was any-<lb/>thing but direct. At first, Chinese people attempted to use existing Chinese <lb/>words and phrases to translate Western words. Such words and phrases were <lb/></body>


			<listBibl>15 Elie Kedourie, Nationalism (New York: F.A. Praeger, 1960.), 12-13. For further discussion <lb/>on the evolution of the term &quot;nation,&quot; see Liah Greenfeld, Nationalism: Five Roads to <lb/>Modernity (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1993), 4-8. <lb/>16 Kedourie, Nationalism, 14. <lb/>17 Eric J. Hobsbawm, Nations and Nationalism since 1780: Programme, Myth, Reality (Cambridge: <lb/>Cambridge University Press, 1990), 3. <lb/>18 Kedourie, Nationalism, 9. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>286 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note><note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  <body>inevitably informed by traditional Chinese worldviews and rational concepts <lb/>that differed greatly from that of the Western concepts they were meant to rep-<lb/>resent. Therefore, Chinese scholars who first attempted to translate Western <lb/>texts into Chinese could only do so by either using barely passable Chinese <lb/>terms or coining new terms. In Lin Zexu&apos;s 林則徐 (1785-1850) Sizhou zhi <lb/>四洲志, a late 1830s Chinese translation of a work on world geography, the <lb/>term for government officials from England (which is rendered yinjili guo <lb/>英吉利國) is translated using the traditional Chinese term for officials, zhi <lb/>guan 職官.19 Similarly, the government and its departments are translated as <lb/>yamen 衙門, their navy translated as shuishi 水師, banks translated as yinhao <lb/>銀號, and expenditures translated as suiyong 歲用. The titles of government <lb/>officials were rendered phonetically with annotations in Chinese. For instance, <lb/>Lin translated the title of government official into lübulai afuxi&apos;er 律布來阿付 <lb/>西爾 with guanyin guan 管印官 (official in charge of seals) as an annotation.20 <lb/>Another example of this is Yan Fu&apos;s 嚴復 (1853-1921) translation of &quot;empire&quot; as <lb/>yinbai&apos;er 英拜兒.21 <lb/>In the latter half of the nineteenth century, it was very difficult to translate <lb/>Western concepts and discourses using the Chinese that was available. When <lb/>translating Thomas Henry Huxley&apos;s (1825-1895) Evolution and Ethics and Other <lb/>Essays, Yan Fu once mentioned the difficulty of adhering to the three prin-<lb/>ciples of translation: reliability (xin 信), accuracy (da 達), and style (ya 雅). <lb/>It is already difficult to remain true to the ideological content of the <lb/>source text; however, if one were to produce an indecipherable text based <lb/>on a correct understanding of the source text, there would be no point in <lb/>the translation. Thus, it is very important to take care with expression…. <lb/>(The translator must) gain masterful understanding of the substance of <lb/>the entire text; only then can the translation gain a natural smoothness. <lb/>If the writing and content of the source text is abstract and difficult to <lb/>understand, then one must do the work of laying the foundation and <lb/>finding the correct resonances in the sections of the translated text that <lb/>both precede and follow. In this way, one can better express its intended <lb/>meaning. These methods are all meant to enhance the expressive power <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>19 The original text renders Yinjili guo with the characters 英咭唎国, showing that the <lb/>transliteration of names of countries continued to undergo revision and reconsideration. <lb/>See Zheng Zhenduo 鄭振鐸, Wan Qing wenxuan 晚清文選 (Beijing: Zhongguo shehu-<lb/>ixue chubanshe, 2002), 4. <lb/>20 Lin Zexu 林則徐, Sizhou zhi 四洲志 (Beijing: Huaxia chubanshe, 2002), 114-17. <lb/>21 <lb/>Lydia H. Liu, Translingual Practice: Literature, National Culture, and Translated Modernity -<lb/>China, 1900-1937 (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1995), 360. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>287 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note><note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>

			<body>of the translated text. Only by achieving a smooth translation can one <lb/>remain true to the source text.22 <lb/>This passage highlights the difference between Chinese and Christian cultures <lb/>while also reflecting how difficult it was for Chinese people to understand <lb/>Western texts and to select the right words and phrases to convey them. Yan <lb/>Fu, the pioneer of translating Western texts into Chinese, met with multiple <lb/>hardships when using old Chinese words to translate the new foreign phrases. <lb/>One can see many examples in works of translation by Chinese translators <lb/>that illustrate Yan&apos;s emphasis on &quot;choosing the word that best fits the mean-<lb/>ing&quot; (ji yi ding ming 即義定名). When translating Western names, place names, <lb/>names of countries, occupations, and ranks of nobility, one must feel one&apos;s <lb/>way through the process, testing and adjusting along the way. Fu Lei 傅雷 <lb/>(1908-1966) translated the title of Honoré de Balzac&apos;s (1799-1850) Le Cousin <lb/>Pons as Bangsi jiujiu 邦斯舅舅 (Uncle Pons), while Mu Mutian 穆木天 (1900-<lb/>1971) translated it as Congxiong pengsi 從兄蓬斯 (Cousin Pons). To convey <lb/>the five hereditary title ranks of the European nobility, Chinese translators <lb/>used the Zhou dynasty&apos;s (1050-221 BCE) five feudal ranks: gong 公, hou 侯, bo <lb/>伯, zi 子, and nan 男.23 Lin&apos;s Sizhou zhi, based on Hugh Murray&apos;s (1779-1846) <lb/>Encyclopaedia of Geography, transliterates the names of countries in ways that <lb/>differ from how they are translated today. For example, Egypt is rendered Yiji <lb/>依揖 instead of Aiji 埃及, and Persia Bashe 巴社 rather than Bosi 波斯. Chapters <lb/>seven and twenty-seven of Sizhou zhi are both called &quot;Duluji guo 都魯機國 (the <lb/>Turkish country),&quot; though they refer separately to the European and Asian <lb/>parts of the Turkish Ottoman Empire.24 Because Chinese knowledge of world <lb/>geography was very limited at the time, Sizhou zhi was a work of translation <lb/>that described the world to Chinese people and broadened their political and <lb/>geographical knowledge. At the same time, this work also contains vestiges of <lb/>the bewilderment faced and explorations pursued by Chinese translators as <lb/>they sought to grasp the concepts and discourses of Western epistemologies. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>22 Yan Fu 嚴復, Tianyan lun 天演論 (Beijing: Huaxia chubanshe, 2002), 10. <lb/></listBibl>
				
		<note place="footnote">23 In 1884, Japan put into practice a new peerage system and granted old high-ranking <lb/>imperial officials, those with an established reputation, and those who had contributed <lb/>notably to the Meiji reformation the rankings of gong, hou, bo, zi, and nan. It is unclear <lb/>whether European aristocrats were first referred to using the same ranks in Chinese trans-<lb/>lated texts or if this translation practice was borrowed from Japanese translators who had <lb/>borrowed the ancient Chinese feudal ranks for both European and Japanese nobles. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>24 Lin Zexu, Sizhou zhi, 114-17. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>288 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>

<body>3 Japanese Terms as a Key Medium through Which Western <lb/>Discourse Was Introduced into China <lb/>Japan&apos;s translations played a unique role in facilitating the translation and <lb/>acceptance of Western knowledge in China. During the Meiji Reformation, <lb/>Japanese scholars systematically translated Western knowledge into Japanese, <lb/>which effectively pushed forward modern developments in Japan&apos;s educa-<lb/>tional and industrial sectors. After the Qing government&apos;s loss in the First <lb/>Sino-Japanese War, many members of the Chinese elite sought to learn from <lb/>Japan&apos;s experience of &quot;reformation&quot; and &quot;leaving Asia to join Europe&quot; as a way <lb/>to save China. Those studying abroad in Japan eagerly studied and consumed <lb/>Western ideas through Japanese publications. Thus, Japanese became an <lb/>established means for introducing Western knowledge into China. From the <lb/>late nineteenth to early twentieth centuries, China set off on a course of book <lb/>translation. Liang Qichao 梁启超 (1873-1929) said that &quot;translating books is <lb/>truly a most pressing matter of today. Every day, those in China who understand <lb/>the times talk constantly of reformation…. if we do not engage in the transla-<lb/>tion of foreign writings with haste, then reformation will become nothing but <lb/>empty talk.&quot;25 In 1905, the Qing government established a Western-style pri-<lb/>mary school where the history textbook was actually translated from Japanese <lb/>educational materials.26 The first Chinese version of The Communist Manifesto <lb/>was also a 1919 translation from Japanese.27 <lb/>In &quot;Gezai Zhong-Xi zhijian de Riben -xiandai hanyu zhong de riyu &apos;wai <lb/>lai yu&apos; wenti&quot; 隔在中西之間的日本 -現代漢語中的日語 &quot;外來語&quot; 問題, pub-<lb/>lished in the eighth issue of Shanghai wenxue 上海文學 in 1998, Wang Binbin <lb/>王彬彬 indicates that &quot;of the specialized terminology we currently use in the <lb/>humanities and social sciences, about 70% comes from Japan.&quot;28 In another <lb/>recent article, &quot;Hunshen fama: bu jiang &apos;Riben hanyu&apos; jiu buneng shuohua&quot; <lb/>渾身發麻: 不講 &quot;日本漢語&quot; 就不能說話, Pei Yu 裴鈺 states, &quot;During the Late <lb/>Qing and Early Republican era, Chinese intellectuals also translated many terms <lb/></body>
			<listBibl>25 Liang Qichao 梁啟超, &quot;Chunqiu Zhongguo yidi bian xu&quot; 春秋中國夷狄辨序, in Yin <lb/>bingshi heji: Wenji 飲冰室合集：文集 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 1989), 2: 57. <lb/>26 Gu Jiegang 顧颉剛, &quot;&apos;Zhongguo benbu&apos; yi ming jiying feiqi&quot; &quot;中國本部&quot;一名極應廢 <lb/>棄, Yishibao 益世報, January 1, 1939. <lb/>27 At the end of 1919, Chen Wangdao 陳望道 translated the Japanese version of The <lb/>Communist Manifesto into Chinese. Chen Duxiu 陳獨秀 and Li Dazhao 李大釗 proof-<lb/>read it. It was published in August of 1920 by the Shanghai Socialist Research Publishing <lb/>Company. <lb/>28 Wang Binbin 王彬彬, &quot;Gezai Zhong-Xi zhijian de Riben -xiandai hanyu zhong de riyu <lb/>&apos;wai lai yu&apos; wenti&quot; 隔在中西之間的日本 -現代漢語中的日語&quot;外來語&quot;問題, <lb/>Shanghai wenxue 上海文學, no. 8 (1998): 71-80. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>289 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  
<body>of the modern Western humanities and natural sciences. What is surprising, <lb/>however, is that, pitted against the Chinese characters Japanese translators had <lb/>used in their terms, the ones that Chinese scholars came up with always lost.&quot;29 <lb/>One can observe this where the terms Chinese scholars came up with in trans-<lb/>lations of Sizhou zhi and other texts around the time were quickly overtaken <lb/>by those used in Japanese translated texts. For &quot;sociology,&quot; Yan Fu had come up <lb/>with &quot;qunxue 群學;&quot; however, the Chinese characters from the Japanese term, <lb/>&quot;shehui xue 社會學,&quot; came to be commonly used. Other such instances include <lb/>the term for economics, rendered zisheng xue 資生學 by Chinese scholars and <lb/>jingji xue 經濟學 by Japanese scholars, and philosophy, rendered zhixue 智学 <lb/>by Chinese translators and zhexue 哲学 by Japanese translators.30 <lb/>Indeed, Japanese texts and terminology played an influential role in the <lb/>establishment of modern thought in Chinese society. Following the First <lb/>Sino-Japanese War (1894-1895), Chinese scholars were in agreement about <lb/>looking to Japanese texts to learn about Western civilization. In 1897, Liang <lb/>Qichao and others pooled the capital to start the Datong Translation Bureau <lb/>(Datong yishu ju 大同譯書局). Their translated texts would &quot;focus on Japanese, <lb/>with some attention to Western languages, and prioritize political studies, fol-<lb/>lowed by the arts … in order to save China from impending crisis.&quot;31 In 1900, <lb/>the late Qing scholar Gu Mingfeng 顧鳴鳳 declared that China should look to <lb/>Japan as a model for self-strengthening because of the difficulty of learning <lb/>Western languages. &quot;From the time of the (Meiji) Reformation,&quot; he wrote, &quot;all <lb/>manner of useful texts on Western politics and art had already been translated <lb/>into Japanese…. Since China and Japan share one writing system, learning <lb/>Japanese should take half the effort it would for a Chinese person to learn <lb/>Western languages and character systems.&quot;32 <lb/>At the time Western knowledge and discourse was being translated into <lb/>Chinese via their Japanese versions, educational reform and the vernacular <lb/>movement in China were also underway. In the case of educational reform, <lb/>China was &quot;retiring the imperial examination system to uplift new learning.&quot; <lb/>The change brought about by Western political, social, and cultural ideas com-<lb/>pletely shook the foundations of traditional Chinese epistemology and political <lb/>discourse. The resulting impact this had on Chinese writing style, grammar, <lb/>punctuation, and conceptual language was historically monumental. <lb/></body>
	  
			<listBibl>29 Pei Yu 裴鈺, &quot;Hunshen fama: bu jiang &apos;Riben hanyu&apos; jiu buneng shuohua&quot; 渾身發麻： 不講 <lb/>&quot;日本漢語&quot;就不能說話, Lianhe zaobao 聯合早報, Feb. 9, 2009. <lb/>30 iang Qichao, &quot;Lun xue Ribenwen zhi yi&quot; 論學日本文之益, in Yinbingshi heji, 4: 80. <lb/>31 Liang Qichao, &quot;Chunqiu Zhongguo yidi bian xu,&quot; 2: 58. <lb/>32 Ge Zhaoguang 葛兆光, Zhai zi Zhongguo: Chongjian youguan &quot;Zhongguo&quot; de lishi lunshu <lb/>宅兹中國：重建有關&quot;中國&quot;的歷史論述 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 2011), 186. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>290 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  
<body>4 Confrontation and War Due to Differing Interpretations of the <lb/>Character Yi 夷 <lb/>Within the traditional worldview of China as the center of &quot;all under heaven,&quot; <lb/>the yixia 夷夏 distinction was an important concept that differentiated Chinese <lb/>peoples from the central plains from those on the frontiers. However, the <lb/>terms Chinese people used to refer to Westerners changed greatly through-<lb/>out the course of their interactions. In Lin Zexu&apos;s 1838 &quot;Chouyi yanjin yapian <lb/>zhangcheng zhe&quot; 籌議嚴禁鴉片章程折, he referred to European countries as <lb/>&quot;foreign countries&quot; (waiyang 外洋). Just one year later, in his &quot;Yu geguo yiren <lb/>chengjiao yantu gao&quot; 諭各國夷人呈繳煙土稿, he referred to them as yi. In the <lb/>Sizhou zhi, which Lin took charge compiling from 1839 to 1840, the British are <lb/>referred to as man 蠻.33 Wei Yuan 魏源 (1794-1857) referred to European coun-<lb/>tries as &quot;Western yi&quot; (xiyi 西夷) in his 1842 Haiguo tuzhi xu 海國圖志敘, but <lb/>added that one should not take the traditional attitude of superiority towards <lb/>these particular yi. From this, it is apparent that yi was commonly used at the <lb/>time with regard to Westerners. By 1858, yi was no longer used to refer to <lb/>the British. However, then provincial administrator of Jiangsu Deng Huaxi <lb/>鄧華熙 (1826-1916) still used &quot;foreign yi&quot; (waiyi 外夷) in reference to the Great <lb/>Powers in an edict to the Guangxu Emperor (r. 1875-1908). <lb/>It is precisely because of the gulf between cultural norms and language <lb/>usage, as well as the resulting mistranslations of words and concepts, that <lb/>serious diplomatic conflicts, even some leading directly to war, have arisen <lb/>between China and the West. In August 1834, the English-language newspaper <lb/>Chinese Repository published a translated order from Lu Kun 盧坤 (1772-1835), <lb/>the governor-general of Guangxi and Guangdong, to the Hong merchants in <lb/>which the term yimu 夷目 (foreign leader) was translated as &quot;barbarian eye,&quot; <lb/>causing great anger amongst British officials. On September 8, 1834, Lord <lb/>Napier (1786-1834), British overseer of trade in China, taking personal offense <lb/>at &quot;barbarian eye,&quot; declared war on the Qing government. Indeed, it could be <lb/>said that &quot;the first British military action in China was occasioned by neither <lb/>opium nor trade,&quot; but instead, &quot;Napier&apos;s determination to vindicate the honor <lb/>of the government of His Britannic Majesty.&quot;34 <lb/>As the use of yi was so central to Sino-British conflict, the Treaty of Tianjin <lb/>signed in 1858 included an Article 51 in Chinese which read, &quot;It is agreed <lb/>that, henceforward, the character &apos;I&apos; 夷 (barbarian) shall not be applied to <lb/></body>
	  
			<listBibl>33 Lin Zexu, Sizhou zhi, 114. <lb/>34 Lydia H. Liu, The Clash of Empires: The Invention of China in Modern World Making <lb/>(Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2004), 63-65. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>291 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  
<body>the Government or subjects of Her Britannic Majesty in any Chinese official <lb/>document issued by the Chinese Authorities either in the Capital or in the <lb/>Provinces.&quot;35 With the official censoring of yi, the character&apos;s use in such words <lb/>as yixing 夷行, referring to foreign trade, and yiwu 夷務, referring to foreign <lb/>affairs, was replaced by yang 洋. <lb/>As Lydia Liu has pointed out, the legal banning of yi by the Treaty of Tianjin <lb/>was responsible for &quot;forcing the Chinese word to refer its signified … onto the <lb/>English word &apos;barbarian.&apos;&quot;36 Additionally, &quot;… yi/barbarian articulates a par-<lb/>ticular vision of sovereignty at the meeting ground of the British and Qing <lb/>empires.&quot;37 In discussions on the matter, Chinese officials continually empha-<lb/>sized that yi did not have negative connotations, that &quot;Mencius himself said, <lb/>&apos;King Shun was an eastern yi and King Wen was a western yi.&quot;38 Yet, when it <lb/>came to this word, which has been in use throughout China&apos;s thousands of <lb/>years of history, it was not the Chinese understanding that mattered for how <lb/>it was interpreted, but the British understanding. The nineteenth century <lb/>Sino-British debate over yi was an interesting case of how Westerners firmly <lb/>took hold of power over Chinese language, including the unilateral power to <lb/>arbitrate on its interpretation. <lb/>5 Adoption of Terms Such as Zhongzu and Minzu <lb/>In today&apos;s China, minzu 民族 has long become a commonly used key term in <lb/>everyday life as well as lawmaking and justice systems. However, its current <lb/>meanings do not stem from traditional Chinese culture or thought but came <lb/>into China during the late Qing. Its nuances and usages are still widely dis-<lb/>cussed and the debates around them are deeply informed by modern Chinese <lb/>history. As such, the terms associated with it are critical to understanding how <lb/>modern Chinese people have forged a new sense of identity and established a <lb/>new thread of focus in modern Chinese thought. <lb/></body>
	  
			<listBibl>35 Ibid., 70-71. <lb/>36 Ibid., 35. <lb/>37 Ibid., 34. <lb/>38 Ibid., 43. This passage appears in the following passage from The Mencius: &quot;Shun was born <lb/>in Zhu Ping, moved to Fu Xia, and died in Ming Tiao. He was a man of the Eastern yi <lb/>lands. King Wen was born in Qi Zhou and died in Bi Ying. He was a man of the Western yi <lb/>lands. The distance between the two lands was over a thousand li. The two men lived over <lb/>a thousand years apart. But when it came to realizing their wishes in the central plains, <lb/>the two were as one. Both the former and the latter are sages; both stood by the same <lb/>principles.&quot; See Jiao Xun 焦循, Mengzi Zhengyi 孟子正義, annot. Shen Wenzhuo 沈文倬 <lb/>(Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 1987), 537-40. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>292 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
				
<body>5.1 &quot;Minzu&quot; in Traditional Chinese Texts <lb/>Notable scholar Ya Hanzhang 牙含章 (1916-1989) has written the entry &quot;Minzu&quot; <lb/>for the Zhongguo da baike quanshu 中國大百科全書: <lb/>The term minzu in Chinese appears rather late period-wise. In ancient <lb/>texts of China, the word zu is often used as is min 民, ren 人, zhong <lb/>種, bu 部, lei 類 as well as minren 民人, minzhong 民種, minqun 民群, <lb/>zhongren 種人, buren 部人, zulei 族類 and so forth. However, the combi-<lb/>nation of min with zu as a single word occurred later. Although there are <lb/>some scholars who believe that minzu was already in use in premodern <lb/>Chinese society, it is difficult to confirm that it maintained a distinct ori-<lb/>entation and stable meaning as a concept from premodern times to the <lb/>present.39 It is even harder to connect its meanings to that of our current <lb/>usage as they originate in different epistemologies. In 1903, Liang Qichao <lb/>introduced to China the German-Swiss political theorist and law scholar <lb/>J.K. Bluntschli&apos;s ideas about ethnicity and nation. Thus, use of the word <lb/>spread, and its meanings are often confused with the concept of race or <lb/>nation. This confusion is inseparable from the influence of the Western <lb/>European ideas.40 <lb/>5.2 Minzu and Zhongzu in 19th Century Chinese Sources <lb/>As the Western ideological system gradually made its way across China in <lb/>the mid-19th century via translated texts, Chinese scholars from the late Qing <lb/>onward inevitably adopted newly imported terms such as race, nation, reli-<lb/>gion, sovereignty, and citizen when discussing Chinese history, society, and <lb/>culture.41 Minzu and its associated concepts was used not only to describe dif-<lb/>ferent groups of people residing in China from the late Qing to Republican <lb/>(1912-1949) period; it, along with the other new terms, was also used to inter-<lb/>pret and describe Chinese society of earlier periods. <lb/></body>
	  
	        <listBibl>39 &quot;With careful research into various examples of minzu&apos;s usage in premodern China, it <lb/>is not hard to realize that its meaning is not clear, seeming to encompass many defini-<lb/>tions, and is largely used to express &apos;minzhi zushu 民之族属 [people&apos;s clan affiliation]&apos; or <lb/>&apos;minzhi zulei 民之族类 [people&apos;s clan].&apos; Its meaning is very similar to zulei.&quot; See Huang <lb/>Xingtao, Chongsu Zhonghua: jindai Zhongguo &quot;Zhonghua minzu&quot; guannian yanjiu, 70. <lb/>40 Ya Hanzhang 牙含章, ed., &quot;Minzu juan&quot; 民族卷, in Zhongguo da baike quanshu 中國大 <lb/>百科全書 (Beijing: Zhongguo da baike chubanshe, 1986), 302. <lb/>41 Liang Qichao emphasized in particular the difference between traditional and modern <lb/>notions of state (guojia 國家): &quot;The state refers to the nation as the private property of a <lb/>group. The premodern idea of the state necessarily began with the family … and referred <lb/>to the nation as the public property of its citizens.&quot; Liang Qichao, &quot;Datong yishu ju xuli&quot; <lb/>大同譯書局敘例, in Yinbingshi heji, 2: 56. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>293 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>

			<body>According to scholarly research, the first use in Chinese of minzu in its mod-<lb/>ern sense appeared in Prussian missionary Karl Friedrich August Gützlaff&apos;s <lb/>(1803-1851) Jiushizhu Yesu Jidu xinglun zhi yaolue zhuan 救世主耶穌基督行論 <lb/>之要略傳: &quot;Preach to the multiple minzu both Chinese and foreign to repent <lb/>one&apos;s sins and lay oneself open to the teachings of our savior Jesus Christ.&quot;42 <lb/>The fact that a European person used the Chinese minzu to translate &quot;nation&quot; <lb/>undoubtedly influenced Chinese scholars. Westerners invented the concept of <lb/>&quot;race&quot; and introduced it to China. It was a Westerner who, in 1892, translated <lb/>into Chinese and published an essay which includes in-depth discussion on <lb/>how to use skin color to racially differentiate humans.43 The Dutch scholar <lb/>Frank Dikötter has noted that the introduction of literary Darwinism to China <lb/>in the nineteenth century by Yan Fu led to an abandonment of the traditional <lb/>Chinese focus on culture as the most important standard by which groups of <lb/>people were differentiated and its replacement by race.44 This was a major <lb/>shift from how group and political identity traditionally operated in China. <lb/>The shifts in framework occurring within the Chinese academic world can <lb/>further be observed through shifts in Liang Qichao&apos;s language usage as one <lb/>of the most influential thinkers of the Late Qing to Republican periods. From <lb/>1896 to 1901, undoubtedly influenced by Yan Fu, Liang used zhongzu in refer-<lb/>ence to groups of people. In 1896, he discussed &quot;racial conflict&quot; (zhongzu zhi <lb/>zheng 種族之爭) in &quot;Bianfa tongyi&quot; 變法通議, arguing that &quot;reforming China <lb/>must necessarily start with equality between Manchu and Han races.&quot;45 In <lb/>1897, he mentioned in &quot;Chunqiu Zhongguo yidi bian xu&quot; 春秋中國夷狄辨序 <lb/>that &quot;when later generations say &apos;yi&apos; and &apos;di,&apos; they are referring to their districts <lb/>as well as race.&quot;46 In 1899, he argued in &quot;Lun Zhongguo yu Ouzhou guoti yitong&quot; <lb/>論中國與歐洲國體異同 that &quot;the Xirong, Lairong, Luhunrong, Qiangrong, <lb/>Huaiyi, Chidi, Baidi, Changdi and other races all live among one another in <lb/>the hinterlands.&quot;47 When referring to different groups who have appeared <lb/>in Chinese history, Liang uses the term &quot;race&quot; (zhongzu). <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>42 Huang Xingtao, Chongsu Zhonghua: jindai Zhongguo &quot;Zhonghua minzu&quot; guannian yanjiu, <lb/>72. <lb/>43 See &quot;Ren wu fen lei shuo&quot; 人五分類說 in Gezhi huibian 格致彙編 7.2 (1892) cited in <lb/>Frank Dikötter 馮克, Jindai Zhongguo zhi zhongzu guannian 近代中國之種族觀念 (The <lb/>Discourse of Race in Modern China), trans. Yang Lihua 楊立華 (Nanjing: Jiangsu renmin <lb/>chubanshe, 1999), 52. <lb/>44 Dikötter, Jindai Zhongguo zhi zhongzu guannian, 63. <lb/>45 Liang Qichao, &quot;Bianfa tongyi, lunyi shu&quot; 變法通議•論譯書, in Yinbingshi heji, 1: 77. <lb/>46 Liang Qichao, &quot;Chunqiu Zhongguo yidi bian xu,&quot; 2: 48. <lb/>47 Liang Qichao, &quot;Lun Zhongguo yu Ouzhou guoti yitong&quot; 論中國與歐洲國體異同, in <lb/>Yinbingshi heji, 4: 64. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>294 <lb/></page>

				<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  
			<body>5.3 Minzu as Race and also as Nation <lb/>Wang Ke argues that &quot;of essays about nationalism written by Chinese thinkers <lb/>at the start of the twentieth century, nearly all were without exception derived <lb/>from Japan.&quot; He believes that the idea of minzu received by late Qing Chinese <lb/>was &quot;a misunderstanding that came from Japan.&quot;48 In Japan, Wang says, the <lb/>English word &quot;nation&quot; was first translated into Japanese with the Chinese char-<lb/>acters 國民 (guomin/kokumin). Further, &quot;prior to the Meiji, the concept the <lb/>Japanese now commonly express using the characters 民族 (minzu/minzoku) <lb/>did not yet exist.&quot;49 In 1888, the geographer Shiga Shigetaka 志贺重昂 (1863-<lb/>1927), in introductory remarks for the magazine Nihonjin 日本人, makes mention <lb/>of the &quot;Yamato race&quot; (Yamato minzoku 大和民族). Wang writes, &quot;the fact that <lb/>minzu would emerge and become widely used in as racially homogenous a <lb/>country as Japan is because it strengthens the idea of &apos;one race as one nation&apos; <lb/>for Japanese people.&quot;50 In other words, as a new group identity formation, the <lb/>emergence of the &quot;Yamato race&quot; discursively establishes a theoretical founda-<lb/>tion for a modern Japanese state based on ethnicity. In 1896, the word minzu <lb/>appeared in an article published in the Chinese newspaper Shiwu bao&apos;s 時務報 <lb/>&quot;Dongfang baoyi&quot; 東方報譯 section, dedicated to translating content from <lb/>Japanese newspapers. Chinese intellectuals immediately took notice, due <lb/>largely to the fact that, following the First Sino-Japanese War, members of the <lb/>Chinese elite of various ethnic backgrounds had been studiously learning from <lb/>Japan lessons on national strengthening. <lb/>In 1898, Liang Qichao traveled to Japan and began engaging with Japanese <lb/>texts. That year, he wrote, &quot;It is my hope that, from now on, the Chinese nation <lb/>(minzu) may once again come into the light and exist in the world freely and <lb/>independently.&quot;51 At the time, he used minzu to refer to the many different <lb/>groups residing within China. In 1901, Liang discussed in his work Zhongguo <lb/>shi xulun 中國史敘論 the first instances where different groups in China used <lb/>the word minzu across Chinese history. He also pointed out the extremely com-<lb/>plex changes experienced by these groups who split up and rejoined as they <lb/>continued into the present. He felt that using current names of ethnic groups <lb/>to describe related ethnic groups he had found mentioned in the textual <lb/>sources would be too simplistic. In the same essay, he also brings attention to <lb/></body>
	  
			<listBibl>48 Wang Ke 王柯, Minzu zhuyi yu jindai Zhongri guanxi 民族主義與近代中日關係 (Hong <lb/>Kong: Xianggang Zhongwen daxue chubanshe, 2015), 45 and 54. <lb/>49 Ibid., 54. <lb/>50 Ibid., 60-61. <lb/>51 Jin Guantao 金觀濤 and Liu Qingfeng 劉青峰, Guannian shi yanjiu: Zhongguo xiandai <lb/>zhongyao zhengzhi shuyu de xingcheng 觀念史研究：中國現代重要政治術語的 <lb/>形成 (Beijing: Falü chubanshe, 2009), 242. <lb/></listBibl>

	  
			<page>295 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>


		<body>a valence of minzu that is close to guozu 國族 (nation): &quot;The final years of the <lb/>Qianlong reign saw the most intense period of widespread conflict between <lb/>Chinese minzu and other Asian minzu, as well as China and Asia.&quot; He goes on <lb/>to say, &quot;The Asia of today is in a period where imperialism is being replaced <lb/>by nationalism (minzu zhuyi 民族主義).&quot;52 Here, Liang uses minzu to mean <lb/>both &quot;nation&quot; and to refer to the various races and ethnicities that make up <lb/>China. In 1902, Liang manifestly introduces the term Zhonghua minzu 中華民 <lb/>族 (Sinitic/Chinese nation) in his work, Lun Zhongguo xueshu sixiang bianqian <lb/>zhi dashi 論中國學術思想變遷之大勢.53 In the same year, he writes in &quot;Xin shi <lb/>xue&quot; 新史學 of the need for China to &quot;unify the nation in order to exclude other <lb/>nations.&quot;54 These examples begin to shed light on the relationship between <lb/>minzu and the concept of nation. <lb/>5.4 Constructing &quot;China&quot;: Does Guozu Include All Chinese People or <lb/>Refer Only to the Ethnic Han? <lb/>Under the influence of foreign discourse, ethnic groups such as the Manchus, <lb/>Han, Mongols, Hui, and Tibetans came to be known as minzu. As this was the <lb/>case, Liang Qichao attempted to put forth two frameworks for group iden-<lb/>tification in order to better distinguish minzu from guozu. In his 1903 essay, <lb/>&quot;Zhengzhixue dajia Bolun zhili zhi xueshuo&quot; 政治學大家伯倫知理之學說, he <lb/>writes, &quot;when speaking of minzu in China, we must encourage big national-<lb/>ism over small nationalism. Small nationalism refers to the ethnic Han and <lb/>other peoples in China whereas big nationalism unites the multiple ethnici-<lb/>ties in China against foreign races.&quot;55 Here, &quot;big nationalism&quot; refers to guozu <lb/>as including all Chinese peoples, whereas &quot;small nationalism&quot; maintains the <lb/>by then popularized practice of referring to different groups within China as <lb/>minzu. Liang emphasizes the importance of the former due to the dire circum-<lb/>stances of the times. <lb/>In his 1903 personal account Geming jun 革命軍, Zou Rong 邹容 (1885-1905) <lb/>referred to &quot;the two hundred and sixty years after the royal Han (Huanghan <lb/></body>

	  
		   <listBibl>52 Liang Qichao, &quot;Zhongguo shi xulun&quot; 中國史敘論, in Yinbingshi heji, 4: 6, 11, and 19. <lb/>53 &quot;齊, 海國也。上古時代，我中華民族之有海思想者厥惟齊。 &quot; Liang Qichao, &quot;Lun <lb/>Zhongguo xueshu sixiang bianqian zhi dashi&quot; 論中國學術思想變遷之大勢, in Yin bing <lb/>shi heji, 7: 21. Shen Songqiao 沈松橋 renders &quot;nation,&quot; &quot;nationalism,&quot; and &quot;nation-state&quot; as <lb/>&quot;國族,&quot; &quot;國族主義,&quot; and &quot;國族-國家,&quot; respectively. See &quot;Wo yi wo xie jian Xuanyuan -<lb/>Huangdi shenhua yu wan Qing de guozu jiangou&quot; 我以我血薦軒轅 -皇帝神話與晚清 <lb/>的國族建構, Taiwan shehui yanjiu jikan 台灣社會研究季刊 28 (1997): 1-77. <lb/>54 Liang Qichao, &quot;Xin shi xue&quot; 新史學, in Yinbingshi heji, 9: 11. <lb/>55 Liang Qichao, &quot;Zhengzhixue dajia Bolunzhili zhi xueshuo&quot; 政治學大家伯倫知理之 <lb/>學說, in Yinbingshi heji, 13: 75-76. <lb/></listBibl>

		
			<page>296 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>minzu 皇漢民族) lost their country,&quot; including himself as one of the &quot;royal <lb/>Han.&quot; He connected the ethnic Han with the Ming dynasty and considered the <lb/>Yellow Emperor as an ancestor. At the same time, he grouped Mongol (as well <lb/>as Manchu) people as a &quot;Siberian race&quot; rather than a Chinese race and sug-<lb/>gested &quot;eliminating those over five million peoples who wear animal furs on <lb/>their bodies and horns on their heads.&quot;56 In his preface to Zou&apos;s work, Zhang <lb/>Taiyan 章太炎 (1868-1936) wrote that &quot;driving away those foreign peoples <lb/>would restore our lands to the glorious times of old. Since the China of today <lb/>has already fallen to foreign invaders, what we should strive for is not revolu-<lb/>tion, but the restoration of what was.&quot;57 In his 1903 work &quot;Jingshi zhong&quot; 警世鐘, <lb/>Chen Tianhua 陳天華 (1875-1905) used the terms &quot;Han race,&quot; &quot;Han people,&quot; <lb/>and &quot;ethnic Han&quot; interchangeably.58 This reflects the fact that, although the <lb/>foreign-derived concepts of &quot;race&quot; and &quot;nation&quot; were beginning to gain traction <lb/>at the time, people&apos;s understandings of these terms were hardly consistent or <lb/>uniform. Zou Rong, Chen Tianhua, and Zhang Taiyan, for instance, produced <lb/>intensely narrow-minded Han nationalist discourse based on these concepts. <lb/>In 1905, Sun Yat-sen 孫中山 (1866-1925) discussed nationalism, civil rights, <lb/>and citizens&apos; welfare in the introductory remarks of the Minbao 民報.59 In 1906, <lb/>in &quot;Zhongguo Tongmenghui geming fanglüe&quot; 中國同盟會革命方略, he juxta-<lb/>posed nationalism conceptualized as &quot;for the nation (minzu)&quot; versus &quot;for the <lb/>people (guomin),&quot; highlighting the importance of &quot;treating a country&apos;s people <lb/>as the basis of nationalist movement&quot; -hence, the concept of guozu.60 Under <lb/>the post-Xinhai Revolution order, Sun officially cast aside the provincial Han <lb/>nationalist position of &quot;driving away Dalu peoples in order to restore China,&quot; <lb/>instead adopting the nation-building ideal of &quot;uniting the five races&quot; especially <lb/>championed in northern China. In January of 1912, in &quot;Linshi Dazongtong xuan-<lb/>yanshu&quot; 臨時大總統宣言書 he clarified that &quot;combining the Han, Manchu, <lb/>Mongol, Hui, and Tibetan lands as one country and bringing together the Han, <lb/>Manchu, Mongol, Hui, and Tibetan races as one people is what is meant by <lb/>national unification.&quot;61 For Sun, the minzu in Zhonghua minzu refers to but <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>56 Zou Rong 邹容, Gemingjun 革命軍 (Beijing: Huaxia chubanshe, 2002), 5, 7, 37, and 42. <lb/>57 Ibid., 1-4. <lb/>58 Chen Tianhua 陳天華, Jingshi zhong, Meng huitou 警世鐘•猛回頭 (Beijing: Huaxia <lb/>chubanshe, 2002). <lb/>59 Sun Zhongshan 孫中山 [Sun Yat-sen], &quot;Mingbao fakan ci&quot;《民報》發刊詞, in Sun <lb/>Zhongshan quanji 孫中山全集 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 2011), 1: 288. <lb/>60 Sun Zhongshan, &quot;Zhongguo tongmenghui geming fanglüe&quot; 中國同盟會革命方略, in <lb/>Sun Zhongshan quanji, 1: 311. <lb/>61 Sun Zhongshan, &quot;Zai Nanjing Tongmenghui huiyuan jianbiehui de yanjiang&quot; 在南京同 <lb/>盟會會員餞別會的演講, in Sun Zhongshan quanji, 2: 2. <lb/></listBibl>


			<page>297 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  
<body>one unit that comprises the minzu guojia 民族國家, or &quot;nation state.&quot; In 1923, <lb/>Sun stated in the &quot;Zhongguo guomindang xuanyan&quot; 中國國民黨宣言 and <lb/>&quot;Zhongguo guomindang danggang&quot; 中國國民黨黨綱 that &quot;(we should) unite <lb/>the various ethnic groups in the country to achieve a great Chinese nation.&quot;62 <lb/>During the first of the new &quot;Sanmin zhuyi&quot; 三民主義 talks a year later, he asked, <lb/>&quot;What is nationalism? Based on the various scenarios in the history of Chinese <lb/>society … nationalism is guozu zhuyi.&quot;63 Additionally, &quot;everyone joins together <lb/>to form a great national group.&quot;64 Sun&apos;s words all speak to the nationalism he <lb/>sought, one which inherently casts the inclusion of all Chinese peoples as the <lb/>change that will lead to a &quot;great Chinese nation.&quot; <lb/>5.5 Applications of Concepts of Minzu to the Studies of Chinese History <lb/>As minzu had by the late Qing entered discourses on relationships between <lb/>different groups in China as well as been used to refer to those different groups, <lb/>it was inevitable that the modern term would make it into the vocabulary <lb/>of scholars who were, at the time, researching inter-ethnic relationships in <lb/>Chinese history. Here, also, it is possible to observe in the diction of such schol-<lb/>ars the indelible mark of Japanese influence. <lb/>In his 1928 publication, Zhongguo minzu shi 中國民族史, Wang Tonglin <lb/>王桐齡 (1878-1953) indicates, &quot;Based on historical observations of events, <lb/>there was only one minzu in the Far East. Historical sources refer to that race <lb/>as the Eastern yi.&quot;65 Wang&apos;s book is one of the first published works on the his-<lb/>tory of race and ethnicity in China. Applying concepts of minzu to describe <lb/>the peoples of ancient China probably reflects his experience as an overseas <lb/>student in Japan. <lb/>Many subsequent works sharing the title of Wang&apos;s books followed in his <lb/>application of minzu. One example is Lü Simian&apos;s 呂思勉 (1884-1957) 1934 <lb/>book which contains a passage on the characteristics of the ethnic Han: <lb/>&quot;As for the Han … the more minzu are absorbed into their population, the <lb/>vaster the nation&apos;s lands shall be.&quot;66 Lin Huixang 林惠祥 (1901-1958) writes in <lb/>another eponymous book of 1936, &quot;The history of minzu in China is a narra-<lb/>tive of the changes undergone by China&apos;s multiple minzu from past to present. <lb/></body>
	  
			<listBibl>62 Sun Zhongshan, &quot;Zhongguo guomindang xuanyan&quot; 中國國民黨宣言, in Sun Zhongshan <lb/>quanji, 7: 3. <lb/>63 Sun Zhongshan, &quot;Sanmin zhuyi&quot; 三民主義, in Sun Zhongshan quanji, 9: 184-85. <lb/>64 Ibid., 242. <lb/>65 Wang Tonglin 王桐齡, Zhongguo minzu shi 中國民族史 (Changchun: Jilin chuban <lb/>jituan, 2010), 9. <lb/>66 Lü Simian 呂思勉, Zhongguo minzu shi 中國民族史 (Beijing: Dongfang chubanshe, <lb/>1996), 3. <lb/></listBibl>


			<page>298 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>More specifically, it is a discussion of the origins of each, the evolution of <lb/>their nomenclature, distinctions between their subgroups, their rises to and <lb/>falls from power, cultural shifts, and issues concerning their interactions <lb/>and intermingling.&quot;67 Thus, minzu came to be adopted and widely used to <lb/>describe different peoples throughout Chinese history. <lb/>6 Concluding Remarks <lb/>Looking back at China&apos;s interactions with Western powers around the time <lb/>of the Opium Wars, it is evident that Western colonizers employed a double <lb/>standard in their dealings with China. In the eyes of Europeans, the difference <lb/>between &quot;civilized&quot; and &quot;barbaric&quot; people was a matter of racial essentialism. <lb/>This is why the Great Powers of Europe applied a different moral and legal <lb/>standard in diplomacy with one another versus when engaging the nations of <lb/>Asia, Africa, and Latin America. Without understanding this point, it is very <lb/>possible to accept the universal value of Western concepts and discourse. <lb/>The Opium Wars represented a turning point in Chinese history. The arrival <lb/>of Western political concepts and language overturned the Chinese cultural <lb/>order and group dynamics that had traditionally been based on the ideas of <lb/>a Chinese empire encompassing &quot;all under heaven&quot; and the &quot;Sino-Barbarian <lb/>dichotomy.&quot; In the new context of Western dominance, the Chinese people <lb/>had little choice but to try to learn, understand, and adopt the foreign lexicon <lb/>while also struggling to find ways to preserve the nation and its people despite <lb/>the humiliating conditions. <lb/>Having now arrived at the international stage of the twenty-first century, <lb/>broadly maintaining relations with many other nations is of utmost impor-<lb/>tance. While doing so, it is also important to communicate using language and <lb/>concepts that are understandable and acceptable to others. The Western con-<lb/>cepts and discourses that entered China during the modern period and which <lb/>have since been adopted as part of the Chinese lexicon are now a necessary <lb/>tool for building such relationships. However, it is precisely for this reason that <lb/>researchers must remain cautious on two counts. <lb/>Firstly, many foreign concepts contain meanings which are incompat-<lb/>ible with traditional Chinese worldviews; thus, we cannot unilaterally apply <lb/>Western concepts to the understanding of ancient China, even less so to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>67 Lin Huixiang 林惠祥, Zhongguo minzu shi 中國民族史 (Beijing: Shangwu yinshu guan, <lb/>1998), 2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>299 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>

			<body>reductive interpretations of China today. To do so would be to risk the procrus-<lb/>tean error of &quot;maiming one&apos;s feet to fit too-small shoes.&quot; Thus, when discussing <lb/>group dynamics in ancient China, we would do well to avoid using such mod-<lb/>ern Western conceptual terms as &quot;nation&quot; and &quot;ethnic group.&quot; Terms such as <lb/>chao 朝 (dynasty) and guo 國 (state) have their own nuances and character-<lb/>istics within the context of Chinese history. They are not interchangeable <lb/>or discursively compatible with words used elsewhere in the world such as <lb/>&quot;empire,&quot; &quot;kingdom,&quot; or, more recently, &quot;nation-state.&quot; <lb/>Secondly, we must carefully untangle the exact route by which these core <lb/>concepts came into China and analyze the cultural background informing the <lb/>different ways Chinese people understood these concepts in different time <lb/>periods. After building concrete scenarios of how these foreign concepts were <lb/>used in Chinese society during and after the Opium Wars, we must give them <lb/>clear definitions. Since it is possible that Chinese people&apos;s understandings of <lb/>these concepts were partially different from their original definitions, it is nec-<lb/>essary to add attributive or conditional words and explanations. Research in <lb/>the fields of conceptual history and sociology of knowledge are essential to <lb/>Chinese-foreign intellectual and cultural exchange. What we are facing are two <lb/>completely different paths of historical development, two sets of fundamental <lb/>concepts and language systems that arose from different political, economic, <lb/>and cultural environments. Only with a strong foundation in conceptual his-<lb/>torical studies can one open up mutual dialogue rooted in the essence of things <lb/>and, gradually, actualize deep understanding between the two sides. <lb/>We must systematically work through all the Western political and cultural <lb/>ideas accepted into China over the past two hundred years, acknowledge the <lb/>gap between the two sides when engaged in comparative analysis of tradi-<lb/>tional China, seek out possible points of similarity, and analyze the reasons <lb/>for the differences. Only by doing so can we truly recognize, through compari-<lb/>son, the Western world and, in turn, gain a deeper understanding of China and <lb/>Chinese society. In terms of participating in international politics and cultural <lb/>exchanges, Chinese people strive towards deep awareness of world civiliza-<lb/>tions, including those of the West. We should also try to understand more <lb/>deeply the political and cultural traditions of the many peoples in China. From <lb/>there, it may be possible to gain political and cultural self-awareness. <lb/>When the alternative to learning from Western countries is to perish as a <lb/>nation, there is no choice but to do so. Only after grasping the rules of the <lb/>West&apos;s games -even drawing on knowledge passed down from Chinese ances-<lb/>tors to exhibit skill on an international stage -can the Chinese people start to <lb/>take the initiative and begin to restore China&apos;s cultural confidence. In order <lb/></body>

			<page>300 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			  <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>
	  <body>to do so, they must position themselves firmly in the present world stage and, <lb/>from its highest institutions of knowledge, learn to recognize the strengths and <lb/>weaknesses of all the civilizations of humanity, including Western, Islamic, <lb/>Indian civilizations as well as the Sinitic civilization. At the same time, they <lb/>must master the ability to communicate cross-culturally and develop skills to <lb/>facilitate harmonious interaction between different cultural groups, perhaps <lb/>even merging them. To this end, the wisdom their ancestors maintained across <lb/>thousands of years of Chinese civilization is an incomparable resource. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <front>Translated by Casey Lee <lb/></front>
	  
	 <listBibl>Works Cited <lb/>
		 
		Chen, Jianming 陳建明. &quot;Chuanjiaoshi zai xinan shaoshu minzu diqu de wenzi chuang-<lb/>zhi huodong&quot; 傳教士在西南少數民族地區的文字創制活動. Zongjiaoxue yanjiu <lb/>宗教學研究, no. 4 (2010): 142-49. <lb/>Chen, Tianhua 陳天華. Jingshi zhong, Meng huitou警世鐘•猛回頭. Beijing: Huaxia <lb/>chubanshe, 2002. <lb/>Dikötter, Frank 馮克. Jindai Zhongguo zhi zhongzu guannian 近代中國之種族觀念 <lb/>(The Discourse of Race in Modern China). Translated by Yang Lihua 楊立華. Nanjing: <lb/>Jiangsu renmin chubanshe, 1999. <lb/>Ge, Zhaoguang 葛兆光. Zhaizi Zhongguo: Chongjian youguan &quot;Zhongguo&quot; de lishi <lb/>lunshu宅兹中國:重建有關&quot;中國&quot;的歷史論述. Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 2011. <lb/>Greenfeld, Liah. Nationalism: Five Roads to Modernity. Cambridge: Harvard University <lb/>Press, 1992. <lb/>Gu, Jiegang 顧颉剛. &quot;&apos;Zhongguo benbu&apos; yi ming jiying feiqi&quot; &quot;中國本部&quot;一名極應廢 <lb/>棄. Yishibao 益世報, January 1, 1939. <lb/>Hobsbawm, Eric J. Nations and Nationalism since 1780: Programme, Myth, Reality. <lb/>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1990. <lb/>Huang, Xingtao 黃興濤. Chongsu Zhonghua: jindai Zhongguo &quot;Zhonghua minzu&quot; guan <lb/>nian yanjiu 重塑中華:近代中國&quot;中華民族&quot;觀念研究. Hong Kong: Sanlian shudian, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Huntington, Samuel P. The Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of World Order. New <lb/>York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1996. <lb/>Jiao, Xun 焦循. Mengzi Zhengyi 孟子正義. Annotated by Shen Wenzhuo 沈文倬. <lb/>Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 1987. <lb/>Jin, Guantao 金觀濤 and Liu Qingfeng 劉青峰. Guannian shi yanjiu: Zhongguo xian <lb/>dai zhongyao zhengzhi shuyu de xingcheng 觀念史研究:中國現代重要政治術語的 <lb/>形成. Beijing: Falü chubanshe, 2009. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>301 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">China under Western Aggression <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Kedourie, Elie. Nationalism. New York: F.A. Praeger, 1960. <lb/>Liang, Qichao 梁啟超. Yinbingshi heji: Wenji 飲冰室合集:文集. Beijing: Zhonghua <lb/>shuju, 1989. <lb/>Lin, Huixiang 林惠祥. Zhongguo minzu shi 中國民族史. Beijing: Shangwu yinshu guan, <lb/>1998. <lb/>Lin, Zexu 林則徐. Sizhou zhi 四洲志. Beijing: Huaxia chubanshe, 2002. <lb/>Liu, Lydia H. The Clash of Empires: the Invention of China in Modern World Making. <lb/>Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2004. <lb/>Liu, Lydia H. Translingual Practice: Literature, National Culture, and Translated <lb/>Modernity -China, 1900-1937. Stanford: Standford University Press, 1995. <lb/>Lu, Fanzhi 魯凡之. Zhongguo fazhan yu wenhua jiegou 中國發展與文化結構. Hong <lb/>Kong: Ji xian she, 1998. <lb/>Lü, Simian 呂思勉. Zhongguo minzu shi中國民族史. Beijing: Dongfang chubanshe, <lb/>1996. <lb/>Mao, Haijian 茅海建. Jindai de chidu: liangci Yapian Zhanzheng junshi yu waijiao <lb/>近代的尺度:兩次鴉片戰爭軍事與外交. Bejiing: Shenghuo dushu xinhe sanlian <lb/>shudian, 2011. <lb/>Pei, Yu 裴鈺. &quot;Hunshen fama: bu jiang &apos;Riben hanyu&apos; jiu buneng shuohua&quot; 渾身發麻: <lb/>不講&quot;日本漢語&quot;就不能說話. Lianhe zaobao 聯合早報, Feb. 9, 2009. <lb/>Shen, Songqiao 沈松橋. &quot;Wo yi wo xie jian Xuanyuan -Huangdi shenhua yu wan Qing <lb/>de guozu jiangou&quot; 我以我血薦軒轅 -皇帝神話與晚清的國族建構. Taiwan shehui <lb/>yanjiu jikan 台灣社會研究季刊 28 (1997): 1-77. <lb/>Smith, Anthony D. National Identity. Reno: University of Nevada Press, 1991. <lb/>Sun, Longji 孫隆基. Lishixue jia de jingxian 歷史學家的經線. Guilin: Guangxi shifan <lb/>daxue chubanshe, 2004. <lb/>Sun, Zhongshan 孫中山 [Sun Yat-sen]. Sun Zhongshan quanji 孫中山全集. Beijing: <lb/>Zhonghua shuju, 2011. <lb/>Wang, Binbin 王彬彬. &quot;Gezai Zhong-Xi zhijian de Riben -xiandai hanyu zhong de <lb/>riyu &apos;wai lai yu&apos; wenti&quot; 隔在中西之間的日本 -現代漢語中的日語&quot;外來語&quot;問題. <lb/>Shanghai wenxue 上海文學, no. 8 (1998): 71-80. <lb/>Wang, Ke 王柯. Minzu zhuyi yu jindai Zhong Ri guanxi 民族主義與近代中日關係. Hong <lb/>Kong: Xianggang Zhongwen daxue chubanshe, 2015. <lb/>Wang, Ke 王柯. Zhongguo, cong &quot;tianxia&quot; dao minzu guojia 中國，從 &quot;天下&quot; 到民族 <lb/>國家. Taipei: Zhengda chubanshe, 2014. <lb/>Wang, Tonglin 王桐齡. Zhongguo minzu shi 中國民族史. Changchun: Jilin chuban <lb/>jituan, 2010. <lb/>Xiao, Zhiqin 肖志欽, and Jian&apos;an Xiao 肖建安. &quot;Limadou ji qi dui Zhongguo fanyi shi de <lb/>gongxian&quot; 利瑪竇及其對中國翻譯史的貢獻. Loudi shizhuan xuebao 婁底師專學報, <lb/>no. 4 (2003): 33-35. <lb/></listBibl>

		<page>302 <lb/></page>
						
			<note place="headnote">Ma <lb/></note>
			<note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 8 (2022) 279-302 <lb/></note>

		<listBibl>Ya, Hanzhang 牙含章, ed. &quot;Minzu juan&quot; 民族卷. In Zhongguo dabaike quanchu 中國大 <lb/>百科全書. Beijing: Zhongguo dabaike chubanshe, 1986. <lb/>Yan, Fu 嚴復. Tianyan lun 天演論. Beijing: Huaxia chubanshe, 2002. <lb/>Yang, Du 楊度. &quot;&apos;Youxue yibian&apos; xu&quot; &quot;遊學譯編&quot;敘. In Xinhai geming qianshinian jian <lb/>shi lun xuan ji 辛亥革命前十年間時論選集, edited by Zhang Nan 張柟 and Wang <lb/>Renzhi 王忍之. Beijing: Shenhuo dushu xinhe sanlian shudian, 1960. <lb/>Zhan, Zhonghe 湛中和. &quot;Dizhonghai wenhuaquan yu qifang wenming dutexing de <lb/>genyuan&quot; 地中海文化圈與西方文明獨特性的根源. Hunan shifan daxue shehui kexue <lb/>xuebao 湖南師範大學社會科學學報, no. 4 (2010): 128-31. <lb/>Zhang, Zhirong 張植榮. Guoji guanxi yu Xizang wenti 國際關係與西藏問題. Beijing: <lb/>Lüyou jiaoyu chubanshe, 1994. <lb/>Zheng, Zhenduo 鄭振鐸. Wan Qing wenxuan 晚清文選. Beijing: Zhongguo shehuixue <lb/>chubanshe, 2002. <lb/>Zou, Rong 邹容. Geming jun 革命軍. Beijing: Huaxia chubanshe, 2002.</listBibl>


	</text>


  
  </TEI>