<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">The Bias and Consequences of Prioritizing Public Morality over Private Morality in Modern China</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Lai</forename>
          <surname>Chen</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="sperber">Marcia Sperber</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-22T21:38:22.768Z">22/12/2025 21:38:22</date>
        <title>Review Luca</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.1163__23521341-12340194</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2025</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.1163/23521341-12340194</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Lai Chen. (2025). The Bias and Consequences of Prioritizing Public Morality over Private Morality in Modern China. Journal of Chinese Humanities, 11(2), 109-124. DOI: 10.1163/23521341-12340194</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-28T13:54:50.897359Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-28T13:54:50.897359Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-22T21:38:22.768Z" status="approved" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Review Luca</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Published with license by Koninklijke Brill BV | doi:10.1163/23521341-12340194 <lb/>© Chen Lai, 2025 | ISSN: 2352-1341 (online) <lb/>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the CC BY 4.0 license. <lb/>Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/>brill.com/joch <lb/>The Bias and Consequences of Prioritizing Public <lb/>Morality over Private Morality in Modern China <lb/>Chen Lai 陳來 <lb/>Professor, Department of Philosophy, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China <lb/>chenlai@mail.tsinghua.edu.cn <lb/>Received 17 January 2025 | Accepted 27 January 2025 | <lb/>Published online 30 July 2025 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>According to definitions put forward by modern Western scholars, personal moral-<lb/>ity refers to conduct or qualities that concern only oneself and do not involve others. <lb/>In ancient China, however, most virtues were not purely individual matters but were <lb/>closely tied to one&apos;s attitudes toward others. As for public morality, traditional Chinese <lb/>society did possess certain forms of it, but these differed from the public ethics and <lb/>etiquette as understood in modern social and civic life. Liang Qichao was influenced <lb/>by Japan&apos;s modern emphasis on public morality, but his advocacy for &quot;public moral-<lb/>ity&quot; focused primarily on civic morality, namely political morality, whereas Japan&apos;s <lb/>approach centered on general social morality. Although civic and social morality can <lb/>both be understood as &quot;public morality,&quot; a stable and mature modern society relies <lb/>more fundamentally on the latter to maintain order. China&apos;s unique modernization <lb/>trajectory has led to an overemphasis on political-civic morality, overshadowing the <lb/>conceptual development and societal promotion of social ethics. The core issue lies <lb/>in how political morality has replaced, marginalized, and even abolished personal <lb/>morality, while social morality has been similarly neglected. This has disrupted <lb/>the proper balance between political, social, and private morality. To rethink con-<lb/>temporary moral discourse in China, it is imperative to restore the independence <lb/>and significance of personal morality, while actively cultivating a culture of social <lb/>morality. <lb/>110 <lb/>Chen <lb/></front>
  
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124<lb/></note>
   
    <front>Keywords <lb/>public morality -private morality -political morality -individual morality <lb/></front>
      
      <body>1 <lb/>Re-examining the Public-Private Morality Framework <lb/>Social morality generally refers to the behavioral norms expected of individu-<lb/>als in social and public settings. In practice, its prohibitions often align with <lb/>the mildest forms of legal regulations, often enforceable through informal <lb/>societal conventions or &quot;soft law.&quot; Scholars note that social morality governs <lb/>interactions among individuals, society, and the natural world -a domain <lb/>richly discussed in classical Chinese thought, particularly Confucianism. <lb/>While Confucian ethics &quot;lacks explicit notions of &apos;citizens&apos; or &apos;civil society,&apos; it <lb/>implicitly addresses principles relevant to public coexistence.&quot;1 In fact, &quot;China&apos;s <lb/>historical identity as a &apos;land of rituals and propriety&apos; [liyi zhi bang 禮儀之邦] <lb/>reflects its longstanding tradition on social morality.&quot; For instance, Guanzi <lb/>管子 articulated the concept of &quot;the four pillars of the state&quot; (guo zhi si wei <lb/>國之四維) -propriety (li 禮), righteousness (yi 義), integrity (lian 廉), and a <lb/>sense of shame (chi 恥) -which constitute the traditional conception of pub-<lb/>lic morality, and at the very least, represent its application within the realm of <lb/>social morality.2 <lb/>The term &quot;public morality&quot; (gongde 公德) in modern Chinese encompasses <lb/>at least two distinct dimensions: civic morality, which reflects the political <lb/>demands imposed by the state on its citizens, and social morality, which per-<lb/>tains to the normative expectations of modern public life. Based on its use in <lb/>the modern era, public morality in its narrow sense refers exclusively to social <lb/>morality, while its broader interpretation includes both social and civic moral-<lb/>ity. It is worth noting, however, political values such as freedom and democracy <lb/>are not considered to be in the domain of either moral or public virtue. Having <lb/>these two dimensions nested within public morality has often caused confu-<lb/>sion in discussions, making it difficult to clarify what the term actually refers <lb/>to, and thus limiting its applicability. <lb/>Modern Chinese scholars have primarily focused on discussions surround-<lb/>ing public morality, with limited attention paid to the conceptualization of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 Liao Shenbai 廖申白, &quot;Gongmin lunli yu Rujia lunli&quot; 公民倫理與儒家倫理, Zhexue yanjiu <lb/>哲學研究, no. 11 (2001): 67-74. <lb/>2 Wu Qiantao 吳潛濤, ed., Lun gonggong lunli yu gongde 論公共倫理與公德 (Wuhan: Hubei <lb/>renmin chubanshe, 2008), 64. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>111 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">PRIORITIZING PUBLIC MORALITY OVER PRIVATE MORALITY <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>

			<body>private morality (side 私德) or its ethical framework. In my book Gudai sixi-<lb/>ang wenhua de shijie 古代思想文化的世界, I address this gap by examining <lb/>virtue narratives from the Spring and Autumn period (770-476 BCE). These <lb/>narratives, I argue, can be categorized into three groups: the &quot;Four Restraints&quot; <lb/>(siwu 四無), the &quot;Eleven Maxims&quot; (shiyiyan 十一言), and the &quot;Two Constants&quot; <lb/>(er weichangbu 二未嘗不). Here, I focus on explicating the first two categories. <lb/>For instance, the &quot;Zhouyu&quot; 周語 chapter of Guoyu 國語 articulates the &quot;Four <lb/>Restraints&quot; as follows: &quot;standing without imbalance [li wu bo 立無跛], a mark <lb/>of uprightness [zheng 正]; gazing without distraction [shi wu huan 視無還], a <lb/>sign of dignity [duan 端]; listening without agitation [ting wu song 聽無聳], an <lb/>expression of composure [cheng 成]; and speaking without exaggeration [yan <lb/>wu yuan 言無遠], a reflection of prudence [shen 慎].&quot;3 These four virtues are <lb/>fundamentally personal. <lb/>Similarly, virtues such as elegance (qi 齊), sagacity (sheng 聖), magna-<lb/>nimity (guang 廣), depth (yuan 淵), clarity (ming 明), fairness (yun 允), <lb/>steadfastness (du 篤), sincerity (cheng 誠), loyalty (zhong 忠), solemnity (su <lb/>肅), reverence (gong 共), excellence (yi 懿), mercy (ci 慈), generosity (hui 惠), <lb/>and harmony (he 和) represent what I term &quot;formal virtues&quot; (xingshixing dexing <lb/>形式性德行), which aim at the general perfection of one&apos;s character and tem-<lb/>perament, rather than adherence to specific ethical norms. In ancient virtue <lb/>theory, these were labeled &quot;dispositional virtues&quot; (xingqing zhi de 性情之德), <lb/>distinct from &quot;moral virtues&quot; (daode zhi de 道德之德), &quot;ethical virtues&quot; (lunli <lb/>zhi de 倫理之德) and &quot;intellectual virtues&quot; (lizhi zhi de 理智之德). The essence <lb/>of dispositional virtues lies in &quot;virtues pertaining to the self,&quot; whereas virtues <lb/>such as benevolence (ren 仁), righteousness, courage (yong 勇), humility (rang <lb/>讓), trustworthiness (xin 信), and propriety constitute &quot;moral virtues.&quot; Filial <lb/>piety (xiaoti 孝悌), parental care (ci&apos;ai 慈愛), and fraternal loyalty (youzhong <lb/>友忠), meanwhile, belong neither to the personal dimension nor to the moral <lb/>sphere but instead are categorized as &quot;ethical virtues.&quot;4 Thus, it would be wrong <lb/>to understand all traditional Chinese morality as a kind of individual morality. <lb/>Defining personal morality solely as ethics pertaining to the self is prob-<lb/>lematic, considering that most foundational personal virtues in ancient China <lb/>were inherently connected to one&apos;s attitudes toward others. What, then, should <lb/>this type of morality be termed? In contrast to morality required by political <lb/></body>
    
              <listBibl>3 Xu Yuangao 徐元誥, Guoyu jijie 國語集解, annot. Wang Shumin 王樹民 and Shen Changyun <lb/>沈長雲 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 2002), 89-90. <lb/>4 Chen Lai 陳來, Gudai sixiang wenhua de shijie: Chunqiu shidai de zongjiao, lunli yu shehui six-<lb/>iang 古代思想文化的世界-春秋時代的宗教、倫理與社會思想 (Beijing: Shenghuo <lb/>dushu xinzhi sanlian shudian, 2002), 344. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>112 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Chen <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>or social groups, this form of morality belongs more appropriately to the ethi-<lb/>cal cultivation of a holistically developed individual. In Aristotelian terms, <lb/>this corresponds to the &quot;virtues of a good person&quot; (shanren pinde 善人品德); <lb/>within Chinese cultural discourse, it is termed &quot;virtues of the exemplary per-<lb/>son&quot; ( junzi pinde 君子品德), encompassing four dimensions: dispositional <lb/>virtues, moral virtues, ethical virtues, and intellectual virtues. Therefore, while <lb/>the public-private morality distinction holds certain value, a vast portion of <lb/>foundational virtues do not actually fit into this framework, exposing the limi-<lb/>tations of such a dichotomy. <lb/>Does this mean that traditional Chinese practices of self-cultivation (xiushen <lb/>修身) were exclusively personal or private in nature? The answer depends on <lb/>how private morality is defined. In Confucianism, self-cultivation rarely occurs <lb/>in isolation from societal life. Virtues like benevolence, righteousness, pro-<lb/>priety, and wisdom (zhi 智) are intrinsically linked to social interactions and <lb/>interpersonal relations, requiring practice within real-world situations. Thus, it <lb/>is inaccurate to equate self-cultivation entirely with private morality. As Liang <lb/>Qichao 梁啓超 (1873-1929) observed, traditional Chinese &quot;private virtues&quot; <lb/>were not confined to individual morality but also applied to public life. The <lb/>Eight Tenets of The Great Learning, for example, are not discrete moral prin-<lb/>ciples, but rather a series of practical disciplines. Each stage represents a moral <lb/>practice, not a separate type of virtue. As the text emphasizes, its principles <lb/>are consistent and do not follow the public-private distinctions. For instance, <lb/>&quot;governing others&quot; (zhi ren 治人) within the framework of &quot;self-cultivation and <lb/>governance of others&quot; (xiuji zhiren 修己治人) is not a &quot;private&quot; endeavor. Due <lb/>to limited scope of social interactions in that era, the text did not foreground <lb/>norms for engaging with unfamiliar individuals. Nonetheless, to claim, as Liang <lb/>Qichao once did, that public morality was entirely absent in traditional China <lb/>is also inaccurate. In terms of applications, traditional Chinese morals focused <lb/>less on virtues for ordinary individuals and more on the moral duties of rulers, <lb/>officials, and scholar-officials. Thus, the virtues of the exemplary person tran-<lb/>scend public-private dichotomies, with their application unified in principle <lb/>yet differentiated in practice. Although civic morality and social morality may <lb/>be understood collectively as public morality, Western thought, from ancient <lb/>Greece to modern times, has prioritized the former over the latter. <lb/>In reality, the internal order of a stable, mature modern state and society <lb/>depends most critically on social morality. Yet China&apos;s unique modernization <lb/>trajectory has prioritized revolutionary morality (geming daode 革命道德) in <lb/>its early modern era and shifted towards civic morality following the Reform <lb/>and Opening-up, while systematically neglecting the conceptualization and <lb/>promotion of social morality. Over the past century, this has resulted in a pro-<lb/>found imbalance: an overemphasis on political morality over social morality. <lb/></body>

			<page>113 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">PRIORITIZING PUBLIC MORALITY OVER PRIVATE MORALITY <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>The urgent task today is to recalibrate this equilibrium, with immediate focus <lb/>on cultivating social morality, that is, ethical norms governing collective life. <lb/>Within the Confucian moral system, virtues that regulate purely individual <lb/>behavior without implicating others are in the minority. The majority of ethi-<lb/>cal teachings inherently encompass &quot;potential effects on others.&quot; Core virtues <lb/>such as benevolence, righteousness, propriety, wisdom, and trustworthiness <lb/>all contain aspects of &quot;obligations toward others.&quot; It is also worth noting that <lb/>&quot;duties to the self&quot; and &quot;duties to others&quot; are not considered separate but rather <lb/>unified in traditional Chinese moral culture. While not all classical virtues <lb/>explicitly address community welfare, each one, in its own way, contributes to <lb/>the benefit, cohesion, and governance of the community. <lb/>Virtues at the core of Chinese moral traditions are all relational ones ori-<lb/>ented toward others. For example, the &quot;five cardinal relationships&quot; (wulun <lb/>五倫), ruler and subject, father and son, elder brother and younger brother, <lb/>husband and wife, and friend and friend, all prescribe relational ethics (guanxi <lb/>lunli 關係倫理) rather than morals concerned with the self. The same holds <lb/>true for filial piety (xiao 孝), fraternal duty (ti 悌), loyalty, and trustworthiness. <lb/>Benevolence and righteousness reflect universal ethical imperatives, while fil-<lb/>ial piety and fraternal duty entail context-specific obligations, none of which <lb/>pertain solely to the self. Furthermore, some virtues, such as equilibrium <lb/>(zhong 中), may appear individualistic during self-cultivation, but they ulti-<lb/>mately serve to realize harmony (he 和), which is an ideal inherently embedded <lb/>in social settings. In a similar vein, sincerity, trustworthiness, respect ( jing 敬), <lb/>and reverence (gong 恭) are all relational concepts, manifesting their moral <lb/>significance within interpersonal relationships. Thus, the concept of &quot;private <lb/>morality&quot; is useful only within a limited scope, as personal virtues remain inex-<lb/>tricably tied to social dynamics. <lb/>2 <lb/>Liang Qichao&apos;s Theory of Public and Private Morality <lb/>Liang Qichao&apos;s discourse on public morality emerged as an application of <lb/>modern Enlightenment ideals to China&apos;s political and ethical landscape, in the <lb/>face of the urgent demands for national transformation and prosperity in early <lb/>20th-century China. Shaped by his exposure to Western social thought dur-<lb/>ing his stay in Japan after the Wuxu Reform, Liang&apos;s theoretical framework of <lb/>morality sought to reconcile traditional ethics with the exigencies of modern <lb/>state-building.5 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>5 It is generally believed that Liang Qichao&apos;s concept of the state was directly influenced by <lb/>Konrad Bornhak and Johann K. Bluntschli. Issues 11 to 31 of Qingyi bao 清議報 featured an <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>114 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Chen <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>In Xinmin shuo 新民說, Liang states: &quot;When each person focuses solely on <lb/>cultivating their own character, it is called private morality; when each per-<lb/>son contributes to the well-being of the group, it is called public morality.&quot;6 In <lb/>other words, public and private morality are two manifestations of a unified <lb/>moral system. Public morality entails moral obligations governing the rela-<lb/>tionship between the individual and the community, whereas private morality <lb/>involves the perfection of one&apos;s personal character in isolation from others. <lb/>Comparatively, the former serves as the antecedent of communal cohesion <lb/>while the latter constitutes the bedrock of individual integrity. The defining <lb/>characteristic of public morality is its concern for the collective good. Liang <lb/>asserts, &quot;A nation cannot be formed by citizens devoid of private morality, <lb/>nor can it be sustained by individuals who possess only private ethics but <lb/>lack public morality.&quot; Liang further emphasizes their interdependence: &quot;A <lb/>complete moral system encompasses both public and private morality; they <lb/>operate side by side without contradiction.&quot;7 This statement serves as a supple-<lb/>ment to the idea of private morality being equivalent to &quot;cultivating the self.&quot; <lb/>Liang&apos;s advocacy for public morality stems from his nationalist stance during <lb/>this period and his use of modern Japan as a model for nation-building.8 From <lb/>a theoretical perspective, however, Liang&apos;s definition of public morality as &quot;the <lb/>individual&apos;s moral obligations toward the community&quot; represents a notable <lb/>departure from Western moral philosophy. <lb/>Liang acknowledges the sophistication of China&apos;s private morality, exempli-<lb/>fied by Confucian classics like the Analects and Mencius, which extol virtues <lb/>such as loyalty, trustworthiness, steadfastness, respect, gentleness (wen 溫), <lb/>kindness (liang 良), reverence, frugality ( jian 儉), and humility. These, he <lb/>argues, teach individuals cultivation practices like &quot;nurturing one&apos;s heart-mind&quot; <lb/>(cunxin yangxing 存心養性), which all aim at enhancing one&apos;s private morality. <lb/>At the same time, he critiques traditional Chinese ethics for its neglect of pub-<lb/>lic morality: &quot;Chinese moral traditions developed remarkably early, yet they <lb/>placed a disproportionate emphasis on private virtues, leaving public morality <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>anonymously translated work titled &quot;Deguo Bolunzhili zhu Guojia lun&quot; 德國伯倫知理著 <lb/>國家論. <lb/>6 Liang Qichao 梁啟超, Xinmin shuo 新民說 (Beijing: Shangwu yinshuguan, 2016), 19. <lb/>7 Ibid., 20. <lb/>8 Xiajian Zhishu 狹間直樹 [Naoki Hazama], &quot;Xinmin shuo lüelun&quot; 新民說略論, in Liang <lb/>Qichao Mingzhi Riben Xifang: Riben Jingdu daxue renwen kexue yanjiusuo gongtong yanjiu <lb/>baogao 梁啟超•明治日本•西方-日本京都大學人文科學研究所共同研究報告 <lb/>(Beijing: Shehui kexue wenxian chubanshe, 2001), 75-76. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>115 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">PRIORITIZING PUBLIC MORALITY OVER PRIVATE MORALITY <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    <body>&gt;almost entirely undeveloped.&quot;9 This imbalance, Liang contends, impeded <lb/>China&apos;s transition into a modern nation-state. <lb/>In the first section of Xinmin shuo, &quot;Lun Xinmin wei jinri Zhongguo diyi <lb/>jiwu&quot; 論新民為今日中國第一急務, Liang declares, &quot;What is public morality? It <lb/>is the virtue upon which a society is formed, and a nation is established.&quot;10 He <lb/>thus emphasizes that public morality serves as the fundamental pillar for the <lb/>establishment of human societies, especially modern nation-states. It enables <lb/>the individual and the state to become integrally linked. By framing public <lb/>morality as the sine qua non of statehood, Liang comes close to treating it as a <lb/>precondition for the very existence of the nation. Yet in reality, social moral-<lb/>ity matures in tandem with the development of social structures. Modern <lb/>Chinese thinkers have often preached cultural modernization as a prerequi-<lb/>site for social modernization, a stance that is theoretically unsound. From a <lb/>practical standpoint, however, disseminating these new concepts undoubtedly <lb/>contributes to social progress. <lb/>Liang Qichao argues that China&apos;s prioritization of private morality over pub-<lb/>lic morality had to be rectified to reverse the nation&apos;s decline in the modern <lb/>world. He asserts: <lb/>Let us compare China&apos;s traditional ethics with Western modern ethics. <lb/>The former categorizes relationships into five domains: ruler-subject, <lb/>parent-child, sibling-sibling, spouse-spouse, and friend-friend; the lat-<lb/>ter emphasizes familial ethics, social or communal ethics and national <lb/>ethics. Traditional ethics focus on one person&apos;s relationship with another <lb/>individual … whereas modern ethics prioritize an individual&apos;s relation-<lb/>ship with a collective.11 <lb/>Liang points out that China&apos;s ancient ethics, primarily based on the five cardi-<lb/>nal relationships, were overly narrow. While familial ethics (e.g., parent-child, <lb/>sibling bonds) were well-developed, social ethics were reduced to friendship, <lb/>and national ethics limited to ruler-subject dynamics. He attributes this imbal-<lb/>ance to a cultural overemphasis on private morality at the expense of public <lb/>morality in the sense that relationships between individuals were prioritized <lb/>over an individual&apos;s obligations towards groups. For Liang, public morality, <lb/>defined as collective consciousness, along with the individual&apos;s ethical duties <lb/>towards the collective, was the cornerstone of modern statehood. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>9 <lb/>Liang Qichao, Xinmin shuo, 19. <lb/>10 <lb/>Ibid., 19. <lb/>11 <lb/>Ibid., 17. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>116 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Chen <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>According to Liang, traditional Chinese moral education primarily focused <lb/>on cultivating private virtues while elements within traditional thought <lb/>actively discouraged the development of public ethics. This was so ingrained <lb/>that it became habitual, leaving the people ignorant of public morality and its <lb/>accompanying obligations. Though ancient China did possess forms of public <lb/>virtues, Liang argues these were primarily reserved for scholar-officials rather <lb/>than the common people. While the scholar-official culture undoubtedly influ-<lb/>enced the broader society, Liang himself does not fully explore those nuances. <lb/>His central argument is that citizens must recognize their obligations to the <lb/>society and the nation, contributing to communal welfare rather than merely <lb/>enjoying its benefits without assuming responsibility. When defining the core <lb/>components of public morality in Xinmin shuo, Liang highlights concepts <lb/>such as national consciousness, a spirit of progress, and awareness of rights. <lb/>Theoretically, however, this framing conflated moral principles with socio-<lb/>political concepts. These concepts generally do not fall under the domain of <lb/>morality. By labeling such ideas and values as &quot;public morality,&quot; Liang creates a <lb/>certain degree of theoretical ambiguity. <lb/>3 <lb/>Liu Shipei&apos;s Ethical Thought <lb/>Liu Shipei 劉師培 (1884-1919) posits that, in ethics, &quot;the individual self should <lb/>be taken as the subject, and the family, society, and state as objects; hence <lb/>self-cultivation stands foremost in the study of ethics.&quot;12 He further uses the <lb/>classical text Yaodian 堯典 to articulate his point. Within this text, he identifies <lb/>three ethical dimensions: familial ethics, embodied in the ideal of &quot;creating <lb/>harmony and unity among clan members&quot;; social ethics, exemplified by the <lb/>action to &quot;evaluate all officials, and commend those who exhibit virtuous con-<lb/>duct&quot;; and ethics pertaining to the self, articulated through virtues like &quot;upright <lb/>yet gentle, magnanimous yet dignified, firm without being harsh, and simple <lb/>without being arrogant.&quot; Liu&apos;s method of analysis aligns with the modern <lb/>Western ethical distinction between &quot;duties to oneself&quot; and &quot;duties to others.&quot; <lb/>In Liu&apos;s view, Confucian ethics from the Qin (221-207 BCE) and Han <lb/>(206 BCE-220 CE) dynasties onwards can be divided into two schools: the <lb/>Self-Cultivation School and the Mutual-Benefit School. The former: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>12 <lb/>Liu Shipei 劉師培, Jingxue jiaokeshu Lunli jiaokeshu 經學教科書 倫理教科書 (Yangzhou: <lb/>Guangling shushe, 2016), 128. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>117 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">PRIORITIZING PUBLIC MORALITY OVER PRIVATE MORALITY <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>holds clarifying one&apos;s mind and putting one&apos;s nature into practice [min-<lb/>gxin jianxing 明心見性] as its core principle, emphasizes correcting one&apos;s <lb/>faults [gaiguo 改過] and cultivating vigilance in solitude [shendu 慎獨], <lb/>and advocates upholding righteousness and illuminating the Way [zhen-<lb/>gyi mingdao 正誼明道] without seeking personal gain or calculating <lb/>results.13 <lb/>whereas the Mutual-Benefit School: <lb/>centers on benevolence and magnanimity [renshu 仁恕], aspired towards <lb/>the Great Unity [datong 大同], and embraces the ethos of regarding all <lb/>people as siblings and all things as companions [minbao wuyu 民胞物與], <lb/>thereby removing the boundaries between self and others.14 <lb/>Liu postulates that &quot;the Self-Cultivation School addresses ethics of the self, <lb/>while the Mutual-Benefit School focuses on the ethics applied to others,&quot; <lb/>suggesting that &quot;integrating both schools would enable the study of ethics to <lb/>progress from knowledge to actual practice.&quot;15 <lb/>In the second volume of his textbook Lunli jiaokeshu 倫理教科書, devoted <lb/>to familial ethics and social ethics, Liu argues that ever since antiquity, the <lb/>Chinese have possessed only private morality without any form of public <lb/>morality. They regard themselves primarily as members of the family, and aside <lb/>from filial piety and fraternal duty, they recognize no other moral obligations. <lb/>Beyond the familial sphere, no obligations are acknowledged. Yet Liu also <lb/>concedes that there are elements of ancient Chinese ethics not confined to <lb/>familial boundaries. For instance, Gongyang zhuan 公羊傳 states, &quot;One should <lb/>not refuse royal duties on account of family matters,&quot; where &quot;royal duties&quot; sig-<lb/>nifies affairs of the nation. When weighed against the state, the family remains <lb/>secondary in importance. <lb/>In his discussion of the father-son ethical relationship, Liu Shipei adopts <lb/>a dual perspective. On the one hand, he stresses that parental care and filial <lb/>piety constitute reciprocal duties between fathers and sons; on the other hand, <lb/>he criticizes the Confucian view that &quot;all children had to fulfill their duties <lb/>only to their parents, not to society or the state,&quot;16 which undermined pub-<lb/>lic morality. Yet Liu acknowledges exceptions even within orthodox texts. For <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 <lb/>Ibid., 132. <lb/>14 <lb/>Ibid., 132. <lb/>15 <lb/>Ibid., 132. <lb/>16 <lb/>Ibid., 209. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>118 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Chen <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>instance, Xiaojing 孝經 asserts that &quot;Establish yourself in the world and follow <lb/>the Way, so that your reputation may endure for future generations, and this <lb/>is the ultimate goal of filial piety.&quot; From this, Liu deduces that &quot;fulfilling ethical <lb/>responsibilities to the society and the state also constitutes one aspect of filial <lb/>piety.&quot;17 In his book, he writes: &quot;When comparing the nation with the family, <lb/>the nation is more important than the family … Thus, the line between the <lb/>public and the private must be clearly distinguished.&quot;18 In the conclusion of his <lb/>section on familial ethics, he contends, &quot;The dominance of familial ideology is <lb/>the reason behind under-development national and social ethics in China.&quot;19 <lb/>In Liu&apos;s textbook, the nineteenth lesson, &quot;Lun gongsi zhi jie shuo&quot; 論公私之 <lb/>界說, marks the beginning of his discussion on social ethics. Here, Liu posits <lb/>that familial ethics belong to the realm of private morality, and only social eth-<lb/>ics constitute public morality. He argues that wherever a public consciousness <lb/>is present, public morality will naturally emerge. He cites a Neo-Confucian <lb/>maxim &quot;regarding the people as siblings and all things as companions&quot; and <lb/>asks, &quot;Is this not the very essence of social ethics?&quot; lamenting that &quot;in recent <lb/>times, however, the Chinese people have neglected public morality, and few <lb/>pay attention to social ethics.&quot;20 This indicates that social ethics indeed exist in <lb/>Chinese culture, one that pertains to public morality by relating the individual <lb/>to the collective or the private to the public. <lb/>Liu traces the decline of public morality to the evolution of autocratic gov-<lb/>ernance since the Ming (1368-1644)-Qing (1616-1911) period, which corroded <lb/>communal ethics, and points out that &quot;the scourge of autocracy lies in its dis-<lb/>solution of collective life among the people, which is the primary cause for <lb/>citizens&apos; disregard of public morality.&quot;21 As a result, the people place little value <lb/>on public morality, rendering social ethics difficult to practice. <lb/>In the twentieth lesson of the same book, &quot;Lun Zhongguo shehui lunli bu <lb/>fada zhi yuanyin&quot; 論中國社會倫理不發達之原因, Liu reviews &quot;partisan disas-<lb/>ters&quot; throughout China&apos;s dynasty history and suggests that during the Han, <lb/>Song (960-1279), and Ming dynasties, the state&apos;s interest generally took prece-<lb/>dence over private gain, whereas the Jin (265-420) and Tang (618-907) periods <lb/>saw rampant political factionalism, where self-serving agendas overshadowed <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>17 <lb/>Ibid., 209-10. <lb/>18 <lb/>Ibid., 210. <lb/>19 <lb/>Ibid., 237. <lb/>20 <lb/>Ibid., 239. <lb/>21 <lb/>Ibid., 240. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>119 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">PRIORITIZING PUBLIC MORALITY OVER PRIVATE MORALITY <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>concerns for national welfare. At the close of this lesson, Liu invokes classical <lb/>texts to critique the erosion of public morality in contemporary China: <lb/>As Liji 禮記 states, &quot;When seated alongside others, do not extend your <lb/>elbows outward.&quot; Ancient proverbs likewise admonish: &quot;Do not damage <lb/>utensils while eating; do not break branches while resting in the shade.&quot; <lb/>These are manifestations of public morality. Yet today, the Chinese <lb/>people, for trifling reasons, lack even a rudimentary sense of public <lb/>responsibility. They defile public roads, destroy shared greenery, jostle for <lb/>seats on boats and carriages, and engage in fraudulent business practices. <lb/>While seemingly trivial, these acts represent profound deficiencies in the <lb/>populace&apos;s virtue.22 <lb/>Liu further discusses benevolence (ren&apos;ai 仁愛), justice (zhengyi 正義), har-<lb/>mony (hemu 和睦), chivalry (yixia 義俠), the selection of friends (zejiao 擇交), <lb/>obedience ( fucong 服從), sincerity and trustworthiness (chengxin 誠信), main-<lb/>taining one&apos;s personal integrity ( jieshen 潔身), and one&apos;s ethical obligations <lb/>toward teachers, friends, and local communities (shiyou, xiangdang zhi lunli <lb/>師友、鄉黨之倫理). By categorizing virtues such as benevolence, righteous-<lb/>ness, and propriety under social ethics, Liu shows that ancient China was not <lb/>devoid of social morality and on the contrary contained abundant resources in <lb/>that regard. At the same time, Liu notes that modern Chinese, in attempting <lb/>to rectify this deficiency, also seek relevant resources within tradition, such as <lb/>the ideal of &quot;interconnectedness between self and others&quot; (renwo xiangtong <lb/>人我相通) and Confucius&apos;s vision of the Great Unity, in which &quot;people do not <lb/>cherish only their own parents, nor care only for their own children.&quot; While <lb/>acknowledging the philosophical depth of these teachings, he argues that <lb/>abstract moral principles alone are insufficient. Without foundational social <lb/>reforms, such ethics remain superficial. <lb/>4 <lb/>Ma Junwu on Public Morality <lb/>Ma Junwu 馬君武 (1881-1940) published his essay &quot;Lun gongde&quot; 論公德 just a <lb/>year after Liang Qichao&apos;s discourse on public morality in Xinmin shuo. It served <lb/>as both a response to Liang and a critique of traditional Chinese society. He <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>22 <lb/>Ibid., 242. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>120 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Chen <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>claims, &quot;The so-called private morality of Chinese has been more than suffi-<lb/>cient to produce docile, subservient slaves, but inadequate for cultivating lively <lb/>and enterprising citizens.&quot;23 For Ma, China&apos;s so-called private morality was <lb/>incapable of cultivating modern national virtues. <lb/>In distinguishing between public and private morality, Ma seems to contend <lb/>that national ethics has both private and public dimensions, with the former <lb/>ideally characterized by vitality and enterprise. He further asserts, &quot;Indeed, pri-<lb/>vate morality is the root of public morality,&quot;24 which at first appears to echo <lb/>Liang Qichao&apos;s 1903 view on private morality, but their premises diverge signifi-<lb/>cantly. According to Liang, even though the Chinese possessed private morality <lb/>without much emphasis on public morality, the latter could be developed <lb/>by extending the former. By contrast, Ma argues that China&apos;s lack of public <lb/>morality does not stem solely from insufficient application of private morality; <lb/>rather, it arises because private morality itself is under-developed. <lb/>What, then, does Ma Junwu mean by &quot;private morality&quot;? In his assess-<lb/>ment, traditional Chinese notions of private morality fail to promote a love <lb/>of honor, rights, and freedom. Consequently, public morality cannot flourish. <lb/>He concludes, &quot;If one regards mere self-restraint, the avoidance of wrongdo-<lb/>ing, self-cultivation, and cultivation of vigilance in solitude as proof of a fully <lb/>realized private morality, that is merely the private morality of a slave state, <lb/>not a free nation.&quot;25 This argument appears plausible on the surface, but is <lb/>in fact misleading. As Liang noted, values like rights and freedom align more <lb/>closely with public morality, not private virtue. Based on Liang&apos;s arguments, <lb/>China was not entirely devoid of public morality but merely lacked its modern <lb/>forms. In contrast, Ma claims that China lacked even a foundational mod-<lb/>ern private morality, necessitating a complete renewal, a moral revolution and <lb/>transformation. <lb/>Could one then argue that private and public morality each have ancient <lb/>and modern forms? While it is plausible to suggest that there is some conti-<lb/>nuity between ancient and modern private morality, modern public morality <lb/>indeed departs significantly from its traditional counterpart. Ma, however, <lb/>does not draw such a distinction. He instead remarks: <lb/>The citizens of our country in antiquity were, in fact, not devoid of public <lb/>morality. This is supported by historical accounts, which describe King <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>23 <lb/>Ma Junwu 馬君武, &quot;Lun gongde&quot; 論公德, in Ma Junwu wenxuan 馬君武文選, ed. Zeng <lb/>Degui 曾德珪 (Guilin: Guangxi shifan daxue chubanshe, 2000), 189. <lb/>24 <lb/>Ibid., 189-90. <lb/>25 <lb/>Ibid., 189-90. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>121 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">PRIORITIZING PUBLIC MORALITY OVER PRIVATE MORALITY <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>Wen of the Western Zhou 周文王 period as having maintained a hunting <lb/>ground extending seventy li 里 in each direction, yet choosing to joyously <lb/>share it with the populace. Another record states that during his reign, <lb/>farmers ceded their field boundaries to each other, travelers stepped <lb/>aside to allow others to pass, and the elderly were spared the burden of <lb/>carrying heavy loads on the road. <lb/>Ma interprets these as evidence of well-developed public morality in the <lb/>Western Zhou era (1046-771 BCE), arguing that such ethics gradually declined <lb/>over time. Yet, Ma&apos;s reasoning falters, because his concept of &quot;national public <lb/>morality&quot; could not have existed under a feudal system where the very notion <lb/>of a &quot;citizenry&quot; was absent. That said, a form of public morality beyond indi-<lb/>vidual concerns did exist in ancient China. Ma&apos;s essay lacks logical precision, <lb/>and his primary concern does not appear to be political or &quot;slave&quot; morality. <lb/>Rather, as Chen Ruoshui 陳弱水 suggests, Ma&apos;s concern lies primarily in social <lb/>morality -namely, ethics pertaining to the public sphere and communal life.26 <lb/>5 <lb/>Zhang Taiyan on Revolutionary Morality <lb/>According to Zhang Taiyan 章太炎 (1869-1936), the fundamental reason behind <lb/>the Han Chinese&apos;s subjugation under Manchu rule and its prolonged inabil-<lb/>ity to &quot;recover its sovereignty&quot; did not lie in the harms stemming from Song <lb/>or Han learning, but rather in the decline of morality. Thus, those commit-<lb/>ted to revolutionary endeavors today must give priority to morality, without <lb/>which they will fail to rally the nation.27 For Zhang, beyond the so-called &quot;great <lb/>virtues&quot; and &quot;public morality,&quot; &quot;minor virtues&quot; and &quot;private morality&quot; must <lb/>not be overlooked. Without moral vigilance, individuals would succumb to <lb/>opportunism, &quot;giving free rein to their emotions and desires, and ultimately <lb/>bringing about destruction and decay.&quot; In his view, public morality is rooted <lb/>in private morality. Zhang further argues that morality recognizes no distinc-<lb/>tion between &quot;great&quot; and &quot;small,&quot; or &quot;public&quot; and &quot;private.&quot; Emphasizing the <lb/>functional importance of morality, Zhang asserts that China lacks not strategic <lb/>acumen but rather moral principles. In his view, an individual who possesses <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>26 <lb/>Chen Ruoshuo 陳弱水, Gongong yishi yu Zhongguo wenhua 公共意識與中國文化 <lb/>(Beijing: Xinxing chubanshe, 2006), 110. <lb/>27 <lb/>Zhang Yong 張勇, &quot;&apos;Daode&apos; yu &apos;geming&apos;: Xinmin wanbao yu Minbao shiqi Liang Rengong yu <lb/>Zhang Taiyan de &apos;daode&apos; jiaoshe&quot; &quot;道德&quot;與&quot;革命&quot;-《新民晚報》與《民報》時 <lb/>期梁任公與章太炎的&quot;道德&quot;交涉, Zhongguo xueshu 中國學術 33: 125. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>122 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Chen <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>sound private morality will also possess sound public morality. In other words, <lb/>the strength of a person&apos;s public morality is determined by the depth of their <lb/>private morality. <lb/>These views closely resemble Liang Qichao&apos;s theory of private morality <lb/>in &quot;Lun side&quot; 論私德. Another element in Zhang&apos;s essay &quot;Geming zhi daode&quot; <lb/>革命之道德 that attracted the attention of later scholars is his approach of <lb/>using occupation as a basis for assessing one&apos;s moral virtue. For Zhang, ethical <lb/>standards vary from profession to profession. He classifies society into sixteen <lb/>occupational categories: &quot;farmers, laborers, vendors, shopkeepers, scholars, <lb/>artisans, intellectuals, soldiers, low-level officials, advisors, merchant-officials, <lb/>capital bureaucrats, provincial officials, military officers, appointed function-<lb/>aries, and hired translators.&quot;28 Zhang believes that those engaging in farming, <lb/>labor, and artistic or technical professions generally uphold moral integrity, <lb/>whereas officials and merchants are prone to moral corruption. His conclu-<lb/>sion that greater knowledge correlates with lesser morality and higher rank <lb/>with deeper moral decay reflects a populist ethos, which resonates in certain <lb/>ways with the ideologies of the Cultural Revolution era. Nonetheless, Zhang&apos;s <lb/>emphasis on private morality remains central to his ethical philosophy. <lb/>6 <lb/>Xu Teli on Public Morality <lb/>In 1950, Xu Teli 徐特立 (1877-1968), a teacher of Mao Zedong 毛澤東 (1893-<lb/>1976), authored an essay titled &quot;Lun guomin gongde&quot; 論國民公德. As an <lb/>educator, Xu evidently took it upon himself to elaborate on Mao&apos;s concept of <lb/>&quot;five loves&quot; (wu&apos;ai 五愛) regarding public morality. He notes, &quot;Mao Zedong&apos;s <lb/>conception of morality does not emphasize personal private virtue but rather <lb/>focuses on political relationships.&quot;29 Xu concurs with Mao&apos;s understanding, <lb/>while also stressing the importance of those aspects of private morality that <lb/>influence political life or public morality. <lb/>This view is significant not only because it stresses political meaning in the <lb/>realm of moral issues, but also because it sheds light on Mao&apos;s perspective <lb/>underpinning the Common Program of the Chinese People&apos;s Political Consul-<lb/>tative Conference (CPPCC), which speaks only of civic morality and does not <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>28 <lb/>Zhang Binglin 章炳麟, &quot;Geming zhi daode&quot; 革命之道德, in Zhang Taiyan zhenglun <lb/>xuanji 章太炎政論選集, ed. Tang Zhijun 湯志鈞 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 1977), 1: <lb/>314-18. <lb/>29 <lb/>Xu Teli 徐特立, &quot;Lun guomin gongde&quot; 論國民公德, in Xu Teli wenji 徐特立文集 <lb/>(Changsha: Hunan renmin chubanshe, 1980), 437. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>123 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">PRIORITIZING PUBLIC MORALITY OVER PRIVATE MORALITY <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
    
    <body>&gt;mention individual private virtue. Indeed, Mao Zedong&apos;s stance profoundly <lb/>influenced the development of moral education in the ensuing decades of <lb/>the People&apos;s Republic of China. Yet Xu Teli&apos;s essay does not directly address <lb/>why the Common Program &quot;establishes public morality for all citizens without <lb/>stipulating individual private virtue.&quot; He merely observes that Mao placed little <lb/>importance on personal private virtue. <lb/>Following this statement, Xu&apos;s discussion focuses primarily on the idea that <lb/>a person&apos;s morality is shaped by changes in social development, which seems <lb/>to imply that private morality will naturally evolve in tandem with societal <lb/>change. If social reforms are successfully implemented, individual moral char-<lb/>acter will also improve. He further supports this view through examples of <lb/>the Great Revolution, the Land Revolution, and the Anti-Japanese National <lb/>Revolution. In regions where social relations are restructured, measures such <lb/>as rents and interest reduction and equal land distribution are employed, and <lb/>broad-based people&apos;s democracy is promoted, both social customs and indi-<lb/>vidual morality witnessed unprecedented transformation.30 Xu&apos;s underlying <lb/>argument is that to discuss personal morality apart from social reform is not <lb/>only misguided, but even &quot;entirely reactionary.&quot;31 <lb/>7 <lb/>Post-1949 Conceptualizations of Public Morality <lb/>Following the establishment of the People&apos;s Republic of China, moral dis-<lb/>course became institutionalized under the leadership of the Party and the <lb/>state. Accordingly, rather than examining individual interpretations, this <lb/>section looks to the National Constitution and Party documents to explore <lb/>understandings of public and private morality in the current era. <lb/>The 1954 Constitution mandated that citizens must uphold social moral-<lb/>ity, including the &quot;five loves,&quot; namely love for the motherland, the people, <lb/>labor, science, and public property. This legally enshrined the &quot;five loves&quot; as <lb/>principles of national public morality. In practice, however, these belonged to <lb/>political morality, which was positioned above social morality understood as <lb/>general public ethics. The 1982 Constitution revised the &quot;five loves&quot; to &quot;love for <lb/>the motherland, the people, labor, science, and socialism,&quot; further politicizing <lb/>public morality while sidelining advocacy for personal morality. Notably absent <lb/>were references to Chinese cultural traditions or traditional virtues, demon-<lb/>strating a trend in which political morality overshadowed social morality. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>30 <lb/>Ibid., 438. <lb/>31 <lb/>Ibid., 438. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>124 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Chen <lb/></note>
      
      <note place="footnote">Journal of chinese humanities 11 (2025) 109-124 <lb/></note>
      
      <body>Subsequent constitutional amendments retained this emphasis, demonstrat-<lb/>ing that the constitutional stance on civic morality has remained unchanged <lb/>despite evolving social realities. <lb/>In conclusion, this article, from an ethical and moral philosophical perspec-<lb/>tive, centers on fundamental personal morality and argues that the paramount <lb/>issue in modern Chinese moral discourse is the ascendancy of political moral-<lb/>ity that has replaced, suppressed, and even abolished personal morality, while <lb/>also neglecting social morality. This imbalance among political, social, and <lb/>individual morality demands redress. To rethink contemporary moral dis-<lb/>course in China, it is imperative to restore the independence and significance <lb/>of personal morality, while actively cultivating a culture of social morality. <lb/></body>
    
    <front>Translated by Epperly Zhang </front>


	</text>


  
  </TEI>