<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">The Covent Garden Old Price Riots: Protest and Justice in Late‑Georgian London</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>James William</forename>
          <surname>Baker</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-22T21:20:14.868Z">22/12/2025 21:20:14</date>
        <title>Review Luca</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.16995__olh.13</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Open Library of the Humanities</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2016</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.16995/olh.13</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>James William Baker. (2016). The Covent Garden Old Price Riots: Protest and Justice in Late‑Georgian London. Open Library of Humanities, 2(1), 4. DOI: 10.16995/olh.13</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-28T13:58:03.095049Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-28T13:58:03.095049Z" status="extraction">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-11T11:25:20.677Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Final_Final_Version</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-22T09:32:48.894Z" status="checked" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Review Kazuyo</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-22T21:20:14.868Z" status="approved" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Review Luca</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Article <lb/>How to Cite: Baker, J 2016 The Covent Garden Old Price Riots: Protest <lb/>and Justice in Late-Georgian London. Open Library of Humanities, 2(1): e4, <lb/>pp. 1-36, DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.16995/olh.13 <lb/>Published: 24 February 2016 <lb/>Peer Review: <lb/>This article has been peer reviewed through the double-blind process of Open Library of Humanities, <lb/>which is a journal published by the Open Library of Humanities. <lb/>Copyright: <lb/>© 2016 The Author(s). This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC-BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distri-<lb/>bution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. See <lb/>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>Open Access: <lb/>Open Library of Humanities is a peer-reviewed open access journal. <lb/>Digital Preservation: <lb/>The Open Library of Humanities and all its journals are digitally preserved in the CLOCKSS scholarly <lb/>archive service. <lb/>James Baker, &apos;The Covent Garden Old Price Riots: Protest and <lb/>Justice in Late-Georgian London&apos; (2016) 2(1): e4 Open Library of <lb/>Humanities, DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.16995/olh.13 <lb/></front><!-- The header / footer of the first page (or the first two pages, if the header is 2 pages long should be in <front>) -->
					
					
					<front>ARTICLE <lb/>The Covent Garden Old Price Riots: Protest <lb/>and Justice in Late-Georgian London <lb/>James Baker 1 <lb/>1 School of History, Art History and Philosophy, University of Sussex, UK <lb/>james.baker@sussex.ac.uk <lb/>This article explores perceptions of the law and of how agents of the law <lb/>responded to events at Covent Garden Theatre during the bitter months <lb/>between mid-October and late-November 1809, the height of the Covent <lb/>Garden Old Price riots. It does so through the lens of the periodical press, a <lb/>vital and voluminous source of not only what happened during the riots but <lb/>also of opinions on what happened and of perceptions of what happened, <lb/>opinions and perceptions that are the primary concern of this article. The <lb/>article begins with a discussion of how the magistrates, &apos;police officers,&apos; <lb/>justices, and lawyers who together were agents of the legal system were <lb/>seen, where they were seen, and what they did. It moves on to examine how <lb/>the actions of those agents and the legal system they represented were <lb/>reported upon. And it concludes with a discussion of how theatregoers and <lb/>Londoners were seen to have responded to those actions, moving a signifi-<lb/>cant element of the conflict outside of Covent Garden Theatre and into the <lb/>public press in a direct response to how they were policed as threats to <lb/>public order and security. It argues that the Covent Garden Old Price riots <lb/>was a significant urban act of multi-class protest because of the ways that <lb/>it intersected with wider late-Georgian concerns, with discursive arenas <lb/>where British liberty and the freedom of her subjects were contested and <lb/>at stake. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>On 18 October 1809, a letter signed by &apos;MINIMUS&apos; appeared in the Morning Chronicle <lb/>newspaper, a London daily. It was one month since a rebuilt Covent Garden Thea-<lb/>tre had reopened, an event that had been met in the nights thereafter with riotous <lb/>opprobrium from sections of London&apos;s populace. The letter, as so many had since <lb/>the Covent Garden Old Price riots began, concerned the ongoing dispute between <lb/>&apos;the Public and the Management of Covent-Garden Theatre.&apos; As the name &apos;Old Price&apos; <lb/>suggests, the riots were sparked by the dissatisfaction of London&apos;s theatregoers with <lb/>the new price of admission to the theatre. As had been the case throughout the <lb/>long eighteenth century, these theatregoers believed in the common ownership of <lb/>theatre prices. 1 The price of admission to Covent Garden Theatre was especially sig-<lb/>nificant because it was one of only two royal patent theatres sanctioned to stage <lb/>five-act spoken word drama within Westminster, even though, in reality, the Lord <lb/>Chamberlain&apos;s jurisdiction extended to the whole of London and its environs. 2 As <lb/>Drury Lane, the other part of this patent duopoly, had burnt down on 24 February <lb/>1809, the situation in mid-September was that the only patent theatre available to <lb/>theatregoers was the reopened Covent Garden Theatre and that the barrier to enter-<lb/>ing this theatre had increased. <lb/>By the time MINIMUS wrote to the Morning Chronicle, the supporters of Old <lb/>Prices (commonly known as &apos;OPs&apos;) had developed a panoply of complaints against <lb/>the beleaguered Covent Garden Theatre management. These included an architec-<lb/>tural redistribution of the theatre with new private boxes for the wealthy offset by a <lb/>restricted and remodelled one-shilling gallery for the less well-off, the suspicion that <lb/>the management had hired Jewish pugilists to suppress the nightly riots inside the <lb/>theatre, the selection of expensive foreign actors as lead players, claims of financial <lb/>mismanagement and embezzlement, the heavy-handedness of the Bow Street &apos;Police&apos; <lb/>called in to handle disturbances, and the criminal charges brought against OPs for <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 For the moral economy of theatre pricing, see an entry into James Boswell&apos;s journal (F. Pottle [ed.], <lb/>Boswell&apos;s London Journal, 1762-3 [New Haven, 1950], 219) where a pseudo-fictional &apos; citizen&apos; of Child&apos;s <lb/>coffee-house muses &apos;I remember when the common price of new plays was sixpence, and no more.&apos; <lb/>2 R. D. Hume, &apos;Theatre as Property in Eighteenth-Century London,&apos; Journal for Eighteenth Century Stud-<lb/>ies 31.1 (2008); H. McPherson, &apos;Theatrical Riots&apos; and Cultural Politics in Eighteenth-Century London,&apos; <lb/>The Eighteenth Century 43.3 (2002); D. Worrall, Theatric Revolution: Drama, Censorship and Romantic <lb/>Period Subcultures, 1773-1832 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2006), pp. 33-102. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>such spurious crimes as having sung, whistled, or sneezed during a performance. In <lb/>short, the OPs were, by 18 October, rioting not because of an increase in admission <lb/>price by itself but rather because of a perceived affront to their freedoms and asso-<lb/>ciated customary rights as &apos;Free-Born Englishmen.&apos; 3 They were loyalists rather than <lb/>radicals, pragmatists rather than theoreticians affronted, as they saw it, by the actions <lb/>of a theatre management in league both with agents of state justice and with wealthy <lb/>elites. <lb/>However, MINIMUS did not, as many OPs had and would, use his letter to address <lb/>these issues directly. Instead his purpose was to share with the public a passage from <lb/>the farce Eurydice Hiss&apos;d, written circa 1740 &apos;by that able Lawyer, upright Magistrate, <lb/>and learned man, Henry Fielding, Esq. who was at the time he wrote it an eminent <lb/>Barrister, and afterwards placed at the head of the Police of the City of Westminster.&apos; <lb/>The selected passage reads thus: <lb/>DRAMATUS PERSONA <lb/>PILLAGE, the Manager. -HONESTUS <lb/>PILLAGE -O, on me ye Gods bestow the pence, <lb/>And give your fame to any fools you please! <lb/>HONESTUS -Your love of pence sufficiently you show, <lb/>By raising still your prices on the Town. <lb/>PIL -The Town for their own sakes those prices pay, <lb/>Which the additional expenses demands. <lb/>HON -In former times, <lb/>When better Actors acted better Plays, <lb/>The Town paid less. <lb/></body>
				
				<listBibl>3 The concept of the &apos;Free-Born Englishman&apos; has a long heritage, stretching back to the seventeenth <lb/>century and the Levellers. It was revived in 1790s in response to restrictions to freedom and ero-<lb/>sions of privacy imposed on Britons as a consequence of the French Revolutionary Wars, not least <lb/>the suspension of habeus corpus in 1794. See J. Barrell, The Spirit of Despotism: Invasions of Privacy <lb/>in the 1790s (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2006); G, Cruikshank, A FREE BORN ENGLISHMAN! <lb/>THE ADMIRATION OF THE WORLD!!! AND THE ENVY OF SURROUNDING NATIONS!!!!! (1819; British <lb/>Museum Satires 13287A); B. Hilton, A Mad, Bad, and Dangerous People?: England 1783-1846 (Oxford: <lb/>Oxford University Press, 2006), pp. 65-74. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>PIL -We have more actors now. <lb/>HON -Ay, many more, I&apos;m certain, than you need, <lb/>Make your additional expence apparent. <lb/>Let it appear quite necessary too, <lb/>And then perhaps they&apos;ll grumble not to pay. <lb/>PIL -What is a Manager whom the Public rule? <lb/>HON -The servant of the Public, and no more; <lb/>For tho&apos; indeed you see the Actors paid, <lb/>Yet from the people&apos;s pockets come the pence; <lb/>They therefore should decide what they <lb/>Will pay for. <lb/>[Exit HONESTUS] <lb/>PILLAGE, Solo -I wish I could have gain&apos;d one honest <lb/>Man over to my side ----------<lb/>But since the attempt is vain, <lb/>Numbers must serve for worth: the vessel sails <lb/>With equal rapid fury and success, <lb/>Borne by the foulest tide as clearest stream. <lb/>Every OP would have understood this choice of passage and could have related to <lb/>its focus on prices and pay, on managerial extravagance and profiteering, on conflict <lb/>over the &apos; ownership&apos; of theatrical space. As MINIMUS himself noted with a hint of <lb/>self-congratulation it was &apos;so applicable to the point at issue&apos; not only with regards <lb/>to what it had said but who had said it. That MINIMUS chose to quote a &apos;Lawyer, [...] <lb/>Magistrate, [...], Barrister, and [...] head of the Police,&apos; and one of such esteem, sug-<lb/>gests that the law and those charged with its defence were integral to the discourses <lb/>that surrounded the Covent Garden Old Price riots. 4 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>4 Henry and his elder brother John Fielding were both well known figures for their roles as magistrates, <lb/>indeed Henry has established the Bow Street office in 1749. See J. M. Beattie, The First English Detec-<lb/>tives: The Bow Street Runners and the Policing of London, 1750-1840 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, <lb/>2012); J. White, London in the Eighteenth Century: a Great and Monstrous Thing (London: Bodley Head, <lb/>2012), pp. 424-465. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Letters addressing the events at Covent Garden Theatre were published in news-<lb/>papers throughout autumn-winter 1809 and continued until after the cessation of <lb/>hostilities in January 1810. They were published because readers were fascinated <lb/>with the Covent Garden Old Price riots, sixty-seven nights of protest often collec-<lb/>tively referred to as the OP war. This demand is evident in the response of the major <lb/>London dailies (Morning Chronicle, Morning Post, The Times) and weeklies (Examiner), <lb/>who, catering for diverse metropolitan and provincial opinions, responded to these <lb/>outbursts of collective action in a timely and voluminous manner. 5 Reports from the <lb/>theatre, the Bow Street magistrates, other judicial venues or the streets appeared in <lb/>most issues and related notices, advertisements, and letters from both readers and the <lb/>Covent Garden Theatre management were just as common. News of events at Covent <lb/>Garden Theatre was not restricted to the capital. Old Price riots-inspired tumult <lb/>reached Chester and Birmingham in October 1809 and Edinburgh&apos;s Caledonian <lb/>Mercury published semi-regular summary reports on the riots. 6 Nevertheless, it was <lb/>in London that the riots and accompanying reportage were most prominent. <lb/>The wealth of newspaper reports surrounding the OP riots is contrasted sharply <lb/>with the paucity of official accounts. A complete loss of the records compiled at <lb/>Bow Street means that periodical sources are in most cases our only record of events <lb/>at the magistrates&apos; court during the riots. 7 The present article, therefore, presents <lb/></body>
				<listBibl>5 Hannah Barker&apos;s model of newspapers as commercial entities is useful here, for it helps to explain <lb/>why some newspapers carried varied, opposing, and often wholly contradictory opinions on the OP <lb/>war within their pages (even if their editorial lines remained consistent). In sum, the discursive busi-<lb/>ness of newspaper proprietors (that beyond their role as forums for advertisements) was less to pur-<lb/>sue a polemical line and more to appeal to potential readers and purchasers of their newspapers; <lb/>H. Barker, Newspapers, Politics And English Society, 1695-1855 (Harlow: Longman, 2000). <lb/>6 For the former pair, see A. Aspinall (ed.) Dorothy Jordan, Mrs. Jordan and Her Family: Being the Unpub-<lb/>lished Correspondence of Mrs. Jordan and the Duke of Clarence, Later William IV (London: Arthur <lb/>Barker, 1951), pp. 118-120. <lb/>7 Beattie, First English Detectives. Though a significant loss, given the brevity of comparable records <lb/>(see Greg Thomas [ed.], Summary Justice in the City: A Selection of Cases Heard at the Guildhall Justice <lb/>Room, 1752-1781 [London: London Record Society, 2013]) and that Bow Street encouraged lengthy <lb/>press reports of its proceedings, the lost case notes may well have amounted to only short summaries. <lb/>In addition to evidence in newspapers, publications on the OP riots did appear after the cessation of <lb/>hostilities, notable among which is Thomas Tegg&apos;s The Rise, Progress, and Termination of the O. P. War, <lb/>in Poetic Epistles (London: Thomas Tegg, 1810). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>findings from a detailed survey of newspapers published in London during autumn <lb/>1809, in particular between mid-October and late-November, weeks characterised <lb/>by bitter struggle. Within these, disaggregating the fact, opinion, and perception <lb/>that the newspaper press traded in is fraught with danger. On those occasions when <lb/>newspapers are used as factual sources of events, I have made attempts to corrobo-<lb/>rate stories between contemporary newspapers and with the judgement of subse-<lb/>quent scholarship. However, even if the newspapers failed to capture with precision <lb/>all that happened during the Covent Garden Old Price riots, they nevertheless are <lb/>vital to reconstructing opinions and perceptions of the law and the legal system at <lb/>this time. <lb/>I The OP Riots in Scholarship <lb/>Scholars have cautiously explored these sources before and their use to explore <lb/>the Old Price riots is familiar to historians of English theatre in the long eighteenth <lb/>century. Marc Baer&apos;s book-length treatment of the conflict, Theatre and Disorder in <lb/>Late Georgian London, argues that the OP war is important because rioting Londoners <lb/>defeated fashionable elites, because of the substantial if restrained confrontational <lb/>spirit of the middle-class Londoners prominent in the campaign, and because the <lb/>conflict offered a prism through which contemporaries could shine light on wider <lb/>social ills. 8 Jane Moody, writing on the falling significance of patent theatres in the <lb/>late eighteenth-century, inserts the OP war into a narrative of public rejections of <lb/>legitimate theatre. 9 Yet, the volume and breadth of coverage allocated to the war by <lb/>London newspapers suggests it deserves greater historiographical attention than it <lb/>has received. Peter Spence, for example, draws the OPs into his history of &apos;Romantic <lb/>Radicalism,&apos; stresses their loyalism, and ponders how soon such a coordinated, <lb/>prolonged, and voluminously reported episode was quietly forgotten. 10 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>8 M. Baer, Theatre and Disorder in Late Georgian London (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1992). <lb/>9 J. Moody, Illegitimate Theatre in London, 1770-1840 (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000). <lb/>10 P. Spence, The Birth of Romantic Radicalism: War, Popular Politics, and English Radical Reformism, <lb/>1800-1815 (Aldershot: Ashfield, 1996). The conflict does not feature, for example, in either John Ste-<lb/>venson, Popular Disturbances in England, 1700-1870 (London: Longman, 1979) or John Stevenson, <lb/>Popular Disturbances in England, 1700-1832 (London: Longman, 1992). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>This wider scholarly inattention, Spence aside, can be partly explained by the <lb/>fact that the OP war was neither an isolated nor unprecedented theatre riot. Theatre <lb/>protest was intertwined with long eighteenth-century multi-class metropolitan <lb/>political expression and theatre-going in this period was not the passive, solemn <lb/>experience we take for granted today. In these lively, volatile metropolitan spaces the <lb/>justification for and exclusiveness of new theatre pricing regimes, the resentment <lb/>of theatre monopolies, and the suspicion of impositions along class lines had been <lb/>issues before. As Hannah McPherson writes, &apos;the precariousness of the social contract <lb/>between management and public&apos; was tested over forty years earlier during the 1763 <lb/>Half-Price Riots at Drury Lane and Covent Garden. 11 Earlier still, David Garrick was <lb/>forced to withdraw the 1755 Drury Lane Chinese Festival in response to riots in and <lb/>outside the theatre. 1743, 1750, 1770, and 1776 saw comparable, violent protests <lb/>at Drury Lane, throughout which theatregoers debated the value and purpose of <lb/>the patent system. McPherson concurs with Baer that long eighteenth-century thea-<lb/>tre audiences were microcosms of society and that the clashes between fashionable <lb/>elites and a multi-class public suspicious of novelty can be fruitfully projected back <lb/>onto wider London and -to a lesser extent -English society in this period. <lb/>Broadly speaking, I agree with this thesis. I expand on it by bringing much needed <lb/>attention to how agents of the legal system, broadly and loosely defined, were repre-<lb/>sented and responded to during this prolonged theatre riot, offering another thread <lb/>out of the world of public entertainments and into the more commonly experienced <lb/>world of public justice. <lb/>This is achieved by exploring newspaper evidence through considerations of pro-<lb/>test, space and policing. The Old Price riots were one of a panoply of events in the <lb/>long eighteenth-century when Britons turned to protest as a means of defending <lb/>customary constructions of liberty, physical and discursive acts that could, as Robert <lb/>Poole reminds us, elide form and argument. 12 In &apos;What happened to class?&apos; Katrina <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>11 McPherson, &apos;Theatrical Riots,&apos; 7. <lb/>12 R. Poole, &apos;The March to Peterloo: Politics and Festivity in Late Georgian England,&apos; Past and Present <lb/>192.1 (2006). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Navickas stresses the potential for reading collective action through the interaction <lb/>between elites and non-elites. 13 As the following makes clear, class interaction -in <lb/>particular a multi-class rejection of perceived elite chicanery -was a crucial feature <lb/>of the OP war. Moreover, the interactions between the theatre management, their <lb/>patrons, the legal establishment, and the London public tease at two further areas <lb/>Navickas seeks to bring to the centre of protest historians&apos; endeavours: those occa-<lb/>sions where collective action was a &apos;vibrant defence of common interests against the <lb/>perceived intrusion of private property and atomizing capitalism&apos; and the extent to <lb/>which policing practices shaped protest. 14 <lb/>The language of &apos;perceived intrusion[s]&apos; remind us that protests are inherently <lb/>spatial: lines are drawn, spaces are ascribed owners, places are reified. Prior to the <lb/>OP war, space had been controversially used at sites of public entertainment at the <lb/>whim of the aristocracy. Protests at the exclusive character of the 1784 Handel com-<lb/>memoration underscore the contemporary non-elite conception that theatres were <lb/>classless public spaces. 15 In Geographies of Exclusion, David Sibley examines the <lb/>socio-political connection between groups and spaces: &apos;spatial boundaries,&apos; he writes, <lb/>&apos; are in fact moral boundaries.&apos; 16 Sibley&apos;s discussion of how societies respond to acts <lb/>of border crossing, when one group moves beyond &apos;their&apos; domain -an imaginary <lb/>space with physical boundaries or signifiers of boundaries -and to border erection <lb/>(whether imaginary, symbolic, or physical) chime with the events at Covent Garden <lb/>Theatre in autumn 1809: the removal of the cheapest section of the house, the one <lb/>shilling gallery, to a &apos;pigeon hole&apos; on high; the expansion of private boxes and the <lb/>enclosure from prying eyes of areas only affordable to the elite; and the cessation <lb/>of sales of half-price tickets after the third act, a custom that had hitherto opened <lb/>up the theatre to a multitude -if not the very poorest -of Londoners and made <lb/>the space egalitarian in its usage. In short, many OPs who entered Covent Garden <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 K. Navickas, &apos;What happened to class? New histories of labour and collective action in Britain,&apos; Social <lb/>History 36.2 (2011). <lb/>14 Navickas, &apos;What happened to class?&apos; 201. <lb/>15 W. Weber, &apos;The 1784 Handel Commemoration as Political Ritual,&apos; Journal of British Studies 28 (1989). <lb/>16 D. Sibley, Geographies of Exclusion (London: Routledge, 1995), p. 39. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Theatre in late-September 1809 saw the new space as false, as abnormal. As Sibley <lb/>writes, &apos;the act of drawing a line in the construction of discrete categories interrupts <lb/>what is naturally continuous. It is by definition an arbitrary act and thus may be <lb/>seen as unjust by those who suffer the consequences of division.&apos; 17 In the suffering <lb/>eyes of the OPs, not only were the lines drawn before September 1809 natural and <lb/>lines drawn thereafter arbitrary, but those who had undertaken and supported the <lb/>redrawing -John Philip Kemble, the theatre management, urban elites, and the legal <lb/>establishment -were outsiders; or, to use Sibley&apos;s parlance, an &apos; out-group&apos; whose <lb/>boundary crossing and redrawing presented a threat to core values of the Covent <lb/>Garden crowd. Private boxes, for example, were novel, constructed zones of ambigu-<lb/>ity whose mechanics -private, hidden, aloof, seemingly beyond reproach -upset <lb/>values the OPs saw as central to London theatregoing, to see and to be seen in a <lb/>public theatre, open exchange, and the equality of all under the law. <lb/>To understand how policing shaped protest and how spatial politics intersected <lb/>with notions of legal equality, attitudes to enforcement and policing prior to the OP <lb/>war must be taken into account. The establishment of the Bow Street runners and <lb/>court in 1749-50 by Henry Fielding had a lasting impact on the reputation of metro-<lb/>politan policing. 18 Hitherto, thief-takers -individuals who solved crimes and restored <lb/>property in exchange for a reward -had been the visible expression of after-the-<lb/>fact legal enforcement in the capital. If corruption and clandestine activities among <lb/>thief-takers were rife, the pre-trial examinations before Bow Street magistrates <lb/>of individuals seized evolved, by contrast, into a public spectacle held in an open <lb/>court. 19 These examinations made ideal newspaper copy and that copy is, in turn, our <lb/>only substantive record of those examinations. In his analysis of how policing was <lb/>reported in London newspapers between 1747 and 1755, a crucial period in their <lb/>mutual development, Richard M. Ward argues that the newspapers established a <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>17 Sibley, Geographies of Exclusion, p. 35. <lb/>18 Beattie, First English Detectives; P. King, Crime, Justice, and Discretion in England, 1740-1820 (Oxford: <lb/>Oxford University Press, 2000); R. M. Ward, Print Culture, Crime and Justice in Eighteenth-Century <lb/>London (London: Bloomsbury, 2014), p. 145. <lb/>19 Ward, Print Culture, pp. 38-9, 152. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>strong relationship with these new agents of the legal system and, in turn, presented <lb/>a broadly positive image of their conduct, probity, and fairness until at least the end <lb/>of the century. 20 In contrast, reports, letters, and notices on the OP war published in <lb/>the newspaper press were characterised -on balance -by a sustained negative por-<lb/>trayal of the agents of the legal system. This does not undermine Ward&apos;s thesis: press <lb/>perceptions and public perceptions were not one and the same and prior to 1809 it <lb/>was not uncommon to find negative portrayals of policing in newspapers and other <lb/>forms of print. 21 Nevertheless, it is important to observe that published attitudes to <lb/>policing during the OP war run contra to the tenor -broadly speaking -of reports <lb/>just a decade or two earlier. <lb/>Finally, and in light of this observation, any investigation into opinions and per-<lb/>ceptions of the OP war must also consider the status of metropolitan policing at the <lb/>time of the OP war, in particular the Bow Street officers and patrol, at whose offices <lb/>so many OPs appeared in the autumn of 1809. As part of the machinery of criminal <lb/>justice, Bow Street was an instrument of state power. 22 This machinery was particu-<lb/>larly conspicuous in late-Georgian London, as radical reform movements -inspired <lb/>by the French Revolution -provoked alarm among the English political establish-<lb/>ment, alarm that manifested itself as efforts to preserve social order. This culminated <lb/>in the 1792 Middlesex Justices Act, which established seven public &apos;police&apos; offices <lb/>across the metropolis. Though these were modelled more or less on Bow Street, Bow <lb/>Street was not mentioned in the act and remained a separate entity. As the historian <lb/>John Beattie argues, in the years after 1792 the Home Office exploited the flexible <lb/>and informal standing of Bow Street to transform its function, funding new tasks <lb/>needed to head off the perceived threat of insurrection. 23 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>20 Ward, Print Culture, pp. 115, 141, 152-6. <lb/>21 An argument made in J. M. Beattie, Policing and Punishment in London, 1660-1750 (Oxford: Oxford <lb/>University Press, 2001). <lb/>22 See Joanna Innes and John Styles, &apos;The Crime Wave: Recent Wrtiing on Crime and Criminal Justice in <lb/>Eighteenth-Century England,&apos; Journal of British Studies 25 (1986), 380-435. <lb/>23 Beattie, First English Detectives, pp. 167-205. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>The Bow Street foot patrol, distinct in conception from the more investigative <lb/>and national Bow Street runners, was expanded. The foot patrol took on the role of <lb/>maintaining public order, of keeping the peace in the streets and at public gatherings <lb/>such as fairs and markets. It was these men, commonly -if erroneously -referred <lb/>to in newspapers as &apos; officers,&apos; who patrolled Covent Garden Theatre during the OP <lb/>war, arrested those who contravened a state influenced notion of public order, and <lb/>brought those arrested to Bow Street for examination. Moreover, the long-standing <lb/>relationship between Bow Street and the management of Covent Garden Theatre <lb/>should not be understated. Located on each other&apos;s doorstep, the theatre was the <lb/>largest place of public entertainments in Bow Street&apos;s area of traditional (if never-<lb/>formalised) jurisdiction and the organisational relationship between the two entities <lb/>was no doubt deepened by the royal security role Bow Street officers played after <lb/>1789, namely accompanying the king and royal family to places of public entertain-<lb/>ments, such as the royal patent theatres. More than any other of the new functions <lb/>that Bow Street undertook on behalf of a jittery Home Office after 1792, their polic-<lb/>ing of the OP war blended their roles as guardians of national security and guardians <lb/>of public order. The suspicion OPs came to hold towards the motives of Bow Street <lb/>suggest that negative portrayals of the agents of the legal system and these new roles <lb/>and functions of Bow Street circa 1809 were not unrelated. <lb/>It is in the context of these multiple scholarly traditions -of theatre history and <lb/>protest history, of human geography and the history of policing -that this article <lb/>explores where the law was seen to be visible, how it was reported upon, and how <lb/>its actions were responded to during the OP war. The article discusses how contem-<lb/>porary Londoners were said to have encountered the magistrates, &apos;police officers,&apos; <lb/>justices, and lawyers who together, however informally connected, were agents of <lb/>the legal system, where these agents were seen, and what they did. It moves on to <lb/>examine how the actions of those agents and the legal system they represented <lb/>were reported upon. It concludes with a discussion of how members of the public <lb/>responded to those actions. Drawing on contemporary periodicals for opinions on <lb/>and for perceptions of what happened, I argue that the Covent Garden Old Price riots <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>were a significant urban conflict because of the ways that the riots intersected with <lb/>wider late-Georgian concerns, with discursive arenas where the liberty of free-born <lb/>Englishmen and women were contested and at stake. <lb/>II Agents of the Legal System <lb/>At the completion of the programme of events planned for 18 September 1809, <lb/>two magistrates stood before the Covent Garden Theatre crowd. The rendition of <lb/>Macbeth offered by John Philip Kemble&apos;s troupe had been drowned out by the whis-<lb/>tles, shouts, calls, songs, and stamps of the paying audience. Magistrates Read and <lb/>Nabes were called the short distance from the Bow Street magistrates&apos; office to read <lb/>the Riot Act. The crowd did not disperse promptly and, as they had begun, closed <lb/>their performance with stirring renditions of &apos;God Save the King&apos; and &apos;Rule, Britan-<lb/>nia!&apos; As befitted such an occasion, the scene was captured by satirical artist-engravers <lb/>and sold in print shops across London. One design by Isaac Cruikshank and his son <lb/>George is as evocative as it is erroneous: a number of details -including the bells, <lb/>rattles, banners, and horns wielded by the theatre crowd were not seen until the <lb/>following night. 24 These fictions do not preclude the use of Cruikshank&apos;s design by <lb/>the historian. Cruikshank&apos;s intention to broadly represent sights common in the pit <lb/>both on and after the opening night highlights the visibility of officers of the law <lb/>during the OP conflict. This section explores that visibility, representations of agents <lb/>of the legal system during the OP war, the means by which those agents expressed <lb/>themselves, and their opinions on the disturbances at Covent Garden Theatre during <lb/>the autumn of 1809. <lb/>After the calamity of the opening night, Bow Street officers patrolled the corridors <lb/>of Covent Garden Theatre and continued to do so into the new year. 25 At the behest <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>24 I. Cruikshank and G. Cruikshank, ACTING MAGISTRATES committing themselves being their first <lb/>appearance on this stage as performed at the National Theatre Covent Garden. Sepr 18 1809 (1809; <lb/>British Museum Satires 11418). For the function of reportage in satirical prints published during the <lb/>OP War see J. Baker, &apos;The OP War, Libertarian Communication and Graphic Reportage in Georgian <lb/>London,&apos; European Comic Art 4.1 (2011). <lb/>25 Old Bailey Proceedings Online (www.oldbaileyonline.org, version 7.0), 21 February 1810, trial of Abra-<lb/>ham Hart and Edward White (t18100221-108). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the doorman, James Brandon, they were tasked with dealing with disturbances in <lb/>order to keep order. During the OP war, the sight of one of these men, or men from <lb/>other &apos;police&apos; offices, was the primary recorded interaction between Covent Garden <lb/>theatregoers and the legal system. For example, on Saturday, 11 November, Lewis <lb/>Vanduduce was arrested by &apos;Mr. Bell, the High Constable for the Holborn Division.&apos; 26 <lb/>The direct identification of the arresting officer here was an exception; rarely were <lb/>they named by newspapers and this partial anonymity had negative consequences. 27 <lb/>During times of heightened tension, such as in late-October 1809, suspicious OPs <lb/>questioned the identity of constables and elided them, by virtue of their actions, with <lb/>the independent and unscrupulous thief-takers thought to have been common in <lb/>the mid-eighteenth century. 28 <lb/>The second group of legal officials who regularly appeared at the theatre were <lb/>not there to arrest OPs, but to develop a rapport with them, and drum up busi-<lb/>ness, by addressing the audience from the pit and galleries on points of law. For <lb/>instance, following an address from Kemble on 20 September, an attorney and a <lb/>barrister rose to speak. Each sought to clarify the owner-actor&apos;s attempts at concili-<lb/>ation from a legal, outwardly impartial, and yet clearly pro-OP perspective. 29 Once <lb/>the &apos;Police,&apos; &apos; constables,&apos; or &apos; officers&apos; from Bow Street identified a disturbance, they <lb/>would attempt an arrest and, if successful, take their prisoner to Bow Street. Here, at <lb/>the Bow Street magistrates&apos; court, the theatregoing public interacted with the legal <lb/>system for a third time, on this occasion before both appointed guardians of the law <lb/>and formal agents of the legal system. Reports from Bow Street at the time of the OP <lb/>conflict mention the Bow Street magistrates Graham, Nabes, and Read. Arrests from <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>26 The Times, 13 November 1809. <lb/>27 The fact that Brandon tended to speak for the prosecution at Bow Street means few other names are <lb/>mentioned with regards to arrest. Indeed the ire OPs developed against the Covent Garden doorman <lb/>meant that most testimonies for the defence addressed Brandon directly, except in cases where one <lb/>member of the audience arrested another and brought them to Bow Street. Reports do make mention <lb/>of witnesses for the prosecution, though it is rarely clear if they were constables or hired-hands. <lb/>28 Morning Chronicle, 17 October 1809; The Times, 23 October 1809. <lb/>29 The Times, 21 September 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Covent Garden Theatre dominated their business and forced them, on days of noted <lb/>tumult, to work &apos;till midnight,&apos; &apos;till past twelve o&apos;clock,&apos; and on the fiftieth day since <lb/>the theatre reopened -the OP Jubilee -&apos;from a little after eight o&apos;clock&apos; until one <lb/>the next morning. 30 Moreover, whilst it was typical for one magistrate to work the OP <lb/>cases each night, on occasions when there were many cases to be heard more than <lb/>one presided over accusations of wrongdoing in the theatre. <lb/>From the courthouse, to the gaol, to the hanging tree, scholars of the long <lb/>eighteenth century have a well-developed notion of the potentially fluid bounda-<lb/>ries between public spaces and spaces of state justice, confinement, and power. 31 <lb/>During the OP war this fluidity was reinforced by the openness with which news-<lb/>papers reported the proceedings at Bow Street and the correlations made between <lb/>activities in the Covent Garden Theatre pit, boxes, and galleries each night with deci-<lb/>sions reached by the magistrates. However, an incident on Saturday 25 November <lb/>problematises this contemporary narrative of judicial openness. On this night <lb/>&apos;Mr. EAGLE, a barrister&apos; was brought before Graham &apos; charged with assaulting Read, <lb/>one of the patrole.&apos; The alleged assault took place when Eagle had attempted to enter <lb/>the Bow Street court, for he presumed that it was a public space. In the reported <lb/>summary of his remarks, Graham made it clear that this was not the case. &apos;It was a <lb/>mistaken notion,&apos; Graham states, &apos;that that was a public Court, as they were not sit-<lb/>ting in judgement, but merely inquiring whether the matters complained of were fit <lb/>to go before a public Court or not.&apos; 32 <lb/>Some agents of the legal system appeared aware that a spatially restricted Bow <lb/>Street could be detrimental to their cause. John Stafford, Chief Clerk of Bow Street, <lb/>issued public proclamations on the OP war, both as notices posted in public places <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>30 The Times, 11 October, 13 November, 27 November 1809. <lb/>31 J. M. Beattie, Crime and the Courts in England, 1660-1800 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1986); <lb/>D. Hay et. al. (eds), Albion&apos;s Fatal Tree: Crime and Society in Eighteenth-Century England (London: <lb/>Allen Lane, 1975); T. Hitchcock, R. Shoemaker, C. Emsley, S. Howard, and J. McLaughlin, et al. The Old <lb/>Bailey Proceedings Online, 1674-1913 (2012), available at http://www.oldbaileyonline.org, version 7.0 <lb/>[Last accessed 4 December 2014]; P. Linebaugh, The London Hanged: Crime and Civil Society in the <lb/>Eighteenth Century (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1992). <lb/>32 The Times, 27 November 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>and in newspapers. 33 Justice Mainwaring sought to address a broad public in presid-<lb/>ing comments made during the October Westminster Quarter Sessions. A month later <lb/>the Attorney General, Sir Vicary Gibbs, expanded on this line of reasoning during an <lb/>address from the Court of King&apos;s Bench. 34 The public character of the sessions held <lb/>at Westminster Hall by the Lord Chief Justice were a counterpoint to the ambiguous <lb/>status of Bow Street. Nevertheless, charges of conspiracy against these men, from <lb/>constables to the Attorney General, became integral to the OP protest. One reason <lb/>for this was the conspicuous absence from the OP war of the Lord Chamberlain, who <lb/>oversaw the patent held by Covent Garden Theatre, and parliamentarians. Evidently, <lb/>this troubled the OPs and perhaps in consequence one jovial Shakespearean placard <lb/>raised in the pit pleaded to a higher authority still: &apos;Angels and Ministers of Grace,&apos; it <lb/>read, &apos; defend us from this imposition.&apos; 35 <lb/>In these varied arenas, agents of the legal system expressed themselves in many <lb/>ways. In the theatre, they arrested perceived troublemakers on both sides, often for <lb/>assault, and tore down placards affixed to boxes, railings, and balconies. By early <lb/>October 1809, it was commonplace for the possession and use of horns or bells <lb/>within the theatre to provoke an attempt at arrest, as was the distribution of handbills <lb/>among the audience. Outside the theatre, they sought to restrict comparable activi-<lb/>ties. James Andrews was arrested and brought to Bow Street by James Brandon on 10 <lb/>October for having distributed a handbill &apos;in the avenues leading to the Theatre.&apos; The <lb/>handbill accused Kemble of having offered free admissions to Covent Garden Theatre <lb/>to a group of Jewish pugilists led by the noted boxer Dan Mendoza. 36 Exacerbated <lb/>by policing, the spaces that surrounded the theatre soon played host to a fierce dis-<lb/>cursive battle. Here, ephemera in support of the OPs competed with proclamations <lb/>from Bow Street &apos;posted about the streets, expressing,&apos; according to The Examiner <lb/>of 15 October, &apos;the determination of the Magistrates to prevent the breach of the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>33 The Times, 16 October 1809. <lb/>34 Examiner, 29 October 1809; The Times, 21 November 1809. <lb/>35 The Times, 22 September 1809. <lb/>36 The Times, 11 October 1809; The Morning Chronicle, 11 October 1809; Examiner, 15 October 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>peace by rioting at the Theatre.&apos; In response to these proclamations, OPs amended <lb/>their behaviour so as to avoid arrest, and, in response to this change in behaviour, <lb/>officers again amended their grounds for arrest. The consequence was that arrests <lb/>in the pit, the corridors, the gallery, the one-shilling gallery, and the private boxes of <lb/>Covent Garden Theatre continued unabated. As the protest moved into November <lb/>1809, men and women were brought before the Bow Street magistrates charged <lb/>with having caused or incited disturbance, riot, and tumult for singing &apos;God Save the <lb/>King,&apos; using rattles, blowing whistles, gesturing, walking about, sneezing loudly, and <lb/>wearing the words &apos;O.P&apos; or &apos;N.P.B&apos; (No Private Boxes) in their hats. <lb/>When arrested, men and women were brought to Bow Street, and there the mag-<lb/>istrates expressed themselves by demanding bail. Bail ranged from £100 to £500, <lb/>plus sureties -normally the same amount paid by two individuals -for the release <lb/>of the accused. If no bail was present or forthcoming, the accused was committed, <lb/>regardless of the gravity of the offence. Mary Austin, for example, was committed &apos;for <lb/>want to bail&apos; on Monday 16 October for little more than use of a rattle. Bow Street <lb/>magistrates also offered advice to those who came before them. Having been the sub-<lb/>ject of a scuffle in defence of her honour on 14 November, Mrs Hewetson &apos; appeared,&apos; <lb/>The Times reported the next day, &apos;in the course of the examination [...] a constant <lb/>frequenter of the Theatre, and very zealous on the part of the Proprietors. As her <lb/>object in visiting it certainly could not be to hear the play, it was suggested that she <lb/>might with more propriety stay at home.&apos; Ten days earlier, Magistrate Graham acquit-<lb/>ted John Winholt of hissing during the performance and found against his accuser <lb/>George White for rough treatment. Nevertheless, Graham cautioned Winholt not to <lb/>repeat his assertion that he would the following night take pistols to the theatre as a <lb/>means of self-defence, for if he did the court &apos;must be under the necessity of advising <lb/>him to find bail to keep the peace.&apos; 37 <lb/>Few attempts at keeping order were planned and when planning did take place <lb/>it tended to be ad hoc at best. On Wednesday 18 November, the Morning Chronicle <lb/>reported a speech from a naval officer who had been active in the pit for some days. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>37 The Times, 6 November 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>&apos;What!,&apos; he proclaimed, &apos; are Englishmen struggling against injustice to be bullied by <lb/>hired ruffians -to be beaten down by the very dregs and refuse of the twelve tribes.&apos; <lb/>Applause rang around the theatre accompanied by a call of &apos;Take care of him.&apos; 38 <lb/>Clearly the OPs feared that having made a connection between &apos;hired ruffians&apos; and <lb/>theatrical tyranny in a public venue, that the naval officer had crossed a line. They <lb/>were right, for as they carried the orator from the theatre in triumph to a coffee <lb/>house on Cecil-street, they were followed, unbeknown to the naval officer and his <lb/>supporters, by John Smith &apos; one of the patrol belonging to the [Bow Street] office.&apos; <lb/>Once the naval officer&apos;s supporters had left, Smith seized him and brought him to <lb/>Bow Street. Here, after &apos; considerable difficulty,&apos; Read and Graham discovered he was <lb/>in fact an assistant druggist by the name of Samuel Dudfield. Dudfield was ordered <lb/>to find bail of £200 and two sureties of £100 each. <lb/>Not all those ordered to find bail at Bow Street went on to face a Grand Jury at <lb/>the Westminster Quarter Sessions. Of those that did fewer still had bills of indictment <lb/>found against them. At the 28 October Sessions, forty-two OP related bills of indict-<lb/>ment were put forward of which only seventeen were found. That twenty-five bills <lb/>were considered not worthy by a Westminster jury placed strain on the impartiality <lb/>of Bow Street&apos;s interpretation of public order. The position of the legal establishment <lb/>was that the disturbances at Covent-Garden Theatre were illegal. Indeed, in the days <lb/>that lead up to the October Sessions, the courts had begun to attach the notion of <lb/>conspiracy to their complaints against OPs. 39 These actions recall national security <lb/>alarms from the 1790s. Reports from the sessions record Justice Mainwaring&apos;s insist-<lb/>ence that the jury were to consider the bills of indictment with respect to points of <lb/>law rather than any sense of OPs possessing a right to protest or to resist oppression. 40 <lb/>In spite of the jury not finding in most cases in favour of Mainwaring, arrests and <lb/>charges against OPs continued, and the offences for which OPs were charged indicate <lb/>a belief that OP was a dangerous and threatening conspiracy. In November 1809, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>38 The Times, 19 November 1809. <lb/>39 The Times, 26 October 1809. <lb/>40 Examiner, 29 October 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>a number of theatregoers were arrested for nothing more than having worn the let-<lb/>ters &apos;O.P.&apos; in their hats. Others were brought to Bow Street for offences as trivial as <lb/>having ran, elevated placards, or used indecent language. 41 <lb/>The actions and expressions of men such as Mainwaring overwhelmingly sug-<lb/>gest that they saw OP as both a threat to public order and a conspiracy. 42 Once the <lb/>Attorney General Sir Vicary Gibbs entered the affair from the Court of King&apos;s Bench <lb/>on 20 November, the latter position was entrenched. Gibbs agreed with affidavits <lb/>that justified the rise in admission prices, allegations of a conspiracy against Covent-<lb/>Garden theatre, suggestions that wearing the letters &apos;O.P.&apos; and raising placards in the <lb/>theatre were riotous conduct, and that the barrister Henry Clifford was their ring-<lb/>leader. He used the strongest possible hyperbole in order to situate the disturbances <lb/>within the history of protest in London: the OP disturbances were, he argued, &apos;the <lb/>greatest riots that had every disgraced the Metropolis.&apos; 43 Greater even it seems than <lb/>the infamous and calamitous Gordon Riots. 44 <lb/>III &apos;The Police last night ascended amongst the Gods&apos; -<lb/>Reporting the Legal System <lb/>The existence of physical and discursive interactions between agents of the legal sys-<lb/>tem and the OPs, and the details of those interactions, were widely reported. Editori-<lb/>als went further and described the consequences of legal activities in Covent-Garden <lb/>Theatre, Bow Street, and the London courts. They included reports of proclamations, <lb/>arrests, and trials, and reveal a concern for three issues: the definition of a crime, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>41 The legal system did on many occasions work to the advantage of the OPs. A Jewish pugilist, presumed <lb/>to have been hired by the Covent Garden Theatre management, was prosecuted at Bow Street on <lb/>10 November (The Times, 11 November 1809). John Winholt, an OP who visited the magistrates&apos; office <lb/>on over four occasions in Autumn 1809, had on 22 November a hat returned to him that had been <lb/>stolen whilst he protested at Covent Garden Theatre (The Times, 23 November 1809). <lb/>42 Henry Hoskins, who appeared at the Old Bailey on 1 November 1809 charged with highway robbery, <lb/>went so far as to use his reluctance to accompany his accuser to Covent Garden Theatre &apos;because <lb/>his intention was to kick up a row in the house&apos; as evidence of his good character. It is tempting, if <lb/>unsubstantiated, to suggest that given the magistracy&apos;s distate for the OPs that this played a part in <lb/>his acquittal. Old Bailey Proceedings Online, 1 November 1809, trial of Henry Hoskins (t18091101-45). <lb/>43 The Times, 21 November 1809. <lb/>44 I. Haywood and J. Reed (eds.), The Gordon Riots: Politics, Culture and Insurrection in Late Eighteenth-<lb/>Century Britain (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>the definition of a criminal, and inconsistencies in legal application. This section <lb/>focuses on the latter concern, by far the most common complaint during the autumn <lb/>1809 phase of the Old Price riots. <lb/>When, on the first night of the OP war, the Bow Street magistrates read the Riot <lb/>Act, this neither alarmed nor dispersed the audience, and because the situation was <lb/>a legal anomaly, the reading was never repeated. The audience had, after all, paid to <lb/>assemble and the audience were assembled in a space which held a patent licence to <lb/>hold public entertainments. What was, The Times asked on 21 September 1809, the <lb/>legality of bringing those who had expressed &apos;marks of disapprobation at a public <lb/>theatre&apos; before a magistrate? As a consequence, reports on legal proceedings for the <lb/>first few nights indicate a cautious and conservative response from agents of the legal <lb/>system; property crimes, a mainstay of long eighteenth-century crime and justice, <lb/>formed the bulk of Bow Street cases reported on 19 September. 45 The editorial reflec-<lb/>tions on these arrests were similarly cautious, concerned with class politics as much <lb/>as the veracity of crimes for which theatregoers were being accused. &apos;Police Officers,&apos; <lb/>The Times commented, were &apos;very awkwardly situated, many of the persons whom <lb/>they have taken into custody being men of respectability.&apos; 46 Given these tensions, hos-<lb/>tility toward the actions of Bow Street was rare at this time -the Morning Chronicle, <lb/>though supportive of the protesters, baulked at censoring officers; The Times, fearful <lb/>of an escalation of violence, called for the protesters to boycott the theatre, and the <lb/>Morning Post, as it would throughout the conflict, cheered on the management, the <lb/>magistrates, and the heavy hand of the law. <lb/>Matters began to change in early-October 1809 as the theatre management, who <lb/>had up until this time appealed to the legal establishment to keep order, began to <lb/>take the law into their own hands in an attempt to quell the protests. The Times <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>45 A single arrest from the opening night was tried at the Old Bailey. William Dyer was brought to the <lb/>court accused of stealing a handkerchief at the door to the Covent Garden Theatre pit. Dyer was <lb/>arrested by his accuser John Goodyear. He was found guilty and sentenced to a shilling fine and <lb/>imprisonment for one year. Old Bailey Proceedings Online, 20 September 1809, trial of William Eakins <lb/>Dyer (18090920-69). <lb/>46 The Times, 21 September 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>noted on 5 October that on the previous night &apos;it was with pain we observed&apos; hired <lb/>hands acting for the management. The paper reiterated its resignation five days <lb/>later and conflated the officers of Bow Street with a panoply of trouble-makers: the <lb/>pit, they commented, &apos; appeared a second Babel&apos; with &apos;Jews, Turks, Hibernians, Bow-<lb/>Street Officers, pugilists, pickpockets, all jumbled together.&apos; 47 It is notable that the <lb/>OPs are not mention as part of this group. The next day, whilst The Times was batting <lb/>away accusations from theatregoers that it sided with the management, the Morning <lb/>Chronicle made first mention of a complaint that would become a feature of report-<lb/>ing on the conflict: the inconsistency of arrest and the apparent tendency of Bow <lb/>Street to arrest only the opponents of the theatre management. 48 <lb/>By mid-October, the management were accused of suppressing a multi-class and <lb/>inter-gender protest by the unethical employment of &apos;the vilest miscreants known in <lb/>the metropolis to trample on its peaceable inhabitants.&apos; 49 The metropolitan newspa-<lb/>pers were highly sensitive to any perceived complicity on the part of the legal system. <lb/>Leigh Hunt&apos;s The Examiner, a reform inclined London weekly, noted on 15 October <lb/>that: <lb/>A Proclamation from Bow-street has been posted about the streets, express-<lb/>ing the determination of the Magistrates to prevent the breach of the peace <lb/>by rioting at the Theatre. -They should, however, have commenced by <lb/>ordering into custody that ferocious set described above, who not only have <lb/>broken the peace, but who went to the Theatre for that express purpose. <lb/>If Hunt was concerned that the law had targeted the wrong side, comparison of <lb/>reports from the theatre and from Bow Street suggest the legal system had certainly <lb/>targeted one side. The Morning Chronicle described the atmosphere in Covent Garden <lb/>Theatre on 13 October as boisterously contemptuous towards the proprietors&apos; means <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>47 The Times, 10 October 1809. <lb/>48 Morning Chronicle, 11 October 1809. <lb/>49 Morning Chronicle, 13 October 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>of intimidation,&apos; that is, their use of hired Jewish pugilists. 50 The Chronicle claimed to <lb/>have seen more placards than on any night since the beginning of the conflict, many <lb/>of which were explicitly anti-Semitic (&apos;The Covent-Garden Synagogue -MENDOZA <lb/>the Grand Rabbi&apos;; &apos;BISH, the Detector of Fraud v MENDOZA, the Leader of hired <lb/>Pugilists&apos;; &apos;Shall Britons be subdued by the wandering tribe of Jerusalem?&apos;). A report <lb/>in The Times on 14 October 1809 described in detail the violent turn the evening <lb/>took: <lb/>Theatrical criticism is now converted into the record of gladiatorial brutality <lb/>and Bow-street conviction [...] no sooner was the war-whoop sounded, than <lb/>the most ferocious, and apparently predetermined, contests took place in <lb/>every part of the house, and particularly in the boxes. Neither the remon-<lb/>strances of the peaceable, not the distress of the female part of the audience, <lb/>had the least influence on the conduct of the combatants. <lb/>Readers of this report might well have concluded that on 13 October offences took <lb/>place on both sides; and The Times&apos; ambiguous use of &apos; combatants&apos; might well indi-<lb/>cate editorial caution. Yet, a clearly one-sided picture emerged in the subsequent <lb/>reports on the arrests and convictions of theatregoers who protested and resisted <lb/>Jewish pugilists that night. Thomas Higham, a servant, was unsuccessfully charged <lb/>by George Jones, one of the box-keepers at Covent-Garden Theatre, for having waved <lb/>his hat and exhibited papers marked &apos;Jew or Gentile&apos; and &apos;Covent-garden Synagogue&apos; <lb/>from the two-shilling gallery. The seventeen-year-old Robert Winduld was charged <lb/>with having waved in the pit a sign that read &apos;Covent-garden Rabbi.&apos; Morris Thomas, <lb/>&apos; a gentleman of respectability,&apos; was charged (and acquitted) with having breached <lb/>the peace by &apos;hooting, hissing, and kicking.&apos; 51 John Soane of Lincoln&apos;s Inn Fields was <lb/>convicted of having shouted and banged his fists. 52 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>50 Morning Chronicle, 14 October 1809. <lb/>51 The Times, 16 October 1809; Morning Chronicle, 16 October 1809. <lb/>52 This John Soane is not to be confused with the famous architect John Soane. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>There are three plausible reasons for this discrepancy in reports on activities <lb/>in and outside Covent Garden Theatre on 13 October: either OPs were targeted for <lb/>arrest; The Times, the Morning Chronicle, et al. selectively reported arrests of OPs; <lb/>or these papers&apos; initial reports of the tumult falsely imagined (for reasons of pro-<lb/>priety, caution, inattention, or otherwise) a scene of conflict where in fact it was <lb/>one of OP-led riot. All these interpretations are plausible, yet for our purposes it is <lb/>important to note that the metropolitan newspapers (the Morning Post excepted) <lb/>presented in their editorial judgements a narrative of injustice. When Morris Thomas <lb/>was discharged, The Times quoted Magistrate Graham as having stated that &apos;he saw <lb/>no ground for charging him with any unlawful expression of his sentiments in the <lb/>Theatre.&apos; 53 The Morning Chronicle report of the same day went further and chose to <lb/>include in its editorial an attack on Thomas&apos; treatment that did not directly pertain <lb/>to the case at hand: <lb/>Submitted to the consideration of the Magistrates the injustice and arbitrary <lb/>interposition of the Police Officers, to prevent the exercise of fair opinion <lb/>of the audience, respective the performances in the Theatre, as a conduct <lb/>which was completely subversive of the rights of Englishmen in a British <lb/>Theatre. He did not deny that he had hissed and hooted at the performance, <lb/>on the contrary, he avowed that he did so, from a principal of unbiased <lb/>judgement. As, however, the charge was brought forward, he must insist in <lb/>meeting it in the open day. He had been dragged ignominiously out of the <lb/>Theatre, in a manner so rudely, that the most outrageous conduct on his part <lb/>would not have warranted. 54 <lb/>Four days later, the Morning Chronicle began a report of an arrest in the one-shilling <lb/>gallery with sarcasm: &apos;The Police,&apos; they wrote, &apos;last night ascended amongst the Gods.&apos; <lb/>Having established a narrative of selective arrest, the OP-supportive newspapers not <lb/>only reported instances where legal processes were not applied universally but also <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>53 The Times, 16 October 1809. <lb/>54 Morning Chronicle, 16 October 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>used suggestive and impartial language to do so. The Bow Street magistrates, The <lb/>Examiner commented on 22 October, &apos; appear as partisans rather than judges.&apos; On <lb/>29 October, The Examiner made a pointed in-versus-out-group juxtaposition between <lb/>the character of a man accused of tumult, singing, and having worn OP insignia and <lb/>the character of an informant that Bow Street officers used in their attempts to con-<lb/>vict him. Mr T. Russell, the accused, was described as the &apos;nephew to a most respect-<lb/>able tradesman in Westminster.&apos; Abraham Mark Braham, the witness of his supposed <lb/>crimes, was described as &apos; a Jew broker of furniture and salesman.&apos; A month later, and <lb/>with OPs having been ordered to find bail for booing, dancing, singing, using rat-<lb/>tles, coughing, sneezing, and making speeches, The Times wryly noted that &apos;the pres-<lb/>ence of the party of Old Prices was only occasionally evinced by a trifling hiss; which <lb/>now seems to be deemed the only legal methods of expressing disapprobation.&apos; 55 <lb/>The emphases here are indicative of how The Times had repositioned itself since <lb/>18 September, for they suggest an editorial belief that something was seriously amiss <lb/>with the &apos;legal&apos; apparatus if &apos; a trifling hiss&apos; was the only disapproving action a theatre-<lb/>goer could make in order to avoid arrest. <lb/>The Morning Post saw matters rather differently. The paper was, Baer argues, &apos;slav-<lb/>ishly Tory&apos; and rarely took against the Covent Garden Theatre management. 56 I can <lb/>find little at fault with this position. Reports on the OP war published in the Morning <lb/>Post portray OPs arrested by the police as irritating members of a &apos;self-denominated <lb/>&quot;Public&quot;&apos; disturbing the peace, harmony, and attention of the true public. 57 OPs <lb/>and theatregoers alike were well aware of this characterisation of the protesters <lb/>as &apos;rebels.&apos; Indeed, one of the many placards they erected on the subject read &apos;The <lb/>Times and Post are bought and sold, By KEMBLE&apos;s pride and KEMBLE&apos;s gold.&apos; 58 The <lb/>Times rejected this accusation both directly and in their editorial position over the <lb/>coming months. The Morning Post, on the other hand, cared little and continued to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>55 Reports suggest that in late-November 1809 numerous arrests for making noise were made without <lb/>clearly verifying the identity of the offender; see for example The Times, 23 November 1809. <lb/>56 Baer, Theatre and Disorder, 113. <lb/>57 Morning Post, 1 December 1809. <lb/>58 The Times, 11 October 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>vigorously defend the actions of the management. When James Thomas, a man they <lb/>had described as having possessed a &apos; dirty appearance,&apos; was brought before the Bow <lb/>Street magistrates on 2 December, the Morning Post eagerly presented his sarcasm <lb/>and insolence as evidence of the OPs&apos; lack of propriety, gentility, and good sense. But <lb/>this exchange also reveals a great deal about how the London public responded to <lb/>the actions of agents of the legal system during the autumn of 1809. It is to James <lb/>Thomas, and the narrative the Morning Post chose to mock, that we now turn. <lb/>IV &quot;I must say, my blood boils in me&quot; -Responses <lb/>to the Legal System <lb/>James Thomas was seized on Friday 1 December. The press disputed the extent of <lb/>the disturbance he had partaken in. The Times thought the uproar little more than <lb/>that which &apos;generally accompanies a piece that is not popular.&apos; 59 The Morning Chroni-<lb/>cle reported that much of the last two acts of A Cure for the Heart Ache and The <lb/>Jubilee, the afterpiece, were &apos; overwhelmed by the noise that prevailed in the house.&apos; 60 <lb/>The Morning Post considered the noise mere interruptions that &apos;were neither loud <lb/>nor long.&apos; 61 All agreed, however, that a man, identified by The Times and Morning Post <lb/>as James Thomas, was taken to Bow Street by James Brandon for, variously, having <lb/>&apos;ventured to display&apos; the initials O.P. in his hat (Morning Chronicle), &apos;brandishing a <lb/>stick over his head in a threatening manner, as if bidding defiance to the authority <lb/>and powers of the Officers&apos; (The Times), and having been the first to attempt to dis-<lb/>turb the entertainments (Morning Post). By the time of his arrival at Bow Street, the <lb/>magistrates had retired for the evening. Thomas spent the night in the watch-house <lb/>and was not examined until the following morning. On Monday 4 December the <lb/>Morning Post featured a lengthy report on Thomas&apos; examination. His exchange with <lb/>Justice Graham was recorded as follows: <lb/>The Clerk to the Prisoner -&quot;What is your name?&quot; <lb/>Prisoner -&quot;James Thomas&quot; <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>59 The Times, 2 December 1809. <lb/>60 Morning Chronicle, 2 December 1809. <lb/>61 Morning Post, 2 December 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Clerk -&quot;What are you?&quot; <lb/>Prisoner -&quot;That is no matter&quot; <lb/>Mr GRAHAM, the Sitting Magistrate, to Prisoner -&quot;Do you not consider yourself in <lb/>the pit of Covent-Garden Theatre?&quot; <lb/>Prisoner -&quot;I do not&quot; <lb/>Clerk -&quot;Where do you live?&quot; <lb/>Prisoner -&quot;Here.&quot; <lb/>Clerk -&quot;Where do you reside?&quot; <lb/>Prisoner -&quot;I did live in Argyle-street.&quot; <lb/>Graham -&quot;Do not tell us where you did reside, but where your residence is now.&quot; <lb/>Prisoner -&quot;I do not think it a fair question, therefore shall not answer.&quot; <lb/>Clerk -&quot;What are you?&quot; <lb/>Prisoner -&quot;A man!&quot; <lb/>Clerk -&quot;You are a very rude man.&quot; <lb/>Graham -&quot;You are much mistaken, if you think this kind of rude behaviour can do <lb/>you any good&quot; <lb/>Prisoner -&quot;I am not rude.&quot; <lb/>Together with an accompanying report that included Thomas&apos; probing cross-<lb/>examination of his accuser, James Brandon, this exchange played into the theatrical <lb/>reporting of the riots often seen in the Morning Post. 62 Yet it appeared on the same <lb/>day in near identical form in both The Times and, with the exception of the exchange <lb/>above (replaced with &apos;He gave his name as &quot;James Thomas,&quot; but refused to state his <lb/>residence&apos;), the Morning Chronicle; this in spite of the three papers disagreeing on <lb/>why and in what context Thomas was arrested. <lb/>Whether it was true or not, this was the story that entered the public domain. <lb/>Removed from the pro-management master narrative the Morning Post put forth, <lb/>Thomas&apos; defiant appearance at Bow Street takes on a witty, daring, and intelligent <lb/>quality that encapsulates many of the frustrations evident in public responses to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>62 Baer, Theatre and Disorder, pp. 113-114. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>the activities of constables, magistrates, and justices during the OP war. Indeed, the <lb/>letters that were written to newspapers, the speeches that were given in the theatre, <lb/>the placards that were hoisted, the mock playbills that were circulated, and the insig-<lb/>nia that were proudly displayed collectively indicate a profound frustration with the <lb/>legal establishment. With these expressions of frustration increasingly suppressed, <lb/>the metropolitan newspapers were, by the time of Thomas&apos; arrest, a vital platform <lb/>through which the OPs could respond to the legal system and sustain and legitimise <lb/>their cause. This final section explores responses to the legal system expressed inside <lb/>Covent Garden Theatre, at sites of justice, and in the public press. <lb/>At the beginning of the OP conflict, some two and half months prior to James <lb/>Thomas&apos; verbal altercation with Justice Graham, most acts of OP protest took place <lb/>within Covent Garden Theatre. Speeches were one method by which OPs articu-<lb/>lated their complaints. On the second night of the OP war, a gentleman sat in one <lb/>of Kemble&apos;s new and controversial private boxes rose to address a Bow Street officer. <lb/>&apos;You should not be too busy,&apos; began The Times report of his speech published 21 <lb/>September 1809: <lb/>You are certainly a useful man in your situation, but in this instance you <lb/>appear to me to be out of your latitude. Your business is to prevent public <lb/>depredations; but at present, it appears to me, you have changed your usual <lb/>plan, and that you are now assisting robbers, and taking the robbed into <lb/>custody. <lb/>Two days later Kemble addressed the audience. They were palpably loyal to King <lb/>and country and had earlier that night sung God Save the King and hoisted placards <lb/>that read &apos;Support King George, resist King Kemble.&apos; But loyalism should not be <lb/>confused with deference. The OPs were suspicious of legal authority and evidently <lb/>unhappy with the appointment -by the management -of the Governor of the Bank <lb/>of England to head a committee tasked with the inspection of Covent Garden Thea-<lb/>tre&apos;s finances. The uproar &apos;became more violent that ever&apos; when Kemble, in an effort <lb/>to demonstrate (as he put it) &apos;how much we wish for impartial justice,&apos; named the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Attorney General as a member of committee. 63 The establishment and the crowd <lb/>were at odds. <lb/>During the second week of October 1809, the noted lottery proprietor Thomas <lb/>Bish used the newspaper press to articulate his accusation that the theatre manage-<lb/>ment were paying Jewish boxers to suppress the OP war. 64 After offences as trivial as <lb/>mock sneezing and nose blowing led to court arrest within the theatre, OPs turned <lb/>to letter writing in protest. John Tackle complained of having received beatings from <lb/>Jewish men and having been a victim of false arrest in a letter published by both <lb/>The Times and the Morning Chronicle on 12 October. Three days later The Examiner <lb/>summarised his tale. <lb/>It is notable that acts of protest began to shift to newspaper publication as <lb/>Jewish pugilists became more prominent as enforcers of the will of the Covent <lb/>Garden Theatre management. These boxers first entered the theatre on 6 October <lb/>and remained active until 14 October. 65 Such was the ferocity of this period that <lb/>some theatregoers appeared to yearn for the return of Bow Street authority. One <lb/>letter writer remarked at: <lb/>The absurdity of an attempt to restore the tranquillity of the Theatre, by <lb/>confiding the preservation of it not to the established Police, but a class of <lb/>persons who notoriously subsist by a violation of the laws of their country. 66 <lb/>If Bow Street were trusted by some to uphold the basic tenets of the law, they were <lb/>criticised by others for their favour towards the tactics of the management. Discrep-<lb/>ancies in bail conditions was one complaint. In a letter to the Morning Chronicle that <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>63 The Times, 23 September 1809. <lb/>64 Morning Chronicle, 12 October 1809; In the same letter Bish admitted to having asked his employee <lb/>James Andrews, who we have seen, to distribute handbills containing the same accusations. This is <lb/>one of a number of letters by Bish that were published in the metropolitan press. <lb/>65 For a detailed account of this phase of the riots, a phase characterised in the contemporary mind by <lb/>the presence of Jewish pugilists in Covent Garden Theatre, see J. Baker, &apos;Jewishness and the Covent <lb/>Garden OP War: Satirical Perceptions of John Philip Kemble,&apos; Nineteenth-Century Theatre and Film <lb/>40.1 (2013). <lb/>66 The Times, 12 October 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>responded to activities during the Jewish phase of the riots, &apos;FAIR JUSTICE&apos; wrote on <lb/>11 October that: <lb/>As a lover of impartial justice, I should be glad to know why the Magistrates <lb/>of Bow-street demand bail to the amount of 800l., that is 400l. the offender, <lb/>and 400l. his sureties, of such persons as are accused of opposing the <lb/>Proprietors&apos; demands, and accepting from the Author of the Blind Boy, <lb/>(accused of riotous conduct in support of the Managers), 40l. i.e. himself 20l. <lb/>and Mr. Brandon (the oathtaking Box-keeper) 20l. 67 <lb/>Days later, a letter from &apos;A CONSTANT READER&apos; published in the Morning Chronicle <lb/>criticised both the magistrates and officers from Bow Street -the latter for having <lb/>allowed &apos; a notorious Prize-fighter&apos; to &apos;publicly and repeatedly&apos; challenge &apos;the whole <lb/>House to fight&apos; in their presence, the former for not having taken &apos; cognizance of this <lb/>matter.&apos; 68 <lb/>During this phase of the riots, arrests in the theatre became a common topic for <lb/>newspaper correspondents. &apos;I made application to several Constables in the Theatre, <lb/>not one would return to the Pit with me to secure the offenders,&apos; read a letter pub-<lb/>lished in The Examiner on 15 October 1809, &apos;Is it not therefore evident, Sir,&apos; one <lb/>&apos;HUMANITAS&apos; continued, &apos;that these ruffians must have been hired?&apos; A day later The <lb/>Times carried a letter from a member of the public whose speech had the previously <lb/>evening caught the attention of the Bow Street officers in attendance. Thwarted in <lb/>their attempts to arrest him &apos;the officers of the justice seized a Gentleman,&apos; the author <lb/>wrote with disgust, &apos;who took no part whatever in the affair.&apos; The pseudonymous &apos;A <lb/>FRIEND TO JUSTICE&apos; had been, until he witnessed this seemingly unwarranted arrest, <lb/>offering some words in support of the management. <lb/>With the departure of the Jewish pugilists, the violence subsided. Yet Bow Street <lb/>officers continued their arrests. Many OPs saw these arrests as indiscriminate and <lb/>situated their experience in relation to ancient precedent. J. Lorraine wrote on 19 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>67 Morning Chronicle, 13 October 1809. <lb/>68 Morning Chronicle, 16 October 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>October that &apos;I want to know on what grounds the Magistrate commits persons, who <lb/>use only the modes of expressing disapprobation, which have been practised since <lb/>the very first invention of the drama by the Greeks.&apos; One individual, who Lorraine <lb/>witnessed the arrest of, was the aforementioned Mary Austin. &apos;Sir,&apos; he continued, <lb/>&apos;I must say, my blood boils in me, as a Briton, at the very idea of a young woman&apos;s <lb/>being sent to prison, for only springing a child&apos;s rattle in the one-shilling gallery of <lb/>Covent-garden Playhouse.&apos; 69 <lb/>Mary Austin had been arrested on Monday 16 October &apos; charged with springing a <lb/>small rattle in the one-shilling gallery, and exciting disturbance on the part of those <lb/>around, by her pernicious example.&apos; These grounds contrasted with reports of her <lb/>deposition, in which she claimed to have been handed the rattle, knew not that it <lb/>might cause harm, and respectfully stated, according to The Times on 21 October, that <lb/>&apos;the Magistrates were at liberty to do what their wisdom might direct.&apos; Committed for <lb/>want of bail by Magistrate Read, the treatment of this young servant clearly aggra-<lb/>vated the OP community. <lb/>Whether or not her testimony and the subsequent reporting of it were true, <lb/>for a brief period Mary Austin became a martyr. Her status is recorded in the list of <lb/>names against funds pledged to a subscription &apos;for the assistance of PERSONS con-<lb/>sidered UNJUSTLY PROSECUTED by the PROPRIETORS and MANAGERS of COVENT <lb/>GARDEN THEATRE.&apos; The idea of a subscription list in support of less wealthy OPs <lb/>was first floated in the public press (The Times at first) by the anonymous &apos;Publicola&apos; <lb/>on 21 October, the day after the appearance of Lorraine&apos;s letter. The following week, <lb/>the same paper carried an advertisement that announced the establishment of the <lb/>list, the locations where money could be left, and an initial subscription of £58 18s. <lb/>Following the lead set by Publicola, wealthy supporters of the OPs pledged anon-<lb/>ymously as &apos;An Enemy to hired Ruffians,&apos; &apos;F.H.,&apos; and &apos;Box keeper&apos;s oath.&apos; The fund <lb/>quickly mushroomed: £79 9s. 6d. was pledged by 30 October, £152 11s. 7d. by 1 <lb/>November, £184 18s. 1d. by 3 November, £248 13s. 7d. by 6 November, and £339 9s. <lb/>7d. by 13 November. It crossed the £400 mark on 23 November. As the subscription <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>69 The Times, 20 October 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>grew, so too blossomed the wit, topicality, and sense of drama of the names used to <lb/>pledge funds: &apos;The KEY to the Private Boxes&apos; on 30 October, &apos;A Christian recovering <lb/>from the wrath of a Jew&apos; on 1 November, &apos;A peep through the pigeon-holes&apos; and &apos;An <lb/>Enemy to partial Justice -Read this&apos; (a pun on Magistrate Read) on 3 November, <lb/>&apos;Query: Are Private Boxes allowed by the Patent&apos; on 4 November and so on. It is here <lb/>that Austin appeared, once on 30 October in a pledge from &apos;Mary Austin&apos;s Rattle&apos; <lb/>and again on 1 November in a pledge from &apos;The Sale of a Rattle.&apos; Her arrest then <lb/>was a symbol of a line having been crossed, of an affront to the ancient privileges of <lb/>theatregoers. <lb/>The funds secured and volume of subscriptions collected suggest the list was <lb/>some success. It was organised by committee, and James Powell of Grove Place, <lb/>Camden Town -a sometime complainant over the appearance of Jewish boxers in <lb/>the theatre -was its secretary. Powell was a passionate advocate of the OP cause and <lb/>on 8 March 1810, long after the dispute had ended, he sent a public notice to the <lb/>metropolitan press that stated: <lb/>ALL PERSONS having any claim upon the above Fund for LEGAL EXPENCES <lb/>incurred in regard to their Defence, and who have not yet sent in their <lb/>Claims, are requested to deliver the same on or before the 25 th of this present <lb/>Month, to Mr. William West, Attorney, No. 14, New Boswell-court, Lincoln&apos;s <lb/>Inn, otherwise they will lose the benefit of the said Fund, as the accounts <lb/>will be at that time closed. 70 <lb/>William West added further legal expertise to the OP committee, much needed given <lb/>the propensity for Bow Street to seek arrest. Thomas Tegg, a bookseller, printer, sta-<lb/>tioner and print seller based on Cheapside was another prominent committee mem-<lb/>ber. Tegg&apos;s shop was one of the premises used to accept subscription list payments, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>70 O. P. Riots. Exhibitions. -Panoramas. -Peace Jubilee and Sundries. 1809-1814. 1809-1814. MS Radi-<lb/>cal Politics and the Working Man in England: Part Two: Sets 47-49, 51-53, 55-63, and 65-72 Set 59; <lb/>Vol 2. British Library, 30. Nineteenth Century Collections Online. Web. 14 Oct. 2014. http://tinyurl. <lb/>galegroup.com/tinyurl/Ktan6 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>and his expertise in advertising and publishing was valuable to the OP cause. Ever the <lb/>opportunist, Tegg exploited the conflict for profit by publishing many satirical prints <lb/>and, in the aftermath, a book reflecting on events of autumn 1809. 71 <lb/>The subscription list, the experience in public arenas of its committee, and <lb/>the way the list was used by OPs to communicate ideas, messages, grievances, and <lb/>humour offer an instructive example of how OPs and their supporters responded to <lb/>the actions of the legal system by moving a significant element of the conflict out-<lb/>side of Covent Garden Theatre. This means of protest was a direct response to how <lb/>OPs were policed as threats to public order and security and it became a vital and <lb/>flexible discursive forum. A letter from A LOVER OF JUSTICE was published in The <lb/>Times on 23 October that stated triumphantly: <lb/>After the despicable means that have been resorted to by the Managers <lb/>of Covent-Garden Theatre to support the ungracious and unseasonable <lb/>demands on the public, I should not wonder if similar attempts have been <lb/>made to stifle the Liberty of the Press. That, however, in spite of all their <lb/>efforts, will, I trust, remain open and pure. This is the only resource left for <lb/>poor John Bull. It may be called the bugle-horn of his grievances -a bugle, <lb/>that all the Jews, prize-fighters, and thief-takers cannot silence. <lb/>Here, once more, guardianship of the legal system was conflated with suppression, <lb/>thief-takers with prize-fighters. The injustices inflicted were debated outside the the-<lb/>atre and beyond into late-November, and the press would remain a vital outlet for <lb/>the OP cause. A letter from &apos;AN ENGLISHMAN&apos; published in The Times 20 November <lb/>1809 read: <lb/>I am sorry to perceive, Sir, that fighters are still sent into the Theatre; and <lb/>I find that now they do not hesitate to knock down all before them. It is <lb/>notorious that orders are issued every morning to various persons, who, in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>71 Tegg, The O. P. War. For his style of business see J. Barnes and P. Barnes, &apos;Reassessing the Reputation of <lb/>Thomas Tegg, London Publisher, 1776-1846,&apos; Book History 3 (2000). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>the evening, are collected in a body, and introduced into the Theatre with <lb/>directions &quot;not to be very nice&quot; with such as dare to express their disapproba-<lb/>tion to the conduct of the Managers. I am far from being one who would <lb/>encourage or assist the least disturbance in a Theatre, or any other place; but <lb/>I cannot help thinking that the conduct of some persons, from the time of <lb/>opening the Theatre, up to this moment, has been such as the public at large <lb/>can never sanction or approve. <lb/>OPs, theatregoers, and those -like this letter writer -merely sympathetic to their <lb/>cause discussed in newspapers not only the OP war itself, but also how the agents <lb/>of the legal system had acted in response to the protests at Covent Garden Theatre <lb/>during the autumn of 1809. Although removed from the original place of conflict, <lb/>their rebuke and dismay in this arena was as palpable as the physical manifestations <lb/>played out inside Covent Garden Theatre. <lb/>---<lb/>We, of course, must keep in mind that the Examiner, Morning Chronicle, and Times <lb/>needed little motivation to publish letters that supported press freedoms, that <lb/>preached non-violence, and that showed public appetite for the OP cause. These <lb/>newspapers were partial witnesses to the OP war. Yet it is notable that even these <lb/>partial witnesses published reports and letters that highlighted public sensitivity <lb/>towards to press partiality, a sensitivity born out of the value OPs ascribed to the <lb/>press as a forum for debate. Proprietors of the Morning Chronicle no doubt delighted <lb/>in publishing on 12 October details of placards raised in Covent Garden Theatre the <lb/>previous night that had read &apos;No wonder the POST condemns JOHN BULL&apos;s Placards, <lb/>when it lies, thick and thin, in support of Jew Blackguards.&apos; But this reporting of <lb/>public sensitivity to press bias worked both ways. We have already observed that The <lb/>Times brought claims that it was in favour of the management, claims it disputed, to <lb/>the attention of its own readers. Though it did so in this case to dismiss those claims, <lb/>on 3 November the same paper published in full a notice on the OP subscription <lb/>that included funds left under the pseudonym &apos;Camelion-like, The Times their optics <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>threw on Kemble&apos;s gold, and instant changed their hue.&apos; No editorial claims to the <lb/>contrary accompanied the notice. <lb/>Censoring these lines would have been futile. Public feeling had reached a head <lb/>the previous evening. Early that day, the Grand Jury found only those indictments <lb/>against OPs that involved damage to property and to the theatre: &apos; all the Bills for <lb/>making a noise, of whatever nature, were thrown out.&apos; 72 Emboldened by both this <lb/>legal victory and the continued outcry against the coercive tactics employed by both <lb/>the Covent Garden Theatre management and Bow Street, OP resistance and disor-<lb/>der within Covent Garden Theatre returned to levels not seen since early-October. <lb/>At half-price, a quiet house was flooded with OPs who wore insignia in their hats, <lb/>carried fresh placards, and in many cases began mock fights and to run along the <lb/>benches in the pit. &apos;Not a word of the last two acts of The Grecian Daughter, or of <lb/>any part of The Turnpike Gate, was heard&apos; reported the Morning Chronicle. 73 At the <lb/>end of their performance, the OPs left &apos;huzzaing&apos; in &apos;procession two and two.&apos; They <lb/>passed through Bow Street and onto the Strand where The Times reported &apos;they have <lb/>three loud cheers at the Chronicle office, and three ditto groans at the Morning Post <lb/>office.&apos; 74 The next night at Covent Garden Theatre the sentiment endured and the <lb/>OPs delighted in &apos;groaning for those newspapers which are inimical to their objects, <lb/>and cheering those which favour them.&apos; 75 <lb/>As the agents of the legal system (and their various hired hands) intensified their <lb/>efforts to police Covent Garden Theatre and to establish the transgressive agenda of <lb/>the theatre&apos;s management, newspapers became more than a venue for reports on <lb/>the Covent Garden Old Price riots. They became a space -alongside Covent Garden <lb/>Theatre, Bow Street, and the courts -where the law and its agents were made visible, <lb/>debated, and judged. The reports on the legal system and responses to their actions <lb/>in the form of the letters and notices that these newspapers carried do not constitute <lb/>a complete, dispassionate, or undistorted record of the conflict. How distorted this <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>72 Morning Chronicle, 3 November 1809. <lb/>73 Ibid. <lb/>74 The Times, 3 November 1809. <lb/>75 The Times, 4 November 1809. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>coverage was is outside of the purview of this study. Nevertheless, it is worth not-<lb/>ing that the fragments of the judicial records that survive aid us little in this regard. <lb/>They tell us that, for example, Richard Raper was committed to Bridewell &apos; on Oath <lb/>of James Brandon with making a Riot and Disturbance in Covent Garden Theatre.&apos; 76 <lb/>They suggest that Brandon -the Covent Garden Theatre doorman -took an active <lb/>role pursuing cases from Bow Street to the Westminster Quarter Sessions on behalf <lb/>of his employer, including those of James Black, Thomas Scott, and the aforemen-<lb/>tioned Samuel Dudfield. 77 They also indicate that whilst OPs accounted for a surge <lb/>in the numbers of prisoners delivered to the Westminster Quarter Sessions for riot <lb/>and disorder in October 1809, riot and disorder was already and would remain a <lb/>significant category of offence (numerically behind only assault and theft) for which <lb/>prisoners were delivered to both the Middlesex and Westminster Quarter Session <lb/>throughout 1809. 78 In short, although revealing in terms of the functioning of jus-<lb/>tice, the surviving judicial record does not help us explore perceptions of the law and <lb/>of how agents of the law responded to events at Covent Garden Theatre during the <lb/>height of the Old Price riots. <lb/>The strength, therefore, of the periodical record, dispassionate or otherwise, is <lb/>that it enables us to grapple with the fragility of the social contract between the legal <lb/>system and theatregoing Londoners. As the relationship worsened between own-<lb/>ers and patrons, between guardians and subjects, it would become clear that more <lb/>than the grievances of the OPs were at stake. On 4 November 1809 the Morning <lb/>Chronicle published a letter from a self-styled &apos;MODERATOR.&apos; &apos;In the name of BRITISH <lb/>FREEDOM,&apos; she wrote: <lb/>Are we to have BOW-STREET OFFICERS, BUM-BAILIFFS, AND OTHER <lb/>CATCHPOLES PRESIDING AT ELECTIONS, SEIZING THE INHABITANTS <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>76 London Metropolitan Archives, WJ/SP/1809. <lb/>77 London Metropolitan Archives, WJ/SB/B/0597. <lb/>78 Sessions Rolls for the Westerminster and Middlesex Session of the Peace can be fruitfully sampled to <lb/>gain a sense of the types of offence brought to these legislative arenas. London Metropolitan Archives, <lb/>(Middlesex) MJ/SR/3798, 3800, 3803, 3805, 3807, 3810; (Westminster) MJ/SR/3797, 3802, 3809, 3812. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>OF WESTMINSTER, AND DRAGGING THEM TO THE OFFICE OF THE <lb/>MAGISTRATES, FOR WEARING COCKADE, OR SURROUNDING WITH THE <lb/>USUAL CRIES AT THE HUSTINGS IN COVENT-GARDEN? What, Sir, are to be <lb/>the limits of the doctrines advanced upon this subject, and to which do they <lb/>not obviously and necessarily tend? <lb/>In contrast to the letter that opened this article, a letter published on 18 October <lb/>and specific to the OP war, MODERATOR addressed the very nature of liberty and the <lb/>freedoms enjoyed by free-born Englishmen. Taking the OP war as a microcosm for <lb/>wider social, political, and cultural concerns, 79 she used the letter to single out the <lb/>law, the agents of the legal system, and establishment co-option of both in the name <lb/>of public order and national security as the biggest threats to &apos;British Freedom.&apos; Her <lb/>letter is perhaps somewhat hyperbolic but, together with the reports on the legal <lb/>system and the public responses to their actions that this article has discussed, it <lb/>underscores the contemporary perception among a literate, theatregoing, but nev-<lb/>ertheless multi-class group of Londoners that the impartiality of justice had been <lb/>eroded and that this erosion was to the disadvantage of the many Britons and to the <lb/>benefit of the fashionable elites; that common interests had been sacrificed to the <lb/>advantage of the interests of the few. <lb/>The OP war ostensibly addressed the price of public entertainment, the nature <lb/>and arrangement of public spaces, and the forced imposition of novelty. Yet, as <lb/>the protest diversified, as policing and justice was perceived as ever more partial, <lb/>and as affronts to freedoms escalated, the Covent Garden Old Price riots became <lb/>a peculiar urban conflict that intersected with wider late-Georgian concerns, with <lb/>discursive arenas where British liberty and the freedom of her subjects were at stake. <lb/>Taken together, the fact that law, policing, and justice were prominent among these <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>79 MODERATOR was not alone in seeing the OP war as a microcosm of wider concerns. The Whig MP <lb/>William Windham wrote in a letter to his private secretary Thomas Amyot in 18 December 1809 that <lb/>&apos;I am the more alive, I suppose, to this defeat of the managers, because I see it as a rehearsal of what <lb/>is meant for higher performance; the managers being the government; the new prices the taxes [...] <lb/>and the O.P.s exactly the same description of persons as at present; L. S. Benjamin (ed.), The Windham <lb/>Papers, 2 vols. (London: Herbert Jenkins, 1913), II, pp. 366. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Baker: The Covent Garden Old Price Riots <lb/></note>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>concerns and that the OPs and their supporters -hardly radicals in their behaviour <lb/>and outlook -were dogged in their use of disorder and public pronouncements to <lb/>protest the injustices they alleged, reveals a fractured consensus regarding the rule <lb/>of law in the liberty of the subject and the extent to which law and liberty were avail-<lb/>able for reinterpretation. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <div type="conflict">Competing Interests <lb/>The author declares that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>
	  
	  <div type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgments <lb/>I thank anonymous peer reviewers and Melodee Beals -the history section editor <lb/>for The Open Library of Humanities -for their critical, rigerous, productive, and <lb/>encouraging comments on manuscript versions of the present article. An early ver-<lb/>sion of this paper was delivered at New Approaches to the History of Popular Pro-<lb/>test and Resistance in Britain and Ireland (1500-1900), University of Gloucestershire, <lb/>2 March 2013. I thank the workshop organisers and participants for their comments <lb/>and reflections. <lb/></div>

			<front>How to cite this article: Baker, J 2016 The Covent Garden Old Price Riots: Protest <lb/>and Justice in Late-Georgian London. Open Library of Humanities, 2(1): e4, pp. 1-36, <lb/>DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.16995/olh.13 <lb/>Published: 24 February 2016 <lb/>Copyright: © 2016 The Author(s). This is an open-access article distributed under the <lb/>terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC-BY 4.0), which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original author and source are credited. See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Open Library of Humanities is a peer-reviewed open <lb/>access journal published by Open Library of Humanities. </front>


	</text>


  
  </TEI>