<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">How the García Cousins Lost Their Accents: Understanding the Language of Title VII Decisions Approving English-Only Rules as the Product of Racial Dualism, Latino Invisibility, and Legal Indeterminacy</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Christopher David Ruiz</forename>
          <surname>Cameron</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-08T14:16:49.946Z">1/8/2026 3:16:49 PM</date>
        <title>review </title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.2307__3481062</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">1997</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.2307/3481062</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Christopher David Ruiz Cameron. (1997). How the García Cousins Lost Their Accents: Understanding the Language of Title VII Decisions Approving English-Only Rules as the Product of Racial Dualism, Latino Invisibility, and Legal Indeterminacy. California Law Review, 85(5), 1347. DOI: 10.2307/3481062</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T14:45:31.015417Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-19T14:45:31.015417Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-20T10:57:22.063Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>1_Version_durch</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-20T18:44:59.608Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Final</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-26T09:05:43.238Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-06T15:29:08.966Z" status="checked" who="#li">
      <desc>Validation completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-08T16:19:47.408Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T10:33:51.185Z" status="approved" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<front>How the Garcia Cousins Lost Their <lb/>Accents: Understanding the Language <lb/>of Title VII Decisions Approving <lb/>English-Only Rules as the Product of <lb/>Racial Dualism, Latino Invisibility, <lb/>and Legal Indeterminacy <lb/>Christopher David Ruiz Cameront <lb/>Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 outlaws discrimination in <lb/>employment based on, among other things, national origin. The adop-<lb/>tion by employers of policies requiring employees to speak only English <lb/>in the workplace would appear to constitute national origin discrimina-<lb/>tion against bilingual Latinos, whose Spanish-speaking ability is central <lb/>to their identity. Yet it is settled in the federal courts that implementing <lb/>&quot;English-only&quot; rules does not even state a prima facie case of discrimi-<lb/>nation. In this Essay, the author seeks to understand why judges hold <lb/>national origin challenges based on language discrimination in such <lb/>low esteem. He argues that three themes drawn from the growing litera-<lb/>ture of LatCrit theory help explain these results: racial dualism, the ten-<lb/>dency of courts to view civil rights discourse in terms of Blacks and <lb/>Whites to the exclusion of Browns and other people of color; Latino <lb/>Copyright 0 1997 California Law Review, Inc. <lb/>t <lb/>Professor of Law, Southwestern University School of Law, Los Angeles. A.B. 1980, <lb/>University of California, Los Angeles; J.D. 1983, Harvard Law School. My thanks to Kevin Johnson, <lb/>George Martfnez, and Eileen Guana for commenting on drafts; to Bill Piatt, Juan Perea, and Rachel <lb/>Moran, whose pioneering work clarified my thinking on the subject; and to Michael Olives, who <lb/>pointed me in the right direction. I also profited from remarks offered by panelists at the First <lb/>Latino/a Critical Studies Conference in La Jolla, California, organized by Laura Padilla, Gloria <lb/>Sandrino, and Frank Valdes, and from workshop participants at the 1997 Western/South-<lb/>western/Southeastern Law Professors of Color Conference in Albuquerque, New Mexico. This <lb/>project was made possible by the generous financial support of the Trustees of Southwestern <lb/>University School of Law. Valuable research assistance was provided by Jeanne Jorgensen (Class of <lb/>1996), Beverlei Colston and Donna Perelman (Class of 1998), and Matthias Wagener (Class of 1999). <lb/>1347 <lb/>LA RAZ4 LAW JOURNAL <lb/>1348 <lb/>CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/>invisibility, the tendency of legal institutions to make Hispanic litigants <lb/>and their injuries disappear; and legal indeterminacy, the tendency of <lb/>the jurisprudential tools of legal reasoning to be ambiguous and ma-<lb/>nipulable. The author concludes that understanding judges&apos; use of <lb/>language-phraseology, choice of metaphor, and silence-offers in-<lb/>sights into the values and prejudices that have assigned Latinos and <lb/>other minorities to second-class legal status. By confronting these values <lb/>and prejudices, courts and combatants may begin to change them and <lb/>accord victims of national origin discrimination the respect they de-<lb/>serve. <lb/></front>
	  
			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>&quot;What happened, Yo?&quot; her mother asked the hand she was pat-<lb/>ting a little later. &quot;We thought you and John were so happy.&quot; <lb/>&quot;We just didn&apos;t speak the same language,&quot; Yo said, simplifying. <lb/>-Yolanda Garcfa de la Torre&apos; <lb/>This is the story of how the federal law of equal opportunity failed <lb/>to protect three bilingual, distant cousins, each of whom bears the family <lb/>name Garcfa, when they spoke Spanish in the workplace. <lb/>The first cousin is Hector Garcfa, &quot;a native-born American of <lb/>Mexican descent.&quot; 2 He worked as a salesman for Gloor Lumber &amp; <lb/>Supply Inc. at its retail store in Brownsville, Texas. Mr. Garcfa was <lb/>among the seven of eight Gloor salesmen who were &quot;Hispanic&quot; 3 -a <lb/>business decision perhaps influenced by the fact that three-quarters of <lb/>the company&apos;s customer base is also Latino &quot;and many of Gloor&apos;s <lb/>customers wish to be waited on by a salesman who speaks Spanish.&quot; 4 <lb/>Mr. Garcfa, who speaks English perfectly well but prefers Spanish, <lb/>because that is the language spoken en casa, was hired by Gloor <lb/>&quot;precisely because he was bilingual.&quot; &apos; Eventually, he was fired for <lb/>the same reason. This happened after Gloor adopted a work rule <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1. JULIA ALVAREZ, HOW THE GARCfA GIRLS LOST THEIR ACCENTS 81 (1991). <lb/>2. Garcfa v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264,266 (5th Cir. 1980). <lb/>3. Id. at 267. Given a choice, I prefer the term &quot;Latino.&quot; See generally Angel R. Oquendo, <lb/>Re-imagining the Latinola Race, 12 HARV. BLACKLETTER J. 93, 96-99 (1995) (discussing the origins <lb/>and meanings of the terms &quot;Hispanic&quot; and &quot;Latino&quot; and arguing that &quot;Latino&quot; is the preferable <lb/>term). However, I shall use the term used by the litigant or court where appropriate. <lb/>4. Garcia, 618 F.2d at 267. <lb/>5. Id. at 269. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
			<front>[Vol. 10:261 <lb/></front>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[TITE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1349 <lb/></page>

			<body>forbidding any on-duty employee from speaking a language other than <lb/>English unless the employee was waiting on a non-English-speaking <lb/>customer. Soon thereafter, Mr. Garcfa was asked a question by another <lb/>Mexican-American employee about an item sought by a customer. Mr. <lb/>Garcfa replied &quot;in Spanish that the article was not available.&quot; 6 Alton <lb/>Gloor, a company officer and stockholder, overheard the conversation; <lb/>Mr. Garcfa was promptly discharged for breaking the rule. 7 <lb/>The second cousin is Priscilla Garcfa, &quot;a fully bilingual&quot; employee <lb/>of the Spun Steak Company of South San Francisco, California. 8 Of <lb/>Spun Steak&apos;s thirty-three employees, Ms. Garcfa is among the twenty-<lb/>four who speak Spanish, &quot;virtually all of whom are &apos;Hispanic&apos; .&quot;&apos; As a <lb/>production line worker, she stands in front of a conveyor belt and places <lb/>poultry and other meats into packages for resale. The company&apos;s pro-<lb/>duction line workers do not appear to have contact with the general <lb/>public, and &quot;Spun Steak has never required job applicants to speak or <lb/>to understand English as a condition of employment.&quot;&apos;&quot; <lb/>Ms. Garcfa&apos;s production line compafiera, Maricela Buitrago, is also <lb/>&quot;fully bilingual,&quot; but the two prefer communicating with one another <lb/>in Spanish.&quot; Two co-workers, one African-American and the other <lb/>Chinese-American, who apparently did not understand Spanish, never-<lb/>theless complained that Garcfa and Buitrago had made &quot;derogatory, <lb/>racist comments in Spanish.&quot;&apos; 2 The company&apos;s president, Kenneth <lb/>Bertelsen, formulated a new workplace rule mandating that employees <lb/>only communicate in English &quot;in connection with work.&quot;&apos; 3 The rule <lb/>permits conversation in languages other than English when speaking in <lb/>situations outside of the work context, such as at lunch and on breaks. 4 <lb/>After catching Ms. Garcfa and Ms. Buitrago speaking in Spanish while <lb/>working, the company issued warning letters and prohibited the pair <lb/>from working next to each other for two months. The workers&apos; union <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>6. Id. at 266. Precisely what the offending Spanish words or phrases were does not appear in <lb/>the decision-a remarkable omission by itself because uttering them got Mr. Garcfa fired. See infra <lb/>Part II.A. <lb/>7. See Garcia, 618 F.2d at 266. <lb/>8. See Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 998 F.2d 1480 (9th Cir. 1993). The opinion does not specify <lb/>Ms. Garcfa&apos;s ancestry, other than to suggest she is &quot;Hispanic.&quot; <lb/>9. Id. at 1483 (&quot;Virtually all of the Spanish-speaking employees are Hispanic.&quot;). <lb/>10. Id. <lb/>11. See id. <lb/>12. Id. <lb/>13. Id. <lb/>14. See id. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">19981 <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1350 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>unsuccessfully filed suit, charging that Spun Steak&apos;s English-only pol-<lb/>icy violates Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964.&quot; <lb/>The third cousin is Yolanda Garcfa de la Torre, a fictional <lb/>American poet, who as a young girl emigrated from the Dominican <lb/>Republic to New York with her parents and sisters Carla, Sandra, and <lb/>Sofia. The lifelong adventures of the Misses Garcfa de la Torre are <lb/>brought to life by novelist and literature professor Julia Alvarez in her <lb/>novel, How the Garcia Girls Lost Their Accents. 6 Although Professor <lb/>Alvarez weaves the Garcfa family tapestry in all its intricate and varie-<lb/>gated splendor, the singular thread in the life of each girl-and espe-<lb/>cially the poet Yolanda, or &quot;Yo&quot;-is her transformation from a <lb/>comfortable Spanish-speaking immigrant child into an unsure bilingual <lb/>American adult, who in struggling with her dual identity cannot help but <lb/>keep one foot firmly planted in the Old World and the other in the <lb/>New. 1 7 <lb/>Soon after their move to the United States, several incidents with a <lb/>neighbor introduce the Misses Garcfa to the United States&apos; resistance <lb/>toward biculturalism-and by extension, bilingualism. La Bruja, the <lb/>old woman &quot;with a helmet of beauty parlor blue hair&quot; who lives in the <lb/>apartment below them, t &quot; has been complaining that, among other things, <lb/>the Garcfas bother her by speaking loudly and in Spanish. One day La <lb/>Bruja stops Mrs. Garcfa and the four girls in the lobby. &quot;Spics!&quot; she <lb/>says, &quot;Go back to where you came from!&quot; 9 <lb/>The stories of the three cousins Garcfa are unremarkable merely <lb/>because they are, or could be, true. Even in what we sometimes suppose <lb/>to be these enlightened times, tales of overt discrimination against U.S. <lb/>citizens and legal residents who looc, speak, or act in a manner that the <lb/>Anglo cultural majority considers &quot;foreign&quot; could be told by all <lb/>too many folks, whether native-born or immigrant, professional or <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>15. See id. at 1484. <lb/>16. ALVAREZ, supra note 1, at 7, 19, 168; cf. Man J. Matsuda, Voices of America: Accent, <lb/>Antidiscrimination Law, and a Jurisprudence for the Last Reconstruction, 100 YALE L.J. 1329 (1991) <lb/>(examining related problem of whether classification based on employee&apos;s accent is national origin <lb/>discrimination). Professor Alvarez&apos;s book has provided useful illustrations for some of my colleagues <lb/>as well. See. e.g., Rachel F. Moran, Foreword: Demography and Distrust: The Latino Challenge to <lb/>Civil Rights and Immigration Policy in the 1990s and Beyond, 8 LA RAZA L.J. 1, 19 (1995) <lb/>(recounting story from Alvarez&apos;s book about how Papi became a U.S. citizen). Professor Alvarez <lb/>has elaborated on the adventures of the de ]a Torre family, this time from the perspective of <lb/>everyone other than Yolanda. See Julia Alvarez, iYo! (1997). <lb/>17. See, e.g., ALVAREZ, supra note 1, at 3-23 (describing Yolanda&apos;s antojos, or cravings, for <lb/>things from her Dominican Republic homeland). <lb/>18. Id. at 170. <lb/>19. Id. at 171. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1351 <lb/></page>

			<body>campesino, Latino or non-Latino. Rather, the Garcfas&apos; stories are re-<lb/>markable because, according to the leading federal appellate decisions, <lb/>none of them states a claim for illegal national origin discrimination. <lb/>In the real life cases of Hector&quot; and Priscilla, 1 the United States <lb/>Court of Appeals for the Fifth and Ninth Circuits, respectively, each held <lb/>that a private employer&apos;s English-only rule could not be considered <lb/>discriminatory.&apos; The Garcfas, these courts reasoned, are bilingual, and <lb/>therefore, can &quot;easily comply&quot; with the directive.&apos; <lb/>Under the law, <lb/>neither Garcfa has the right to speak Spanish while on duty-to supervi-<lb/>sors, co-workers, or even customers-unless communicating with some-<lb/>body else who speaks Spanish only. So Mr. Garcfa must stay fired, and <lb/>Ms. Garcfa shall remain segregated from her Spanish-speaking com-<lb/>pafiera for as long as her boss sees fit. <lb/>Even in the fictional case of Yolanda Garcfa, were the super to pla-<lb/>cate La Bruja by putting the Garcfa family out on the street, there is rea-<lb/>son to doubt whether a legal challenge could be successful. In the eyes <lb/>of the law, the family&apos;s ancestry, and especially its bilingualism, is more <lb/>of a liability than an asset. Nearly twenty-five years ago, the United <lb/>States Supreme Court held that Title VII&apos;s ban on &quot;national origin&quot; <lb/>discrimination does not mean what it appears to say, and, in fact, permits <lb/>an employer to deny a job to a lawful resident alien from Mexico based <lb/>solely upon her alienage. 24 Unfortunately for the Garcfa family, Title <lb/>VIII of the Civil Rights Act of 1968,1 which purports to outlaw <lb/>&quot;national origin&quot; discrimination in public housing, contains language <lb/>similar to that found in Title VII and is practically indistinguishable. 26 <lb/>United States society&apos;s serious misunderstandings about bilingual <lb/>speakers have even invaded courtroom proceedings. Just six years ago, <lb/>the Supreme Court decided that a prosecutor&apos;s use of peremptory chal-<lb/>lenges to exclude bilingual Latinos from jury service does not violate <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>20. See Garcfa v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264(5th Cir. 1980). <lb/>21. See Garcia v. Spun Steak Co., 998 F.2d 1480 (9th Cir. 1993). <lb/>22. The Ninth Circuit panel remanded to the district court to determine whether the company&apos;s <lb/>English-only rule discriminated against monolingual Spanish-speakers. See id. at 1490. <lb/>23. See Garcla, 618 F.2d at 270; Garcla, 998 F.2d at 1487-88. <lb/>24. See Espinoza v. Farah Mfg. Co., 414 U.S. 86, 95 (1973). <lb/>25. 42 U.S.C. § 3604 (1994). <lb/>26. The provision reads as follows: <lb/>[Ut shall be unlawful-<lb/>(a) To refuse to sell or to rent after the making of a bona fide offer ... a dwelling to any <lb/>person because of... national origin. <lb/>(b) To discriminate against any person in the terms, conditions, or privileges of sale or <lb/>rental of a dwelling.., because of... national origin. <lb/>Id. 42 U.S.C. § 3604(a)-(b). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1352 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>

			<body>the Equal Protection Clause.&quot; The prosecutor had struck two jurors be-<lb/>cause he was afraid they would listen to and use the direct testimony of <lb/>Spanish-speaking witnesses, rather than the official English translation. 28 <lb/>&quot;It is a harsh paradox,&quot; wrote Justice Kennedy for the Court, &quot;that one <lb/>may become proficient enough in English to participate in trial ... only <lb/>to encounter disqualification because he knows a second language as <lb/>well.&quot;29 <lb/>It is precisely this &quot;harsh paradox&quot; that merits a searching inquiry. <lb/>In our times, U.S. citizens seem obsessed with passing laws that, far from <lb/>preserving bilingualism, direct everyone to speak English only.&quot; <lb/>Although a First-Amendment challenge to such a rule for state govern-<lb/>ment employees was recently before the United States Supreme Court, 3 &apos; <lb/>the case did little to resolve either U.S. feelings about bilingualism in <lb/>general or the validity of such rules for private sector employees in par-<lb/>ticular. This is unfortunate, because English-only rules constitute pre-<lb/>cisely the type of national origin discrimination that violates Title VII. <lb/>Title VII is supposed to secure equal opportunity with respect to the <lb/>terms, conditions, and privileges of employment of all workers, regard-<lb/>less of &quot;race, color, religion, sex, or national origin.&quot; 32 <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>27. See Hernandez v. New York, 500 U.S. 352, 369 (1991). <lb/>28. See id. at 356. <lb/>29. Id. at 371. <lb/>30. At least eighteen states have adopted &quot;official English&quot; laws, including Alabama, ALA. <lb/>CoNsT. amend. DIX; Arkansas, ARK. CODE ANN. § 1-4-117 (Michie 1996); Arizona, ARIZ. CONST. <lb/>art. XXVIII; California, CAL. CONST. art. III, § 6; Colorado, COLO. CONST. art. II, § 30a; Florida, <lb/>FLA. CONSr. art. II, § 9; Georgia, 1986 Ga. Laws 529; Hawaii, HAw. CoNsT. art. XV, § 4; Illinois, 5 <lb/>ILL. COMP. STAT. ANN. § 460/20 (West 1993); Indiana, IND. CODE ANN. § 1-2-10-1 (West Supp. <lb/>1996); Kentucky, KY. REV. STAT. ANN. § 2.013 (Michie 1992); Mississippi, Miss. CODE ANN. § 3-3-<lb/>31 (1991); Nebraska, NEB. CONSr. art. I, § 27; North Carolina, N.C. GEN. STAT. § 145-12 (1995); <lb/>North Dakota, N.D. CENT. CODE § 54-02-13 (1989); South Carolina, S.C. CODE ANN. § 1-1-696 <lb/>(Law Co-op. Supp. 1996); Tennessee, TENN. CODE ANN. § 4-1-404 (1991); and Virginia, VA. CODE <lb/>ANN. § 22.1-212.1 (Michie Supp. 1996). <lb/>31. See Yniguez v. Arizonans for Official English, 69 F.3d 920 (9th Cir. 1995) (en banc), cert. <lb/>granted sub nom. Arizonans for Official English v. Arizona, 116 S. Ct. 1316 (1996) (granting review <lb/>of question whether ARiz. CoNsr. art. XXVIII, requiring state government officials and employees <lb/>to &quot;act&quot; in English only, unconstitutionally restricts free expression), vacated as moot, 117 S. Ct. 1055 <lb/>(1997). Yniguez marks the second time the Supreme Court has vacated as moot an important Ninth <lb/>Circuit opinion by Judge Stephen Reinhardt finding an English-only rule to constitute national origin <lb/>discrimination. See Gutierrez v. Mun. Court, 838 F.2d 1031 (9th Cir. 1988), vacated as moot, 409 U.S. <lb/>1016 (1989). For an analysis of Yniquez see Ivan A. Tamayo, &quot;Official Language Legislation: Literal <lb/>Silencing/Silenciando La Lengua, 13 HARV. BLACKLErER J. 107 (1997). <lb/>32. <lb/>(a) It shall be an unlawful employment practice for an employer-<lb/>(1) to fail or refuse to hire or to discharge any individual, or otherwise to discriminate <lb/>against any individual with respect to his compensation, terms, conditions, or privileges of <lb/>employment, because of such individual&apos;s.., national origin; or <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1353 <lb/></page>

			<body>Under Title VII, a work rule whose adverse effects fall exclusively <lb/>upon the most widely accepted class of protected workers-African-<lb/>American men 3 3 -ordinarily would raise a prima facie violation of the <lb/>statute. 4 In most of our courts, an attempt to defend such a rule by <lb/>claiming it could easily be complied with would be rejected, if not <lb/>mocked, as the equivalent of telling an African-American that she may <lb/>lawfully be &quot;required to sit at the back of a bus&quot; because she could <lb/>easily do so. 35 How, then, can a work rule which effectively requires a <lb/>bilingual employee &quot;to sit at the back of the bus&quot; escape the grasp of <lb/>the employment discrimination laws? <lb/>That English-only rules have a discriminatory impact on bilingual <lb/>Latinos ought to be beyond rational debate. 3 &apos; As I summarize below, the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>(2) to limit, segregate, or classify his employees or applicants for employment in any way <lb/>which would deprive or tend to deprive any individual of employment opportunities <lb/>or otherwise adversely affect his status as an employee, because of such <lb/>individual&apos;s ... national origin. <lb/>42 U.S.C. § 2000e-2(a) (1)-(2) (1994). <lb/>33. See, e.g., Griggs v. Duke Power Co., 401 U.S. 424, 430-31 (1971) (holding that an <lb/>employer&apos;s requirement, as applied to Black applicants, that prospective employees possess a high <lb/>school diploma or pass an aptitude test when the practice is unrelated to job performance establishes <lb/>a paradigmatic prima facie Title VII violation). <lb/>34. See id. But even a Black plaintiff will face serious obstacles in attempting to make out a <lb/>prima facie case if he presents a discrimination charge that falls outside this immediately <lb/>recognizable paradigm. See, e.g., Odima v. Westin Tucson Hotel, 53 F.3d 1484 (9th Cir. 1995) <lb/>(reversing grant of summary judgment against national origin discrimination challenge by qualified <lb/>Nigerian-born Black, who spoke clear but accented English, for hotel&apos;s failure to promote him from <lb/>laundry room to accounting department); Rogers v. American Airlines, 527 F. Supp. 229 (S.D.N.Y. <lb/>1981) (granting summary judgment against race and sex discrimination challenge by African-<lb/>American woman to airline&apos;s rule prohibiting the wearing of braided hairstyles). For an insightful <lb/>critique of judicial reliance on false dichotomies, including the purported contrast between &quot;mutable&quot; <lb/>(e.g., hairstyle) and &quot;immutable&quot; (e.g., &quot;race&quot;) characteristics in cases like Rogers, see Paulette M. <lb/>Caldwell, A Hair Piece: Perspectives on the Intersection of Race and Gender, 1991 DuE LJ. 365, <lb/>370 (&quot;Hair seems to be such a little thing. Yet it is the little things, the small everyday realities of life, <lb/>that reveal the deepest recesses and values of a culture... ). <lb/>35. See, e.g., Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 13 F.3d 296, 298 (9th Cir. 1993) (Reinhardt, J., <lb/>dissenting) (denial of rehearing en banc); accord McLaurin v. Oklahoma State Regents for Higher <lb/>Educ., 339 U.S. 637 (1950) (segregating Black public law school student by requiring him to sit only <lb/>in portion of classroom reserved for his exclusive use violated the Equal Protection Clause). <lb/>36. Neither this Essay nor my criticisms of the cases cited herein is primarily concerned with <lb/>the employer&apos;s right, as protected by long established Title VII law, to adopt and enforce English-<lb/>only rules demanded by business necessity, such as the need for safety during work hours. Instead, I <lb/>focus here on challenges to such rules preventing the speaking of non-English languages, especially <lb/>Spanish, between employees during working hours when there is no proof in the record that tangible <lb/>harm to the employer&apos;s business either has been caused or could be caused by such activity. See, <lb/>e.g., Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 13 F.3d 296, 302 &amp; n.1l (9th Cir. 1993) (Reinhardt, J., dissenting) <lb/>(denial of rehearing en banc) (&quot;No reasonable person would suggest that Title VII requires the <lb/>operator of an English language radio station to permit a hired broadcaster to broadcast in whole or in <lb/>part in another language, contrary to the station&apos;s policies.&quot;); see also Juan F. Perea, English-Only <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">19981 <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1354 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>Spanish language is central to Latino identity. People whose primary <lb/>language is Spanish constitute a cognizable group-a &quot;discrete and in-<lb/>sular minority&quot;-who historically have been, and continue to be, sub-<lb/>ject to discrimination. Therefore, English-only policies that appear to <lb/>be neutral workplace regulations are actually language discrimination <lb/>against bilingual employees, including Spanish-speakers. This is illegal <lb/>national origin discrimination, as so many commentators have persua-<lb/>sively argued. 37 <lb/>The question, then, is not whether English-only rules are national <lb/>origin discrimination, but why courts have consistently refused to find <lb/>them so. I believe the explanation lies partly in the tendency of judges <lb/>toward &quot;racial dualism&quot;-the tendency to view civil rights discourse in <lb/>terms of Blacks and Whites only. Racial dualism is a world view that <lb/>infects judicial decision making, as reflected in the reported opinions of <lb/>cases dealing with challenges to English-only rules brought under Title <lb/>VII. This view embraces, among other things, reliance on false di-<lb/>chotomies, such as the traditional jurisprudential distinction between <lb/>&quot;mutable&quot; and &quot;immutable&quot; personal characteristics. Decisions ap-<lb/>proving English-only rules in the workplace are based largely on <lb/>judges&apos; limited understandings of the forms that national origin dis-<lb/>crimination can take: after all, for a bilingual employee, isn&apos;t Spanish-<lb/>speaking ability a mutable characteristic, changeable without causing <lb/>serious inconvenience? <lb/>Racial dualism is problematic not only because it limits judges&apos; <lb/>understanding of national origin claims, but also because it makes <lb/>Latinos and their problems in the workplace invisible. If racial dualism <lb/>were a coin, then its &quot;flip&quot; side would be blank. When there are only <lb/>two ways of seeing things-Black or White-other colors, such as <lb/>Brown, are bound to remain hidden from view. <lb/>Finally, racial dualism and invisibility are often submerged, and <lb/>thereby left unexamined, in the texts of judicial decisions. This happens <lb/>because the jurisprudential tools of legal reasoning are constructed so as <lb/>to conform to pre-existing world views. That is, legal rules, and no-<lb/>where more so than in the realm of national origin discrimination, are <lb/>indeterminate, making it not only possible but also easy to reach results <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Rules and the Right to Speak One&apos;s Primary Language in the Workplace, 23 U. MICH. J.1. REFORM <lb/>265, 299 (1990) (&quot;[A] bilingual stage actor cast in the role of Hamlet would not have a right to <lb/>deliver the soliloquy in Spanish .... [The actor&apos;s use of Spanish] would constitute poor performance, <lb/>and the employer could properly discipline or discharge a poorly performing employee.&quot;). <lb/>37. See, e.g., Alfredo Mirand6, &quot;En la Tierra del Ciego, El Tuerto Es Rey&quot; (&quot;In the Land of the <lb/>Blind, the One Eyed Person Is King&quot;): Bilingualism as Disability, 26 N.M. L. REv. 75 (1996). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1355 <lb/></page>

			<body>that make English-only policies seem benign to the decision-makers <lb/>who consider them. <lb/>By their use of language-phraseology, choice of metaphor, or <lb/>silence-parties and judges offer insights into why the bilingual popu-<lb/>lation receives a second-class (if any) form of protected status. These <lb/>insights yield a rich harvest of information about their, and our, belief <lb/>systems concerning the treatment of minority cultures in the workplace. <lb/>By confronting these values and prejudices, combatants and courts alike <lb/>may begin to change their belief systems and accord victims of national <lb/>origin discrimination the respect they truly deserve. <lb/>In this Essay, I will examine the manner in which litigants and <lb/>judges discuss English-only rules. I will do so by referring to what I <lb/>believe to be three interrelated, yet distinct, themes that are emerging in <lb/>the recent literature of Latino Critical Legal Theory.&quot; Part I explores <lb/>the limits of racial dualism, the traditional characterization of race <lb/>relations along a binary Black/White paradigm, 39 in addressing the study <lb/>of oppression of Latinos. Too often the corpus of civil rights literature <lb/>is seen as the product of a clash between &quot;two races,&quot; one Black and <lb/>one White.&quot; Although the racial dualism analyzed by this literature is <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>38. See supra pp. 11-13. For purposes of writing this Essay, I have identified, labeled, and <lb/>perhaps oversimplified these themes as I understand them to be present in the body of literature cited <lb/>herein and in the thinking of some but not all of the panelists who presented papers at the First <lb/>Latino/a Legal Critical Studies Conference held in May 1996 in La Jolla, California. I make no <lb/>representations that the authors whose work I have cited would agree with my characterizations, <lb/>understandings, or uses of these themes. <lb/>For a word of caution on the difficulty of undertaking &quot;Latino&quot; scholarship in general, see Kevin <lb/>R. Johnson, Some Thoughts on the Future of Latino Legal Scholarship, 2 HARV.-LATINO L REV. <lb/>(forthcoming 1997) (offering &quot;circumspection about the possibility of formulating a coherent &apos;Latino&apos; <lb/>vision,&quot; but contending there exists &quot;a distinct need for the development of Latino legal scholarship&quot;). <lb/>39. See, e.g., Robert S. Chang, Toward an Asian American Legal Scholarship: Critical Race <lb/>Theory, Post-Structuralism, and Narrative Space, 81 CALIF. L. REV. 1241, 1245-50 (1993); Kevin R. <lb/>Johnson, Civil Rights and Immigration: Challenges for the Latino Community in the Twenty-First <lb/>Century, 8 LA RAZA L.J. 42,64-66 (1995); Moran, supra note 16, at 10-13, 16-19; Oquendo, supra <lb/>note 3, at 99-102; Juan F. Perea, Ethnicity and the Constitution: Beyond the Black and White Binary <lb/>Constitution, 36 WM. &amp; MARY L REV. 571, 571-72 (1995); Deborah Ramirez, Multicultural <lb/>Empowerment: It&apos;s Not Just Black and White Anymore, 47 STAN. L REV. 957, 958-60 (1995); <lb/>William R. Tamayo, When the &quot;Coloreds&quot; Are Neither Black Nor Citizens: The United States Civil <lb/>Rights Movement and Global Migration, 2 ASIAN L.J. 1, 9-11 (1995); see generally IAN F. HANEY <lb/>L6PEZ, WHITE BY LAW: THE LEGAL CONSTRUCTION OF RACE 63-80 (1996) (discussing how <lb/>Latinos, Asians, and other minorities sought to characterize themselves as &quot;Whites&quot; rather than <lb/>&quot;Blacks&quot; so as to enjoy the benefits of White persons codified in federal immigration laws). <lb/>40. See, e.g., ANDREW HACKER, Two NATIONS: BLACK AND WHITE, SEPARATE, HOSTILE, <lb/>UNEQUAL (rev. ed. 1995); RAPHAEL J. SONENSHEIN, POLITICS IN BLACK AND WHITE: RACE AND <lb/>POWER IN Los ANGELES (1993). Americans who get their news from television rather than from <lb/>print media sampled this perspective recently when a popular network program hosted by journalist <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1356 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>undeniably important to our study of equal opportunity law, it does not <lb/>translate well when applied to Latinos, whose oppression is not limited to <lb/>odious classifications based upon skin color or race but also includes <lb/>language capability, religious tradition, immigration status, and other <lb/>markers of non-Anglo &quot;otherness.&quot; Part I offers examples of how <lb/>employers argue, and how judges report and analyze, national origin <lb/>claims in terms of a Black/White paradigm, and thereby oversimplify <lb/>and diminish Latinos&apos; claims. <lb/>Focusing on a closely related theme, Part II argues that the law so <lb/>ignores the plight of Latinos in the United States that we are virtually <lb/>&quot;invisible.&quot; 4 &apos; In many ways, the oppression resulting from a policy of <lb/>conscious discrimination against a recognized people is less intractable <lb/>than the oppression resulting from denying that such a people exists at <lb/>all. At least in the former case, there can be improvement once the key <lb/>task-persuading the majority culture to recognize that the victimized <lb/>&quot;other&quot; faces a problem-is undertaken. But in the latter case, there <lb/>can be no progress unless and until the majority culture recognizes <lb/>there is a victim. Part II offers examples of how parties and decision <lb/>makers, both in their language and failure to use language, make <lb/>Latinos invisible by ignoring how English-only rules create victims. <lb/>Part III argues that the indeterminacy of modern legal materials-<lb/>here, cases and statutes-leaves open to discretion a large and important <lb/>field of decisions, in all areas of the law, that can be manipulated to jus-<lb/>tify multiple outcomes to lawsuits. 42 Legal indeterminacy is particularly <lb/>apparent in the various courts&apos; interpretations of Title VII. Although <lb/>Title VII prohibits national origin discrimination, the subject merited <lb/>hardly a paragraph in the statute&apos;s legislative history, and the task of <lb/>defining the term fell largely to the Equal Employment Opportunity <lb/>Commission (&quot;EEOC&quot;). Part I offers examples of how employers <lb/>and courts have taken full advantage of this indeterminacy in litigation <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Ted Koppel broadcasted an otherwise insightful series on race relations. See Nightline: America in <lb/>Black and White (ABC television broadcasts, Sept. 23-27, 1996). <lb/>41. See LA RAZA: FORGOTTEN AMERICANS (Julian Samora ed., 1966); Kevin R. Johnson, Los <lb/>Olvidados: Images of the Immigrant, Political Power of Noncitizens, and Immigration Law and <lb/>Enforcement, 1993 BYU L. REV. 1139 (1993); Juan F. Perea, Los Olvidados: On the Making of an <lb/>Invisible People, 70 N.Y.U. L. REV. 965 (1995); see also GEORGE I. SANCHEZ, FORGOTTEN PEOPLE <lb/>(1967) (recounting the history of New Mexicans). <lb/>42. See George A. Martinez, Legal Indeterminacy, Judicial Discretion, and the Mexican-<lb/>American Litigation Experience: 1930-1980, 27 U.C. DAVIS L REV. 555, 557-60 (1994); see <lb/>generally THE POLITICS OF LAW: A PROGRESSIVE CRITIQUE (David Kairys ed., 1982); RICHARD A <lb/>POSNER, THE PROBLEMS OF JURISPRUDENCE (1990); Joseph William Singer, The Player and the <lb/>Cards: Nihilism and Legal Theory, 94 YALE L.J. 1 (1984); Mark V. Tushnet, Following the Rules Laid <lb/>Down: A Critique of Interpretivism and Neutral Principles, 96 HARV. L. REV. 781 (1983). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">(Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1357 <lb/></page>

			<body>over the validity of English-only rules and the EEOC&apos;s interpretation of <lb/>Title VII as applied to them, sometimes in ways that subvert the purpose <lb/>of the statute. <lb/>Finally, this Essay concludes with the hope that, by understanding <lb/>how we speak of Latinos, litigants and judges will better appreciate the <lb/>seriousness of national origin discrimination and treat meritorious <lb/>claims challenging English-only rules with the respect they deserve. <lb/>Throughout this Essay, I shall return not only to the stories of the <lb/>three cousins Garcfa, but also to those of other Latino litigants in the <lb/>decisions interpreting Title VII. <lb/>I <lb/>THE LIMITS OF RACIAL DUALISM IN NATIONAL ORIGIN CLAIMS <lb/>&quot;Sky,&quot; she tried. Then, the saying of it made it right: &quot;I want to <lb/>be the sky.&quot; <lb/>&quot;That&apos;s not allowed... Your own rules: you&apos;ve got to rhyme <lb/>with your own name. &quot; <lb/>&quot;I&quot;-she pointed to herself-&quot;rhymes with the sky&quot;! <lb/>&quot;But not with [Yo]!&quot; John wagged his finger at her. His eyes <lb/>softened with desire. He placed his mouth over her mouth and <lb/>ohhed her lips open. <lb/>&quot;Yo rhymes with cielo in Spanish.&quot; Yo&apos;s words fell into the dark, <lb/>mute cavern of John&apos;s mouth. Cielo, cielo, the word echoed. <lb/>And Yo was running, like the mad, into the safety of her first <lb/>tongue, where the proudly monolingual John could not catch <lb/>her, even if he tried. <lb/>-Yolanda Garcfa de la Torre 43 <lb/>As Rachel Moran has reminded us, U.S. history is associated with at <lb/>least two models purporting to account for how the Anglo cultural ma-<lb/>jority has traditionally welcomed &quot;other&quot; peoples to this country. <lb/>These may be referred to as the &quot;civil rights&quot;&quot; model and the <lb/>&quot;immigration&quot; 4 5 model. <lb/>In the civil rights model, the world consists of Black people, who <lb/>historically have been denied their basic human rights, and White <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>43. ALVAREZ, supra note 1, at 72. <lb/>44. See Moran, supra note 16, at 4, 10. <lb/>45. See id. at 13, 16-17. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURAAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1358 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>people, who by law, force, or both have been responsible for it. In more <lb/>recent times, our society has attempted to reform the law and how it is <lb/>enforced in order to liberate Blacks and their descendants from their <lb/>oppression by Whites and their forebears. Because the overclass is <lb/>composed of Whites and the underclass is composed of Blacks, the civil <lb/>rights model is binary in nature; civil rights are understood as having <lb/>been denied, and therefore as now in need of redress, on the basis of <lb/>Whiteness or Blackness. Thus, the study of U.S. race relations has tradi-<lb/>tionally been the study of what Angel Oquendo calls &quot;racial dual-<lb/>ism&quot;:6 the inquiry into the brutal enslavement and tentative <lb/>emancipation of Blacks by Whites to the exclusion of the study of op-<lb/>pressive conditions suffered by other minorities, especially Latinos. <lb/>&quot;The U.S. racial imagination,&quot; says Oquendo, <lb/>posits a bifurcated universe, in which the black-white divide <lb/>overwhelms all other differences. This conception of race is not <lb/>surprising in light of the prominence in U.S. history of the <lb/>oppression of people of African ancestry by individuals of <lb/>European extraction. <lb/>The institutions of enslavement and <lb/>discrimination have created and reinforced the perception that <lb/>the opposition between these two groups is essential and <lb/>universal. Racial dualism is but the other side of dualist racism. 7 <lb/>The trouble with this &quot;bifurcated universe&quot; is that Latinos have neither <lb/>a place in it nor a need for access to the machinery of civil rights law. If <lb/>&quot;racial dualism is but the other side of dualist racism,&quot; then racism is <lb/>only a problem for Blacks and Whites and nobody else. <lb/>In the immigration model, the superior people are still White, but <lb/>now what makes them superior is a type of nativism characterized by <lb/>their Anglo, English-speaking, monolingual background. The superior <lb/>people, with the Statue of Liberty as their emblem, welcome by invita-<lb/>tion non-Anglo, non-English-speaking inferiors, especially those from <lb/>continental Europe, but only so long as they promise to assimilate-that <lb/>is, try to become more like Anglo English-speakers and less like the <lb/>folks they used to be. <lb/>Neither model accurately depicts our actual traditions, much less <lb/>the story of Latino Americans in the United States. The civil rights <lb/>model fails to account for the Latino experience in at least two <lb/>respects. First, in the White-and-Black world, only skin color matters; <lb/>the other meaningful differences that may distinguish a people-such as <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>46. Oquendo, supra note 3, at 99. <lb/>47. Id. at 99-100. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1359 <lb/></page>

			<body>language, culture, religion, and the like-are ignored. In reality, Latinos <lb/>have diverse racial and ethnic origins and are attuned to questions of <lb/>class and wealth, not merely race or ethnicity. 48 Yet as many Latinos of <lb/>my acquaintance and in my family have told their stories, to so many <lb/>Whites, all minorities are &quot;niggers.&quot; 49 <lb/>Second, the key institution whose effects the civil rights model is <lb/>designed to address--chattel slavery-was not extensively used by <lb/>Anglos to subjugate Latinos in what became the territorial United States. <lb/>Whereas African Americans trace their roots in the United States to <lb/>1619, when the first slaves arrived at Jamestown, Virginia, Latino <lb/>Americans often trace their roots to 1519, when a century earlier, Cortes, <lb/>in leading the Conquest, initiated the uniquely Latino tradition of mesti-<lb/>zaje, or the mixing of European and Indian blood by miscegenation, <lb/>thus creating a race of people who never existed before. Indeed, many if <lb/>not most Latino Americans trace their ancestry back much further than <lb/>the Spanish Conquest. Latino identity is based upon not only mestizaje, <lb/>but also pre-Columbian roots in the Americas, indigenous roots among <lb/>Indian peoples who called the land home well before 1519. To be sure, <lb/>Latinos faced oppression by Spanish and Anglo-American conquerors, <lb/>but it was an oppression accomplished by means other than slavery. 50 <lb/>And whereas the Civil War was fought and our Constitution amended in <lb/>hopes of resolving the proper status of former slaves, an endless web of <lb/>legal entanglements, unresolved to the present day, has been spun to <lb/>determine the &quot;proper&quot; status of Latinos as minorities here. 5 &apos; <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>48. See Moran, supra note 16, at 10. <lb/>49. My grandfather Frank X. Ruiz and my colleague J. Michael Echevarria, each bearing a <lb/>phenotype much darker and more Indian than mine, have both related to me childhood stories in <lb/>which Anglo youths welcomed them to a new neighborhood or school by calling out, &quot;Hi, nigger!&quot; <lb/>Conversation with Frank X. Ruiz (July 1996); Conversation with J. Michael Echevarria (July 1992). <lb/>50. Which is not to deny the essential role that race played in the establishment and <lb/>stratification of Mexican colonial society following the Conquest. As the historian Ram6n Eduardo <lb/>Ruiz has put it: <lb/>The Spaniards... had established a pigmentocracy, with status based, to a large extent, on <lb/>appearance. To be light of skin, a European characteristic, was a mark of honor and <lb/>prestige; to be dark of skin, or moreno, was not. <lb/>Whites, whether peninsulares, criollos, or fair-skinned mestizos, were the &quot;happy <lb/>few.&quot; Without a close examination of racial pedigrees, they made up, at best, no more than <lb/>one-fifth of the population. Of New Spain&apos;s 6.1 million inhabitants in 1810, just over 1 <lb/>million were of the &quot;white race.&quot;... <lb/>Given these statistics, and the value ittached to being of Spanish descent, one&apos;s racial <lb/>classification acquired major importance. Everyone wanted to be white .... <lb/>RAM6N EDUARDO Ruiz, TRIUMPH AND TRAGEDY: A HISTORY OF THE MEXICAN PEOPLE 119 <lb/>(1992). <lb/>51. See generally RICHARD GRISWOLD DEL CASTILLO, THE TREATY OF GUADALUPE <lb/>HIDALGO: A LEGACY OF CONFLICT (1990) (offering excellent in-depth study of the events leading <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">19981 <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1360 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>

			<body>Similarly, the immigration model fails to account for the Latino <lb/>condition in at least two respects. First, as Rachel Moran has pointed <lb/>out, it is based on the supposed historical experience of immigrants <lb/>from Europe, who are believed to have come &quot;by invitation only&quot; to <lb/>the United States, where they received a &quot;warm reception&quot; for accept-<lb/>ing the challenges of assimilation. 52 But many present-day Latinos are <lb/>not the descendants of immigrants, at least as we commonly use the <lb/>term; rather, they are the children of ancestors who had settled the New <lb/>World centuries before Anglos first arrived in the Southwest. Whereas <lb/>the ancestors of most European Americans voluntarily came to the <lb/>United States, the ancestors of Latino Americans in the old California, <lb/>New Mexico, and Texas territories involuntarily had the United States <lb/>come to them through the forced annexation of their homelands. 53 <lb/>Even Latinos whose ancestors immigrated here after the Texas Rebellion <lb/>of 1836 or the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo of 1848, which ended the <lb/>Mexican-American War by transferring one-half of all Mexican home-<lb/>lands to the U.S., came not from Europe but from the Caribbean, <lb/>Central America, Mexico, or South America. <lb/>Second, the &quot;immigration&quot; model ignores the rich non-Anglo, <lb/>multilingual heritage our country has enjoyed since its inception. As <lb/>Juan Perea 4 and Bill Piatt&quot; 5 have documented, the United States is not <lb/>now and has never been an exclusively Anglo, English-speaking, mono-<lb/>lingual nation. The Dutch, French, German, and Spanish languages <lb/>were each spoken contemporaneously with English. Indeed, Spanish <lb/>was the first European language spoken in the New World, including <lb/>North America. By the late sixteenth century, the conquistadores had <lb/>expanded New Spain to present-day New Mexico and begun a <lb/>centuries-long tradition in which Spanish remained the principal lan-<lb/>guage, even after that territory had become annexed to the U.S. 56 <lb/>Unfortunately, lessons about the limits of racial dualism as applied <lb/>to bilingual Latinos have been largely lost on the courts hearing Title <lb/>VII cases. Below, I identify two common errors, traceable to the United <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>up to and following the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which transferred about one-half of sovereign <lb/>Mexican lands to the U.S.). <lb/>52. See Moran, supra note 16, at 17. <lb/>53. See generally GRISWOLD DEL CASTILLO, supra note 51. <lb/>54. See Perea, supra note 41, at 972; Juan F. Perea, Demography and Distrust: An Essay on <lb/>American Languages, Cultural Pluralism, and Official English, 77 MINN. L. REv. 269, 271-81 (1992). <lb/>55. See BILL PiATT, LANGUAGE ON THE JOB 4-5 (1993); BILL PIATT, LONLY ENGLISH? LAW <lb/>AND LANGUAGE POLICY IN THE UNITED STATES 3-11 (1990) [hereinafter PIATr, LONLY <lb/>ENGLISH?]. <lb/>56. See PIATT, LONLY ENGLISH?, supra note 55, at 11-12. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1361 <lb/></page>

			<body>States&apos; tendency toward racial dualism, found in reported decisions in-<lb/>volving English-only rules: (A) the belief that a &quot;mere inconvenience&quot; <lb/>occasioned by a classification based on national origin, such as requir-<lb/>ing a bilingual Latino to speak English only, does not constitute dis-<lb/>crimination; and (B) the understanding that the only legitimate index of <lb/>a protected class is some &quot;immutable&quot; characteristic, such as race. <lb/>A. English-Only Rules and the Veil Of &quot;Inconvenience&quot; <lb/>In Garcia v. Spun Steak Co., the Ninth Circuit, with little fanfare, <lb/>raised what turned out to be an insurmountable barrier for Priscilla <lb/>Garcfa: it insisted that, in order to establish a prima facie case of dispa-<lb/>rate impact, she prove that Spun Steak&apos;s speak-English-only rule have a <lb/>&quot;significantly adverse impact&quot; on the protected class of bilingual <lb/>Spanish-speaking workers.&apos; This construction of Title VII opened the <lb/>door to a discussion of how the rule was &quot;merely [an] inconvenience&quot; <lb/>and could not &quot;significantly&quot; affect people like Ms. Garcfa. <lb/>Judge O&apos;Scannlain addressed the plaintiff&apos;s claims as arising from <lb/>the fact &quot;that fully bilingual employees are hampered in the enjoyment <lb/>of the privilege [of conversing] because for them switching from one <lb/>language to another is not fully volitional.&quot; 8 He rejected this argument <lb/>as irrelevant, even assuming it could be proven. 59 According to Judge <lb/>O&apos;Scannlain: <lb/>Title VII is not meant to protect against rules that merely incon-<lb/>venience some employees, even if the inconvenience falls <lb/>squarely on a protected class. Rather, Title VII protects against <lb/>only those policies that have a significant impact. The fact that <lb/>an employee may have to catch himself or herself from occa-<lb/>sionally slipping into Spanish does not impose a burden signifi-<lb/>cant enough to amount to the denial <lb/>of equal <lb/>opportunity.... The fact that a bilingual employee may, on oc-<lb/>casion, unconsciously substitute a Spanish word in the place of <lb/>an English one does not override our conclusion that the bilin-<lb/>gual employee can easily comply with the rule.&apos; <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>57. Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 998 F.2d 1480, 1486 (9th Cir. 1993) (emphasis added). <lb/>58. Id. at 1487-88. <lb/>59. See id. at 1488. <lb/>60. Id. (emphasis in original). Judge O&apos;Scannlain also explained that there is no disparate <lb/>impact with respect to a privilege of employment &quot;if the rule is one that the affected employee can <lb/>readily observe and nonobservance is a matter of individual preference.&quot; Id. at 1487 (quoting Garcfa <lb/>v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264,270 (5th Cir. 1980)). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">19981 <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1362 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>There are three remarkable things about this reasoning. First, <lb/>Judge O&apos;Scannlain cited no persuasive authority for the proposition that <lb/>adverse impact analysis is limited only to &quot;significant&quot; adverse impacts. <lb/>Indeed, for the most part, he cited no authority at all.&apos; Yet the language <lb/>of Title VII does not single out &quot;significant&quot; as opposed to <lb/>&quot;insignificant&quot; discrimination. 62 The fair-and literal-reading of the <lb/>statute is that limiting, segregating, or classifying an employee &quot;in any <lb/>way&quot; which would even &quot;tend&quot; to deprive her of employment oppor-<lb/>tunities, or to &quot;adversely affect&quot; her employment status, is <lb/>&quot;unlawful.&quot; 3 Thus, under a traditional plain-meaning approach to <lb/>statutory interpretation, the reasoning of Garcia v. Spun Steak Co. <lb/>failed. <lb/>Second, Judge O&apos;Scannlain never sought to explain from whose <lb/>perspective the measure of &quot;insignificance&quot; should be taken. That of <lb/>the plaintiff? The employer? A reasonable bilingual person? Absent <lb/>any explanation, we have little choice but to assume he meant his own <lb/>perspective, or more generally, that of the three judges on this panel of <lb/>the Ninth Circuit-which, so far as we can tell, is the Anglo monolin-<lb/>guist&apos;s perspective. Thus, it is not surprising that a rule restricting a bi-<lb/>lingual person&apos;s language usage to English can be dismissed as a mere <lb/>inconvenience. <lb/>Third, Judge O&apos;Scannlain posits an internal contradiction. In one <lb/>breath, he says that Spun Steak&apos;s English-only rule does not discrimi-<lb/>nate, because Ms. Garcfa and other bilingual workers &quot;can easily com-<lb/>ply&quot; with it. In the next breath, however, he concedes that &quot;slipping <lb/>into Spanish&quot; can be &quot;involuntary.&quot; This begs the question: if the <lb/>speaker cannot avoid &quot;slipping into Spanish,&quot; how can she &quot;easily <lb/>comply&quot; with such a rule? Curiously, Judge O&apos;Scannlain demurred <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>61. Compare id. at 1486 (citing Connecticut v. Teal, 457 U.S. 440, 446 (1981)), with id. at 1488 <lb/>(citing no authorities whatsoever). Teal does not use the modifier &quot;significant&quot; to describe adverse <lb/>impact. <lb/>62. In making this point, I understand Judge O&apos;Scannlain to be assigning to the term <lb/>&quot;significant&quot; the meaning that most laypersons would assign to it-namely, &quot;meaningful,&quot; <lb/>&quot;important,&quot; or &quot;weighty.&quot; WEBSTER&apos;S II NEw RIVERSIDE DICTIONARY 643 (1984). Nowhere does <lb/>Title VII use the adjective &quot;significant&quot; in such a way. I recognize, however, that it is long-settled <lb/>under Title VII that a plaintiff seeking to prove that a purportedly neutral employment policy <lb/>discriminates against a protected class of persons must offer statistically significant evidence of its <lb/>disparate impact, which is quite another matter altogether. See, e.g., MACK A. PLAYER, FEDERAL <lb/>LAW OF EMPLOYMENT DISCRIMINATION 90 (3d ed. 1991). <lb/>63. See supra note 32 (reprinting text of Title VII). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1363 <lb/></page>

			<body>from addressing the issue altogether. 6 &apos; &quot;Whether a bilingual speaker <lb/>can control which language is used in a given circumstance,&quot; he said, <lb/>&quot;is a factual issue that cannot be resolved at the summary judgment <lb/>stage.&quot; &apos; <lb/>What does the tortuous reasoning of Garcia v. Spun Steak Co. have <lb/>to do with the limits of racial dualism? It is simply this: the Anglo ma-<lb/>jority culture has been taught to understand, and is willing to sanction, <lb/>only the least subtle types of offenses against minorities in the work-<lb/>place. Accordingly, a case that clearly offends our modem civil rights <lb/>tradition, such as assigning a college-educated, minority applicant to the <lb/>hotel&apos;s laundry room rather than its accounting department, 6 6 will draw <lb/>the opprobrium of Anglo judges. But something less familiar, such as a <lb/>workplace rule banning a minority from speaking a language other than <lb/>English, will not. <lb/>Most Anglo judges are monolingual or speak non-English lan-<lb/>guages as second languages. Thus, they have little experience with, <lb/>much less sympathy for, poor treatment based on language capability. <lb/>So insisting that somebody who has the ability to speak English now be <lb/>required to do so does not seem nearly so serious to them as situations <lb/>in which employees are terminated because of the color of their skin. 67 <lb/>Other courts upholding English-only rules against bilingual em-<lb/>ployees have made the same mistake the Ninth Circuit did in Garcia v. <lb/>Spun Steak Co.. For example, Hector Garcfa could be fired because he <lb/>&quot;could readily comply with the speak-English-only rule; as to him <lb/>nonobservance was a matter of choice.&quot;68 A Mexican-American disc <lb/>jockey could be fired for uttering some words of &quot;street Spanish&quot; on <lb/>the air, because he &quot;had the ability to conform to the English-only or-<lb/>der, but chose not to do so.&quot;69 And a Filipina nurse could be demoted <lb/>for speaking Tagalog on the evening shift of a hospital&apos;s maternity unit, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>64. See generally Jeanne M. Jorgensen, Comment, &quot;English Only&quot; in the Workplace and Title <lb/>VII Disparate Impact: The Ninth Circuit&apos;s Misplaced Application of &quot;Ability to Comply&quot; Should be <lb/>Rejected in Favor of the EEOC&apos;s Business Necessity Test, 25 Sw. U. L REV. 407 (1996). <lb/>65. Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 998 F.2d 1480, 1488 (9th Cir. 1993). <lb/>66. See Odima v. Westin Tucson Hotel, 53 F.3d 1484, 1494 (9th Cir. 1995) (finding national <lb/>origin discrimination against qualified Nigerian-born Black who spoke clear but accented English). <lb/>67. Cf. HANEY L6PEZ, supra note 39, at 56-57, 61, 163 (discussing our law&apos;s difficulty <lb/>addressing racial hierarchies imposed by socialization); see also supra note 34 (discussing Rogers v. <lb/>American Airlines, 527 F. Supp. 229 (S.D.N.Y. 1981) as a non-traditional case, brought by an <lb/>African-American woman, that failed). <lb/>68. Garcia v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264, 270 (5th Cir. 1980). <lb/>69. Jurado v. Eleven-Fifty Corp., 813 F.2d 1406, 1411 (9th Cir. 1987). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1364 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>&quot;not because she was unable to comply, but because she believed that it <lb/>was her civil right to speak her native tongue. 7 <lb/>°Each <lb/>of these examples demonstrates that determining who should <lb/>be afforded protection under Title VII is more complicated than the <lb/>simplistic constructions of &quot;minority&quot; admitted by racial dualism. <lb/>That the markers tying claims of &quot;national origin&quot; discrimination to <lb/>&quot;national origin&quot; victims appear to have less precision than those <lb/>markers evidencing racial discrimination does not render English-only <lb/>rules less odious. <lb/>The Black/White race paradigm is inadequate especially in its fail-<lb/>ure to address the importance of language issues to Latinos. Although <lb/>the history of the oppression of African Americans undeniably includes <lb/>the destruction of ancestral languages, it cannot be said today that <lb/>&quot;non-English speaking&quot; ability plays exactly the same role in dis-<lb/>crimination against Blacks that it does against Latinos. 7 t For the most <lb/>part, Whites and Blacks in the United States are monolingual speakers of <lb/>related dialects of the same language: English. But Latinos, whether <lb/>fluent Spanish speakers or not, &quot;all have some common connection <lb/>with the [Spanish] language.&quot;&quot; If we do not speak it ourselves, 73 then it <lb/>is the language of our ancestors. <lb/>The Spanish language is central to Latino identity in at least two <lb/>crucial ways. First, sociologists and sociolinguists tell us that Spanish, <lb/>like any primary language, is a fundamental aspect of ethnicity. 74 If <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>70. Dimaranan v. Pomona Valley Hosp. Med. Ctr., 775 F. Supp. 338, 344 (C.D. Cal. 1991). <lb/>Curiously, Judge Rafeedie insisted that the hospital&apos;s no-Tagaog rule was not really an English-only <lb/>rule. See id. at 342-43. <lb/>71. In light of the recent debate over whether teachers in the Oakland, California public school <lb/>system ought to teach Black English, or &quot;Ebonics,&quot; to their pupils, I take care not to overstate the <lb/>point. <lb/>72. Oquendo, supra note 3, at 94; see also Deborah A. Ramirez, Excluded Voices: The <lb/>Disenfranchisement of Ethnic Groups From Jury Service, 1993 Wis. L REv. 761, 762 n.5 (citing U.S. <lb/>Bureau of the Census data that 75% of all Latinos speak Spanish). <lb/>73. Like many second-and third-generation Latinos, I did not learn Spanish in my parents&apos; <lb/>home, and the Spanish that I do speak I learned in high school or here and there around older <lb/>relatives-as did my mother, who grew up in my bilingual, Mexican-born grandfather&apos;s home. Many <lb/>of my contemporaries tell a similar story. See, e.g., Steven W. Bender, Consumer Protection for <lb/>Latinos: Overcoming Language Fraud and English-Only in the Marketplace, 45 AM. U. L REV. 1027, <lb/>1032 n.17 (1996) (&quot;Although I was born and raised in an East Los Angeles barrio, I spoke English at <lb/>school and home and know only some Spanish.&quot;); Kevin R. Johnson, Civil Rights and Immigration: <lb/>Challenges for the Latino Community in the Twenty-First Century, 8 LA RAZA LJ. 42, 67-72 (1995) <lb/>(&quot;My mother speaks some Spanish but never taught the language to her sons.&quot;). <lb/>74. See JOSHUA A. FISHMAN, THE RISE AND FALL OF THE ETHNIC REVIVAL: PERSPECTIVES <lb/>ON LANGUAGE AND ETHNICITY 71, 146 (1985); see also Perea, supra note 36, at 276-79 <lb/>(summarizing views of sociologists and sociolinguists). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[V/ol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1365 <lb/></page>

			<body>ethnicity is &quot;both the sense and the expression of collective, intergen-<lb/>erational cultural continuity,&quot; &apos; <lb/>75 then for Latino people the Spanish lan-<lb/>guage is the vehicle by which this sense and expression are conveyed. <lb/>Spanish-speaking bilinguals associate the use of Spanish with family <lb/>and friendship and values of intimacy.&quot; After all, language <lb/>is not merely a carrier of content, whether latent, or manifest. <lb/>Language itself is content, a referent for loyalties and animosi-<lb/>ties, an indicator of social statuses and personal relationships, a <lb/>marker of situations and topics as well as of the societal goals <lb/>and the large-scale value-laden areas of interaction that typify <lb/>every speech community. 7 7 <lb/>Second, Spanish-speaking ability is the historic basis upon which <lb/>Anglo society discriminates against Latinos. Prejudice against the lan-<lb/>guage is recognized as a cause of the low esteem with which Spanish is <lb/>often regarded. &quot;Spanish-influenced English is more often scorned <lb/>than any other language variety in the Chicano verbal repertoire .... <lb/>Neither Chicanos nor Anglos have much respect or affection for it.&quot; 79 <lb/>Thus it is no accident, as the venomous tongue of La Bruja reminds the <lb/>Misses Garcfa, 0 that the derogatory term used by Anglos to refer to a <lb/>Latino of any national origin is &quot;spic,&quot; which emphasizes &quot;how <lb/>Latino[]s &apos;speak&apos; rather than how they look.&quot;&quot; <lb/>Indeed, long before English-only became a rule in the U.S. work-<lb/>place, Latino children, especially children of Mexican descent, were <lb/>routinely humiliated, 82 disciplined, 83 or beaten 84 for speaking Spanish in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>75. FISHMAN, supra note 74, at 4 (internal quotations omitted). <lb/>76. See Lawrence Greenfield, Situational Measures of Normative Language Views in Relation <lb/>to Person, Place, and Topic Among Puerto Rican Bilinguals, in 2 ADVANCES IN THE SOCIOLOGY OF <lb/>LANGUAGE 17, 33 (Joshua A. Fishman ed., 1972); see also Joshua Fishman, The Sociology of <lb/>Language: An Interdisciplinary Social Science Approach to Language in Society, in 1 ADVANCES IN <lb/>THE SOCIOLOGY OF LANGUAGE 217, 251 (Joshua Fishman ed., 1971) [hereinafter Fishman, The <lb/>Sociology of Language] (stating that, among bilinguals, Spanish is primarily associated with family and <lb/>friendship, which constitute the &quot;intimacy value cluster&quot;). <lb/>77. Fishman, The Sociology of Language, supra note 76, at 219 (emphasis in original). <lb/>78. See, e.g., NANCY FAIRES CONKLIN &amp; MARGARET A. LOURIE, A HosT OF TONGUES: <lb/>LANGUAGE COMMUNITIES IN THE UNITED STATES 193 (1983). <lb/>79. Id. at 192. <lb/>80. See ALVAREZ, supra note 1, at 171. <lb/>81. Oquendo, supra note 3, at 94. <lb/>82. See, e.g., Juan F. Perea, Presentation to the First Latino/a Critical Legal Studies Conference <lb/>in La Jolla, California (May 2-5, 1996). I was impressed by the courage of Professor Perea, who <lb/>publicly shared the torments he suffered as the immigrant son of parents from Colombia and Costa <lb/>Rica, when on U.S. schoolyards his classmates called him &quot;greaser&quot; and taunted him for speaking <lb/>English with an accent. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/>[Vol. 10:261 <lb/></note>

			<page>1366 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>school. In the Southwest, the story of the Mexican-American child who <lb/>is punished for speaking Spanish in an Anglo teacher&apos;s classroom is <lb/>nearly as common as the story of the African-American man who is <lb/>pulled over by the police for the &quot;crime&quot; of driving through a White <lb/>community.&quot; Even the Supreme Court, which generally has offered a <lb/>cold shoulder to the argument that language discrimination equals na-<lb/>tional origin discrimination, 86 has occasionally acknowledged &quot;Spanish-<lb/>speaking&quot; persons as a &quot;minority group&quot; in need of special protec-<lb/>tion. 87 <lb/>To suppress the speaking of Spanish is to suppress an essential, if <lb/>not the essential, component of Latino identity. 8 This essentialism is <lb/>reflected in the works of many Latino writers, such as Sandra Cisneros, 89 <lb/>Octavio Paz,&apos; and Earl Shorris, 91 whose essays, poems, and stories <lb/>demonstrate how the Spanish language remains the lifeblood of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>83. See, e.g., Jorge C. Rangel &amp; Carlos Alcala, Project Report: De Jure Segregation of <lb/>Chicanos in Texas Schools, 7 HARV. C.R.-C.L. L REV. 307, 310 n.20 (1972) (&quot;Even today, some <lb/>schools in Texas have what is referred to as Spanish detention, whereby a child caught speaking <lb/>Spanish is usually held after school. Persistence by the child in using his native language may result in <lb/>a spanking from the principal or even expulsion.&quot;). <lb/>84. See, e.g., Kevin Baxter, Finding His Roots-and a Powerful Voice, L.A. Times, Apr. 19, <lb/>1996, at 81 (relating classroom experiences of author Victor Villasefior). <lb/>85. Although the analogy is mine, I am indebted to Margaret Montoya for underscoring the <lb/>frequency of this experience among Mexican Americans who grew up in Arizona, California, New <lb/>Mexico, and Texas. See, e.g., United States v. Texas, 506 F. Supp. 405, 412 (E.D. Tex. 1981) <lb/>(&quot;Mexican-American children were prohibited from speaking their native language anywhere on <lb/>school grounds. Those who violated the &apos;no Spanish&apos; rule were severely punished.&quot;), rev&apos;d on other <lb/>grounds, 680 F.2d 356 (5th Cir. 1982). <lb/>86. See Hernandez v. New York, 500 U.S. 352, 369 (1991). <lb/>87. See Fullilove v. Klutznick, 448 U.S. 448,454 (1980). <lb/>88. See, e.g., Rachel F. Moran, Bilingual Education as a Status Conflict, 75 CALIF. L REV. 321, <lb/>345-55 (1987) (analyzing controversy over bilingual education as representing status conflict <lb/>between Latinos and Anglos). In saying this, however, I am mindful that the discourse of <lb/>&quot;essentialism&quot; has many pitfalls. See, e.g., Francisco Valdes, Foreword: Under Construction: LatCrit <lb/>Consciousness, Community, and Theory, 85 CALIF. L. REV. 1087, 1106-08 (1997), 10 LA RAZA LJ. <lb/>1, 20-22 (1997); see generally Angela P. Harris, Race and Essentialism in Feminist Legal Theory, 42 <lb/>STAN. L. REV. 581 (1990) (criticizing essentialism for silencing important voices, including those of <lb/>Black women). <lb/>89. See SANDRA CISNEROS, WOMAN HOLLERING CREEK 146, 153 (1991) (describing Flavio <lb/>Mungufa Galindo: &quot;When Flavio accidentally hammered his thumb, he never yelled &apos;iOuch!&apos; he said <lb/>&apos;iAay!&apos; The true test of a native Spanish speaker.&quot;). <lb/>90. See OcrAvo PAZ, THE LABYRINTH OF SOLITUDE 18 (Lysander Kemp trans., Grove Press <lb/>ed. 1985) (describing reaction of author&apos;s &quot;Mexican friend&quot; who, upon visiting Berkeley, California, <lb/>agreed that the town was &quot;lovely&quot; but that she &quot;didn&apos;t belong&quot; there because &quot;[e]ven the birds speak <lb/>English&quot;). <lb/>91. See EARL SHoRRIs, LATINOs: A BIOGRAPHY OF THE PEOPLE 3 (1992) (describing the <lb/>demise of Jewish immigrant Bienvenida Peti6n, who dies &quot;not of illness but of English&quot; when she is <lb/>confined to a nursing home where nobody else speaks Spanish). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1367 <lb/></page>

			<body>Latinos. Indeed, English-only rules are a painful reminder that, as de-<lb/>scendants of the native peoples of the New World, &quot;Latinos have lost <lb/>their language twice&quot;:&quot;&apos; first, when Spain conquered the Americas and <lb/>substituted Spanish for the Indian languages; second, when the U.S. <lb/>conquered the Southwest and substituted English for Spanish, a process <lb/>that continues to the present day. <lb/>As Judge Reinhardt, who dissented from the court&apos;s denial of re-<lb/>hearing en banc of Garcia v. Spun Steak Co., explained, &quot;Language is <lb/>intimately tied to national origin and cultural identity: its discriminatory <lb/>suppression cannot be dismissed as &apos;inconvenience&apos; to the affected em-<lb/>ployees .... &quot;I&apos; <lb/>B. The False Dichotomy: Mutable vs. Immutable <lb/>Latinos have historically been subjected to discrimination based on <lb/>their Spanish language usage. Nonetheless, attempts by Latino plaintiffs <lb/>to challenge English-only policies as national origin discrimination have <lb/>repeatedly failed because the courts insist that language usage is a mu-<lb/>table characteristic and thus unprotected by Title VII. Placing such im-<lb/>portance on the false dichotomy between mutable and immutable <lb/>characteristics to determine whether a policy is discriminatory ensures <lb/>that courts will continue to fail to recognize that discriminatory lan-<lb/>guage policies are a form of national origin discrimination. <lb/>In Garcia v. Gloor, the Fifth Circuit reasoned that Hector Garcfa&apos;s <lb/>claim must be rejected largely because Title VII &quot;focuses its laser of <lb/>prohibition&quot; on characteristics, such as color or race, that are &quot;beyond <lb/>the victim&apos;s power to alter &apos; 95 -and that Mr. Garcfa, as the record dem-<lb/>onstrated, had the power to alter his language ability from Spanish to <lb/>English when necessary but declined to do so. 9 &quot; &quot;No one[,]&quot; wrote <lb/>Judge Rubin, <lb/>can change his place of birth (national origin), the place of birth <lb/>of his forbears (national origin), his race or fundamental sexual <lb/>characteristics.... [But tlhe EEO Act does not support an inter-<lb/>pretation that equates the language an employee prefers to use <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>92. See James Harvey Domengeaux, Comment, Native-Born Acadians and the Equality Ideal, <lb/>46 LA. L REV. 1151, 1167 (1986) (&quot;Language is the lifeblood of every ethnic group. To <lb/>economically and psychologically penalize a person for practicing his native tongue is to strike at the <lb/>core of ethnicity.&quot;). <lb/>93. Antoinette Sedillo Lopez, Introduction to LATINO LANGUAGE AND EDUCATION: <lb/>COMMUNICATION AND THE DREAM DEFERRED ix (Antoinette Sedillo Lopez ed., 1995). <lb/>94. Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 13 F.3d 296, 298 (9th Cir. 1993) (Reinhardt, J., dissenting). <lb/>95. Garcfa v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264,269 (5th Cir. 1980). <lb/>96. See id. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1368 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>with his national origin. To a person who speaks only one <lb/>tongue or to a person who has difficulty using another language <lb/>than the one spoken in his home, language might well be an <lb/>immutable characteristic like skin color, sex or place of birth. <lb/>However, the language a person who is multi-lingual elects to <lb/>speak at a particular time is by definition a matter of choice.&apos; <lb/>Judge Rubin&apos;s characterization of speaking one&apos;s mother tongue <lb/>as volitional-as a matter of &quot;choice&quot;-is important, because it reflects <lb/>a cherished value of a free society: a person may be condemned for en-<lb/>gaging in conduct that can be an act of free will, but not for having a <lb/>status over which the person has no control. In employment law, this <lb/>value is codified in Title VII&apos;s ban on discrimination based on color, <lb/>race, sex, and other so-called &quot;immutable&quot; characteristics. 98 Possessing <lb/>such a marker is what makes a person identifiable as a minority, and it is <lb/>believed that the person should not be penalized merely because of who <lb/>that person is. However, individuals who have the power to act and <lb/>acquire certain characteristics after birth are to be judged differently. <lb/>Accordingly, they should be held accountable for what they do. <lb/>According to Garcia v. Gloor, the capacity to speak Spanish as well <lb/>as English is a &quot;mutable&quot; rather than an &quot;immutable&quot; characteristic. 9 <lb/>Because a bilingual person, by definition, has chosen to learn English as <lb/>a second language, he can also choose to speak it in the workplace.)&apos; <lb/>According to this logic, failure to comply with an employer&apos;s request to <lb/>speak English is seen as simple insubordination, an offense indisputably <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>97. Id. at 269-70 (emphases added). <lb/>98. This value is also reflected in federal laws forbidding discrimination based on an <lb/>individual&apos;s disability. See Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, 42 U.S.C. § § 12101-12213 <lb/>(1994). <lb/>99. See Garcfa v. Gloor, 618 F.2d at 269 (&quot;Equal employment opportunity may be secured only <lb/>when employers are barred from discriminating against employees on the basis of immutable <lb/>characteristics, such as race and national origin ... &quot;) (emphasis omitted) (quoting Willingham v. <lb/>Macon Tel. Publ&apos;g Co., 507 F.2d 1084, 1091 (5th Cir. 1975)). <lb/>100. <lb/>To a person who speaks only one tongue or to a person who has difficulty using another <lb/>language than the one spoken in his home, language might well be an immutable <lb/>characteristic like skin color, sex or place of birth. However, the language a person who is <lb/>multi-lingual elects to speak at a particular time is by definition a matter of choice. No <lb/>claim is made that Garcfa and the other employees engaged in sales were unable to speak <lb/>English. Indeed, it is conceded that all could do so and that this ability was an occupational <lb/>qualification because of the requirement that they wait on customers who spoke only <lb/>English or who used that language by choice. <lb/>Id. at 270. <lb/></listBibl>
				
		<note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1369 <lb/></page>

			<body>punishable by termination or other discipline,&apos;&apos; rather than as national <lb/>origin discrimination, which is prohibited by society&apos;s collective judg-<lb/>ment that status should not be penalized. This understanding of bilin-<lb/>gualism allowed the court to reduce Hector Garcfa&apos;s claim &quot;to a <lb/>contention that the statute commands employers to permit employees to <lb/>speak the tongue they prefer,&quot; and then conclude, &quot;[w]e do not think <lb/>that the statute permits that interpretation.&quot;&apos; 0&apos;2 Similarly, other courts <lb/>have emphasized the &quot;mutability&quot; of bilingualism as a basis for up-<lb/>holding English-only rules, especially in cases where the employee <lb/>&quot;chose deliberately to speak Spanish,&quot;&apos; 0 3 &quot;had the ability to con-<lb/>form,&quot;&apos;&quot; or &quot;could have easily complied.&quot;&apos; 0 5 <lb/>This immutable-versus-mutable dichotomy raises at least three <lb/>troubling questions. First, nowhere in Title VII does it say that a pro-<lb/>tected class must be defined by its &quot;immutable&quot; rather than mutable <lb/>characteristics. In fact, as Judge Rubin conceded e 6 but did not attempt <lb/>to reconcile°7-discdmination based on the mutable characteristic of an <lb/>employee&apos;s religion is also prohibited by Title VII. Even assuming that <lb/>race, sex, and the rest are indeed immutable characteristics,&apos; Judge <lb/>Rubin could have concluded that the framers of the statute, by specifi-<lb/>cally including the concededly mutable characteristic of religion, in-<lb/>tended the ban on &quot;national origin&quot; discrimination to address such <lb/>discrimination in all its manifestations, whether &quot;mutable&quot; <lb/>or <lb/>&quot;immutable.&quot; &apos; &quot; o <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>101. See ADOLPH M. KOVEN &amp; SUSAN L. SMITH, JUST CAUSE: THE SEVEN TESTS 245 (Donald <lb/>Farwell ed., rev. ed. 1992) (noting that insubordination is usually considered just cause supporting <lb/>termination). <lb/>102. Garcfa v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264, 271 (5th Cir. 1980). <lb/>103. Id. at 268 <lb/>104. Jurado v. Eleven-Fifty Corp., 813 F.2d 1406, 1411 (9th Cir. 1987). <lb/>105. Dimaranan v. Pomona Valley Hosp. Med. Ctr., 775 F. Supp. 338, 344 (C.D. Cal. 1991). <lb/>106. See Garcta v. Gloor, 618 F.2d at 269 (asserting that, &quot;[s]ave for religion,&quot; Title VII bans <lb/>discrimination based on immutable characteristics or the exercise of fundamental rights). <lb/>107. <lb/>We need not here explore the extent to which the EEO Act forbids discrimination based on <lb/>characteristics that are not immutable. For the purpose of this opinion, we accept the thesis <lb/>that there may be a disparate impact based on some mutable conditions, such as where an <lb/>employee lives. Religion is, of course, a forbidden criterion, even though a matter of <lb/>individual choice. <lb/>Id. at 270 n.6. <lb/>108. An increasingly dubious assumption, especially in light of the literature making the <lb/>persuasive case that so much of one&apos;s ethnic, racial, and even sexual identity is a matter of personal <lb/>choice as well as social construction. See works cited infra notes 112-114. <lb/>109. See discussion infra Part III (discussing legal indeterminacy under Title VII). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1370 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>

			<body>Second, the mutable-versus-immutable dichotomy ignores the per-<lb/>suasive argument, made by a host of scholars, that even so-called <lb/>&quot;immutable&quot; characteristics such as race 10 and sex&apos; are social <lb/>constructs rather than anthropological or biological facts of life. So <lb/>much of human relations in the United States is the product of either, or <lb/>both, the construction by Whites of social identities for non-Whites <lb/>and/or the construction by non-Whites of identities for themselves. The <lb/>social construction of identity has been especially true for Latinos, <lb/>whose multiracial heritage, as Kevin Johnson,&quot;&apos; Angel Oquendo,&quot; 3 and <lb/>Deborah Ramirez&quot; 4 have noted, often perplexes bureaucracies fixated <lb/>on traditional &quot;check the box&quot; categories. If the mutable/immutable <lb/>dichotomy is not so hard-and-fast, then it makes little sense to limit our <lb/>legal definitions of &quot;national origin&quot; discrimination in the context of <lb/>language ability. <lb/>Third, the dichotomy reflects the simplistic assumption of so many <lb/>monolingual people that language is interchangeable, that the words and <lb/>phrases used to express a concept in Spanish can be translated so as to <lb/>convey exactly the same meaning in English, and vice versa.&quot; 5 Although <lb/>one does not have to be bilingual to understand that the nuances of one <lb/>tongue cannot easily be expressed in another, by and large it is people <lb/>from minority cultures, like Latinos, who are more likely to appreciate <lb/>this. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>110. See, e.g., HANEY L6PEz, supra note 39, at 79-80, 102-07; MARY C. WATERS, ETHNIC <lb/>OrIoTNS: CHOOSING IDENTITIES 166 (1990); Ian F. Haney L6pez, The Social Construction of Race: <lb/>Some Observations on Illusion, Fabrication, and Choice, 29 HARV. C.R.-C.L. L REV. 1, 47 (1994). <lb/>111. See, e.g., Kenneth L. Karst, Myths of Identity: Individual and Group Portraits of Race and <lb/>Sexual Orientation, 43 UCLA L REV. 263, 283-84 (1995) (discussing how peoples are assigned to <lb/>&quot;Yes or No&quot; categories to identify labels, including homosexual or heterosexual). For an interesting <lb/>discussion of the latter, see generally Francisco Valdes, Queers, Sissies, Dykes, and Tomboys: <lb/>Deconstructing the Conflation of &quot;Sex,&quot; &quot;Gender,&quot; and &quot;Sexual Orientation&quot; in Euro-American Law <lb/>and Society, 83 CALIF. L REV. 1 (1995). <lb/>112. See Kevin R. Johnson, Racial Restrictions on Naturalization: The Recurring Intersection of <lb/>Race and Gender in Immigration and Citizenship Law, 11 BERKELEY WOMEN&apos;S L.J, 142, 151-52 <lb/>(1996) (discussing racial hierarchies and multiracial issues among Latinos); Kevin R. Johnson, <lb/>&quot;Melting Pot&quot; or &quot;Ring of Fire&quot;?: Assimilation and the Mexican-American Experience, 85 CALIF. L <lb/>REV. 1259, 1262-63 (1997), 10 LA RAZA LJ. 173, 176-77 (1997) (relating mixed Anglo and <lb/>Mexican-American heritage of author and his family to same among greater Latino population). <lb/>113. See Oquendo, supra note 3, at 95 (recalling author&apos;s reaction to the query on the Scholastic <lb/>Aptitude Test (&quot;SAT&apos;) that he identify his heritage by checking a single appropriate box). <lb/>114. See Ramirez, supra note 39, at 964-69 (discussing how commonly the heritage of Latinos <lb/>and other minorities is found to be multiracial). <lb/>115. Juan Perea has gone a step further by making the persuasive case, supported by linguists&apos; <lb/>research, that an adult&apos;s primary language ability is practically immutable. See Perea, supra note 36, <lb/>at 279-87. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1371 <lb/></page>

			<body>For example, Octavio Paz, Mexico&apos;s premier poet, essayist, and <lb/>novelist, tells the story of a female &quot;Mexican friend&quot; who, upon visiting <lb/>him in Berkeley, California, reacted to his opinion that the town is <lb/>&quot;lovely&quot;: <lb/>Yes, it&apos;s lovely, but I don&apos;t belong here. Even the birds speak <lb/>English. How can I enjoy a flower if I don&apos;t know its right <lb/>name, its English name, the name that has fused with its colors <lb/>and petals, the name that&apos;s the same thing as the flower? If I say <lb/>bugambilia to you, you think of the bougainvillea vines you&apos;ve <lb/>seen in your own village, with their purple, liturgical flowers, <lb/>climbing around an ash tree or hanging from a wall in the after-<lb/>noon sunlight. They&apos;re a part of your being, your culture. <lb/>They&apos;re what you remember long after you&apos;ve seemed to forget <lb/>them. It&apos;s very lovely here, but it isn&apos;t mine ... ,116 <lb/>Yolanda Garcfa, the fictional &quot;Yo&quot; of Julia Alvarez&apos;s novel, reveals <lb/>the Latino sentiment even more clearly. As a Spanish-speaking immi-<lb/>grant, she spends her girlhood struggling to reconcile the concepts she <lb/>understands in Spanish with the new ones that she is learning in English. <lb/>For example, Yo recalls an incident that occurred on the first day of a <lb/>college English literature seminar. A student with whom she would have <lb/>her first romantic involvement, &quot;Rudolf Brodermann Elmenhurst, the <lb/>third,&quot; strolled into her class ten minutes late.&quot; 7 Owing to the sound of <lb/>his name, Yo assumed that the young man was tardy &quot;because he&apos;d just <lb/>whizzed in from his small barony somewhere in Austria.&quot;&quot;&apos; In fact, <lb/>&quot;Rudolf Brodermann Elmenhurst, the third&quot; was a monolingual Anglo <lb/>born in the United States. When she found out, Yolanda cursed her <lb/>&quot;immigrant&apos;s failing, literalism.&quot;&quot; 9 Again and again, Yolanda finds <lb/>being bilingual and bicultural to be both a blessing and a curse; 0 it <lb/>permits her to see and describe the world from at least two different per-<lb/>spectives, yet it alienates her from Anglos &quot;like the proudly monolin-<lb/>gual John&quot; described at the outset of this Part.&apos; 2 &apos; <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>116. PAZ, supra note 90, at 18. <lb/>117. ALVAREZ, supra note 1, at 88-89. <lb/>118. Id. at 89. <lb/>119. Id. <lb/>120. <lb/>For the hundredth time, I cursed my immigrant origins. If only I too had been born in <lb/>Connecticut or Virginia, I too would understand the jokes everyone was making on the last <lb/>two digits of the year, 1969; I too would be having sex and smoking dope; I too would have <lb/>suntanned parents who took me skiing in Colorado over Christmas break, and I would say <lb/>things like &quot;no shit,&quot; without feeling like I was imitating someone else. <lb/>Id. at 94-95. <lb/>121. See id. at 72. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1372 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>The limits of racial dualism are reflected perfectly in the notion <lb/>that bilingualism can be both a blessing and curse. Whereas a bilingual <lb/>person can view the world in its complexity, in stereophonic sound, a <lb/>monolingual person can view the world only in its simplicity, in mono-<lb/>phonic sound. So to the extent that monolingual judges are called upon <lb/>to decide the English-only cases, it should come as no surprise that the <lb/>outcomes, and the reasoning upon which they are based, are recorded in <lb/>mono rather than stereo sound, too. <lb/>II <lb/>LATINO INVISIBILITY IN NATIONAL ORIGIN DECISIONS <lb/>The girls glanced at each other and looked towards their <lb/>mother, who rolled her eyes. &quot;La Bruj a,&quot; she explained. &quot;I for-<lb/>got.&quot; The old woman in the apartment below, who had a helmet <lb/>of beauty parlor blue hair, had been complaining to the super <lb/>since the day the family moved in a few months ago. The <lb/>Garcias should be evicted. Their food smelled. They spoke too <lb/>loudly and not in English. The kids sounded like a herd of wild <lb/>burros. The Puerto Rican super, Alfredo, came to their door al-<lb/>most daily. Could Mrs. Garcia turn the radio down? Could <lb/>Mrs. Garcfa maybe keep the girls more in line? The neighbor <lb/>downstairs had been awakened by the clatter of their shoes on <lb/>the floor. <lb/>&quot;If I keep them any more in line,&quot; their mother began-and then <lb/>Sandi heard her mother&apos;s voice breaking. &quot;We have to walk <lb/>around. We have to breathe.&quot; <lb/>-Sandra Garcfa de la Torre1 22 <lb/>Latino invisibility is the consequence of racial dualism; without it <lb/>racial dualism could not exist. As the limits of racial dualism might <lb/>suggest,&quot; one of the distinguishing features of being Latino in the <lb/>United States is being treated as if our people did not exist. Latinos are <lb/>conspicuous by their absence from the hallmarks of Americana both <lb/>large and small: bookstores,&apos; 24 civil rights dialogue,&apos;1 5 history books, 26 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>122. Id. at 170 <lb/>123. See, e.g., Johnson, supra note 38, at 12-13 (&quot;The predominance of seeing race issues as <lb/>black/white conflict contributed to the call for the first annual Lat/Crit conference, where a group of <lb/>Latino/as, as well as other minorities and kindred spirits thinking critically about issues of race, came <lb/>together to explore changing the tenor of the dialogue.&quot;). <lb/>124. See, e.g., Perea, supra note 41, at 970 (&quot;When I travel, I spend a lot of time in bookstores <lb/>searching for books on Latino life and history. It is hard to find such books.&quot;). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261  <lb/>19981 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1373 <lb/></page>

			<body>major newspapers, 7 and even accounts of who the victims of the spring <lb/>1992 Los Angeles civil unrest were.&quot;&apos; And in those rare fora where <lb/>Latinos have been recognized, often their portrayal has not been in a <lb/>positive light.&apos; 29 Kevin Johnson&apos; and Juan Perea&apos;&apos; have each used the <lb/>same term to describe this invisibility: Latinos are Los Olvidados, or <lb/>&quot;the Forgotten Ones.&quot; <lb/>Latino invisibility, that is, the relative lack of a positive public <lb/>Latino identity and legitimacy, 13 2 has not happened by accident. The <lb/>United States has written a rich history in which Latinos systematically <lb/>are made invisible.1 3 As Laura Garcfa, mother of Yolanda and the other <lb/>Garcfa girls learned, Latinos shall be tolerated only if they keep them-<lb/>selves &quot;in line,&quot; where they won&apos;t bother Anglos like their neighbor La <lb/>Bruja. <lb/>A cruel irony for Latinos is that, when we are not being criticized <lb/>for refusing to stay &quot;in line,&quot; we are being criticized for refusing <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>125. See, e.g., Moran, supra note 16, at 10 (Although the Black/White race paradigm &quot;has <lb/>elevated race and ethnicity to a position of central importance in defining equality of <lb/>opportunity... race and ethnicity have proven to be somewhat artificial organizing principles for <lb/>Latinos because they have different racial origins and come from a range of countries.&quot;); Ramirez, <lb/>supra note 39, at 958 n.5 (&quot;When courts and legislatures first created race-conscious remedies in the <lb/>1960s, the United States was seen as a black and white society.... [B]lacks were, for all practical <lb/>purposes, the only racial minority group of significant size.&quot;). <lb/>126. See, e.g., GRISWOLD DEL CASTILLO, supra note 51, at 113 (discussing an influential college <lb/>textbook that emphasized political and military aspects of the Mexican-American War and Treaty of <lb/>Guadalupe Hidalgo, but ignored their effects on &quot;the 100,000 Mexicans citizens annexed in the <lb/>bargain&quot; who &quot;remained invisible in this national history.&quot;). <lb/>127. See, e.g., Johnson, supra note 38, at 9 (&quot;Los Angeles&apos; [Eastside], the area east of <lb/>downtown-from East Los Angeles to Montebello to the San Gabriel Valley-where a great many <lb/>Latinos live, simply does not exist in the eyes of the regional newspaper of record, the Los Angeles <lb/>Times.&quot;). <lb/>128. See Kevin R. Johnson, Civil Rights and Immigration: Challenges for the Latino Community in <lb/>the Twenty-first Century, 8 LA RAZA L.J. 42, 64 (1995) (&quot;[L]et us return briefly to the disturbances in <lb/>South Central Los Angeles in the spring 1992. In the reconstruction process, Latino leaders <lb/>complained that government ignored the impact of the violence on the Latino community.&quot;). <lb/>129. See, e.g., Johnson, supra note 38, at 9 (&quot;When East Lost Angeles is mentioned in the news, <lb/>it generally is a story about crime, a shooting, robbery, gangs, and the like.&quot;); see also Johnson, supra <lb/>note 41, at 1144-47. <lb/>130. See Johnson, supra note 41, at 1139. <lb/>131. See Perea, supra note 41, at 966. <lb/>132. See id. <lb/>133. See Johnson, supra note 38, at 13 (&quot;The long history of subordination of Asian Americans, <lb/>Mexican Americans, Native Americans, and other groups in the United States demonstrates the <lb/>unfortunate richness of subordination American style.&quot;); see generally RONALD TAKAKI, A <lb/>DIFFERENT MIRROR: A HISTORY OF MULTICULTURAL AMERICA (1993). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1374 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>

			<body>to &quot;assimilate. &apos; 34 Latinos&apos; persistence in maintaining cultural ties, es-<lb/>pecially language, is often fodder for conservatives&apos; cannons against the <lb/>immigration of Mexicans and Latin Americans to the United States.&apos; 35 <lb/>Properly understood, however, this &quot;refusal to assimilate&quot; is just an-<lb/>other way of complaining that we refuse to remain invisible. 36 <lb/>In the context of Title VII litigation challenging speak-English-<lb/>only rules, Latino invisibility is demonstrated by at least two phenom-<lb/>ena: (A) the inattention paid to the Spanish words and phrases actually <lb/>uttered by the bilingual employees in violation of the challenged rules <lb/>and (B) the master-servant roles presupposed for Anglos and Latinos. <lb/>A. Donde Estd el Espafiol? 3 7 <lb/>Without a doubt, the most curious thing about the published judi-<lb/>cial opinions addressing attacks on English-only rules is the failure of <lb/>any of their authors to state, in either the original Spanish or the trans-<lb/>lated English, exactly what the employees said (or were suspected of <lb/>saying) to offend the rule. Save for the surnames of most of the plain-<lb/>tiffs, not so much as a single word of Spanish-or indeed, any other <lb/>foreign language except perhaps Latin-appears in these opinions. <lb/>This is true of every one of the ten reported cases&apos; 3 addressing chal-<lb/>lenges to English-only rules under Title VII, including the three in <lb/>which the employee ultimately prevailed 13 9 and the six in which she <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>134. See, e.g., Richard Delgado, Rodrigo&apos;s Fourteenth Chronicle: American Apocalypse, 32 <lb/>Harv. C.R.-C.L. L. Rev. 275, 296 (1997) (discussing pressure on Latinos to assimilate); Johnson, supra <lb/>note 39, at 79 (collecting statements about why Latinos should give up Spanish and adopt English). <lb/>135. See, e.g., ARTHUR M. SCHLESINGER, JR., THE DISUNITING OF AMERICA 107-10 (1992) <lb/>(criticizing bilingual education spurred by a &quot;flood of immigration from Spanish-speaking <lb/>countries&quot;); see also PETER BRIMELOW, ALIEN NATION: COMMON SENSE ABOUT AMERICA&apos;S <lb/>IMMIGRATION DISASTER 272 (1995) (identifying &quot;bright spots&quot; in Hispanics&apos; chances for <lb/>assimilation). <lb/>136. See, e.g., George A. Martinez, Latinos, Assimilation and the Law: A Philosophical <lb/>Perspective 19 UCLA CHICANO-LATINO L. REV. (forthcoming 1998) (paper prepared for Yale Law <lb/>School&apos;s 10th Anniversary Critical Race Theory Conference); see also Sylvia Lazos Vargas, Coming <lb/>to Terms with Diversity: A Trans-disciplinary Critique of Homogeneity &quot;as Cultural Ideology 72 TUL. L <lb/>R. (forthcoming 1998) (criticizing law and legal institutions for elevating homogeneity over <lb/>diversity). <lb/>137. &quot;Where&apos;s the Spanish?&quot; <lb/>138. These ten cases actually produced 16 published opinions, of which only Justice Kennedy&apos;s <lb/>opinion for the Supreme Court in Hernandez contains even a word of the offending language. <lb/>139. See Gutierrez v. Municipal Court, 838 F.2d 1031 (9th Cir. 1988); Flores v. Hartford Police <lb/>Dep&apos;t, 25 Fair Empl. Prac. Cas. (BNA) 180 (D. Conn. 1981); Saucedo v. Brothers Well Serv., Inc., <lb/>464 F. Supp. 919 (S.D. Tex. 1979); see also Hernandez v. Region Nine Housing Corp., 670 A.2d 95 <lb/>(App. Div.), rev&apos;d, 684 A.2d 1385 (1996) (allowing challenge to plaintiff&apos;s termination for speaking <lb/>Spanish in the apartment lobby where he worked despite EEOC&apos;s having issued adverse <lb/>administrative determination). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1375 <lb/></page>

			<body>ultimately failed.&quot; And it is true of all but one of the ten major re-<lb/>ported cases addressing challenges to similar rules under other laws.&apos; 4 &apos; <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>140. See Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 998 F.2d 1480 (9th Cir. 1993); Garcfa v. Gloor, 609 F.2d 156 <lb/>(5th Cir. 1980); Dimaranan v. Pomona Valley Hosp. Med. Ctr., 775 F. Supp. 338 (C.D. Cal. 1991); <lb/>Jurado v. Eleven-Fifty Corp., 630 F. Supp. 569 (C.D. Cal. 1986), aft&apos;d, 813 F.2d 1406 (9th Cir. 1987); <lb/>see also Long v. First Union Corp. of Va., No. 95-1986, 1996 U.S. App. LEXIS 12431 (4th Cir. May <lb/>29, 1996) (rejecting challenge to alleged discriminatory application of bank&apos;s English-only rule); De <lb/>Ia Cruz v. New York City Human Resources Admin. DSS, 884 F. Supp. 112 (S.D.N.Y. 1995) <lb/>(rejecting challenge to plaintiff&apos;s transfer to another department despite the charge that a supervisor <lb/>had told plaintiff to &quot;shut up&quot; when she heard him speaking Spanish), aft&apos;d, 82 F.3d 16 (2d Cir. 1996). <lb/>141. Compare Yu Cong Eng v. Trinidad, 271 U.S. 500 (1926) (sustaining free expression <lb/>challenge to Philippines Island law outlawing the keeping of business records in any language except <lb/>English, Spanish, or a Filipino dialect), Meyer v. Nebraska, 262 U.S. 390 (1923) (same), Farrington v. <lb/>Tokushige, 11 F.2d 710 (9th Cir. 1926), aff&apos;d, 273 U.S. 284 (1927) (sustaining free expression <lb/>challenge to state law strictly regulating Japanese language schools), Hernandez v. Erlenbusch, 368 <lb/>F. Supp. 752 (D. Or. 1993) (sustaining 42 U.S.C. § 1981 challenge to English-only rule in public <lb/>tavern), Yniguez v. Mofford, 730 F. Supp. 309 (D. Ariz. 1990), aff&apos;d sub nom. Yniguez v. Arizonans <lb/>for Official English, 42 F.3d 1217 (9th Cir. 1994), reh&apos;g granted, 53 F.3d 1084, aff&apos;d en banc, 69 F.3d <lb/>920 (9th Cir. 1995), vacated as moot, 117 S. Ct. 1055 (1997) (sustaining First Amendment challenge to <lb/>English-only rule for state government officials and employees), Asian Am. Bus. Group v. City of <lb/>Pomona, 716 F. Supp. 1328 (C.D. Cal. 1989) (enjoining enforcement of municipal ordinance requiring <lb/>business sign with foreign alphabetical letters to devote at least 50% of sign space to English), and <lb/>Bartels v. Iowa, 132 N.E. 20 (Ohio 1921), rev&apos;d, 262 U.S. 404 (1923) (sustaining free expression <lb/>challenge to statute forbidding teaching of German and other non-English languages to school <lb/>children), with Vazquez v. McAllen Bag &amp; Supply Co., 660 F.2d 686 (5th Cir. Unit A 1981) (rejecting <lb/>42 U.S.C. § 1981 challenge to English-only rule for hiring truck drivers), and Hemandez v. State, 528 <lb/>N.Y.S.2d 625 (1986) (rejecting equal protection challenge to listen-to-English-tmnslation-only rule <lb/>for bilingual Latinos called to jury duty in criminal cases in which official interpreter relates <lb/>testimony of Spanish-speaking witnesses), af&apos;d, 75 N.Y.2d 350, 552 N.E.2d 621 (1990), affd sub <lb/>nom. Hernandez v. New York, 500 U.S. 352, 369 (1991). Although in Hernandez Justice Kennedy <lb/>omitted the Spanish words or phrases that might have been at issue in that case, he did, in a footnote, <lb/>report the prosecutor&apos;s citation of United States v. Perez, 658 F.2d 654 (9th Cir. 1981), to illustrate <lb/>&quot;the sort of problems that may arise where a juror fails to accept the official translation of foreign-<lb/>language testimony&quot;: <lb/>DOROTHY KIM (JUROR NO. 8): Your honor, is it proper to ask the interpreter a <lb/>question? I&apos;m uncertain about the word La Vado [sic]. You say that is a bar. <lb/>THE COURT: The Court cannot permit jurors to ask questions directly. If you want to <lb/>phrase your question to me-<lb/>DOROTHY KIM: I understood it to be a restroom. I could better believe that they would <lb/>meet in a restroom rather than a public bar if he is undercover. <lb/>THE COURT: These are matters for you to consider. If you have any misunderstanding of <lb/>what the witness testified to, tell the Court now what you didn&apos;t understand and we&apos;ll place <lb/>the-<lb/>DOROTHY KIM: I understand the word La Vado [sic]-I thought it meant restroom. She <lb/>translates it as bar. <lb/>MS. IANZITI: In the first place, jurors are not to listen to the Spanish but to the English. I <lb/>am a certified court interpreter. <lb/>DOROTHY KIM: You&apos;re an idiot. <lb/>Hernandez, 500 U.S. at 360-61 n.3 (quoting Perez, 658 F.2d at 663). Upon further questioning, Justice <lb/>Kennedy reported, &quot;the witness indicated that none of the conversations in issue occurred in the <lb/>restroom. The juror later explained that she had said &apos;it&apos;s an idiom&apos; rather than &apos;you&apos;re an idiot,&apos; but <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1376 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>By omitting the words spoken in Spanish by the bilingual plaintiffs, <lb/>the courts&apos; decisions mirror the challenged work place rules that pro-<lb/>hibit Spanish. This absence of the Spanish words from the court deci-<lb/>sions has at least two deleterious effects. <lb/>First, omission permits us to assume the harm posed by the chal-<lb/>lenged rule is, as this Essay noted above, &quot;insignificant.&apos; &apos;42 An insig-<lb/>nificant infringement on one&apos;s employment rights based on national <lb/>origin is not something that we have to take seriously. The matter can <lb/>be disposed of without much concern because the harm, if any, is de <lb/>minimis. <lb/>For example, in Garcia v. Spun Steak Co., the court omitted the <lb/>Spanish words the plaintiffs used, even though it was in response to <lb/>those words that the company adopted its English-only work rule. In-<lb/>stead, Judge O&apos;Scannlain dutifully reported the ostensibly beneficent <lb/>purpose for which Spun Steak had adopted its speak-English-only rule: <lb/>to address &quot;complaints that some workers were using their bilingual <lb/>capabilities to harass and to insult other workers in a language they <lb/>could not understand.&quot;&apos; 4 3 This was a serious charge and, if true, merited <lb/>a serious response.&apos;&quot; But just what were the offending words or <lb/>phrases? Judge O&apos;Scannlain&apos;s entire analysis never offered more than a <lb/>few cryptic hints. <lb/>Instead he rejected the argument of Priscilla Garcfa and her com-<lb/>pafiera Maricela Buitrago that denying the right to speak Spanish on <lb/>the job worked a denial of the right to express their ethnic culture and <lb/>identity. 145 Judge O&apos;Scannlain called the argument a demand for the <lb/>same &quot;privilege&quot; given by the employer to native-English speakers: the <lb/>ability &quot;to make small talk&quot; on the job in the language with which they <lb/>felt most comfortable. 46 Thus, Judge O&apos;Scannlain, in rejecting the <lb/>pair&apos;s claim, devalued the importance of their ethnic culture and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>she was nevertheless dismissed from the jury.&quot; Id. at 361 (quoting Perez, 658 F.2d at 663) (citation <lb/>omitted). <lb/>142. See supra Part II.A. <lb/>143. Garcia v. Spun Steak, 998 F.2d at 1483. <lb/>144. Of course, an employer should take steps to combat such hostile conduct even if the <lb/>harassment and insults are made in a language the victims can understand. Such conduct often takes <lb/>the form of racial or ethnic slurs. See, e.g., Richard Delgado, Words That Wound: A Tort Action for <lb/>Racial Insults, Epithets, and Name Calling, 17 HARV. C.R.-C.L. L REV. 133, 146 (1982) (contending <lb/>racial insults cause psychological harm because they evoke and intensify past &quot;stigmatization, <lb/>labeling, and disrespectful treatment&quot;). <lb/>145. See Garcia v. Spun Steak, 998 F.2d at 1487. <lb/>146. See id. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1377 <lb/></page>

			<body>identity to that of small talk. How important could a &quot;privilege&quot; to <lb/>engage in &quot;small talk&quot; be?&apos; 47 <lb/>Other courts have followed a similar pattern. One upheld a grant <lb/>of summary judgment against the plaintiff despite evidence in the rec-<lb/>ord that his supervisor would tell him to &quot;shut up&quot; when she heard him <lb/>speaking Spanish in the hallway. 4 8 Likewise, summary judgment was <lb/>entered against a bilingual Spanish-speaking disc jockey who used a few <lb/>words and phrases of &quot;&apos;street&apos; Spanish&quot; on his program, because he <lb/>refused to comply with a new English-only rule &quot;merely... for per-<lb/>sonal reasons-he wanted to preserve the value of his radio personal-<lb/>ity.&quot;&quot;&apos; 4 Even a victorious plaintiff, who was fired for violating the <lb/>boss&apos;s rule against &quot;&apos;Mesican&apos; talk&quot;&apos; 50 by asking a bilingual co-worker <lb/>&quot;in two Spanish words&quot;&apos; 5 &apos; where in the store an item should be placed, <lb/>learned that his was &quot;not a substantial case from the standpoint of dam-<lb/>ages.&quot;2 <lb/>Second, omission encourages readers to assume the worst about <lb/>bilingual speakers and their motivations. It makes the outlawed lan-<lb/>guage seem mysterious and perhaps evil. Our imaginations about the <lb/>nasty things that might actually have been said are allowed to run wild. <lb/>Recall once again Garcfa v. Spun Steak Company. Having char-<lb/>acterized Ms. Garcfa and Ms. Buitrago&apos;s claim as the assertion of a mere <lb/>&quot;privilege,&quot; Judge O&apos;Scannlain then suggested why the employer&apos;s <lb/>stake in withholding the privilege was strong: &quot;A privilege, however, is <lb/>by definition given at the employer&apos;s discretion; an employer has the <lb/>right to define its contours.&quot;&apos; 5 3 In defining the &quot;contours&quot; of the <lb/>privilege, he wrote, an employer may limit small talk to certain times of <lb/>the day, to the performance of certain tasks, or to certain topics. And <lb/>most important, an employer &quot;may even forbid the use of certain <lb/>words, such as profanity.&quot;&apos;&quot; <lb/>Mark well the implications of this reasoning. We do not know ex-<lb/>actly what Ms. Garcfa and Ms. Buitrago said, but it might have been <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>147. In fact, Judge O&apos;Scannlain&apos;s point is irrelevant. Title VII clearly outlaws discrimination <lb/>against any individual &quot;with respect to ... privileges of employment&quot; based on national origin. 42 <lb/>U.S.C § 2000e-2(a) (1) (1994) (emphasis added). <lb/>148. See De La Cruz v. New York City Human Resources Admin. DSS, 82 F.3d 16, 19 (2d Cir. <lb/>1996). <lb/>149. Jurado v. Eleven-Fifty Corp., 813 F.2d 1406, 1408, 1411 (9th Cir. 1987). <lb/>150. Saucedo v. Brothers Well Serv., Inc., 464 F. Supp. 919, 921 (S.D. Tex. 1979). <lb/>151. Id. The words were probably, &quot;IDonde va?&quot; (&quot;Where do you want it?&quot;). <lb/>152. Id. at 922. <lb/>153. Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 998 F.2d 1480, 1487 (9th Cir. 1993). <lb/>154. Id. (emphasis added). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">19981 <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1378 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>profanity, and it might have been racial harassment. Few of us would <lb/>hesitate to condemn either as having no place in the workplace. Such <lb/>words are often &quot;&apos;fighting&apos; words,&quot;&apos; 55 words that provoke chaos and <lb/>violence. But to omit a report and translation of what these profane <lb/>words actually were, if indeed they were uttered at all, suggests the <lb/>broader, indefensible conclusion that all Spanish words are profane <lb/>words, or worse, racial harassment. Yet to operate under such an as-<lb/>sumption makes it seem sensible to ban the language altogether. <lb/>Indeed, how is somebody who speaks no Spanish-usually the supervi-<lb/>sor-to know the difference between good Spanish and &quot;scurrilous&quot;&apos; 56 <lb/>Spanish? <lb/>A Mexican-American folk tale from Texas captures perfectly for <lb/>Latino ears the fear of monolingual Anglos that secretly, behind their <lb/>backs, they are being mocked by bilingual Spanish-speakers: <lb/>Well this mojado [&quot;wetback&quot;] had just held up a bank and was <lb/>running away with the money with a rinche (Texas Ranger) after <lb/>him. When the mojado went around the comer he put the <lb/>money in a garbage can. Then the Texas Ranger caught him <lb/>and wanted to know where the money was, but he couldn&apos;t speak <lb/>Spanish and the mojado couldn&apos;t speak English. Then the <lb/>rinche called a Mexican-American who was passing by and told <lb/>him to ask the &quot;Meskin&quot; about the money. &quot;He wants to know <lb/>what you did with the money[,&quot; the bilingual man said.] The <lb/>mojado answered, &quot;I put the money in a garbage can.&quot; The <lb/>rinche says, &quot;What did he say.? What did he say?&quot; And the <lb/>Chicano says, &quot;He says you are a chicken sonofabitch and <lb/>you&apos;re not man enough to kill him!&quot; 157 <lb/>Even if unintentional, the reported opinions from other cases lead <lb/>us down this path. One court reported a bank manager&apos;s justification <lb/>for having an English-only rule in a memorandum to employees this <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>155. See Chaplinsky v. New Hampshire, 315 U.S. 568, 572 (1942). But see Cohen v. California, <lb/>403 U.S. 15, 16 (1971) (reversing conviction under California &quot;offensive conduct&quot; law for wearing <lb/>jacket emblazoned with inscription &quot;Fuck the Draft&quot;); Yniguez v. Arizonans for Official English, 69 <lb/>F.3d 920, 935 (9th Cir. 1995) (en banc) (&quot;Under Article XXVIII, of course, the state [of Arizona] is <lb/>not singling out one word for repression, but rather entire vocabularies.&quot;). <lb/>156. See Yniguez, 69 F.3d at 935 (&quot;Mhe languages of Cervantes, Proust, Tolstoy, and Lao-Tze, <lb/>among others, can hardly be described as &apos;scurrilous.&quot;&apos;). As someone who specializes in labor and <lb/>employment issues, I find the solution to the alleged problem of bilingual employees misbehaving in <lb/>their native tongues to be quite simple: hire bilingual supervisors. This seems to me to be not only <lb/>more desirable than banning non-English languages but also necessary to manage the workforce. <lb/>157. JOHN 0. WEST, MEXICAN AMERICAN FOLKLORE: LEGENDS, SONGS, FESTIVALS, <lb/>PROVERBS, CRAFTS, TALES OF SAINTS, OF REVOLUTIONARIES, AND MORE 105 (1988) (emphasis <lb/>added). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>1998] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>293 <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1379 <lb/></page>

			<body>way: &quot;How would you feel if everyone around you were speaking and <lb/>laughing aloud in a language that you could not understand?&quot;&apos; &apos; 8 An-<lb/>other agreed with a hospital that the speaking of Tagalog by Filipina <lb/>nurses in its mother-baby unit was &quot;rude and disruptive&quot; and <lb/>&quot;contribut[ed] to... dissension.&quot;&apos; 5 9 And still another reported em-<lb/>ployers&apos; concern that the continued speaking of non-English languages <lb/>would turn the workplace into a Tower of &quot;Babel&quot; where &quot;inefficiency <lb/>and chaos&quot; would reign.&apos;&quot; <lb/>Of course, far from reporting any evidence that multilingual em-<lb/>ployees cause &quot;inefficiency and chaos,&quot; these courts failed even to tell <lb/>us what the offending words and phrases were thought to be. In <lb/>contrast, those courts do not hesitate to report exactly what was said to <lb/>strike the nerve in workplace cases in which the employers and employ-<lb/>ees speak English.&apos; 6 &apos; No reason has been offered about why things <lb/>should be different merely because the key words happen to be in <lb/>Spanish, or indeed, any other tongue. <lb/>This is Latino invisibility at its most ironic: even when a Latino <lb/>plaintiff gets her day in court, the judge fails to consider and evaluate <lb/>exactly what caused all the fuss in the first place. Perhaps this is be-<lb/>cause, as Juan Perea has argued, the &quot;mere sound of Spanish offends <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>158. Long v. First Union Corp. of Va., 1996 U.S. App. LEXIS 12431, at *3 n.5 (4th Cir. May 29, <lb/>1996). The manager also called one of the plaintiffs, who refused to acknowledge the memo by <lb/>signing it, a &quot;troublemaker.&quot; Id. at *3. <lb/>159. Dimaranan v. Pomona Valley Hosp. Med. Ctr., 775 F. Supp. 338, 341 (C.D. Cal. 1991). <lb/>160. See Yniguez v. Arizonans for Official English, 69 F.3d 920, 936, 943 (9th Cir. 1995) (en <lb/>banc), vacated as moot sub nom., Arizonans for Official English v. Arizona, 117 S. Ct. 1055 (1997). <lb/>161. See, e.g., Harris v. Forklift Sys., Inc., 510 U.S. 17, 19 (1994) (upholding hostile work <lb/>environment claim of female plaintiff whose employer told her, &quot;You&apos;re just a dumb woman, what do <lb/>you know&quot; and &quot;Let&apos;s go to the Holiday Inn to negotiate [your] raise.&quot;). For a more recent example, <lb/>see Delph v. Dr. Pepper Bottling Co., No. 1:94-CV-71 (E.D. Mo. Sept. 19, 1996), reported in 1996 <lb/>Daily Lab. Rep. (BNA) No. 185, at p. D-12 (Sept. 24, 1996) (awarding Black plaintiff, whose <lb/>supervisor frequently called him &quot;nigger,&quot; damages of $225,000 in hostile racial working <lb/>environment case). Even Judge Reinhardt, whose authorship of the majority opinions in Gutierrez and <lb/>Yniguez and whose dissent from denial of rehearing and suggestion for en banc in Garcia v. Spun <lb/>Steak Co. stand out as especially sensitive to Latino language issues, failed to report what Spanish <lb/>words and phrases offended. But making an analogy to the speaker&apos;s protected use of a well-known <lb/>but controversial idiom, he did not hesitate to defend the bilingual plaintiff&apos;s choice of the Spanish <lb/>language to communicate with bilingual members of the public: <lb/>The Supreme Court recognized the First Amendment status of choice of language in <lb/>somewhat different circumstances when it ratified a speaker&apos;s freedom to say &quot;fuck the <lb/>draft&quot; rather than &quot;I strongly oppose the draft.&quot; Like the proponents of Article XXVIII, the <lb/>state in Cohen had described Cohen&apos;s choice of language as conduct equivalent to burning <lb/>a draft card [which is prohibited as unprotected conduct rather than free speech]. The <lb/>Court unequivocally rejected the comparison, stating that Cohen&apos;s conviction rested &quot;solely <lb/>upon speech.&quot; <lb/>Yniguez, 69 F.3d at 935 (Reinhardt, J.) (citations ommitted). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1380 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>and frightens many English-only speakers, who sense in the language a <lb/>loss of control over what they regard as their country.&quot; 62 If they and <lb/>their language can be kept hidden from view, the reasoning might go, <lb/>then perhaps we can maintain control of our institutions. <lb/>B. Anglo Masters and Latino Servants <lb/>The other striking thing about the reported English-only decisions <lb/>is that in each of them the plaintiff was a bilingual employee of color, <lb/>usually Latino, and the defendant was an employer managed by a <lb/>monolingual Anglo. The plaintiffs have names like de la Cruz, Flores, <lb/>Garcfa, Gutierrez, Jurado, Saucedo, and Yniguez; the defendants or their <lb/>supervisors have names like Benson, Berman, Bertelsen, Gloor, Holliday, <lb/>and Mofford. Observing this pattern, with only the names of the parties <lb/>changing, one might logically conclude that the natural order of things <lb/>is that Anglos are masters and Latinos are servants-a condition bound <lb/>to make the former visible and the latter invisible. <lb/>Now at first glance it should come as no surprise that Title VII, a <lb/>statute designed to protect the rights of disenfranchised minorities, <lb/>should produce a body of reported decisions in which all the plaintiffs <lb/>are persons of color and all the defendants are not. But in light of the <lb/>foregoing observations about Latino invisibility, I think it worth noting <lb/>for two reasons. <lb/>First, finding that Latinos are always the servants reflects a basic <lb/>presumption about their proper place in the employment hierarchy. In <lb/>so many of the workplaces affected by these cases, bilingual Spanish-<lb/>speaking employees like Hector Garcfa were employed precisely be-<lb/>cause of their bilingual capabilities;&apos; 64 so it seems odd that, with perhaps <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>162. Perea, supra note 41, at 965. Conversely, Professor Perea has speculated, it is because <lb/>Spanish also frightens many Latinos, &quot;for it proclaims their identity as Latinos, for all to hear.&quot; Id. <lb/>The price for becoming so identified may include the loss of a job, scapegoating, or simply invisibility <lb/>as an outsider-a price that, for some Latinos, may be simply too high to pay. See id. <lb/>163. Of course, I must be among the first to concede that having a traditional Spanish surname is <lb/>not the definitive marker of a Latino; in my own case, I have my father&apos;s Anglo surname. Indeed, in <lb/>my own extended Mexican-American family, many surnames-such as Adam, Carr, and Mallett, to <lb/>mention but a few-would seem to belie our family&apos;s heritage just as others-such as Ruiz, Nevarez, <lb/>and Zamora-would seem to confirm it. <lb/>164. See Garcfa v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264, 266 (5th Cir. 1980); see also, e.g., Yniguez, 69 F.3d at <lb/>924 (involving plaintiff Maria-Kelley Yniguez, a medical malpractice claims administrator who, prior <lb/>to the enactment of Arizona&apos;s English-only law, communicated in Spanish with monolingual Spanish-<lb/>speaking claimants and in a combination of Spanish and English with bilingual claimants); Gutierrez <lb/>v. Municipal Court, 838 F.2d 1031, 1036 (1988) (in addition to her other duties, plaintiff Alva <lb/>Gutierrez, a bilingual deputy court clerk with the Los Angeles Municipal Court, translated for the <lb/>non-English-speaking public). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1381 <lb/></page>

			<body>one exception,&quot; none of the supervisors of these employees appeared <lb/>to be either Latino or bilingual himself. The implication is that, al-<lb/>though bilingual Latinos are essential to getting the work done, they <lb/>should not become so prominent that they actually call the shots. <lb/>Rather, they should disappear unless and until sent for. <lb/>Second, by never questioning the roles presupposed for workplace <lb/>actors who perform in these case law dramas, courts ratify the historic <lb/>subordination of Latinos as &quot;peons&quot;-servant people who may be <lb/>taken for granted. This subordination is the product of centuries of op-<lb/>pression of the mestizo and Indian workforce, first by the Spaniards and <lb/>criollos,&apos; who conquered New Spain (and produced mestizos-<lb/>Latinos-by miscegenation with Indians) 6 7 and later by Anglos and <lb/>their descendants who conquered northern Mexico. 16 It is a subordina-<lb/>tion born of the fact that instead of prospering, Latinos, and especially <lb/>Mexicans, actually have fallen victim to &quot;their desirability as work-<lb/>ers.&quot;&apos; 69 The sentiment that workers of Mexican heritage will work the <lb/>hardest jobs for the longest hours at the lowest pay, all under the watch-<lb/>ful eye of El Patr6n, 70 has a rich tradition.&apos; <lb/>In praise of Mexican <lb/>workers, one early Anglo observer advised: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>165. See Saucedo v. Brothers Well Serv., Inc., 464 F. Supp. 919, 920 (S.D. Tex. 1979) <lb/>(identifying one of owners of employer as Jarrel Nohavistza); cf. Odima v. Westin Tucson Hotel, 53 <lb/>F.3d 1484 (9th Cir. 1995) (identifying laundry room supervisor of Nigerian-born plaintiff, who <lb/>brought accent discrimination claim against hotel, as Larry Garcfa). <lb/>166. A Spaniard born in the New World. See, e.g., JUAN G6mEz-QuI&amp;ONES, MEXICAN-<lb/>AMERICAN LABOR, 1790-1990 at 19 (1994); RAM6N EDUARDO Ruiz, TRIUMPHS AND TRAGEDY: A <lb/>HISToRY OF THE MEXICAN PEOPLE 54 (1992). <lb/>167. According to historian Juan G6mez-Quifiones: <lb/>The group consciousness and identity of this population [Mexicans) developed in a manner <lb/>consistent with the fact that they were neither Indian nor Spaniard. Regardless of the <lb/>attitudes of the criollos (American-born Spaniards), the mestizos&apos; consciousness and <lb/>numbers were to be important in the future. Mestizaje mitigated distinct ethnic divisions. <lb/>Furthermore, although criollo, mestizo, negro, and indio all held prejudices against each <lb/>other, they all suffered prejudice from a common source-the Spaniards-for the common <lb/>reason of colonization. <lb/>G6MEz-QuIF4oNES, supra note 166, at 19. <lb/>168. See id. at 39, 45. Ken Bums&apos; recent six-part documentary for public television about the <lb/>settlement of the American West illustrated the extent to which Mexican descendants of the <lb/>Spaniards and others who first settled the California, New Mexico, and Texas territories were treated <lb/>as &quot;foreigners&quot; and displaced from their centuries-old homelands by American Anglos in the mid-to <lb/>late-nineteenth century. The West (PBS broadcasts Sept. 15-18 &amp; 23-24, 1996). <lb/>169. G6MEZ-QUIRONES, supra note 166, at 3. <lb/>170. &quot;The Boss.&quot; Even my mother, an easygoing Mexican-American woman who prides herself <lb/>on treating employees with respect and dignity, says the Latino workers she has managed in various <lb/>distribution warehouses tend to refer to her as La Patrofia. Conversation with Sylvia Ruiz Cameron <lb/>(July, 1991). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1382 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>When gold shall begin to fail, or require capital or machinery, <lb/>you will want these hardy men to quarry rocks and feed your <lb/>stampers.... They will become the hewers of wood and the <lb/>drawers of water to American capital and enterprise.&quot;&apos; <lb/>In a less complimentary vein, an agricultural employer admitted: <lb/>We want the Mexicans because we can treat them as we cannot <lb/>treat any other living man. We can control them at night behind <lb/>bolted gates, within a stockade eight feet high, surrounded by <lb/>barbed wire. We make them work under armed guard in the <lb/>fields. 73 <lb/>Anglo perceptions of workers of Mexican heritage prompted one <lb/>historian to write: <lb/>In discussing Mexican immigrants, Anglos often employed the <lb/>term &quot;peon&quot; <lb/>as a synonym for &quot;Mexican.&quot; <lb/>Just as <lb/>Americans&apos; perceptions of the Chinese became inextricably <lb/>linked to the image of the coolie, so their concept of Mexicans <lb/>melded with the image of the peon. The Mexican was defined <lb/>by the labor he performed.&quot; <lb/>Octavio Paz has acknowledged this condition as the &quot;servant men-<lb/>tality.&quot;&apos; 175 While cautioning against the oversimplification that may ac-<lb/>company the use of such a label, 17 6 Paz sees the &quot;servant mentality&quot; <lb/>manifested in the Mexican tendency toward suspicion, dissimulation, <lb/>irony, and courtesy in dealings with strangers, including employers-all <lb/>&quot;traits of a subjected people who tremble and disguise themselves in the <lb/>presence of the master.... Slaves, servants, and submerged races always <lb/>wear a mask, whether smiling or sullen.&apos; 7 7 <lb/>If the perpetual condition of a Latino in the workplace is one of <lb/>subordination, then it becomes easy to forget that she deserves the same <lb/>respect that any Anglo would claim, namely, that he exists. What else <lb/>could explain the back-handed compliment of the judge who, perhaps <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>171. A chapter of one book, entitled &quot;The Anglo Perception of the Mexican Worker,&quot; contains <lb/>quotation after quotation from employers who alternately praise and scorn Mexicans and Mexican <lb/>Americans for their willingness to work under difficult conditions. See MARK REISLER, By THE <lb/>SWEAT OF THEIR BROW: MEXICAN IMMIGRANT LABOR IN THE UNITED STATES, 1900-1940 at 127-<lb/>50 (1976). <lb/>172. G6MEZ-QuIRONeS, supra note 166, at 17 (quoting Walter Colton). <lb/>173. Id. ht 3 (quoting unidentified grower). <lb/>174. REISLER, supra note 171, at 132 (citations omitted). <lb/>175. PAZ, supra note 90, at 70. <lb/>176. See id. at 71. <lb/>177. Id. at 70. For a feminist perspective on the wearing of masks by Latinas, see Margaret E. <lb/>Montoya, Mascaras, Trenzas, y Greflas: Un/Masking the Self While Un/Braiding Latina Stories and <lb/>Legal Discourse, 17 HARV. WOMEN&apos;S L.J. 185, 193 (1994). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1383 <lb/></page>

			<body>with the best of intentions, credited the testimony of an employee who <lb/>protested his employer&apos;s English-only rule, because he was &quot;an intelli-<lb/>gent and fairly well educated Mexican-American&quot;? 1 7 8 Or the radio <lb/>station program director who advised his bilingual disc jockey to stop <lb/>speaking &quot;street Spanish&quot; on the air because his program was &quot;too <lb/>ethnic&quot; and studies showed the station did not &quot;need the Mexicans or <lb/>blacks to win in L.A.&quot;?&apos; 79 Or the bank manager who screamed at two <lb/>Latino employees that &quot;the next person ... speaking Spanish [is] going <lb/>out the door&quot;? 80 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>178. Saucedo v. Brothers Well Serv., Inc., 464 F. Supp. 919, 922 (S.D. Tex. 1979). What is <lb/>remarkable about Judge Cowan&apos;s statement in Saucedo is not that he thought it probative to describe <lb/>Perez as &quot;fairly well educated&quot; but that he thought it necessary to say Perez was a &quot;fairly well-<lb/>educated Mexican-American&quot;-suggesting there was something unusual about discovering a Chicano <lb/>who actually had attended a postsecondary institution other than a trade school. It is doubtful that <lb/>Judge Cowan would have bothered to describe in quite the same way an Anglo witness cast in <lb/>Perez&apos;s role (viz., &quot;Perry is a fairly well educated Anglo&quot;). <lb/>The remark reminds me of a recent incident in my own home involving my 80-year-old <lb/>grandfather, who was born in Aguascalientes, Mexico, and entered the U.S. when he was 3. My <lb/>abuelo came to live with us during a period when his advancing age made it difficult for my <lb/>grandmother to take care of him by herself. Like most folks in my neighborhood, our family pays a <lb/>Latino man who works for himself to mow the lawn and trim the shrubs once a week. One day, an <lb/>elderly but vigorous Anglo man came to the door to promote his landscaping business. I had <lb/>answered the door when my abuelo came shuffling up behind me. The man was explaining how <lb/>thorough his work would be when my abuelo interrupted, &quot;Will you do all the work yourself?.&quot; <lb/>&quot;Heavens no,&quot; came the reply. &quot;I have a couple of Mexican fellas do it.&quot; I put my arm around my <lb/>grandfather and said: &quot;You know, we&apos;re a couple of Mexican fellas.&quot; Without batting an eye, the <lb/>man added: &quot;They&apos;re very hard workers, the Mexican fellas, they just need some guidance. I show <lb/>them how they can make more money working for me.&quot; Now, when I help my abuelo with things like <lb/>getting in the car, he winks at me and says, &quot;Sometimes, I just need some guidance.&quot; Our parents and <lb/>grandparents often have important stories to tell. See, e.g., Michael A. Olivas, The Chronicles, My <lb/>Grandfather&apos;s Stories, and Immigration Law: The Slave Traders Chronicles as Racial History, 34 ST. <lb/>Louis U. L.J. 425 (1990). <lb/>The employer in Saucedo did not put so fine a spin on things. Steve Perez, the protesting <lb/>employee, was beaten by Cleighton E. (&quot;Doc&quot;) Holliday, an Anglo who &quot;simply did not tolerate <lb/>&apos;Mesican&apos; talk&quot; at work, for daring to complain. See Saucedo, 464 F. Supp. at 921. (The decision <lb/>suggests but does not say that Holliday was a foreman.) Even though the employer&apos;s owner <lb/>witnessed the assault, Holliday was not so much as disciplined. See id. at 922. Yet John Saucedo, the <lb/>employee who violated the English-only rule by asking Perez &quot;in two words of Spanish&quot; where to put <lb/>a heavy part, was fired for his transgression. See id. at 921. <lb/>179. Jurado v. Eleven-Fifty Corp., 813 F.2d 1406, 1410 (9th Cir. 1987). The employer&apos;s decision <lb/>was curious for two more reasons: first, because a prior station program director actually had <lb/>encouraged Valentine Jurado, the disc jockey, to speak some Spanish on the air in order to attract a <lb/>Hispanic audience; and second, because the station continued to permit Rick Dees, an Anglo disc <lb/>jockey, to use some Spanish on his program. Id. at 1408, 1410. <lb/>180. Long v. First Union Corp. of Va., No. 95-1986, 1996 U.S. App. LEXIS 12431, at *7 n.6 (4th <lb/>Cir. May 29, 1996). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1384 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>Octavio Paz recalled a servant in his own employ who seemed to <lb/>have internalized others&apos; wishes for her invisibility, who had become a <lb/>&quot;[n]obody&quot;: <lb/>I remember the afternoon I heard a noise in the room next to <lb/>mine, and asked loudly, &quot;Who is in there?&quot; I was answered by <lb/>the voice of a servant who had recently come to us from her vil-<lb/>lage: &quot;No one, sefior. I am.&quot;&apos;&apos; <lb/>]I <lb/>LEGAL INDETERMINACY OF NATIONAL ORIGIN DISCRIMINATION LAW <lb/>Yolanda gazes at the cake [shaped like the Caribbean island of <lb/>Hispahola]. Below her blazes the route she has worked out on a <lb/>map for herself, north of the city through the mountains to the <lb/>coast.... She leans forward and shuts her eyes. There is so <lb/>much she wants, it is hard to single out one wish. There have <lb/>been too many stops on the road of the last twenty-nine years <lb/>since her family left this island behind. She and her sisters have <lb/>led such turbulent lives-so many husbands, homes, jobs, wrong <lb/>turns among them. But look at her cousins, women with <lb/>households and authority in their voices. Let this turn out to be <lb/>my home, Yolanda wishes. <lb/>-Yolanda Garcia de la Torre1 82 <lb/>&quot;In every legal system,&quot; according to H.L.A. Hart, &quot;a large and <lb/>important field is left open for the exercise of discretion by the courts <lb/>and other officials in rendering initially vague standards determinate, in <lb/>resolving the uncertainties of statutes, or in developing and qualifying <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>181. PAZ, supra note 90, at 44. Paz elaborated with the plot summary of a morality play <lb/>contrasting an outgoing patriarch named &quot;Don No One&quot; with his self-effacing son called &quot;Nobody&quot;: <lb/>Don No One, who is Nobody&apos;s Spanish father, is able, well fed, well respected; he has <lb/>a bank account and speaks in a loud, self-assured voice. Don No One fills the world with <lb/>his empty, garrulous presence.... He either holds office or wields influence, and his <lb/>manner of not-being is aggressive and conceited. Nobody is quiet, timid and resigned. He <lb/>is also intelligent and sensitive. He always smiles. He always waits. When he wants to say <lb/>something, he meets a wall of silence; when he pleads or weeps or cries out, his gestures <lb/>and cries are lost in the emptiness created by Don No One&apos;s interminable chatter .... <lb/>It would be a mistake to believe that others prevent [Nobody] from existing. They <lb/>simply dissimulate his existence and behave as if he did not exist. They nullify him, cancel <lb/>him out, turn him into nothingness. It is futile for Nobody to talk, to publish books, to paint <lb/>pictures, to stand on his head. He is the name we always and inevitably forget, the eternal <lb/>absentee, the guest we never invite, the emptiness we can never fill. <lb/>Id. at 45. <lb/>182. ALVAREZ, supra note 1, at 11. <lb/></listBibl><note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1385 <lb/></page>

			<body>rules only broadly communicated by authoritative precedents.&apos; &apos; 3 <lb/>Seizing on this truth, a wide range of legal thinkers, including legal re-<lb/>alists, 184 pragmatists,&quot; and critical legal scholars,&quot; 6 have argued that the <lb/>law is indeterminate in the sense that legal materials-statutes and court <lb/>decisions interpreting them-often permit a judge to justify multiple <lb/>outcomes to lawsuits. 87 <lb/>As George Martfnez has pointed out, the indeterminacy of the law <lb/>in the areas of bilingual education, land grants, public accommodations, <lb/>restrictive covenants, racial slurs, and school desegregation has permitted <lb/>jurists to manipulate outcomes in cases affecting Latino litigants, espe-<lb/>cially Mexican Americans. 8 &apos; In each of these areas, the text of the ap-<lb/>plicable statute or authoritative case law was so general that the court, far <lb/>from being &quot;bound&quot; by precedent to rule against the Mexican-<lb/>American litigant, &quot;could have gone the other way.&quot; &apos; <lb/>189 &quot;Exposing the <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>183. <lb/>H.L.A. HART, THE CONCEPT OF LAW 132 (1961). <lb/>184. See, e.g., JEROME FRANK, LAW AND THE MODERN MIND 7 (1936) (&quot;In fields other than <lb/>law there is today a willingness to accept probabilities and to forego the hope of finding the absolute <lb/>certain.... Since legal tentativeness is inevitable and often socially desirable, it should not be <lb/>considered an avoidable evil.&quot;); KARL N. LLEWELLYN, JURISPRUDENCE: REALISM IN THEORY AND <lb/>PRACTICE 122-23 (1962) (&quot;[W]hen the urges of justice and policy are clear enough, [judges] can <lb/>find a distinction to avoid or whittle almost any precedent.... Mhe precedents are capable of being <lb/>shaped as they are followed or applied, so as to bring judgment out on one side or the other.&quot;); Felix <lb/>S. Cohen, Transcendental Nonsense and the Functional Approach, 35 COLUM. L REv. 809, 833 <lb/>(1935) (&quot;[Ihe really creative legal thinkers of the future will not devote themselves.., to the <lb/>taxonomy of legal concepts and to the systematic explication of principles of &apos;justice&apos; and &apos;reason,&apos; <lb/>buttressed by &apos;correct&apos; cases. Great legal thought will more and more look behind the pretty array of <lb/>&apos;correct&apos; cases to the actual facts of judicial behavior.&quot;); Roscoe Pound, The Call for a Realist <lb/>Jurisprudence, 44 HARV. L. REV. 697, 707 (1931) (&quot;Radical neo-realism seems to deny that there are <lb/>rules or principles or conceptions or doctrines at all, because all judicial action, or at times much <lb/>judicial action, can not be referred to them; because there is no definite determination whereby we <lb/>may be absolutely assured that judicial action would proceed on the basis of one rather than another <lb/>of two competing principles .... &quot;). <lb/>185. See, e.g., RICHARD A. POSNER, THE PROBLEMS OF JURISPRUDENCE 23 (1990) (&quot;[T]he <lb/>American legal tradition is now so rich, variegated, conflicted, and ambivalent that a strand of it can <lb/>easily be found to support either side in difficult cases.&quot;). <lb/>186. See, e.g., DAVID KAIRYs, THE POLITICS OF LAW: A PROGRESSIVE CRITIQUE 140, 160-61 <lb/>(1982) (&quot;Since precedents and reasoning can be distinguished, modified, or discarded, they do not <lb/>require any particular rule or result.... [T]he law merely provides a variety of bases for justifying <lb/>choices made on other grounds.&quot;); Mark V. Tushnet, Following the Rules Laid Down: A Critique of <lb/>Interpretivism and Neutral Principles, 96 HARv. L REv. 781, 819 (1983) (arguing prior decisions <lb/>cannot restrain present decisions because &quot;it turns out that the limits of craft are so broad that in any <lb/>interesting case any reasonably skilled lawyer can reach whatever result he or she wants.&quot;). <lb/>187. See Martfnez, supra note 42, at 558. <lb/>188. See id. at 559, 573, 584, 606, 611, 618; see also George A. Martfnez, Some Thoughts on <lb/>Law and Interpretation, 50 SMU L. Rev. 1651, 1653-62 (1997) (discussing distinctive role of <lb/>interpretation in law from a philosophical perspective). <lb/>189. Id. at 583. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1386 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>lack of inevitability in civil rights judicial decision-making,&quot; writes <lb/>Professor Martinez, &quot;may help eliminate barriers to racial reform.&quot;&apos;1&apos; 9 <lb/>For the reasons I explore below, we may now add employment dis-<lb/>crimination to the list of areas of civil rights law in which the indetermi-<lb/>nacy of the law permits multiple outcomes to national origin claims <lb/>brought under Title VII. The primary source of indeterminacy in judi-<lb/>cial decisions addressing English-only rules is the uncertain statutory <lb/>definition of what constitutes a prima facie case of national origin dis-<lb/>crimination under Title VII. <lb/>The plain language of Title VII offers no definition of what con-<lb/>stitutes &quot;national origin&quot; discrimination, let alone an answer as to <lb/>whether an employer&apos;s implementation of an English-only rule consti-<lb/>tutes such discrimination. Section 703 merely makes it an unlawful <lb/>employment practice for an employer &quot;to discriminate against any in-<lb/>dividual with respect to his... terms, conditions, or privileges of em-<lb/>ployment because of such individual&apos;s ... national origin.&quot;&apos;&apos;9 <lb/>The <lb/>only &quot;direct definition&quot;&apos;&quot; 2 of the term was offered by Congressman <lb/>Roosevelt, chairman of the House subcommittee which reported out the <lb/>bill that eventually became Title VII, who said during the floor debate: <lb/>&quot;It means the country from which you or your forbears came.... You <lb/>may come from Poland, Czechoslovakia, England, France, or any other <lb/>country .,&quot;93 <lb/>The bill&apos;s mark-up seemed to support this interpretation, however <lb/>vague. An earlier version of the bill had referred to discrimination be-<lb/>cause of &quot;race, color, religion, national origin, or ancestry.&quot;&apos; 9 4 <lb/>Although the word &quot;ancestry&quot; was deleted from the version that passed, <lb/>a House report stated that the deletion was not intended to be a material <lb/>change,&apos; 95 suggesting that Congress considered the terms &quot;national ori-<lb/>gin&quot; and &quot;ancestry&quot; to be synonymous.&apos; 96 <lb/>Lacking a clear definition, then, courts hearing claims of national <lb/>origin discrimination under Title VII faced a wide open field; they had <lb/>plenty of discretion to decide whether and to what extent English-only <lb/>rules, and an employer&apos;s implementation of them, would be considered <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>190. Id. at 560. <lb/>191. 42 U.S.C. § 2000e-2(a) (1) (1994). <lb/>192. Espinoza v. Farah Mfg. Co., 414 U.S. 86, 89 (1973). <lb/>193. 110 CONG. REc. 2549 (1964) (remarks of Rep. Roosevelt). Tellingly, the few examples <lb/>offered by Congressman Roosevelt were of persons of European origin only. <lb/>194. H.R. REP. No. 88-7152, at 804 (1963) (emphasis added). <lb/>195. See H.R. REP. No. 88-914, at 87 (1963). <lb/>196. See Espinoza, 414 U.S. at 89. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>1998] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1387 <lb/></page>

			<body>unlawful. As we have seen, 9 7 the Fifth Circuit, which in Garcia v. Gloor <lb/>became the first federal appellate court to report an English-only deci-<lb/>sion, exercised this discretion by ruling against Hector Garcfa. 9 Curi-<lb/>ously, Judge Rubin sought to make a case of first impression seem as <lb/>though the statute compelled only the result that the court finally <lb/>reached. Mr. Garcfa&apos;s argument, Judge Rubin explained, &quot;reduces it-<lb/>self to a contention that the statute commands employers to permit em-<lb/>ployees to speak the tongue they prefer. We do not think the statute <lb/>permits that interpretation, whether the preference be slight or strong or <lb/>even closely related to self-identity.&quot;&apos; &apos; <lb/>Responding to Garcia v. Gloor,r ° as well as to the spread of <lb/>English-only rules in private workplaces, the EEOC issued its <lb/>&quot;Guidelines on Discrimination Because of National Origin.&quot; 2 , The <lb/>Guidelines, which essentially codified the agency&apos;s administrative dispo-<lb/>sition of several early complaints on the subject, 0 2 provided then as now <lb/>that promulgation of an English-only rule burdens the employee whose <lb/>primary language is not English, and so makes out a prima facie case of <lb/>national origin discrimination against the employee. 0 3 But this prima <lb/>facie case, according to the Guidelines, may be overcome by the em-<lb/>ployer&apos;s proof that the rule is based upon legitimate business necessity, <lb/>such as promoting workplace safety.&apos; <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>197. See supra Part I.A. <lb/>198. See Garcfa v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264, 269-71 (5th Cir. 1980) (Garcia I). <lb/>199. Id. at 271 (emphasis added). <lb/>200. See Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 13 F.3d 296, 299 n.5 (1993) (Reinhardt, J., dissenting from <lb/>denial of rehearing en banc) (&quot;In fact, the Guideline at issue here was enacted shortly after (the <lb/>lower court decided the case], probably in order to reserve the effect of that decision.&quot;). <lb/>201. 45 Fed. Reg. 85, 636 (1980) (codified at 29 C.F.R. § 1606.7 (1996)). In pertinent part, the <lb/>Guidelines provide: <lb/>(a) When applied at all times. A rule requiring employees to speak English only at all times <lb/>in the workplace is a burdensome term and condition of employment. The primary <lb/>language of an individual is often an essential national origin characteristic. Prohibiting <lb/>employees at all times, in the workplace, from speaking their primary language or the <lb/>language they speak most comfortably, disadvantages an individual&apos;s employment <lb/>opportunities on the basis of national origin. It may also create an atmosphere of inferiority, <lb/>isolation and intimidation based on national origin which could result in a discriminatory <lb/>working environment. Therefore, the Commission will presume that such a rule violates <lb/>title VII and will closely scrutinize it. <lb/>(b) When applied only at certain times. An employer may have a rule requiring that <lb/>employees speak only in English at certain times where the employer can show that the rule <lb/>is justified by business necessity. <lb/>29 C.F.R. § 1606.7(a)-(b). <lb/>202. See 29 C.F.R. § 1606.7(a) n.7 (1996) (citing EEOC decisions). <lb/>203. See id. § 1606.7(a). <lb/>204. See id. § 1606.7(b). The six reasons most commonly proffered by employers to defend <lb/>English-only rules out of business necessity are (1) ensuring worker safety, (2) assuring effective <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1388 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>Since the EEOC adopted the Guidelines, the Ninth Circuit has been <lb/>the first and only federal appellate court to decide any challenges to <lb/>English-only rules. The court has published opinions in three cases: <lb/>Jurado v. Eleven-Fifty Corp.,25 Gutierrez v. Municipal Court,&quot; and <lb/>Garcia v. Spun Steak. 2 &apos; The wildly inconsistent results produced by <lb/>various panels of the Ninth Circuit in these cases is a classic illustration <lb/>of how legal indeterminacy may be exploited to manipulate the law and <lb/>to achieve preferred results. <lb/>In Jurado, the court affirmed a grant of summary judgment against <lb/>a bilingual disc jockey &quot;of Mexican-American and Native-American <lb/>descent&quot; who challenged his discharge for violating the radio station&apos;s <lb/>new rule prohibiting him from using some words and phrases of &quot;street <lb/>Spanish&quot; on the air.&quot; 0 8 Although Judge Wiggins, who wrote for the <lb/>court, justified the ruling with what I characterized above as some dubi-<lb/>ous reasons,&apos; ° he did predicate his conclusion that Jurado had not made <lb/>out a prima face case upon &quot;insufficient evidence that [the radio sta-<lb/>tion] discharged him for discriminatory motives.&quot; 10 According to <lb/>Judge Wiggins, the undisputed evidence showed that the English-only <lb/>rule was &quot;a programming decision motivated by marketing, ratings, and <lb/>demographics concerns.&quot; &apos; &apos; The station&apos;s program director was wor-<lb/>ried that Jurado&apos;s bilingual format would confuse listeners and hurt lis-<lb/>tenership. 212 In fact, Judge Wiggins found Jurado&apos;s old bilingual format <lb/>&quot;had not improved [the radio station&apos;s] performance in the target <lb/>Hispanic community.&quot; 2 3 <lb/>Which brings us back to the EEOC Guidelines. Although I might <lb/>argue with Judge Wiggins about whether these concerns truly scuttled <lb/>Jurado&apos;s claim for failure to present sufficient evidence of the radio <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>supervision, (3) increasing productivity and efficiency, (4) promoting worker harmony, (5) improving <lb/>customer relations and satisfaction, and (6) improving employees&apos; English proficiency. <lb/>See <lb/>Jorgensen, supra note 64, at 421-27 (explaining application of same). But see Perea, supra note 36, at <lb/>302-17 (critiquing application of same). <lb/>205. 813 F.2d 1406 (9th Cir. 1987). <lb/>206. 838 F.2d 1031 (9th Cir. 1988), vacated as moot, 490 U.S. 1016 (1989). <lb/>207. 998 F.2d 1480 (9th Cir. 1993). <lb/>208. 813 F.2d at 1408. <lb/>209. See supra Part I.A. (discussing court&apos;s references to bilingual Jurado&apos;s &quot;ability to conform&quot; <lb/>to the English-only rule); see also Jurado, 813 F.2d at 1411. <lb/>210. Jurado, 813 F.2d at 1409. <lb/>211. Id.at 1410. <lb/>212. See id. <lb/>213. Id. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1389 <lb/></page>

			<body>station&apos;s discriminatory motive, 1 4 I would find it difficult to accuse him <lb/>of ignoring the Guidelines. Indeed, Judge Wiggins cited them with ap-<lb/>parent approval. 2 &apos; <lb/>5 <lb/>Although nothing in the Guidelines says the <lb/>EEOC&apos;s presumption of national origin discrimination may be ignored <lb/>if it is shown that the employer was more worried about ratings than <lb/>race, nothing says such a showing is insufficient to rebut the presump-<lb/>tion, either. Moreover, Jurado might be interpreted as a case that actu-<lb/>ally satisfies the Guidelines, insofar as Judge Wiggins&apos; emphasis on <lb/>ratings might be considered as establishing a business necessity de-<lb/>fense. 1 6 In short, the question of how to interpret even the Guidelines <lb/>themselves may be considered indeterminate. Authority exists to sup-<lb/>port the opposite outcome. <lb/>But in Gutierrez, another panel of the same court saw the merits of <lb/>an English-only rule somewhat differently. There the Ninth Circuit <lb/>enjoined a rule requiring bilingual municipal court clerks, whose offi-<lb/>cial duties included translating for monolingual, Spanish-speaking <lb/>members of the public, to refrain from speaking Spanish while on duty <lb/>except when translating. 1 7 Writing for the court, Judge Reinhardt relied <lb/>in part on the Guidelines, which he said were entitled to considerable <lb/>deference, because they were not inconsistent with Title VII. 2 8 &quot;The <lb/>EEOC [G]uidelines, by requiring that a business necessity be shown be-<lb/>fore a limited English-only rule may be enforced, properly balance the <lb/>individual&apos;s interest in speaking his primary language and any possible <lb/>need of the employer to ensure that in particular circumstances only <lb/>English shall be spoken.&quot; 2 9 Jurado was distinguished, alternatively, as <lb/>either an &quot;ability to conform&quot; case outside the Guidelines, or as a <lb/>&quot;business necessity&quot; defense case within the Guidelines. 2 2 <lb/>Then a fateful thing happened: Alva Gutierrez quit her job as a <lb/>clerk with the Los Angeles Municipal Court. As a result, the Supreme <lb/>Court vacated the Gutierrez panel&apos;s published opinion as moot. 221 <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>214. Jurado made a strong case that the ratings defense was a smokescreen for racial animus. <lb/>For example, a consultant wrote that the station was &quot;preoccupied with ethnicity to a frightening <lb/>degree.&quot; And the program director thought Jurado&apos;s show was &quot;too ethnic&quot; and claimed that the <lb/>station &quot;did not need the Mexicans or the blacks to win in L.A.&quot; Id. at 1410. <lb/>215. See id. at 1411 (citing 29 C.F.R. § 1606.7). <lb/>216. See Gutierrez v. Municipal Court, 838 F.2d 1031, 1041 (9th Cir. 1988) (characterizing <lb/>Jurado as such). <lb/>217. See id. at 1036. <lb/>218. See id. at 1039 n.7 (Reinhardt, J.) (citing Espinoza v. Farah Mfg. Co., 414 U.S. 86, 94-95 <lb/>(1973)). <lb/>219. Id. at 1040. <lb/>220. See id. at 1041. <lb/>221. 490U.S. 1016 (1989). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1390 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>Although the published opinion remained on the books as persuasive <lb/>authority, it no longer carried the weight of binding precedent in the <lb/>Ninth Circuit.m 2 <lb/>So in Garcta v. Spun Steak Co., Judge O&apos;Scannlain felt uncon-<lb/>strained by any determinate rules of law. He was free to write on a rela-<lb/>tively clean slate. Relying on Garcia v. Gloor rather than Gutierrez, 2 1 <lb/>he found that Priscilla Garcfa had not stated a prima facie case of na-<lb/>tional origin discrimination for the two reasons that I noted above:&apos; <lb/>first, because the burden imposed by Spun Steak&apos;s English-only rule <lb/>was not &quot;significant enough to amount to the denial of equal opportu-<lb/>nity&quot;;&apos; and second, because she was able but unwilling to comply with <lb/>the rule. 226 In a three-sentence footnote, Judge O&apos;Scannlain dismissed <lb/>Gutierrez as non-binding and declined to address the arguments em-<lb/>braced by Judge Reinhardt. 227 <lb/>There still remained one obstacle: the EEOC Guidelines. But even <lb/>these did not prevent Judge O&apos;Scannlain from reaching &quot;a conclusion <lb/>opposite to the EEOC&apos;s longstanding position.&quot; z 8 The court rejected <lb/>the English-only Guideline, because of &quot;compelling indications that it <lb/>was wrong&quot; &apos; <lb/>namely, the absence of any mention of English-only <lb/>rules in the legislative history.Y 0 Once dismissed as incorrect, the <lb/>Guidelines could no longer prevent the court from being &quot;impressed <lb/>by Judge Rubin&apos;s pre-Guidelines analysis&quot; in Garcia v. Gloor? 3 &apos; <lb/>Judge Reinhardt, the author of Gutierrez, blasted Judge <lb/>O&apos;Scannlain&apos;s legal manipulations in his dissent from denial of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>222. Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 998 F.2d 1480, 1487 (9th Cir. 1993); see also 13A CHARLES A <lb/>WRIGHT &amp; ARTHUR R. MILLER, FEDERAL PRACTICE AND PROCEDURE § 3533.10 (1984) (vacating <lb/>court of appeals judgment as moot vacates opinion&apos;s status as binding precedent but not its <lb/>persuasiveness); accord Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 13 F.3d 296, 301 (9th Cir. 1993) (Reinhardt, J., <lb/>dissenting from denial of rehearing en banc) (citing same). <lb/>223. See Garcia v. Spun Steak, 998 F.2d at 1487, 1489 (9th Cir. 1993) (citing Garcfa v. Gloor, <lb/>618 F.2d 264 (5th Cir. 1980)). <lb/>224. See supra Part L.A-B. <lb/>225. Garcia v. Spun Steak, 998 F.2d at 1488. <lb/>226. See id. at 1487-88. <lb/>227. See id. at 1487 n.1 (&quot;The Spanish-speaking employees rely on the reasoning in <lb/>Gutierrez ... which held that English-only policies adversely impact Spanish-speaking employees. <lb/>The case has no precedential authority, however, because it was vacated as moot by the Supreme <lb/>Court. We are in no way bound by its reasoning.&quot;) (citations omitted). <lb/>228. Id. at 1489. <lb/>229. Id. (quoting Espinoza v. Farah Mfg. Co., 414 U.S. 86, 94 (1973)). <lb/>230. See id. at 1490. <lb/>231. Id. at 1489. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[Vol. 10:261 <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1391 <lb/></page>

			<body>rehearing en banc,n 2 decrying Judge O&apos;Scannlain&apos;s legal reasoning for <lb/>its manipulation of precedent. 3 Judge Reinhardt gave three reasons of <lb/>consequence here. First, Gutierrez, as the most recent ruling by the <lb/>Ninth Circuit on the subject, deserved better treatment than a conclusory <lb/>footnote. 4 After all, the validity of an opinion&apos;s reasoning remains <lb/>unaffected even though the merits are vacated as moot. 35 Second, <lb/>Garcia v. Gloor was a pre-Guidelines case-a factor that even Judge <lb/>O&apos;Scannlain acknowledged.&quot;s Such authority should not have been <lb/>elevated to so persuasive a position once Title VII&apos;s expert agency, the <lb/>EEOC, had issued interpretive Guidelines. Finally, Garcia v. Spun <lb/>Steak&apos;s application of the law of judicial deference to statutory inter-<lb/>pretation by administrative agencies was &quot;incomprehensible 2 3 7 and &quot;a <lb/>total non sequitur. &apos; &quot;&quot; Judge O&apos;Scannlain relied on the absence of leg-<lb/>islative history to conclude that the EEOC&apos;s interpretation must be inva-<lb/>lid, thereby <lb/>elevat[ing] legislative history to a new height. Those who believe <lb/>that even affirmative legislative history is, in general, not com-<lb/>pelling may be surpri sed to learn that its absence can be so cru-<lb/>cial as to constitute a basis for invalidating an agency rule.... <lb/>[T]he real basis of the majority&apos;s objection to the EEOC pre-<lb/>sumption is that the majority does not agree with the Guideline <lb/>on the merits. This substantive disagreement is at least rational <lb/>(though the majority&apos;s view is wrong), but it should not be trans-<lb/>formed into a wholly baseless attack on agency authority to <lb/>promulgate general rules. 9 <lb/>Judges use their discretion not only to decide cases involving inde-<lb/>terminate authority, but also to manipulate determinate authority so that <lb/>they may insert their discretion into subsequent decisions. Exposing <lb/>both the exercise of judicial discretion and the lack of inevitability in <lb/>these cases reveals the extent to which courts can-or can refuse-to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>232. See Garcfa v. Spun Steak Co., 13 F.3d 296 (9th Cir. 1993) (Reinhardt, J., dissenting from <lb/>denial of rehearing en banc). <lb/>233. See id. at 299-301. <lb/>234. See id. at 301. <lb/>235. See id. (citing 13A CHARLES A. WRIGHT JR. &amp; ARTHUR R. MILLER, FEDERAL PRACTICE <lb/>AND PROCEDURE § 3533.10 (1984)). <lb/>236. See id. at 301 n.10. (quoting Garcia v. Gloor, 618 F.2d 264, 268 n.1 (5th Cir. 1980)) (The <lb/>EEOC &quot;has adopted neither a regulation stating a standard for testing such language rules nor any <lb/>general policy, presumed to be derived from the statute, prohibiting them. We therefore approach <lb/>the problem on the basis of the statute itself and the case law.&quot;). <lb/>237. Id. at 229. <lb/>238. Id. at 300. <lb/>239. Id. at 300 &amp; n.7. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">19981 <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<page>1392 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">CALIFORNIA LAW REVIEW <lb/>[Vol. 85:1347 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>address the claims of victims of discriminatory language policies that <lb/>constitute national origin discrimination. 240 <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>The radio is all static-like the sound of the crunching metal of a <lb/>car; the faint, blurry voice on the airwaves her own, trapped in-<lb/>side a wreck, calling for help. In English or Spanish? she won-<lb/>ders. That poet she met at Lucinda&apos;s party the night before <lb/>argued that no matter how much of it one lost, in the midst of <lb/>some profound emotion, one would revert to one&apos;s mother <lb/>tongue. He put Yolanda through a series of situations. What <lb/>language, he asked, looking pointedly into her eyes, did she love <lb/>in? <lb/>-Yolanda Garcia de la Torre 2 41 <lb/>In this Essay, I have shown how judges and parties, by their use of <lb/>language-phraseology, choice of metaphor, or silence-offer insights <lb/>into why the bilingual population receives a second-class (if any) form <lb/>of protected status. The language of judicial opinions approving <lb/>English-only rules in the workplace is better understood as the product <lb/>of three interrelated but distinct themes that have become the subject of <lb/>recent scholarship studying Latinos and the law: the limits of racial du-<lb/>alism, Latinos&apos; invisibility, and legal indeterminacy. With the help of <lb/>the cousins Garcia and others, I hope to persuade courts and combatants <lb/>alike to change their belief systems and accord victims of discriminatory <lb/>English policies which constitute national origin discrimination the re-<lb/>spect they truly deserve. Our courts should recognize and address the <lb/>inescapable relationship between discriminatory English-only policies <lb/>and valid national origin discrimination claims under Title VII. <lb/>Although much of this Essay has focused on the application and <lb/>interpretation of formal Title VII doctrine, I have taken the opportunity <lb/>to illustrate some of the lessons of the law with anecdotes borrowed <lb/>from Latino literature, both serious and sublime, touching on language <lb/>issues. Nothing better captures my desire that barriers to the improved <lb/>treatment of these issues be razed than the following Mexican-American <lb/>folktale: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>240. See Martfnez, supra note 42, at 618. <lb/>241. ALVAREZ, supra note 1, at 13. <lb/>[Vol. 10:261 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/>1997] <lb/>TITLE VII AND ENGLISH-ONLY RULES <lb/></note>

			<page>1393 <lb/></page>

			<body>A gringa walked in [to a pet store] and asked, &quot;How much is <lb/>this parrot?&quot; The owner said, &quot;Oh, ma&apos;am, this is a very expen-<lb/>sive parrot, because he speaks both Spanish and English.&quot; <lb/>&quot;Oh really, can you get him to speak in both languages?&quot; <lb/>&quot;Oh yes. Look: if you pull his left leg, he speaks English.&quot; <lb/>And he pulled the parrot&apos;s leg and the parrot said, &quot;Good <lb/>morning!&quot; &quot;And if you pull his right leg like this, he speaks <lb/>Spanish.&quot; And the parrot said, &quot;iBuenos dfas!&quot; <lb/>Asked the gringa: &quot;What happens if you pull both of his legs-<lb/>will he speak Tex-Mex?&quot; <lb/>And the parrot said: &quot;No, I&apos;d fall on my ass, you stupid <lb/>gringa. &apos; <lb/>242 <lb/>None of us need think as the gringa did. Instead, we should appre-<lb/>ciate the essential role that bilingualism plays, especially at work, in the <lb/>proper classification and recognition of claims of national origin dis-<lb/>crimination. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>242. WEs&apos;r, supra note 157, at 92 (reprinting popular version of this tale). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
			<note place="headnote">1998] <lb/>LA RAZA LAW JOURNAL <lb/>CALIFORNIA LAWREVIEW </note>


	</text>

</TEI>