<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Bodies’ Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body in Jean Luc Nancy’s Corpus</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Boutheina</forename>
          <surname>Boughnim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-22T21:30:46.644Z">22/12/2025 21:30:46</date>
        <title>Review Luca</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.30958__ajha.12-4-4</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Athens Institute for Education and Research ATINER</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2025</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.30958/ajha.12-4-4</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Boutheina Boughnim. (2025). Bodies’ Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body in Jean Luc Nancy’s Corpus. Athens Journal of Humanities &amp;amp; Arts, 12(4), 423-438. DOI: 10.30958/ajha.12-4-4</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-28T13:59:21.819788Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-28T13:59:21.819788Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-11-28T14:50:09.036Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>1_Version_achtung_#Kommentare</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-06T10:48:22.152Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Final_Version</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-06T10:48:49.133Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Final_Final_Version</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-11T11:08:07.286Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections_Final_Final_Version</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-18T10:19:47.666Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-22" status="checked" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Review</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts -Volume 12, Issue 4, October 2025 -Pages 423-438 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.30958/ajha.12-4-4 <lb/>doi=10.30958/ajha.12-4-4 <lb/>Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body in <lb/>Jean Luc Nancy&apos;s Corpus <lb/>By Boutheina Boughnim * <lb/>Through the ages, and more significantly during the modern and postmodern eras, the <lb/>human body has relentlessly been the source of inspiration, amazement, repulsion etc. for <lb/>both philosophers and writers, all currents confounded. From Merleau-Ponty to Bakhtin, <lb/>Bataille and others, thinkers and artists&apos; approaches to the body abounded from different <lb/>perspectives. J. L. Nancy&apos;s envisionment of the notion of the body, which he compellingly <lb/>expounds in his essay-book Corpus, remains largely overlooked in comparison with other <lb/>mainstream phenomenological approaches, such as, Merleau-Ponty&apos;s. The present essay <lb/>seeks, through a close reading of Nancy&apos;s philosophical oeuvre, Corpus, to identify the <lb/>main characteristics of Nancy&apos;s thought pertaining to the body, his &apos;corporeal&apos; philosophy <lb/>foregrounding &quot;excription&quot; while writing (on) the body, which originates in a writing <lb/>that &quot;touches&quot; (upon) both the body and the other. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The ineffable mystery and complexity of (the writing) subject as both a self and <lb/>a body addressing another self and being is inexorably confronted with a &quot;double <lb/>failure&quot;, 1 the one of producing an inadequate discourse &apos;on&apos; the body, and also that <lb/>of the impossibility to avoid such undertaking. Such &quot;double failure&quot; may be <lb/>summed up as one and unique failure, or at least, formidable difficulty: how to <lb/>produce a &quot;textual body&quot;, a new fibre of writing that &quot;touches&quot; the &apos;other&apos; &quot;with <lb/>tact&quot; 2 without for all that reducing the body to meaning. Nancy points out that the <lb/>body (and by extrapolation the self with its attendant affects, like tenderness) is not, <lb/>cannot, be inscribed into discourse as a meaningful construct, a reducible entity; its <lb/>economy transcends discursive reduction. It is not to be found in what writing <lb/>encapsulates, but rather, what it &quot;excribes.&quot; 3 Only &quot;excription,&quot; &quot;discharges of <lb/>writing&quot;, can address the &quot;body&quot; in all its complexity and approach its ungraspable <lb/>character. In his later published long essay, published as a book entitled Corpus <lb/>(2008), Nancy 4 provides a compelling philosophical inquiry into the sense of the <lb/>body, the attendant pitfalls when treating such concept in writing or psychology <lb/>and the proper ways to counter them. The present essay seeks to analyse Nancy&apos;s <lb/>thought pertaining to the body and probe into his notion of &quot;excription&quot; to find out <lb/></body>

	<front>* <lb/>Assistant Professor, The Faculty of Letters, Arts and Humanities of Manouba, Tunisia. <lb/></front>
	  
	  <listBibl>1. J. L. Nancy, The Birth to Presence (US: Stanford University Press, 1993), 320. <lb/>2. Ibid, 321. <lb/>3. Ibid, 320. <lb/>4. Nancy, Corpus (US: Fordham University Press, 2008). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Boughnim: Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body… <lb/></note>
	  
	  <page>424 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <body>what is it that kind of discourse which &quot;excribes&quot;, which allows it to&quot;touch&quot; (upon) <lb/>both the body and the other. <lb/>The Concept of the Body in Modern and Postmodern Thought: <lb/>Three Key Approaches <lb/>Through the ages, particularly in modern and postmodern thought, the <lb/>human body has sparked a vivid interest among philosophers and writers. From <lb/>Bakhtin&apos;s &quot;grotesque body&quot; to Bataille&apos;s dead corpses, or still, to Merleau-Ponty&apos;s <lb/>&quot;gaze, the human body has been subjected to a scrutinous study and relentless <lb/>reflection. While Bakhtin devoted a whole book to the image of the body in Rabelais&apos; <lb/>work, Bataille was obsessed with the dead body as a taboo and the endemic <lb/>violence associated with its sight. As to Merleau-Ponty, he adamantly denounced <lb/>the reification, objectified reduction of the body as an objective idea rather than an <lb/>experiential entity. <lb/>As for Bakhtin, was intrigued by the grotesque portrayal of the body in Rabelais&apos; <lb/>works, notably Gargantua. In his compelling book devoted to the Rablesian oeuvre <lb/>entitled Rabelais and His World, Bakhtin 5 dwells on his fascination with Rabelais&apos; <lb/>endemic sardonic, bawdy vein when evoking bodily displays like laughter, but <lb/>also the body&apos;s gluttonous indulgence in epicurean pleasures. Bakhtin is seized by <lb/>the wealth and variety of the body imagery in Rabelais&apos; work, notably in Gargantua, <lb/>in which the multifarious manifestations of the body invariably converge into the <lb/>&quot;grotesque. Bakhtin sustains that the &quot;grotesque body&quot; as displayed, in Rabelais&apos; <lb/>literary oeuvre, with its attendant protuberances and orifices is a body which <lb/>exceeds its own limits, a body set on a perennial self-conception. In this sense <lb/>Bakhtin points out: &quot;The grotesque body, as we have often stressed, is a body in <lb/>the act of becoming… This is why the essential role belongs to those parts of the <lb/>grotesque body in which it outgrows its own self, transgressing its own body, in <lb/>which it conceives a new, second body: the bowels and the phallus.&quot; (312) According <lb/>to Bakhtin, the exaggerated exhibition of the body&apos;s &quot;convexities&quot; and &quot;orifices&quot; in <lb/>Rabelaisian oeuvre are passageways and contact zones propitious for an &quot;interchange&quot; <lb/>and an &quot;interorientation&quot; between the body and other bodies and the world: &quot;it is <lb/>within them that the confines between bodies and between the body and the world <lb/>are overcome: there is an interchange and an interorientation.&quot; (312) Bakhtin traces <lb/>the centrality of the bodies&apos; protrudences and orifices to their vicinity to vital bodily <lb/>organs and pivotal role in the &quot;bodily drama&quot; (313): &quot;Eating, drinking, defecation <lb/>and other elimination (sweating, blowing of the nose, sneezing), as well as <lb/>copulation, pregnancy, dismemberment, swallowing up by another body-all these <lb/>acts are performed on the confines of the body and the outer world, or on the <lb/>confines of the old and new body.&quot; (313) <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>5. M. Bakhtin, Rabelais and his World (Indiana University Press, 1984). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>425 <lb/></page>

			<body>Not far from Bakhtin&apos;s consecration of the grotesquely repulsive imagery the <lb/>body ranging from the lower parts to bodily secretions and excrements, Bataille <lb/>zeroes in on the dead body, the corpse left to rot. Though utterly helpless and <lb/>harmless, the dead body is associated by Bataille with an endemic sense of &quot;violence&quot; <lb/>and &quot;contagion&quot;. It stands for the materialization of the irrevocable brutality which <lb/>rounds off human existence: &quot;For each man who regards it with awe, the corpse is <lb/>the image of his own destiny. It bears witness to a violence which destroys not one <lb/>man alone but all men in the end.&quot; 6 <lb/>According to Bataille, the sight of a dead body is fundamentally perceived by <lb/>all cultures as a &quot;taboo&quot; (44) which we instinctively cringe from and hastily keep <lb/>away through the burial act. In this sense, &quot;[t]he corpse will rot; this biological <lb/>disorder, like the newly dead body a symbol of destiny, is threatening in itself. We <lb/>no longer believe in contagious magic, but which of us could be sure of not quailing <lb/>at the sight of a dead body crawling with maggots?&quot; (46) In his study, Bataille notes <lb/>how some primitive burial rites performed by &quot;ancient peoples&quot; which consist of <lb/>blenching the dead body&apos;s bones by way of &quot;pacification of [the dead person&apos;s] <lb/>spirit&quot;, and, in the second place, to ward off death&apos;s danger. (46) <lb/>A further philosopher we may refer to within the scope of the thinkers who <lb/>broached the concept of the body is perhaps the closest to J. L. Nancy&apos;s thought and <lb/>theory of &quot;corpus&quot;: the French philosopher Maurice Merleau-Ponty. From the <lb/>perspective of a fervent advocate of phenomenology, Merleau-Ponty laments the <lb/>&quot;obsession&quot; with the intellect or &quot;being&quot; as an abstract, objectified, synthesized <lb/>notion imposed by Rationalism. Such &quot;obsession&quot;, according to him, falls short of <lb/>the intrinsic &quot;perspectivism of my experience&quot; (73) since it subordinates what <lb/>is/should be my primary medium to discern the world surrounding us, notably the <lb/>&quot;gaze&quot;. According to Merleau-Ponty, my corporeal, perceptual experience is to be <lb/>the terminus a quo, the inception of my apprehension of the world and of my own <lb/>self: &quot;I consider my body, which is my point of view upon the world, as one of the <lb/>objects of that world. I repress the consciousness that I had of my gaze as a means <lb/>of knowing and I treat my eyes as fragments of matter.&quot; (73) Merleau-Ponty points <lb/>out how &quot;the objective thought of common sense and science&quot; strips us from the <lb/>&quot;perceptual experience&quot; which constitutes the core of our perception of and <lb/>continuation with the world and ourselves. (74) From an exclusively rationalistic <lb/>approach to my physical being, Merleau-Ponty sustains, &quot;I no longer pay attention <lb/>to my body, to time, or to the world such as I live them in pre-predicative <lb/>knowledge, that is, in the inner communication that I have with them. I only speak <lb/>of my body as an idea, of the universe as an idea, and of the idea of space and of <lb/>time.&quot; (74) Such reification of the body, time and the world coops up formidable <lb/>repercussions on the subject in his/her experience of subjectivity and engaging with <lb/>world, causing human consciousness to be numbed, deadened: &quot;The whole life of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>6. G. Bataille, Death and Sensuality: A Study of Eroticism and the Taboo (Walker and Company, <lb/>1962), 44. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Boughnim: Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body… <lb/></note>

			<page>426 <lb/></page>

			<body>consciousness tends to posit objects… it takes itself up and gathers itself together <lb/>in an identifiable object. And yet the absolute positing of a single object is the death <lb/>of consciousness, since it congeals all of experience, as a seed crystal introduced <lb/>into a solution causes it suddenly to crystallize.&quot; (74) <lb/>Nancy&apos;s Corpus (2008) <lb/>Like Merleau-Ponty, the contemporary French philosopher Jean Luc Nancy <lb/>belongs to the phenomenological tradition. His conception of the body and the <lb/>writing poetics of the body, which he extensively expounds in his book-essay Corpus <lb/>remain largely overlooked in comparison to the thoughts of his contemporary <lb/>compatriot Merleau-Ponty, for instance. The present essay proposes to closely <lb/>examine Nancy&apos;s conception of the body, and the writing poetics Nancy recommends <lb/>when broaching the concept of the body. <lb/>Ever since the body has been subjected to thought, Nancy points out in the <lb/>opening sections of Corpus, it laid open to the slash inflicted by the sword of sense, <lb/>the intent attempts of theologians, philosophers, writers at reducing it to a sign, an <lb/>&quot;organon&quot; (of sense). In reality, Nancy argues, the body &quot;sets trap for the sign&quot;; &quot;it <lb/>never stops signifying.&quot; Nancy asks whether we can survive a new approach to the <lb/>body, our bodies, which would be sense-free, or would it better for us to keep to <lb/>our reductive, the construct-loaded conceptions of our bodies and run even the risk <lb/>the undergo a haemorrhagic of meaning; the latter may be more salutary than the loss <lb/>of sense as meaning. Using a gripping metaphoric blood imagery Nancy argues: <lb/></body>

			<body>Sense escapes from the wound, drop by drop, frightfully, derisively-perhaps even <lb/>serenely, if not joyfully? This question is prompted by a bloodless dawn rising on a <lb/>world of bodies. Can we deal with a loss of sense, and have a sense of that loss-but <lb/>without concession or deceit concerning the loss itself? Can we reach what has already <lb/>been extended and opened by this loss? Namely, the world of bodies, as the gaping <lb/>end of the organon of sense delivers it, or lets it come? (emphasis added, 81) <lb/>Nancy hails the advent of a &quot;bloodless dawn&quot; which will inaugurate a new <lb/>phase in the philosophical treatment of the (written) body: a phase exempt from <lb/>too stifling and reductive meaning constructs and characterized by a broadening <lb/>of corporeal horizons through a redistribution of sense as &quot;ectopias&quot;. (25) In Corpus, <lb/>from the outset, Nancy sustains that this loss of sense, &quot;or losing this body-of-<lb/>sense&quot; would lead us, as we shall see, to a restoration of our time and &quot;space&quot;, <lb/>&quot;properly&quot; (81). Surprisingly, according to Nancy, this loss of sense would legitimate <lb/>&quot;anguish&quot;: &quot;it&apos;s its melancholic incorporation&quot;/ &quot;hysterical incarnation&quot;, but not <lb/>&quot;suffering&quot; (81). For Nancy, &quot;suffering isn&apos;t&quot;, shouldn&apos;t be, &quot;given a sense&quot;: &quot;We <lb/>suffer because organized for sense, and the loss of it wounds us, cuts us.&quot; As a <lb/>matter of fact, instead of suffering and its attendant meaningful constructs there <lb/>should lie an open &quot;wound&quot;, a &quot;space&quot; where the subject is ready to face his <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>427 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;areality&quot; and the world: &quot;Here, at the point of suffering, is only an open &quot;subject,&quot; <lb/>cut, anatomized, deconstructed, disassembled, deconcentrated. The dawn of a <lb/>spacing, clarity itself, the risk and chance for areality as what we&apos;re exposed to, and <lb/>what exposes us, as we-as a we-world.&quot; (Nancy&apos;s italics, 81) <lb/>Nancy is confounded when realizing that the increasingly crowded, swarming <lb/>world&apos;s population have never come to be truly tangent: &quot;More than…generic being.&quot; <lb/>We have been obsessed by, consumed with, our desire to consecrate difference, our <lb/>differences whether they be gender, racial, purely physical which keep us from <lb/>touching upon the generic, essential bond which grounds us as human beings and <lb/>at the same time reinforces our awareness of every distinct vibrant fiber of every <lb/>sensing body: &quot;More than five billion human bodies. Soon to be eight billion. Not <lb/>to mention other bodies. Humanity becomes tangible: but what we can touch isn&apos;t <lb/>&quot;mankind,&quot; it&apos;s precisely not this generic being… We talk about its nongeneric <lb/>nature, its nongenerality.&quot; Specific senses, culturally-loaded constructs have kept <lb/>humans from meeting in a juste-milieu, reach a space of a &quot;juste-clarté&quot;, their &quot;a-<lb/>reality&quot; where they can truly touch (each other). Nancy asks: <lb/>What is the space opened between eight billion bodies, and, within each one, between <lb/>phallus and cephale, among the thousand folds, postures, falls, leaps and bounds of <lb/>each? In what space do they touch each other and stray from each other, with none of <lb/>them, or their totality, being absorbed into a pure and empty sign of the self, into a <lb/>body of-sense? Sixteen billion eyes, eighty billion fingers: seeing what? Touching <lb/>what? And if it&apos;s only to exist and be these bodies, and to see, touch and sense the <lb/>bodies of this world, what might we invent to celebrate their number? Can we even <lb/>think about it, we whom the wound fatigues… (83) <lb/>Writing the Body: &quot;A Writing that is Not to Be Read&quot; <lb/>Writing the body, according to Nancy, implies, treating it as &quot;the anatomical <lb/>sign of &quot;self&quot; which doesn&apos;t signify, but cuts, separates, exposes.&quot; (85) Nancy&apos;s written <lb/>corpus would not be meant to signify, but to reinforce &quot;the dialogue of dialogue&quot;, not <lb/>even abide by &quot;the contract of sense.&quot; (85) On the contrary, it absolves, as much as <lb/>it can, since we are intrinsically programmed for sense, and imposes its own <lb/>caesura of sense by following its own flow of inspiration. It veers towards countless <lb/>&quot;swerves&quot; of deconstructed configurations, extrapolations and infinite stretchability of <lb/>the sign. In this sense, Nancy hails a forthcoming, promising aesthetic &quot;gliding&quot; which <lb/>operates as follows: <lb/>This isn&apos;t the philosophico-medical anatomy of dissection, a dialectician&apos;s dismembering <lb/>of organs and functions. An anatomy more of numbering than dismembering. An <lb/>anatomy of configurations, of the plasticity of what we&apos;d have to call states of body, <lb/>ways of being, bearing, breathings, paces, staggerings, sufferings, pleasures, coats, <lb/>windings, brushings, masses. Bodies, to begin with, are masses, masses offered with <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Boughnim: Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body… <lb/></note>

			<page>428 <lb/></page>

			<body>nothing to be articulated about them, nothing to link them to, whether a discourse or <lb/>a story: palms, cheeks, wombs, buttocks. Even an eye is a mass, as are tongue and ear-<lb/>lobe. (85) <lb/>Nancy remarkably catches the fundamentally disjoint nature of the body&apos;s <lb/>reality through his jerky, almost spasmodic language loosely knitted with mere <lb/>juxtaposition. Similarly, Nancy conceives of each organ of the body, separately, but <lb/>more importantly, as a &quot;black hole&quot; (84) in its own right, a self-sufficient galaxy <lb/>which both secretes and sucks the meaning it produces and keeps expanding in the <lb/>shape of an infinitely malleable of mass, a sort of density without core. In other <lb/>words, Nancy regards the slightest anatomical part of the body as a &quot;mass,&quot; not as <lb/>Freud or Tardes make use of the term in their notion of &quot;mass phenomena&quot; based <lb/>on the idea of &quot;concentration&quot;, which, according to Nancy, even disadvantages the <lb/>body by omitting its proper space. According to him, bodies are to be treated as <lb/>&quot;sites of density&quot;, not &quot;concentration of meaning&quot;, but a sort of gravitational space, <lb/>delineated but continuously expanding in its own periphery: <lb/>They have no center, no black hole. They are right at the surface of the skin-right at the <lb/>surface of the hand that can grasp them. It&apos;s a massed space, a spacious mass, extension <lb/>exposed like a grain, like a weight, like a swelling, like a limited arrangement, a local <lb/>color where the partes extra partes make their areality more dense, but without falling <lb/>into partes intra partes. (Nancy&apos;s emphasis, 84) <lb/>Some pages later, Nancy explains that the true &quot;techné of bodies&quot; is not to be <lb/>conceived as a modally singular form of reproduction, the religious model of thought, <lb/>according to which (divine) &quot;&apos;Creation&apos; is the techne of bodies.&quot; (84) Nancy refutes the <lb/>Christian version of Creation which he regards as lame, inefficient in accounting for <lb/>the real weal of the bodies&apos; reality. By conceiving of all the bodies as descendants <lb/>from one, unique self-begotten body, that of Christ: &quot;Not bodies produced by the <lb/>autoproduction of the spirit and its reproduction-which, at any rate, can produce <lb/>only a single body, a single visible image of the invisible (hence the fact that the <lb/>body of woman is regarded by Aristotle as poorly engendered and defective, or <lb/>marked, according to Christians, with an impure wound).&quot; (87-88) Nancy evokes <lb/>Elaine Scarry&apos;s book The Body in Pain in which Elain sustains that when &quot;the world, <lb/>the self, the voice are lost in the intensity of the suffering of torture,&quot; what ensues <lb/>is &quot;the dissolution of the world, the uncreation of the created world.&quot; (Elain quoted <lb/>in Nancy, 89) In this sense, Nancy argues that the notion of &quot;Creation&quot; is to be <lb/>thought as creation of bodies, primarily, a &quot;world of bodies&quot; governed by the <lb/>&quot;technical&quot; reproduction, proliferation of bodies. Nancy calls for a new thinking of <lb/>Creation, of the creation of the bodies, which consecrates a whole &quot;echotechnical&quot; <lb/>(89) system that binds the world of bodies to the world (of sense). According to this <lb/>system of thought, &quot;…[The] body [is] given as multiplied, multi-sexed, multi-<lb/>figured, multi-zoned, phallic and aphallic, cephalic and acephalic, organized, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>429 <lb/></page>

			<body>inorganic. Bodies thus created, which is to say, coming, and whose coming spaces <lb/>the here, the there, every time&quot;. (91) <lb/>Bathing in this &quot;echotechnical&quot; envisioning of the bodies&apos; interactional connections <lb/>with the world, in its larger sense, beyond the demographic world of bodies, the <lb/>world which bids manifold ways of cerebral and affective engagements with both <lb/>the body and the community, the body becomes, itself, thus, a cosmic miniature of <lb/>this multi-layered, functionally zoned connection. In other words, a body is not to <lb/>be classified, reduced to its gender, race or else. It ceaselessly creates its space, an <lb/>open site for the interplay, the displacement of functions and fixed associations: <lb/>&quot;… a body given as multiplied…every time.&quot; (89) Nancy makes it clear that such <lb/>interplay between the body and the world&apos;s bodies is neither dialectic, nor <lb/>immanent, nor transcendental; it simply occurs, openly, extendedly, in the Other&apos;s <lb/>vicinity without prior or subsequently intended end of containment. From this <lb/>perspective, Nancy proclaims: &quot;The Judeo-Christian-Islamic &quot;neighbor&quot; resided in <lb/>the particular and the universal, in the dialecticization of the two, which doesn&apos;t <lb/>fail to end up in the universal. But here the neighbor would be what comes, what <lb/>takes place in an approach, and what also touches and diverges, thus localizing, <lb/>displacing, the touch.&quot; (89) <lb/>A compellingly imaginative &quot;paradigm&quot; which Nancy makes use of to illustrate <lb/>how we should conceive, think and write the body according to the echotechnical, <lb/>gravitational law of Creation, evoked above, is the woman&apos;s breast (85). The latter <lb/>is to be intimated as a site of &quot;ectopic&quot;, fractal associations, orbed mass/density of <lb/>extrapolations, gushing from a &quot;space&quot;, an &quot;emotion&quot; (motherhood, sexual arousal <lb/>etc.). Nancy declares: <lb/>

			Its paradigm is probably the woman&apos;s breast, a mass that localizes many an ectopia. <lb/>Nourishment, separate object, visibility of sex, independent movement, erection, <lb/>overflowing, doubling, the obverse of a vigorous breastplate, the bearing of a curve, <lb/>bearing fruit: the b(e)aring of breasts exemplifies every birth as an essential modalizing of <lb/>areality-and also lets us see how this modalizing can, in every sense, be called an <lb/>emotion. This privilege of dense and zoned areality is named, and spaced, as areola. (88) <lb/>An &quot;areola&quot;, would best embody best the &quot;areality&quot; of the body and the way <lb/>we should conceive of, write about it in a &quot;corpus&quot; without its subsumption into <lb/>an &quot;inscriptive surface&quot; or a &quot;recording of signification&quot; (85). As a matter of fact, <lb/>Nancy&apos;s allegory of the woman&apos;s breast, notably the areola, compellingly summons <lb/>the meaning(s) attached to the body as a compactly complex set of (cognitive, affective, <lb/>philosophical, religious etc.) associations which would pop up like rounded rhizomes <lb/>of meaning(s) strung together into a hoop, the areola&apos;s. Nancy adds, &quot;[i]n this <lb/>anatomy of masses… [n]o &quot;written body&quot;, no writing at the body; and nothing <lb/>whatsoever of a somatography. …That we write, no doubt is the body, but <lb/>absolutely not where we write, nor is a body what we write but a body is always <lb/>what writing excribes.&quot; (Nancy&apos;s emphasis, 87) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Boughnim: Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body… <lb/></note>

			<page>430 <lb/></page>

			<body>But what is it that Nancy&apos;s corpus excribes about/in the body and how? <lb/>Nancy has already provided us, already, with an allegorical intimation of the <lb/>&quot;what,&quot; the kind of substance cooped up in the proper writing on/of the body <lb/>through the paradigm of the woman&apos;s breast as an &quot;aureola&quot; of sundry, associative <lb/>projections revolving around the nipple-centre, a miscellany of zoned spaces or <lb/>emotions. The question that remains is how this writing against writing, writing <lb/>against inscription, subsumption into any fixed category of meaning, &quot;excription,&quot; <lb/>is to be undertaken? <lb/>Nancy sustains that what is &quot;excribed&quot; resides at, hinges on the &quot;edge&quot; of <lb/>&quot;inscription&quot;, a sort of incipient, inchoate signification conceived on the verge of a <lb/>prior inscription/meaning; &quot;In all writing …body is.&quot; (87) Writing the body as <lb/>&quot;corpus&quot; and reading it would pertain to a new &quot;letricity&quot;, that of &quot;tact&quot;, a &quot;letricity&quot; <lb/>of touch, tracking down sensory palpability, a &quot;letricity&quot; of spaced tangibility <lb/>involving limit, space and contact, each body is touched in a zoned, fractal manner. <lb/>Meaning turns, thus, into body and not the other way round. The body is no longer <lb/>expressed in meaningfully reducible constructs. In one word, as Nancy sums it up, <lb/>&quot;sense senses itself sensing.&quot; (83) <lb/>Body and thought and the Need for Corpus <lb/>For Nancy body and thought are necessarily contiguous or at least bound to <lb/>an inevitable vicinity. They mutually summon each other without, for all that, <lb/>merging into each other. &quot;…[T]hey are only their touching each other, the touch of <lb/>their breaking down, and, into each other. This touching is the limit and spacing of <lb/>existence.&quot; (Nancy&apos;s emphasis, 37) Nancy explains that this seemingly uncanny <lb/>bound between body and thought being governed by both a frontier/ &quot;limit&quot; and <lb/>interceding, intermediary area or &quot;spacing&quot; has a &quot;name&quot; which he coins in a <lb/>quadruply compound term: &quot;body-thought-joy-pain/sorrow.&quot; (37) The tangency <lb/>between body and thought is the spacing margin of existence, a sort of backdrop <lb/>against which the unanimously common &quot;combination&quot; &quot;body-thought-joy-pain/ <lb/>sorrow&quot; is played out. Nancy even assigns a name for this phenomenon: &quot;sex&quot;, <lb/>which he argues &quot;doesn&apos;t name anything that would be exposed: it names the <lb/>process of touching upon exposition itself.&quot; (37) Nancy sustains that sex &quot;touches <lb/>upon the untouchable&quot; in its relation to the body. He insists that sex cease to be a <lb/>mere denominator, a sheer gender indicator, a sort of &quot;… the body&apos;s flash-name&quot;, <lb/>assigning meaning to add a further layer to the separation between bodies, &quot;a <lb/>supplementary aesthesia.&quot; (37) Instead, Nancy exhorts that sex be broached anew <lb/>as the space or the playground for the integrative, &quot;body-thought-joy-pain/ <lb/>sorrow&quot; drama of our lives is played out and in which body and thought concurrently <lb/>take part like two actors who would unknowingly pass each other while performing <lb/>their respective roles. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>431 <lb/></page>

			<body>Nancy sustains that we, our bodies, are desperately in need of a &quot;corpus&quot;: a <lb/>body of writing that would not be &quot;a narrative&quot;. Nor would it be explicated or <lb/>theorized 7 into reducible constructs and meaning-tied terms. This &quot;corpus&quot; would <lb/>take the form of a &quot;promise&quot;, a silently promulgated &quot;promise&quot;. (51) Articulated as <lb/>such, it is not subject to theory, recitation or even fictional writing as a technical <lb/>element like a character or setting. It is &quot;… a kind of promise to keep silent.&quot; (51) <lb/>This does not mean to mute the body but to extort meaning from it, to emancipate <lb/>it from the oppressive shackles of signification, and ultimately to supplant sense by <lb/>sense/the sensory. As a matter of fact, Nancy&apos;s corpus is &quot;[s]ilent less &quot;about&quot; the <lb/>body than from the body, subtracting it materially from its signifying imprints: and <lb/>doing so here, on the read and written page. (Nancy&apos;s emphasis, 51) <lb/>Nancy argues that the acts of both writing and reading imply a touching, a <lb/>body&apos;s touching of the page, of the hand holding a book (51), and one may may <lb/>add of the fingers pressing the keyboard&apos;s keys. No matter how infinite the circuit <lb/>of transmission, the &quot;deferral&quot; or the dispersal of this touching with the book <lb/>handed down from hand to hand, photocopied, disseminated, there remains, Nancy <lb/>argues, &quot;…[an] infinitesimal dust of contact… In the end here and now, your own <lb/>gaze touches the same traces of characters as mine, and you read me, and I write <lb/>you.&quot; (51) This act of touching cannot take place unless what is written or read <lb/>articulates a &quot;silent promise&quot; about, from the body, as has been suggested by Nancy <lb/>from the start. He assimilates the &quot;corpus&quot; he extolls to a new technique which <lb/>would not be meant to improve, accelerate diffusion of information or the literary <lb/>text through xeroxing or fax. On the contrary, his corpus&apos; technique operates in a <lb/>&quot;discrete&quot; and &quot;potent&quot; manner to disseminate touch. (52) Using a pun on the term <lb/>flash to ironize the relation of writing, as corpus, to technology, he argues that it <lb/>does not immediately disseminate, as a flash disc would do, but rather holds in a <lb/>halt with the touching power of imminence, that of a &quot;silent promise&quot;: &quot;Like a silent <lb/>flash, a momentary suspension of the circuits, the touch of a promise…&quot; (53) <lb/>The model of &quot;corpus,&quot; as Nancy conceives of, is at the image of the Roman <lb/>&quot;Corpus Juris,&quot; (53) which means it has the form of a &quot;compilation,&quot; &quot;a catalogue.&quot; 1 <lb/>It is a body of law overarchingly personalised; &quot;it is neither chaos nor organism: it <lb/>doesn&apos;t fall between the two, but lies somewhere else.&quot; (53) Though it is a juridical <lb/>corpus it is neither absolute nor transcendental, nor synthetic. (53) It is a law which <lb/>institutes the space of each body. Space is, in fact, juridical, in that it installs &quot;the <lb/>space of the law&quot;. The latter would be the space/distance incumbent upon, relevant <lb/>to each body according to its &quot;case&quot;: &quot;The body and the case fit each other. There <lb/>is a jurisdiction proper to each body: &quot;hoc est enim&quot;…&quot; (53) Accordingly, Nancy&apos;s <lb/>corpus is neither pure categorization, nor abysmal chaos: &quot;It&apos;s prose from a <lb/>different space, the law of the law being unlawful.&quot; (53) It is, we may infer, a kind <lb/>of prose which consecrates the idiosyncratic, the specific, the exceptional and <lb/>encourages contagion, trespassing and experience: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>7. &quot;… not subject to a treatise.&quot; (51) <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Boughnim: Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body… <lb/></note>

			<page>432 <lb/></page>

			<body>The corpus obeys a law that passes from case to case, a discrete continuity of rules and <lb/>exceptions, of demands and derogations. Jurisdiction consists less in enunciating the <lb/>absolute of the Law, or in unfolding its reasons, than in saying what the law can be <lb/>here, there, now, in this case, in this place. Hoc est enim ...: its diction is local, spaced, <lb/>horizontal, a diction less of the law&apos;s being than of its practice, competence, and <lb/>capacity in this case. But the case has no essence or transcendental synthesis: there are <lb/>only successive apprehensions, accidental contours, modifications. Here, in an <lb/>essential, all-embracing and exclusive way, ontology is modal-or modifiable, or <lb/>modifying. And the writing of this is a corpus. (Nancy&apos;s emphasis, 52) <lb/>

			As has been clarified, for J. L. Nancy, there is no such thing as a comprehensive, <lb/>all-including writing of the body or corpus, but a case for case, local writing <lb/>approach. The outcome would be a highly atypical writing, a labyrinthine discourse <lb/>with diverse, varied &quot;enteries&quot;. (52) <lb/>Expeausition (Skin-Show) <lb/>Nancy conceives of the body&apos;s &quot;seity,&quot; that is its most intimate foundation, its <lb/>proper being as fundamentally elusive, &quot;on the verge of a movement&quot;, geared <lb/>towards departure; he confirms that &quot;[t]he body is self in departure.&quot; (33) He <lb/>relentlessly, in an almost cherishing manner, refers to Christ&apos;s consecrated statement <lb/>on the Last Supper evening: Hoc est nimabsentia corporis et tamen corpus ipse 8 to attest <lb/>the &quot;singularity,&quot; &quot;the spacing,&quot; the &quot;extremity&quot; delineating every part of the body, <lb/>its movements and its very being as fated to a swirling &quot;swerve.&quot; Such notion of <lb/>&quot;swerve&quot; is essential to Nancy&apos;s definition of the body in relation to itself and to <lb/>the other. Its intimacy &quot;exposes&quot;, not a self-contained &quot;seity&quot; but following this <lb/>&quot;swerve&quot;, the trajectory of a positively fragmented, compartmented seity an &quot;a-<lb/>seity&quot; which foregrounds movement, spacing and departure (back again to the self <lb/>or the other). Thus, Nancy argues: &quot;The intimacy of the body exposes pure a-seity <lb/>as the swerve and departure that it is. Aseity-the a-self), the to-itself, the by-itself of <lb/>the Subject-exists only as the swerve and departure of this a-(of this a-part-self), <lb/>which is the place, the moment proper of its presence, its authenticity, its sense. The <lb/>a-part-self as departure, is what&apos;s exposed.&quot; (33) <lb/>Nancy deconstructs the godly attribute of &quot;aseity&quot; which he confers upon the <lb/>body by typographically distancing the &quot;a&quot; from seity in attempt to allude to its <lb/>antagonistic meaning as a prefix which would suggest a twofold meaning, a sort <lb/>of double bind which is intrinsic to the body being both self-sufficient, self-<lb/>contained and whole, on the one hand, and wide-ranging, motile and transferrable, <lb/>on the other. Nancy insists that &quot;exposition&quot;, as he construes it, is not a sort of &quot;a <lb/>translation&quot;, a &quot;putting on view&quot; or &quot;staging&quot; of the body&apos;s intimacy or an attempt <lb/>to extirpate this intimacy from &quot;withdrawal&quot; which is one of its fundamental <lb/></body>
	  
		<listBibl> 8. Nancy&apos;s emphasis (33). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>433 <lb/></page>

			<body>properties. Expression as &quot;expeausition&quot; should enact the body&apos;s very truth, the <lb/>&quot;a-part-self&quot; truth, &quot;partes extra partes&quot;, leaving room for spacing, &quot;a lone gulf in the <lb/>spacing the [the body] himself is&quot; (33) as withdrawal. As a matter of fact, &quot;Expostion&quot; <lb/>as expeausition&quot; or &quot;excription&quot; should enact the very being of intimacy, not to say <lb/>of existence itself which is the perennial withdrawal of the self into the self, its <lb/>revelation as undisclosable. 9 To recapitulate, the &quot;exposition&quot; of intimacy as the <lb/>understanding of the body&apos;s innermost truth would lead to fathoming the inmost <lb/>meaning of existence itself, of being. This is possible only on the condition that <lb/>exposition of the body be broached as self-reflexity, a merging of the subject&apos;s being <lb/>and the body according to which the &quot;essence&quot; of its being is &quot;self-positing&quot;; the <lb/>body &quot;is the being exposed of the being&quot; in and of itself. In this sense, Nancy evokes <lb/>the notion of &quot;the aesthetic body&quot; (Nancy&apos;s emphasis, 35). <lb/>The body as construed by Nancy is a congregate of senses, a piling up, a <lb/>separation, delineation and interpenetrable contiguity at the same time. The body <lb/>is to be intimated, according to Nancy, a site for a merging of spacing and intimacy, <lb/>an infinity of friction, brushing, tapping, penetration, interpenetration of textures, <lb/>tissues, impressions, memories, tastes, etc., a sort of sublation of &quot;phallus and <lb/>cephale&quot;: <lb/>

		One on top of the other, inside the other, right at the other, thus exposed are all those <lb/>aesthetics whose assembly-discrete, multiple, and swarming is the body. Its members-<lb/>phallus and cephale-its parts-cells, membranes, tissues, excrescences, parasites-its <lb/>teguments, its sweatings, features, colors, all its local colors (we&apos;ll never get past racism <lb/>unless we stop saying generic human brotherhood is its contrary instead of linking it to <lb/>the dis-location, affirmed and confirmed, of our races and characteristics, black, yellow, <lb/>white, thick-lipped, snub-nosed, frizzy, thick, shaggy, oily, braided, flat-nosed, coarse, <lb/>fine, prognathous, hook-nosed, creased, musky ... ). Everywhere, from bodies to bodies, <lb/>from place to place, from places where bodies are in zones and body-points, everywhere the <lb/>random disassembly of what might allow a body to be assumed. (My emphasis, 36) <lb/>Accordingly, Nancy fervently lays emphasis on the necessity to restore to each <lb/>part, each sense of the body its aesthetic singularity which has been wrongly <lb/>subsumed into generic categories or constructs, whether racial, aesthetic or other. <lb/>Only by displacing, deconstructing those generic reductive constructs, can we put <lb/>an end to that &quot;auto-anesthesia&quot; we have inflicted upon our bodies by treating <lb/>them all alike, both in themselves and with other bodies. Instead, they should be <lb/>regarded locally, case by case, sense by sense to come to realize their singularity, <lb/></body>
		  
		  <listBibl><lb/> 9. Exposition&quot; doesn&apos;t mean that intimacy is extracted from its withdrawal, and carried <lb/>outside, put on display. Because then the body would be an exposition of the &quot;self,&quot; in the <lb/>sense of a translation, an interpretation, or a staging. &quot;Exposition,&quot; on the contrary, means <lb/>that expression itself is an intimacy and a withdrawal. The a-part-self is not translated or <lb/>incarnated into exposition, it is what it is there: this vertiginous withdrawal of the self from <lb/>the self that is needed to open the infinity of that withdrawal all the way up to self. The body <lb/>is this departure of self to self. (Corpus, 33) <lb/></listBibl> 

			<note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Boughnim: Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body… <lb/></note>

			<page>434 <lb/></page>

			<body>their richness as inherent in their cohesive disassembly. What he refers to as &quot;singular <lb/>
			dis-assembly of the &quot;five senses.&quot; (37) <lb/>To better seize Nancy&apos;s claim, we need to be acquainted with his notion of <lb/>&quot;finite thinking&quot; which he advocates as the approach we should endorse when <lb/>philosophically broaching notions like the body, the world, history, religion, being <lb/>itself. &quot;Finite thinking&quot;, according to Nancy should consecrate the plurality of <lb/>&quot;sense&quot; [sens], which constitutes the absolute singularity of the notion probed: a <lb/>sense that makes sense, &quot;the sense that exists or produces existing.&quot; (5) As such, <lb/>&quot;sense&quot; senses itself while making sense of the world, existence etc. This leads to a <lb/>sort of double bind, or what Nancy refers to as &quot;chiasmus&quot; (6). The self-reflexivity <lb/>of sense is traceable, according to Nancy, to the fact that &quot;what senses in sense is <lb/>that it includes what it senses, and what produces sense in sense is the fact that it senses <lb/>itself while producing sense.&quot;(6) Elsewhere, Nancy draws upon the metaphor of <lb/>touching as he asserts that &quot;sense&quot; touches itself while touching and &quot;pertinence&quot; <lb/>is a matter of touching. 10 <lb/>Derrida&apos;s Reading of Nancy&apos;s Corpus: &quot;Self-Touching You&quot; <lb/>In his book On Touching -Jean Luc Nancy-, Derrida provides a thorough <lb/>philosophical review of the sense of touching from Plato and Aristotle to Nancy <lb/>with a particular focus on Nancy&apos;s compelling oeuvre entitled Corpus. Derrida <lb/>starts from one of the anchoring points of Nancy&apos;s thought which is the <lb/>ineluctable self-reflexity of the act of touching which is ascribable to its intrinsic <lb/>twofolded purport: literal, that is the physical, tactile act of palpating, but also <lb/>metaphorical or figural: to touch as a cerebral effort, &quot;to touch upon&quot; &quot;to tamper <lb/>with&quot;, &quot;to grope for.&quot; (268) The &quot;aporetic&quot; intertwinement between both senses <lb/>of touch, touch as one of five senses and touch (upon) as sense that is meaning <lb/>is, according to Derrida, both baffling and inexorable. He asserts: <lb/>When this non-distinction becomes troubling, one can no longer avoid eyeing this <lb/>double writing. Is it touching upon something or is it touching upon touching <lb/>itself, there where, having more or less surreptitiously drawn our attention to the <lb/>irreducible figure of touching, this writing makes us put our finger on language, <lb/>touching itself by touching us and getting to us while making us notice what is <lb/>going on with touching, to be sure in a manner that is as obscure as it is aporetic, <lb/>but above all in a touching manner to the point where all affect, all desire, all <lb/>fascination, all experience of the other seems to be involved, in an unavoidably <lb/>sensitive, or sentimental, fashion? (270) <lb/></body>
	  <listBibl>10. Corpus, 86. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>435 <lb/></page> 

			<body>Whether it is in relation to language, oneself or the other, touch, or the act <lb/>

		of touching, seems to summon more than one sense. The act of writing draws, <lb/>in fact, upon a miscellany of senses: the tactile, visual, 11 cerebral and affective ones. <lb/>This notion of touch pushed to the extreme, to the periphery, peripheral <lb/>touch, if we may venture the expression, can only be broached through what <lb/>Nancy identifies as &quot;finite thinking.&quot; The latter is a mode of thinking which, at <lb/>the image of touching, touches upon its own limit, acknowledges its own <lb/>finiteness and specificity, which leads to the experience of &quot;excription&quot; (of meaning). <lb/>Nancy, thus, defines &quot;finite thinking,&quot; which Derrida evokes, as a &quot;… a thinking that, <lb/>without renouncing truth or universality, without renouncing sense, is only ever <lb/>able to think at the extent that it also touches on its own limit and its own <lb/>singularity.&quot; (Nancy quoted in Derrida, 272) &quot;Touching&quot;, acknowledging its own <lb/>limit does not, for all that, mean the disavowal of notions like &quot;universality&quot; or <lb/>&quot;truth&quot; or even &quot;sense&quot;, Derrida clarifies (272). &quot;Finite thinking&quot;, Derrida adds, <lb/>operates as a sort of &quot;confession&quot;, a &quot;reminder&quot; of the so-far overlooked, in the <lb/>history of (philosophical) thinking, of the &quot;privilege of touch&quot; in foregrounding <lb/>periphery, singularity and contingency. It is a &quot;privilege&quot; which has been snubbed <lb/>by philosophers like Plato and Descartes whose philosophical theories adamantly <lb/>consecrated the (in)visible, the eidetic at the detriment of the tactual. Derrida evokes <lb/>&quot;… this battle between the haptical and the optical, and in the places where the value <lb/>of the visible (eidos, revelation, unveiling, intuition, and so forth) …&quot; (272) <lb/>The Heart and the Will to Touch <lb/>Derrida points out that in Nancy&apos;s thought, the &quot;heart&quot; is indissociable <lb/>from the act of touch: &quot;… it [&quot;finite thinking&quot;] acknowledges this certainly that <lb/>touching, in any case, touches the heart and on the heart, but inasmuch as it is <lb/>always the heart of the other.&quot; (Nancy&apos;s emphasis, 273) We note in Nancy&apos;s <lb/>statement about the &quot;heart&quot; its intrinsic bind with the notion of alterity, so dear to <lb/>phenomenological thought, or what Derrida refers to, elsewhere, as &quot;absolute <lb/>nonabsoluteness&quot;. 12 There is no self-appropriation of one&apos;s heart without mutual <lb/>&quot;originary exappropriation,&quot; a willing for interchange with the heart of the other, <lb/>and that would be &quot;love&quot; which is, according to Derrida, a manifestation of self-<lb/>touching (273). 13 Referring ourselves to Nancy&apos;s envisioning of the act of touch, <lb/></body>
		  
	  <note place="footnote">11. Derrida&apos;s use of &quot;eyeing&quot; is not inadvertent; it has sublating intentions as touch is <lb/>also visual. It reminds us of the French expression &quot;déshabiller du regard&quot; which we may <lb/>translate as &apos;strip someone naked through the gaze&apos;. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>12. Derrida, Points, 163. <lb/>13. Derrida evokes a delicate episode in Nancy&apos;s own life course which is his heart <lb/>transplant which he relates in his book L&apos;Intrus and which would deeply impact his <lb/>conception of himself and the other. (257) <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Boughnim: Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body… <lb/></note>

			<page>436 <lb/></page> 

			<body>one may ask: Is there a &quot;limit of touch&quot; of and upon the &quot;heart,&quot; one&apos;s own and the <lb/>other&apos;s, touch as &quot;self-touching&quot;? The answer, as Derrida points out, is simply no. <lb/>Derrida sustains that for Nancy, the self-reflexivity endemic to the act of <lb/>touch, merging it with &quot;self-touching&quot; itself enacts, stages the essence of sense <lb/>in general, as conceived by Nancy&apos;s phenomenological thought, and referred to <lb/>above: &quot;sense sensing itself&quot;. It transpires that the sense of touch is the sense of <lb/>all senses since it &quot;… is the being of every sense in general, the being sense, the <lb/>condition of possibility of sensibility in general, the very form of space and time, <lb/>and so forth.&quot; (247) Such self-reflexive property of (the sense of) touch does not, <lb/>however, undermine personal will and alterity, or even the Other. On the <lb/>contrary, Derrida explicates, touch as self-touching &quot;vicariously&quot; summons the <lb/>Other by foregrounding the sense of empathy and congenial connectedness <lb/>even though via a &quot;masturbatory&quot; or by proxy experience: &quot;… a vicarious <lb/>surplus of masturbatory pleasure does in no way reduce the alterity of the other <lb/>who comes to inhabit the self-touching, or at least to haunt it, at least as much <lb/>as it spectralizes any experience of &quot;touching the other&quot; (My emphasis, 274). In <lb/>order for this experience of &quot;self-touching&quot; to subsume, &apos;incorporate&apos; the Other, <lb/>so to speak, an &quot;affect&quot; is called upon: &quot;desire&quot;. (274) Desire for Derrida, is <lb/>nothing more than the &quot;the passive activity of the will&quot; (Derrida&apos;s emphasis, 274) <lb/>Derrida draws a parallelism between &quot;desire,&quot; &quot;the ontological&quot; and &quot;the <lb/>transcendental&quot;: all three strike up their own condition of possibility as soon as <lb/>they come into contact , touch upon their own quintessence, which is found in <lb/>the will, or to be more precise, &quot;the will to touch.&quot; Derrida makes it clear that <lb/>&quot;[l]ike the ontological and the transcendental, the will affects itself with its other <lb/>from the first contact, as soon as it touches or one touches on touch, as soon as <lb/>one wants touch, wants to touch it, itself [dès qu&apos;on veut le toucher, lui-même]&quot; <lb/>(Derrida&apos;s emphasis, 274) <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Accordingly, starting from Christ&apos;s overarching statement during the Last <lb/>Supper, &quot;Hoc est enim&quot;, in which he respectively assimilates his flesh and blood <lb/>with bread and wine, J. L. Nancy seizes upon the sensually rich, allegorical <lb/>dimension of Christ&apos;s words to elaborate a new poetics of writing the body. He <lb/>proposes a multi-layered, both tactful and tactual writing which rather than <lb/>seeking to inscribe the body, contents itself with touching it, touching upon its <lb/>endless semantic and experiential associations. Nancy recourses to the allegorical <lb/>paradigm of the woman&apos;s breast, notably the areola to suggest a new cosmos of <lb/>meaning(s) ascribed to the (written) body, a gravitational order of senses <lb/>operating around the body and each part of it. According to this new register of <lb/>the body which he dubs &quot;Corpus,&quot; each organ lends itself to a miscellany of <lb/>corporeal dimensions partaking of the experience of touch(ing). Nancy evokes <lb/>a &quot;system,&quot; what we may refer to as a sort of double bind inherent in touch <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>

			<page>437 <lb/></page> 

			<body>and/or the will to touch, which is the irrepressible desire to reach out for oneself <lb/>or the other without the least intention for (self)-appropriation. It is rather a <lb/>kind of open solicitation for merging boundaries, the periphery of both skin and <lb/>the writing printed on paper. To touch the other and let oneself, inexorably, be <lb/>touched simultaneously, is assimilable to that fateful encounter between the <lb/>writer and the reader via a writing which &quot;excribes,&quot; a writing which thaws the <lb/>stultified meaning-constructs attached to the body and acknowledges its open, <lb/>exposed penetrability, the epidermal porousness laying ready for haptical <lb/>contact and sense transfer. From this perspective, Nancy declares: <lb/>

			It is the will to touch: the wish that the hands touch, across the book, and through <lb/>the book; that its hands touch, reaching just as far as its skin, 14 its parchment; that <lb/>our hands touch always through the intermediary of skin, but touch nonetheless. To <lb/>touch oneself, to be touched right at oneself, outside oneself, without anything <lb/>being appropriated. That is writing, love and sense. (My emphasis, 93) <lb/>Despite pertaining to the mimetic tradition, the act of writing the body, <lb/>according to Nancy, is/should not be an act of appropriation, but rather an act <lb/>of (sense-) liberation. It is a writing, almost ritualistic, performed on skin, &quot;a <lb/>parchment&quot;, as evoked above, a sort of scribbling which titillates, tickles and <lb/>tingles the skin. To write (the body) inexorably implies, for Nancy, some form <lb/>of touch, both a tactical and tactful contact, the breaking of the reader-writer <lb/>frontier, whether geographical, ideological or historical. It is a type of touch <lb/>which consecrates the notion of limit, the &quot;intermediary&quot;, the edge, only to <lb/>trespass it, to celebrate it as the outer, violable limit of (codified/stultified) <lb/>meaning(s) and the passageway to a new experience of writing based on the <lb/>intrinsic double-bind of the act of touch. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>Bibliography <lb/>Bakhtin, M. Rabelais and his World. Translated by Helen Iswolski. Indiana University Press, <lb/>1984. <lb/>Bataille, G. Death and Sensuality: A Study of Eroticism and the Taboo. Walker and Company, 1962. <lb/>Derrida, J. Points…: Interviews, 1974-1994. Edited by E. Webber. Translated by Peggy Kamuff <lb/>and Others. US: Stanford University Press, 1995. <lb/>____. On Touching: Jean Luc Nancy. US: Stanford University Press, 2005. <lb/>Merleau-Ponty, M. Phenomenology of Perception. Translated by Donald A. Landes. Routledge, <lb/>2012. <lb/>Nancy, J. L. Corpus. Translated by R. A. Rand. US: Fordham University Press, 2008. <lb/>____. The Birth to Presence. Translated by B. Holmes and Others. US: Stanford University <lb/>Press, 1993. <lb/></listBibl>	
	  
	  <note place="footnote"><lb/>14. Note the pun Nancy uses in &quot;skin&quot; to imply both the epidermis and the book&apos;s <lb/>cover, which heightens this merging by the act of touching between writer and reader.<lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Boughnim: Bodies&apos; Touch: The Poetics of Writing and/on the Body… <lb/></note> 

			<page>438 </page> 


	</text>


  </TEI>