<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Act of Grace Payments and the Constitution</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Oscar</forename>
          <surname>Roos</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Yee-Fui</forename>
          <surname>Ng</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T07:31:04.612Z">30/01/2026 08:31:04</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.30722__slr.19653</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>The University of Sydney Library</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.30722/slr.19653</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Oscar Roos, Yee-Fui Ng. (2024). Act of Grace Payments and the Constitution. Sydney Law Review, 46(1), 55-86. DOI: 10.30722/slr.19653</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-01-02T12:25:20.679792Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2026-01-02T12:25:20.679792Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T14:57:46.427Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>started first pass</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-08T15:39:24.044Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>First pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-12T08:51:29.485Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith second pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T09:04:14.671Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-25T16:01:43.966Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T07:31:46.525Z" status="candidate" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<front>© 2024 Sydney Law Review and authors <lb/>Act of Grace Payments and the <lb/>Constitution <lb/>Oscar I Roos * and Yee-Fui Ng † <lb/>Abstract <lb/>This article focuses on a hitherto underexplored but increasingly important area <lb/>of public expenditure: act of grace payments. Act of grace payments are <lb/>voluntary, highly discretionary gifts of money made by the executive in the <lb/>absence of any legal duty to do so. The expenditure on such payments in Australia <lb/>has been significant, and a lack of transparency creates serious risks to integrity. <lb/>Further, the cases of Pape v Federal Commissioner of Taxation, Williams v <lb/>Commonwealth and Williams v Commonwealth [No 2] have transformed the <lb/>constitutional framework for public expenditure. Accordingly, this article <lb/>conducts a fine-grained analysis of the constitutional legality of act of grace <lb/>payments at the Commonwealth, state and territory levels. The authors argue that <lb/>there are significant constitutional issues with act of grace payments at the <lb/>Commonwealth level, and that many state-based act of grace payments are likely <lb/>to be illegal. To address these issues, and to reduce the risk that payments will be <lb/>made illegally, the authors recommend several legislative and soft law changes. <lb/>Please cite this article as: <lb/>Oscar I Roos and Yee-Fui Ng, &apos;Act of Grace Payments and the Constitution&apos; (2024) 46(1) <lb/>Sydney Law Review 55. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.30722/slr.19653 <lb/>This work is licensed via CC BY-ND 4.0 https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0. <lb/>Unmodified content is free to use with proper attribution. <lb/>* Senior Lecturer, Deakin Law School, Deakin University, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia; Member of <lb/>the Victorian Bar. Email: oscar.roos@deakin.edu.au; ORCID iD: <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-<lb/>8035-7605. <lb/> † Associate Professor, Faculty of Law, Monash University, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia. ORCID iD: <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2459-0634. <lb/>The authors would like to thank Callum Linehan and Ariella Gordon for their research assistance and <lb/>the Australian Institute of Administrative Law for the opportunity to present an earlier version of this <lb/>article at its 2022 National Conference. The authors would also like to thank the anonymous <lb/>reviewers and the Sydney Law Review editorial board for their helpful comments on this article. All <lb/>errors and omissions are the authors&apos; own. <lb/></front>

		<front>56 <lb/>SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></front>
	  
	  <body>I <lb/>Introduction <lb/>In the Australian federation, judicial review of both administrative and legislative <lb/>action is axiomatic and fundamental to the constitutional assumption of the rule of <lb/>law. But it is also well recognised that there are areas where judicial review cannot, <lb/>or will not, go. One of the areas where in the 20 th century the High Court went <lb/>infrequently concerned the constitutionality of executive spending. In the <lb/>Commonwealth sphere it was widely understood -as a result of the High Court&apos;s <lb/>equivocal and obscure 1975 decision in the AAP Case 1 -that an appropriation Act <lb/>enacted pursuant to ss 81 and 83 of the Constitution was effectively unchallengeable <lb/>and that it conjunctively authorised spending by the Commonwealth executive of <lb/>the appropriated moneys. 2 In the absence of any clear authority to the contrary it was <lb/>assumed that the executive&apos;s capacity to spend was either (1) constitutionally <lb/>unlimited, like that of a natural person; or (2) slightly more narrowly confined only <lb/>by the scope of the Commonwealth express legislative powers, such that the <lb/>executive could spend money within the Commonwealth&apos;s areas of legislative <lb/>competence without specific legislative authority other than a facultative <lb/>appropriation provision. 3 That generous assumption was no doubt to the executive&apos;s <lb/>liking, but in the first two decades of the 21 st century, things changed. Specifically: <lb/>• In 2009 in Pape v Federal Commissioner of Taxation the High Court rejected <lb/>the Commonwealth&apos;s submissions that s 81 gave the Commonwealth a power <lb/>to spend and that an appropriation Act was sufficient legal authority for <lb/>Commonwealth executive expenditure. 4 <lb/>• In 2012 in Williams v Commonwealth (&apos;Williams No 1&apos;) the High Court <lb/>rejected both (1) the Commonwealth&apos;s submission that the Commonwealth <lb/>executive has the capacity in common with other legal persons to spend, <lb/>unrestricted by the contours of federal legislative power; 5 and (2) the <lb/>narrower assumption common to all the parties that the Commonwealth <lb/>executive could spend appropriated moneys without specific statutory <lb/>authority, provided that the Commonwealth Parliament could so legislate. 6 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 Victoria v Commonwealth (1975) 134 CLR 338 (&apos;AAP (Australian Assistance Plan) Case&apos;). <lb/>2 See Cheryl Saunders, &apos;The Sources and Scope of Commonwealth Power to Spend&apos; (2009) 20(4) <lb/>Public Law Review 256; Cheryl Saunders, &apos;The Development of the Commonwealth Spending <lb/>Power&apos; (1978) 11(3) Melbourne University Law Review 369. <lb/>3 Shipra Chordia, Andrew Lynch and George Williams, &apos;Williams v Commonwealth: Commonwealth <lb/>Executive Power and Australian Federalism&apos; (2013) 37(1) Melbourne University Law Review 189, <lb/>190-1. <lb/>4 Pape v Federal Commissioner of Taxation (2009) 238 CLR 1, 55 [111] (French CJ), 73-5 [178]-<lb/>[183] (Gummow, Crennan and Bell JJ), 113 [320] (Hayne and Kiefel JJ), 210-11 [601]-[602] <lb/>(Heydon J) (&apos;Pape&apos;); Peta Stephenson, Nationhood, Executive Power and the Australian Constitution <lb/>(Hart Publishing, 2022) 54. <lb/>5 Williams v Commonwealth (2012) 248 CLR 156, 180 [4], 192-3 [35]-[37], 216 [83] (French CJ), <lb/>236-9 [150]-[159] (Gummow and Bell JJ), 258-9 [215]-[217], 271 [252]-[253] (Hayne J), 353 <lb/>[524] (Crennan J), 368-74 [576]-[595] (Kiefel J) (&apos;Williams No 1&apos;). <lb/>6 Ibid 179-80 [4], 187 [27], 192-3 [36]-[37], 216-17 [83] (French CJ), 232-3 [134]-[137] (Gummow <lb/>and Bell JJ), 356-8 [539]-[544] (Crennan J). See also Stephenson (n 4) 28-31. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>
	  
	  <page>57 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <body>• In 2014 in Williams v Commonwealth [No 2] (&apos;Williams No 2&apos;) the Court <lb/>rejected the Commonwealth&apos;s submission that the express incidental head of <lb/>power, s 51(xxxix) of the Constitution, generally empowered the Parliament <lb/>to legislate to authorise executive spending of appropriated moneys. 7 <lb/>These three High Court decisions have made assessing the lawfulness of spending <lb/>by the Commonwealth executive more complex. Effectively they mean that, apart <lb/>from limited exceptions, the Commonwealth executive can only spend money with <lb/>specific, enacted statutory authority (in addition to a &apos;mere appropriation&apos;), and that <lb/>this authority must be characterisable as a law made with respect to a substantive <lb/>head of Commonwealth legislative power. Furthermore, they have added to the <lb/>uncertainty about the hitherto largely unexamined spending powers of the state <lb/>executives. <lb/>Act of grace payments are voluntary, highly discretionary &apos;gifts of money&apos; 8 <lb/>made by the executive &apos;out of grace&apos; in the absence of any legal duty to do so. No <lb/>payment sets a precedent for future decisions, and each &apos;responds to a particular <lb/>case, not the generic claim&apos;. 9 They are akin to ex gratia payments, but the former are <lb/>a &apos;last resort&apos; concession to a specific person who has been unfairly disadvantaged <lb/>by some government action, 10 whereas the latter are governed by &apos;guidelines and <lb/>rules developed for a group of individuals suffering a particular class of losses&apos;. 11 <lb/>Although act of grace payments &apos;should promote equal treatment of all <lb/>members of the community and should not be used to advantage some people over <lb/>others&apos;, 12 they -and the opacity which frequently attends decisions about who gets <lb/>paid and how much -pose obvious risks for government integrity. The expenditure <lb/>on such payments in Australia has been significant, 13 and the lack of transparency <lb/>that frequently attends such payments is a serious, aggravating problem. Moreover, <lb/>payments are not necessarily confined to the impecunious and to obvious objects of <lb/>sympathy, such as the welfare recipient who, relying on erroneous government <lb/>advice, suffers a financial detriment which they can ill afford. 14 Big companies may <lb/>also apply for, and receive, large amounts of money. For example, in the Australian <lb/>Capital Territory in 2019-20, act of grace payments worth $1.033 million were made <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>7 <lb/>Williams v Commonwealth [No 2] (2014) 252 CLR 416, 469-70 [85]-[87] (French CJ, Hayne, <lb/>Kiefel, Bell and Keane JJ) (&apos;Williams No 2&apos;). <lb/>8 <lb/>Commonwealth Ombudsman, To Compensate or Not To Compensate? Own Motion Investigation of <lb/>Commonwealth Arrangements for Providing Financial Redress for Maladministration (Report, <lb/>September 1999) 74 (&apos;To Compensate&apos;). <lb/>9 <lb/>Stephen Winter, &apos;Australia&apos;s Ex Gratia Redress&apos; (2009) 13(1) Australian Indigenous Law Review 49. <lb/>10 <lb/>See Butterworths Australian Legal Dictionary (Butterworths, 1997) &apos;Act of grace payment&apos;. <lb/>11 <lb/>To Compensate (n 8) 34. See also at 45, 76, 83, 88; Commonwealth Ombudsman, Executive Schemes <lb/>(Report No 12, August 2009) 8. This distinction is not universally observed: see, eg, Treasury (NSW), <lb/>Ex Gratia Payments (Circular, NSW TC 11/02, 1 February 2011) (&apos;NSW Treasury Circular&apos;). <lb/>12 <lb/>To Compensate (n 8) 37. <lb/>13 <lb/>For example, in 2020-21 the Commonwealth government paid $16 million in act of grace payments <lb/>under s 65 of the Public Governance, Performance and Accountability Act 2013 (Cth) (&apos;PGPA Act&apos;), <lb/>and $45 million in 2019-20: Department of Finance, Decisions Made on Waivers of Commonwealth <lb/>Debts under Section 63 and Act of Grace Payments under Section 65 of the Public Governance, <lb/>Accountability and Performance Act 2013 (PGPA Act) (Report, 2021). <lb/>14 <lb/>See, eg, Pearce v Minister for Finance (2020) 352 FLR 34. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>58 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>

			<body>to Casino Canberra, as well as small-and medium-club gaming machine licensees <lb/>as part of the economic survival package from the COVID-19 health emergency. 15 <lb/>While it is now well settled that act of grace decision-making is judicially <lb/>reviewable, a lis inter partes 16 is required before judicial power can be exercised, <lb/>and it is rare for the legality of payments of government money to be challenged. <lb/>Moreover, any constitutional challenge would almost inevitably work against the <lb/>interests of a disappointed applicant for a payment, and no other persons (with the <lb/>exception of the states) are likely to have standing to bring a judicial review <lb/>application. 17 Litigants such as Bryan Pape and Robert Williams who dispute the <lb/>constitutionality of government payments that are ostensibly for their direct or <lb/>indirect benefit are rare exceptions, and both may have been denied standing to <lb/>litigate in any event, had their standing been vigorously contested. 18 Unsurprisingly, <lb/>the Commonwealth has blithely assumed it has the power to make act of grace <lb/>payments since the first decade after Federation. 19 <lb/>It is taken as given that Australian governments have a &apos;&quot;settled ethical&quot; <lb/>commitment&apos; 20 to spending public money lawfully, and Australian public service <lb/>codes of conduct echo the High Court&apos;s expectation that &apos;discretionary powers must <lb/>be exercised in accordance with any applicable law, including the Constitution <lb/>itself&apos;. 21 Although the agencies comprising the so-called integrity arm of <lb/>government -such as that of the ombudsman and the auditor-general -may be <lb/>much better placed than the judiciary and legislature in combatting any unlawful <lb/>maladministration of act of grace payment schemes, as well as promoting their good <lb/>administration, 22 the work of those agencies must be predicated on a sound <lb/>understanding of the legal parameters within which act of grace decisions are made. <lb/>The scarcity of &apos;black letter&apos; legal scrutiny of the various act of grace payment <lb/>schemes in the Australian federation therefore seems to us to be an unfortunate <lb/>deficiency, albeit a constitutionally and practically understandable one. This article <lb/>is our modest contribution to remedying it. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>15 <lb/>ACT Gambling and Racing Commission, Annual Report 2019-20 (Report, May 2019) 52-3. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">16 <lb/>Legal suit between parties. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>17 <lb/>Gabrielle Appleby and Stephen McDonald, &apos;Looking at the Executive Power through the High <lb/>Court&apos;s New Spectacles&apos; (2013) 35(2) Sydney Law Review 253, 280. <lb/>18 <lb/>Pape (n 4) 34-6 [45]-[53] (French CJ), 68-9 [150]-[159] (Gummow, Crennan, and Bell JJ), 98-9 <lb/>[399]-[402] (Hayne and Kiefel JJ), 137-8 [271]-[274] (Heydon J); Williams No 1 (n 5) 223-4 [111]-<lb/>[112] (Gummow and Bell JJ), 288-93 [315]-[331] (Heydon J). <lb/>19 <lb/>See, eg, Commonwealth, Parliamentary Debates, Senate, 29 September 1910, 3947; <lb/>Commonwealth, Parliamentary Debates, House of Representatives, 7 October 1909, 4275; <lb/>Commonwealth, Parliamentary Debates, House of Representatives, 15 September 1909, 3472; <lb/>Commonwealth, Parliamentary Debates, House of Representatives, 5 June 1908, 12197; <lb/>Commonwealth, Parliamentary Debates, Senate, 2 April 1908, 10060; Commonwealth, <lb/>Parliamentary Debates, Senate, 14 December 1907, 7496; Commonwealth, Parliamentary Debates, <lb/>House of Representatives, 27 June 1901, 1778. <lb/>20 <lb/>Will Bateman, Public Finance and Parliamentary Constitutionalism (Cambridge University Press, <lb/>2020) 231, quoting Judith N Shklar, &apos;Political Theory and the Rule of Law&apos; in Allan Hutchinson and <lb/>Patrick J Monahan (eds), The Rule of Law: Ideal or Ideology (Carswell, 1987) 1, 3. <lb/>21 <lb/>Wotton v Queensland (2012) 246 CLR 1, 9 [9] (French CJ, Gummow, Hayne, Crennan and Bell JJ). <lb/>See Public Service Act 1999 (Cth) s 13(4). <lb/>22 <lb/>W Bateman (n 20) 267-7. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>59 <lb/></page>

			<body>Because constitutionality predicates all questions of legality -whether those <lb/>questions arise during original decision-making, merits review, judicial review or <lb/>the work of integrity agencies -the article contains a fine-grained analysis of the <lb/>constitutional legality of these payments at the Commonwealth, state and territory <lb/>levels. Specifically, Part II considers the constitutional validity of the two general <lb/>Commonwealth act of grace payment schemes, the scheme under the Public <lb/>Governance, Performance and Accountability Act 2013 (Cth) (&apos;PGPA Act&apos;) (&apos;PGPA <lb/>Scheme&apos;) and the non-statutory Compensation for Detriment Caused by Defective <lb/>Administration scheme (&apos;CDDA Scheme&apos;); and Part III considers the constitutional <lb/>validity of the general schemes operating in the state and territory jurisdictions. <lb/>Finally, it should be noted that, to confine this article&apos;s length within publishable <lb/>limits, we focus exclusively on the general act of grace payment schemes operating <lb/>in the various Australian jurisdictions (in contrast to the range of subject-specific act <lb/>of grace payment schemes), 23 although many of the arguments presented could be <lb/>applied to those specialist schemes. <lb/>As our detailed analysis below shows, the Commonwealth&apos;s general statutory <lb/>act of grace provision, s 65 of the PGPA Act, is likely to be limited by the scope of <lb/>Commonwealth executive power under s 61 of the Constitution. Thus, any payments <lb/>under s 65 will need to arise in the course of (in terms of s 61) the exercise of &apos;the <lb/>executive power of the Commonwealth&apos; which &apos;extends to the execution and <lb/>maintenance of the Constitution [or] the laws of the Commonwealth&apos;. Of greater <lb/>concern, however, is our conclusion that the Commonwealth&apos;s CDDA Scheme and <lb/>several state-based act of grace payment schemes are on constitutionally shaky <lb/>ground, meaning that many act of grace payments may be illegal. To ensure <lb/>constitutionality, we argue that the Commonwealth and several states need to amend <lb/>or enact legislation to put act of grace payments on firmer legal footing. Further, all <lb/>Australian jurisdictions, including the Australian Capital Territory and the Northern <lb/>Territory, should provide soft law instruments on act of grace decision-making <lb/>which guide decision-makers on the constitutional constraints that must limit and <lb/>inform their decisions. As it felicitously turns out, these changes are relatively small <lb/>and achievable, although explaining why they need to be made requires the detailed <lb/>and comprehensive analysis which this article undertakes. <lb/>II <lb/>Two Commonwealth Act of Grace Payment Schemes <lb/>Of the two Commonwealth act of grace payment schemes, the PGPA Scheme is the <lb/>older, broader and more centralised. Its statutory ancestry can be traced back to s 25 <lb/>of the Audit Amendment Act 1979 (Cth) which inserted a new s 34A, entitled &apos;Act of <lb/>grace payments&apos;, into the (now repealed) Audit Act 1901 (Cth). 24 Section 34A -<lb/>like its successors, s 33 of the Financial Management and Accountability Act 1997 <lb/>(Cth) (&apos;FMA Act&apos;) and s 65 of the PGPA Act -reposed act of grace decision-making <lb/>power centrally in the Ministry of Finance (specifically in the Finance Minister, or <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>23 <lb/>Senate Legal and Constitutional Affairs References Committee, Parliament of Australia, Review of <lb/>Government Compensation Payments (Report, December 2010) (&apos;Review of Government <lb/>Compensation Payments&apos;). <lb/>24 <lb/>Repealed by Audit (Transitional and Miscellaneous) Amendment Act 1997 (Cth) sch 1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>60 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>persons authorised by that Minister). 25 By contrast, the CDDA Scheme was <lb/>established in 1995 as a more decentralised adjunct to the existing statutory scheme <lb/>to deal specifically with a narrower range of circumstances, namely &apos;defective <lb/>administration&apos;. 26 It authorised Commonwealth agencies to provide a financial <lb/>remedy for the effects of their own defective administration as a &apos;last resort&apos;, <lb/>hopefully inducing agencies to fix any systemic problems to avoid further <lb/>payments. 27 <lb/>Neither the PGPA Scheme nor the CDDA Scheme is &apos;designed to assist <lb/>claimants who have a viable claim for legal compensation against the <lb/>Commonwealth Government&apos;. 28 <lb/>A <lb/>PGPA Scheme <lb/>As noted, the PGPA Scheme is administered by the Finance Minister. Section 65 of <lb/>the PGPA Act provides that the &apos;Finance Minister may, on behalf of the <lb/>Commonwealth, authorise, in writing, one or more payments to be made to a person <lb/>if the Finance Minister considers it appropriate to do so because of special <lb/>circumstances&apos;, even if the payments &apos;would not otherwise be authorised by law or <lb/>required to meet a legal liability&apos;. 29 This section has been described as envisaging <lb/>&apos;an interrelationship and interaction between the circumstances, their specialness <lb/>and the appropriateness of authorising a payment. It contemplates a melange of those <lb/>considerations, rather than some neat compartmentalisation or division between <lb/>them&apos;. 30 Although the terms &apos;appropriate&apos; and &apos;special circumstances&apos; are not <lb/>defined in the PGPA Act, <lb/>[a]n object of the Act is, under s 5, to require the Commonwealth and <lb/>Commonwealth entities to meet high standards of governance, performance <lb/>and accountability, so what is generally (but not exclusively) contemplated <lb/>under s 65(1) is authorisation of payments in appropriate cases where those <lb/>standards are not met. 31 <lb/>The Minister&apos;s powers under s 65 may be delegated under s 107(1) of the PGPA Act <lb/>by written instrument to the Secretary of the Department of Finance, but the <lb/>Secretary can only authorise payments capped at $100,000 per payment. 32 <lb/>Additionally, r 24 of the Public Governance, Performance and Accountability Rules <lb/>2014 (Cth) provides that, if the Minister &apos;proposes to authorise&apos; an act of grace <lb/>payment exceeding $500,000, the Minister must establish an advisory committee to <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>25 <lb/>To Compensate (n 8) 102-3. <lb/>26 <lb/>Ibid 86. <lb/>27 <lb/>Ibid 69, 73, 81, 83, 104. <lb/>28 <lb/>Janina Boughey, Ellen Rock and Greg Weeks, Government Liability: Principles and Remedies <lb/>(LexisNexis Butterworths, 2019) 295. <lb/>29 <lb/>PGPA Act (n 13) s 65. <lb/>30 <lb/>Dobie v Minister for Finance [2022] FCA 528, [29] (Rangiah J) (&apos;Dobie&apos;). See also Toomer v Slipper <lb/>[2001] FCA 981, [28]-[32] (&apos;Toomer&apos;); Dennis v Minister for Finance [2017] FCCA 45, [46], [59], <lb/>[64]; Tomson v Minister for Finance and Deregulation (2013) 136 ALD 610, 620 [35]. <lb/>31 <lb/>Dobie (n 30) [27] (Rangiah J). <lb/>32 <lb/>Ashby v Commonwealth (2021) 386 ALR 23, 32-5 [40]-[53]; Ashby v Commonwealth (2022) 291 <lb/>FCR 585, 589-90 [15]-[17], 592-3 [31]-[39]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>61 <lb/></page>

			<body>report on the appropriateness of the authorisation and must consider the report before <lb/>making the authorisation. <lb/>There is no provision for merits review, but s 65 decision-making is amenable <lb/>to judicial review in the High Court under s 75(iii) or (v) of the Constitution, or the <lb/>Federal Court under s 39B(1) or (1A)(c) of the Judiciary Act 1903 (Cth) (&apos;Judiciary <lb/>Act&apos;). In addition, s 65 decisions can be reviewed under the Administrative Decisions <lb/>(Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) (&apos;ADJR Act&apos;), as they are made &apos;under an <lb/>enactment&apos;. 33 <lb/>B <lb/>CDDA Scheme <lb/>The CDDA Scheme hinges on the concept of defective administration and is thus <lb/>more prescriptive than the PGPA Scheme. 34 It is also more limited in its scope <lb/>because it only encompasses claims against non-corporate Commonwealth entities, <lb/>not private contractors nor Commonwealth corporations. 35 <lb/>The CDDA Scheme purports to be established pursuant to the authority of <lb/>the Commonwealth executive, 36 and seeks to provide compensation to members of <lb/>the public where there is no legal remedy but there is a moral justification to provide <lb/>&apos;purely restorative&apos; 37 compensation for &apos;detriment&apos;. Detriment comprises &apos;a <lb/>quantifiable loss as a direct consequence of defective administration&apos;, 38 and can <lb/>include financial compensation for non-financial damage. 39 However, the Scheme <lb/>is not available to offset the payment of any recoverable debt owed to the <lb/>Commonwealth, even if the debt arose from defective administration. <lb/>The CDDA Scheme &apos;is permissive, in that it permits but does not oblige the <lb/>decision-maker to approve a payment in any particular case&apos; 40 and is intended to <lb/>&apos;operate in a relatively flexible and responsive manner, lacking the rigid formality <lb/>and procedures utilised by [other] legal mechanisms&apos;. 41 It is primarily regulated in <lb/>accordance with RMG 409, a guide written by the Department of Finance which <lb/>&apos;aims to assist staff of non-corporate Commonwealth entities in managing and <lb/>determining CDDA Scheme claims&apos;. 42 RMG 409 allows individual portfolio <lb/>Ministers and their staff (as agents) 43 to make act of grace payment decisions at their <lb/>discretion for &apos;defective administration&apos;, with the proviso that the Scheme &apos;is not to <lb/>be used in relation to … claims in which it is reasonable to conclude that the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>33 <lb/>Boughey, Rock and Weeks (n 28) 309. <lb/>34 <lb/>Ibid 302-7. <lb/>35 <lb/>Department of Finance, Scheme for Compensation for Detriment Caused by Defective Administration <lb/>(Resource Management Guide 409) [13] (&apos;RMG 409&apos;). <lb/>36 <lb/>Ibid 66. <lb/>37 <lb/>Commonwealth Ombudsman, Putting Things Right: Compensating for Defective Administration: <lb/>Administration of Decision-Making under the Scheme for Compensation for Detriment Caused by <lb/>Defective Administration (Report, August 2009) 31 (&apos;Putting Things Right&apos;). <lb/>38 <lb/>To Compensate (n 8) 36. <lb/>39 <lb/>Ibid 67-8. <lb/>40 <lb/>Ibid 67. <lb/>41 <lb/>Ellen Rock, Measuring Accountability in Public Governance Regimes (Cambridge University Press, <lb/>2022) 265. <lb/>42 <lb/>RMG 409 (n 35). <lb/>43 <lb/>Ibid [2], [7]-[9]. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>62 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>Commonwealth would be found liable, if the matter were litigated&apos;. 44 RMG 409 <lb/>provides that CDDA payments may be made where a claimant suffers detriment <lb/>caused by &apos;a specific and unreasonable lapse in complying with administrative <lb/>procedures&apos;, &apos;an unreasonable failure to institute appropriate administrative <lb/>procedures&apos;, the giving of ambiguous advice, or an unreasonable failure to give <lb/>proper advice. 45 There is no obligation upon a decision-maker to approve or refuse <lb/>compensation in any given case; compensation is at the discretion of the department <lb/>or agency and &apos;the scheme is not limited by the quantum of the loss&apos;. 46 <lb/>CDDA Scheme decision-making, being non-statutory, is not subject to merits <lb/>review; nor is it made &apos;under an enactment&apos; 47 in terms of the ADJR Act and hence <lb/>subject to judicial review under that Act. 48 However, CDDA decisions are <lb/>reviewable in the High Court under s 75(iii) or (v) of the Constitution, or the Federal <lb/>Court under s 39B(1) of the Judiciary Act. Specifically, the High Court&apos;s original <lb/>jurisdiction under s 75(v) and the Federal Court&apos;s analogous jurisdiction under s <lb/>39B(1) can be invoked on the basis that the decision-maker falls within the <lb/>constitutional expression &apos;officer of the Commonwealth&apos;. 49 <lb/>C <lb/>Constitutionality <lb/>In December 2010, more than a year after the High Court published its reasons in <lb/>Pape, the Senate Legal and Constitutional Affairs References Committee tabled its <lb/>report on the Review of Government Compensation Payments. 50 The review <lb/>examined both the Commonwealth&apos;s general act of grace payment scheme under the <lb/>now superseded FMA Act (which, as mentioned, has been substantially re-enacted <lb/>as the PGPA Scheme) and the CDDA Scheme. For our purposes, what is noteworthy <lb/>about the review is the persistence of the pre-Pape orthodoxy that the <lb/>Commonwealth executive&apos;s capacity to spend was effectively unlimited by the <lb/>Constitution: the report simply asserts that &apos;[t]he power to make payments under the <lb/>CDDA Scheme arises from the Commonwealth&apos;s executive power under s 61 of the <lb/>Constitution&apos;, 51 and tacitly assumes that the relevant provisions of the FMA Act are <lb/>constitutionally valid. Perhaps such blithe constitutional optimism can be explained <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>44 <lb/>Ibid [23]. <lb/>45 <lb/>Ibid [17]. <lb/>46 <lb/>Putting Things Right (n 37) 2. <lb/>47 <lb/>Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1977 (Cth) s 3 (&apos;ADJR Act&apos;). <lb/>48 <lb/>Smith v Oakenfull (2004) 134 FCR 413. This case was, however, decided before the enactment of the <lb/>Financial Framework Legislation Amendment Act (No 3) 2012 (Cth) (&apos;FFLA Act No 3&apos;) which, it <lb/>has been claimed, places the CDDA Scheme on a statutory footing: see below in Part II(C)(2). We <lb/>dispute that claim and, if we are right, the reasoning in Smith v Oakenfull is accordingly unaffected <lb/>by the enactment of the FFLA Act No 3. However, even if we are wrong on this point, the ADJR Act <lb/>ibid still does not apply to CDDA Scheme decisions. This is because: (1) the substantive power &apos;to <lb/>make, vary or administer the arrangement or grant&apos; referred to in Financial Framework <lb/>(Supplementary Powers) Regulations 1997 (Cth) is found in s 32B of the Financial Framework <lb/>(Supplementary Powers) Act 1997 (Cth) (&apos;FF(SP) Act&apos;); (2) s 32B decisions are decisions under pt 2 <lb/>of that Act; and (3) FF(SP) Act pt 2 decisions are decisions to which the ADJR Act does not apply: <lb/>see ADJR Act ibid sch 1(he). <lb/>49 <lb/>Putting Things Right (n 37) 19. <lb/>50 <lb/>Review of Government Compensation Payments (n 23). <lb/>51 <lb/>Ibid 47 [3.33]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>63 <lb/></page>

			<body>by the limited scope of the Senate&apos;s reference to the committee, confined as it was <lb/>to &apos;[t]he administration and effectiveness of current mechanisms used by federal and <lb/>state and territory governments to provide discretionary payments in special <lb/>circumstances&apos;. 52 However, as we will see below, establishing the constitutional <lb/>validity of both the PGPA and CDDA Schemes is much more complex than the <lb/>report suggests. <lb/>1 <lb/>PGPA Scheme <lb/>(a) <lb/>Is Section 65 of the PGPA Act Characterisable as a Law with Respect to a <lb/>Commonwealth Head of Legislative Power? <lb/>At first glance it might seem that the PGPA Scheme is constitutionally secure <lb/>because it is statutory and hence avoids the strictures of Williams No 1 (that is, the <lb/>general principle that Commonwealth executive spending must be authorised by <lb/>specific statute). However, that begs the Williams No 2 question: is s 65 of the PGPA <lb/>Act characterisable as a law with respect to a Commonwealth head of legislative <lb/>power? <lb/>Because s 65 is cast in such general terms, the section can only be <lb/>characterised as a law with respect to: <lb/>• s 97 of the Constitution in combination with s 52(xxxvi); <lb/>• s 52(ii) of the Constitution which gives the Commonwealth Parliament <lb/>exclusive legislative power &apos;to make laws … with respect to … matters <lb/>relating to any department of the public service&apos;; or <lb/>• s 52(xxxix) of the Constitution which gives the Commonwealth Parliament <lb/>power to make laws with respect to &apos;matters incidental to the execution of <lb/>any power vested by this Constitution in … the Government of the <lb/>Commonwealth … or any department or officer of the Commonwealth&apos;. <lb/>The text of s 65 is not even tenuously or remotely linked to the other specific heads <lb/>of Commonwealth legislative power. <lb/>(i) <lb/>Section 97 of the Constitution in Combination with Section 51(xxxvi) <lb/>Under the heading &apos;Audit&apos;, s 97 of the Constitution provides: <lb/>Until the Parliament otherwise provides, the laws in force in any Colony <lb/>which has become or becomes a State with respect to … the expenditure of <lb/>money on account of the Government of the Colony … shall apply to … the <lb/>expenditure of money on account of the Commonwealth in the State in the <lb/>same manner as if the Commonwealth, or the Government or an officer of the <lb/>Commonwealth, were mentioned whenever the Colony, or the Government or <lb/>an officer of the Colony, is mentioned. 53 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>52 <lb/>Ibid 1 [1.1]. <lb/>53 <lb/>Constitution s 97 (emphasis added). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>64 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>Conjunctively, s 51(xxxvi) of the Constitution provides that the Commonwealth <lb/>Parliament &apos;subject to this Constitution&apos; has power to make laws with respect to <lb/>&apos;[m]atters in respect of which this Constitution makes provision until the Parliament <lb/>otherwise provides&apos;. Given that the Australian colonies engaged in the practice of <lb/>making non-statutory act of grace payments, 54 could it be argued that s 65 of the <lb/>PGPA Act can be characterised as a law with respect to s 51(xxxvi) -in other <lb/>words, that s 65 is a law made by the Commonwealth Parliament to replace the laws <lb/>which it inherited, by means of s 97 of the Constitution, from the colonies in relation <lb/>to act of grace payments? <lb/>Putting aside the powerful objection that this argument necessitates a radical <lb/>departure from the hitherto settled, vestigial understanding of s 97 -the section is <lb/>understood to encompass solely &apos;the review and audit of federal accounts&apos; 55 and its <lb/>only purpose was to ensure that &apos;until the enactment of Commonwealth legislation&apos; <lb/>(which occurred in 1901) &apos;State laws were to apply to the auditing of Commonwealth <lb/>moneys within each State&apos; 56 -we maintain that the argument is also fundamentally <lb/>inconsistent with the High Court&apos;s reasoning in Pape and the Williams cases. <lb/>Whatever non-statutory executive capacities the non-federal colonies enjoyed to <lb/>spend public moneys subject to a relevant appropriation by a colonial Parliament <lb/>(which capacities may be analogised to the unlimited power of the Crown in right of <lb/>the United Kingdom to spend in a unitary jurisdiction), the basic premise of Pape <lb/>and the Williams cases is that any such capacity was denied to the Commonwealth <lb/>executive by the entrenched and federal Constitution. Thus, the Constitution <lb/>forecloses the possibility that the Commonwealth executive inherited from the <lb/>colonies a capacity to make act of grace payments without statutory support, such <lb/>that the Commonwealth Parliament could subsequently &apos;otherwise provide&apos; for such <lb/>support in the form of s 65 of the PGPA Act using s 51(xxxvi). That the s 51(xxxvi) <lb/>head of power is &apos;subject to this Constitution&apos; only serves to reinforce this point. <lb/>(ii) <lb/>Section 52(ii) of the Constitution <lb/>Section 52(ii) of the Constitution gives the Commonwealth Parliament exclusive <lb/>legislative power &apos;to make laws … with respect to … matters relating to any <lb/>department of the public service the control of which is by this Constitution <lb/>transferred to the Executive Government of the Commonwealth&apos;. This head of power <lb/>needs to be read in conjunction with s 69 of the Constitution which provides for the <lb/>transfer of the state departments of &apos;[p]osts, telegraphs, and telephones&apos;, &apos;[n]aval and <lb/>military defence&apos;, &apos;[l]ighthouses, lightships, beacons, and buoys&apos; and &apos;[q]uarantine&apos; <lb/>to the Commonwealth. 57 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>54 <lb/>See below footnote 130 and accompanying text. <lb/>55 <lb/>John Quick and Robert Randolph Garran, The Annotated Constitution of the Australian <lb/>Commonwealth (Angus &amp; Robertson, 1901) 872. <lb/>56 <lb/>John Trone, Lumb, Moens and Trone: The Constitution of the Commonwealth of Australia Annotated <lb/>(LexisNexis, 10 th ed, 2021) 467. <lb/>57 <lb/>Re Residential Tenancies Tribunal (NSW); Ex parte Defence Housing Authority (1997) 190 CLR <lb/>410, 435-6 (Dawson, Toohey and Gaudron JJ), 424 (Brennan CJ), 449 (McHugh J), 462 (Gummow <lb/>J); Quick and Garran (n 55) 660-1, 715; Trone (n 56) 423, 517-18. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>65 <lb/></page>

			<body>Section 52(ii) is at best only a partial solution to the characterisation problem <lb/>because s 65 of the PGPA Act can only be characterised as a law with respect to <lb/>s 52(ii) of the Constitution if it is capable of being read down to authorise act of <lb/>grace payments relating only to the Commonwealth departments particularised in <lb/>s 69 of the Constitution. This seems highly unlikely. Reading down &apos;is part of the <lb/>process of ascertaining the essential meaning of the words of the provision&apos; 58 and <lb/>there is nothing in the text of s 65 which would provide a toehold for such a narrow <lb/>interpretation. Indeed, statutory context points in the opposite direction, towards a <lb/>broad interpretation of the section. Specifically: <lb/>• s 65 is in pt 2-4 of the PGPA Act which concerns &apos;the use and management <lb/>of public resources by the Commonwealth and Commonwealth entities&apos;; 59 <lb/>• the objects of the PGPA Act include &apos;to require the Commonwealth and <lb/>Commonwealth entities to use and manage public resources properly&apos; 60 and <lb/>&apos;to establish a coherent system of governance and accountability across <lb/>Commonwealth entities&apos;; 61 <lb/>• the expression &apos;public resources&apos; is defined in s 8 of the PGPA Act as <lb/>&apos;relevant money, relevant property, or appropriations&apos;, and &apos;relevant money&apos; <lb/>is defined in the same section as &apos;(a) money standing to the credit of any bank <lb/>account of the Commonwealth or a corporate Commonwealth entity; or <lb/>(b) money that is held by the Commonwealth or a corporate Commonwealth <lb/>entity&apos;; 62 and <lb/>• &apos;relevant property&apos; is defined in s 8 of the PGPA Act as &apos;(a) property (other <lb/>than relevant money) that is owned or held by the Commonwealth or a <lb/>corporate Commonwealth entity; or (b) any other thing prescribed by the <lb/>rules&apos;. 63 <lb/>Given the PGPA Act&apos;s text and statutory context, for what &apos;reason based upon the <lb/>law itself&apos; 64 or &apos;the terms of the law&apos; 65 could the capacious words &apos;the <lb/>Commonwealth or a corporate Commonwealth entity&apos; permit an interpretation <lb/>which encompasses only the Commonwealth departments referred to in s 69 of the <lb/>Constitution: a fortiori when such an interpretation would establish an incoherent <lb/>system of governance and accountability across Commonwealth entities in <lb/>contradiction of a clear legislative intention that &apos;the law was intended to operate <lb/>fully and completely according to its terms&apos;? 66 And if reading down is not possible, <lb/>there is no &apos;separately expressed&apos; 67 &apos;substantially independent part&apos; 68 of s 65 -or <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>58 <lb/>Clubb v Edwards (2019) 267 CLR 171, 313 [416] (Edelman J) (&apos;Clubb&apos;). <lb/>59 <lb/>PGPA Act (n 13) s 50 (emphasis added). <lb/>60 <lb/>Ibid s 5(c)(iii) (emphasis added). <lb/>61 <lb/>Ibid s 5(a) (emphasis added). <lb/>62 <lb/>Ibid s 8 (emphasis added). <lb/>63 <lb/>Ibid (emphasis added). <lb/>64 <lb/>Pidoto v Victoria (1943) 68 CLR 87, 108 (Latham CJ) (&apos;Pidoto&apos;). <lb/>65 <lb/>Victoria v Commonwealth (1996) 187 CLR 416, 502 (Brennan CJ, Toohey, Gaudron, McHugh and <lb/>Gummow JJ) (&apos;Industrial Relations Act Case&apos;). <lb/>66 <lb/>Pidoto (n 64) 108 (Latham CJ). <lb/>67 <lb/>Re Tracey; Ex parte Ryan (1989) 166 CLR 518, 577 (Brennan and Toohey JJ). <lb/>68 <lb/>Clubb (n 58) 317 [422] (Edelman J). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>66 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>

			<body>of the &apos;one collective expression&apos; 69 &apos;the Commonwealth or a corporate <lb/>Commonwealth entity&apos; -which can be &apos;blue pencilled&apos; and severed. <lb/>(iii) Section 51(xxxix) of the Constitution <lb/>The characterisation of s 65 of the PGPA Act as a law with respect to s 51(xxxix) is <lb/>complicated by the High Court&apos;s decision in Williams No 2, which forecloses the <lb/>argument that s 65 is a law with respect to s 51(xxxix) on the basis that the placitum <lb/>empowers the Parliament to enact a law authorising expenditure by the <lb/>Commonwealth executive of any moneys lawfully appropriated in accordance with <lb/>ss 81 and 83 of the Constitution, no matter what the purpose of the expenditure may <lb/>be. The Court in Williams No 2 maintained that such an expansive construction of <lb/>s 51(xxxix) would erroneously treat spending by the Commonwealth executive as <lb/>incidental to an appropriation Act and bring the expenditure of any moneys <lb/>appropriated in accordance with ss 81 and 83 within the power of the <lb/>Commonwealth. It would thus, the Court reasoned, be fundamentally inconsistent <lb/>with the Court&apos;s earlier decision in Pape which characterised an appropriation Act <lb/>as a &apos;mere earmarking&apos; of revenue, and which recognised justiciable limits on the <lb/>Commonwealth executive&apos;s power to spend appropriated moneys. 70 <lb/>Following Pape, one must turn to the powers vested in the Commonwealth <lb/>executive by the Constitution, specifically s 61 which describes the executive power <lb/>of the Commonwealth. Two possibilities will be considered. The first is the so called <lb/>&apos;nationhood power&apos;; the second relies on the attribution of a non-literal, legal <lb/>meaning to s 65 of the PGPA Act. <lb/>The canonical expression of the nationhood power is that of Mason J in the <lb/>AAP Case: <lb/>[T]here is to be deduced from the existence and character of the <lb/>Commonwealth as a national government and from the presence of <lb/>ss 51(xxxix) and 61 a capacity to engage in enterprises and activities <lb/>peculiarly adapted to the government of a nation and which cannot otherwise <lb/>be carried on for the benefit of the nation. 71 <lb/>Accordingly, it could be argued that (1) a Commonwealth executive power to make <lb/>act of grace payments can &apos;be deduced from the existence and character of the <lb/>Commonwealth as a national government&apos;; and (2) s 51(xxxix) allows that power to <lb/>be given &apos;legislative expression&apos; 72 in the form of s 65 of the PGPA Act. To put that <lb/>argument at its highest, &apos;a polity must possess all the powers that it needs to function <lb/>as a polity&apos; 73 and the state governments cannot be expected &apos;to engage effectively <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>69 <lb/>Newcastle &amp; Hunter River Steamship Co Ltd v A-G (Cth) (1921) 29 CLR 357, 369 (Knox CJ, <lb/>Higgins, Gavan Duffy, Powers, Richard Starke JJ). <lb/>70 <lb/>Williams No 2 (n 7) 462-3 [52]-[55], 469-70 [85]-[87] (French CJ, Hayne, Kiefel, Bell and <lb/>Keane JJ). <lb/>71 <lb/>AAP Case (n 1) 397. <lb/>72 <lb/>Stephenson (n 4) 65. <lb/>73 <lb/>Williams No 2 (n 7) 467-8 [78] (French CJ, Hayne, Kiefel, Bell and Keane JJ), quoting from the <lb/>defendants&apos; submissions. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>67 <lb/></page>

			<body>in the … activity in question&apos; 74 that is, to make act of grace payments in relation to <lb/>Commonwealth activities. Hence, the making of act of grace payments by the <lb/>Commonwealth &apos;involves no real competition with State executive or legislative <lb/>competence&apos; 75 and -as an adjunct to the Commonwealth&apos;s primary activities -is <lb/>itself an &apos;exclusively&apos; 76 Commonwealth activity &apos;which cannot otherwise be carried <lb/>on for the benefit of the nation&apos; 77 under s 61 of the Constitution &apos;in the execution <lb/>and maintenance of this Constitution and of the laws of the Commonwealth&apos;. <lb/>Additionally, such payments are non-coercive and voluntarily received, and hence <lb/>do not interfere with the legal rights and duties of individuals. 78 <lb/>However, the nationhood power argument seems to us to be unconvincing. <lb/>The nationhood power does not encompass &apos;all those matters that are reasonably <lb/>capable of being seen as of national benefit or national concern&apos; 79 and the argument <lb/>misses the nationhood power&apos;s essential and fundamental national character. 80 The <lb/>making of act of grace payments is not an activity &apos;peculiarly adapted to the <lb/>government of a nation&apos;, 81 nor &apos;appropriate to a national government&apos;, 82 nor a power <lb/>&apos;possessed by the national government alone&apos;. 83 Rather it is an ad hoc, sporadic but <lb/>enduring activity of all governments within the common law world, whether national <lb/>or sub-national, including the several (sub-national) Australian states. Moreover, as <lb/>Peta Stephenson has observed, &apos;since Pape the nationhood power has been defied as <lb/>a power to respond to national emergencies&apos;, 84 and act of grace payments (in contrast <lb/>to the payments unsuccessfully impugned in Pape) are clearly not &apos;short-term fiscal <lb/>measures taken to respond to a national financial and economic crisis&apos;. 85 <lb/>However, the problems with the nationhood power can be avoided: it is <lb/>possible to mount a simple and plausible argument for the constitutional validity of <lb/>s 65 of the PGPA Act anchored in orthodox principles of statutory interpretation and <lb/>constitutional text. If s 65 is read literally, it does not manifest an obvious connection <lb/>with s 61 of the Constitution. But we would argue that is not its legal meaning. 86 It <lb/>is a basic constitutional principle of statutory interpretation (recognised in s 15A of <lb/>the Acts Interpretation Act 1901 (Cth)) that a statutory provision should be <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>74 <lb/>Davis v Commonwealth (1988) 166 CLR 79, 111 (Brennan J) (&apos;Davis&apos;). <lb/>75 <lb/>Ibid 94 (Mason CJ, Deane and Gaudron JJ). See also Pape (n 4) 60 [127] (French CJ), 90-1 [239] <lb/>(Gummow, Crennan and Bell JJ). <lb/>76 <lb/>Williams No 1 (n 5) 348 [503] (Crennan J). <lb/>77 <lb/>Pape (n 4) 87 [228], approving the formulation in Davis (n 74) 111 (Brennan J) of the principle stated <lb/>in AAP Case (n 1) 397 (Mason J). <lb/>78 <lb/>Pape (n 4) 24 [10] (French CJ), 92 [244]-[245] (Gummow, Crennan and Bell JJ). <lb/>79 <lb/>Williams No 2 (n 7) 466-7 [72] (French CJ, Hayne, Kiefel, Bell and Keane JJ) (emphasis in original). <lb/>80 <lb/>Peta Stephenson, &apos;Justice Mason in the Australian Assistance Plan Case (1975): Nationhood, <lb/>Federalism and Commonwealth Executive Power&apos; in Andrew Lynch (ed), Great Australian Dissents <lb/>(Cambridge University Press, 2016) 169, 180-3. See also Williams No 1 (n 5) 348 [503] (Crennan <lb/>J). <lb/>81 <lb/>AAP Case (n 1) 397 (Mason J) (emphasis added). See also Pape (n 4) 63 [133] (French CJ); Williams <lb/>No 2 (n 7) 466 [71] (French CJ, Hayne, Kiefel, Bell and Keane JJ). <lb/>82 <lb/>AAP Case (n 1) 397 (Mason J) (emphasis added). <lb/>83 <lb/>Peter Hanks, Frances Gordon and Graeme Hill, Constitutional Law in Australia (LexisNexis <lb/>Butterworths, 4 th ed, 2017) 214. <lb/>84 <lb/>Stephenson (n 4) 57 (emphasis added). <lb/>85 <lb/>Ibid 54. <lb/>86 <lb/>Project Blue Sky Inc v Australian Broadcasting Authority (1998) 194 CLR 355. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>68 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>

			<body>interpreted in conformity, rather than disconformity, with the Constitution, provided <lb/>such a validating constructional choice is reasonably open. 87 Accordingly, the <lb/>following can be implied into the legal meaning of s 65(1) without violating its text, <lb/>to secure the necessary validating connection between it and s 61: <lb/>The Finance Minister may on behalf of the Commonwealth authorise in <lb/>writing one or more payments to be made to a person if the Finance Minister <lb/>thinks it is appropriate to do so because of special circumstances which have <lb/>arisen in the exercise of executive power under s 61 of the Constitution. <lb/>(b) <lb/>Is RMG 401 Consistent with the Constitutionally Determined Meaning of <lb/>Section 65 of the PGPA Act? <lb/>It is unfortunate that the constitutional constraints on the meaning of s 65 of the <lb/>PGPA Act are not expressly referred to in RMG 401. 88 In its current form, the guide <lb/>may mislead its presumably largely non-legally-qualified audience into approving a <lb/>payment not authorised by s 65. Paragraph 13 of RMG 401 states: <lb/>Payments under the act of grace mechanism must be made from money <lb/>appropriated by the Parliament. Therefore, as a matter of practice, the act of <lb/>grace mechanism is generally not available: <lb/>• <lb/>when a request has arisen from private circumstances outside the sphere <lb/>of Commonwealth administration, there has been no involvement of an <lb/>agent or NCE [non-corporate Commonwealth entity] of the <lb/>Commonwealth and the matter is not related to the impact of any <lb/>Commonwealth legislation … <lb/>However, the words &apos;as a matter of practice … is generally not available&apos; obscure <lb/>the underlying hard law constitutional prohibition on payments in the circumstances <lb/>described in the accompanying dot point imposed by (the constitutionally <lb/>determined, read-down meaning of) s 65. The risk that RMG 401&apos;s audience will <lb/>breach the constitutional limits on their powers is exacerbated by the advice in <lb/>paragraph 9 of RMG 401 that &apos;&quot;special circumstances&quot; and &quot;appropriate&quot; are not <lb/>defined in the PGPA Act and are for the decision-maker to assess&apos;. That advice fails <lb/>to draw a distinction between the definition of terms within a statute, and the <lb/>application of that definition to a set of facts. Paragraph 9 of RMG 401 may thus <lb/>unfortunately imply, in the minds of its non-legally-qualified audience, that the <lb/>meaning of &apos;special circumstances&apos; and &apos;appropriate&apos; can be determined at their <lb/>discretion. But a discretion allowed by statute must be exercised &apos;according to law, <lb/>and not humour&apos;, 89 and the High Court -drawing on United States Supreme Court <lb/>Marshall CJ&apos;s foundational constitutional declaration in 1803 in Marbury v Madison <lb/>that &apos;[i]t is emphatically the province and duty of the judicial department to say what <lb/>the law is&apos; 90 -has committed the Australian legal system &apos;to a strict version of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>87 <lb/>Williams No 2 (n 7) 457 [36] (French CJ, Hayne, Keifel, Bell and Keane JJ); Industrial Relations Act <lb/>Case (n 65) 501-3 (Brennan CJ, Toohey, Gaudron, McHugh and Gummow JJ). <lb/>88 <lb/>Department of Finance, Requests for Discretionary Financial Assistance under the Public <lb/>Governance, Performance and Accountability Act 2013 (Resource Management Guide 401) (&apos;RMG <lb/>401&apos;). <lb/>89 <lb/>Sharp v Wakefield [1891] AC 173, 179 (Lord Halsbury LC). <lb/>90 <lb/>Marbury v Madison, 5 US (1 Cranch) 137, 177 (1803). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>69 <lb/></page>

			<body>judicial supremacy&apos;. 91 Accordingly, it is presumed that a statutory expression must <lb/>have a meaning and its correct meaning can only be authoritatively determined by <lb/>the courts applying the relevant rules of statutory interpretation, including of reading <lb/>down, to the extent reasonable constructional choices are open, to avoid <lb/>constitutional invalidity. Hence, it would be more constitutionally prudent if RMG <lb/>401 advised its audience that, although the terms &apos;special circumstances&apos; and <lb/>&apos;appropriate&apos; are not further defined in the PGPA Act, they do have a legal meaning <lb/>and then to posit that meaning (subject to the proviso that in our constitutional <lb/>system, only courts can determine legal meaning authoritatively). <lb/>Unfortunately, the constitutional problems with RMG 401 worsen in its <lb/>paragraph 10. In that paragraph&apos;s list of &apos;[e]xamples of special circumstances that <lb/>may make it appropriate to approve an act of grace payment&apos;, the following dot point <lb/>appears: &apos;the matter is not covered by legislation or specific policy, but the <lb/>Commonwealth intends to introduce such legislation or policy, and it is considered <lb/>desirable in a particular case to apply the benefits of the relevant policy <lb/>prospectively&apos;. 92 But that gives rise to an obvious objection: how is a <lb/>Commonwealth payment based not on existing legislation or policy but on a mere <lb/>intention of the Commonwealth executive to introduce legislation or policy <lb/>supported by the legal meaning of s 65(1), constitutionally confined, as it must be, <lb/>to circumstances &apos;which have arisen in the course of the execution and maintenance <lb/>of the Constitution and of the laws of the Commonwealth&apos;? Although, as will be <lb/>explained shortly, it can be argued that s 65(1) encompasses payments made in the <lb/>ordinary, well-established course of Commonwealth executive administration (by <lb/>the link between the Commonwealth executive power to make such payments and <lb/>s 51(xxxix)), it would be very difficult, if not impossible, to maintain that a payment <lb/>made based on intended, but non-existing, legislation or policy falls within that <lb/>description. <lb/>2 <lb/>CDDA Scheme <lb/>The constitutional status of the CDDA Scheme is far more questionable than the <lb/>status of the PGPA Scheme. Although the Department of Finance website asserts <lb/>that the &apos;CDDA scheme was established under the executive power of section 61 of <lb/>the Constitution&apos;, 93 following Pape and the Williams cases, the scheme still requires <lb/>statutory support. Boughey, Rock and Weeks seem to be confident that it is <lb/>constitutionally secure, by virtue of a reference to the Scheme in the Financial <lb/>Framework Legislation Amendment Act (No 3) 2012 (Cth) (&apos;FFLA Act No 3&apos;) which <lb/>was hastily enacted by the Commonwealth in response to Williams No 1. 94 However, <lb/>we are not as sanguine as they are about the effectiveness of the FFLA Act No 3 <lb/>amendments. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>91 <lb/>W Bateman (n 20) 184. <lb/>92 <lb/>RMG 401 (n 88) [10]. <lb/>93 <lb/>&apos;Scheme for Compensation for Detriment caused by Defective Administration (CDDA Scheme)&apos;, <lb/>Department of Finance (Web Page, 2024) &lt;https://www.finance.gov.au&gt;. <lb/>94 <lb/>Boughey, Rock and Weeks (n 28) 293-4. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>70 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>Boughey, Rock and Weeks appear to assume that item 407.059 in sch 2 of <lb/>the FFLA Act No 3 -which now appears as item 407.059 in pt 4 of sch 1AA of the <lb/>Financial Framework (Supplementary Powers) Regulations 1997 (Cth) (&apos;FF(SP) <lb/>Regulations&apos;) -refers to the CDDA Scheme. 95 The item reads: <lb/>Compensation and Debt Relief <lb/>Objective: To provide access for eligible recipients to discretionary payments <lb/>in special circumstances or financial relief from amounts owing to the <lb/>Commonwealth. <lb/>If Boughey, Rock and Weeks&apos; assumption is correct, then there is, at very least, a <lb/>plausible argument that the CDDA Scheme has sufficient statutory support to pass <lb/>constitutional muster. The argument can be set out thus: <lb/>Proposition 1: Section 32B(1) of the Financial Framework (Supplementary Powers) <lb/>Act 1997 (Cth) (&apos;FF(SP) Act&apos;) relevantly provides: <lb/>If: <lb/>(a) apart from this subsection, the Commonwealth does not have <lb/>power to make, vary or administer: <lb/>(i) an arrangement under which relevant money or other <lb/>[Consolidated Revenue Fund] money is, or may become, <lb/>payable by the Commonwealth; or <lb/>… <lb/>(iii) a grant of financial assistance to a person other than a State <lb/>or Territory; and <lb/>(b) the arrangement or grant, as the case may be: <lb/>(i) is specified in the regulations; or <lb/>(ii) is included in a class of arrangements or grants, as the case <lb/>may be, specified in the regulations; or <lb/>(iii) is for the purposes of a program specified in the regulations; <lb/>the Commonwealth has power to make, vary or administer the arrangement <lb/>or grant, as the case may be. <lb/>Proposition 2: The CDDA Scheme is either: <lb/>• specified in the FF(SP) Regulations; <lb/>• included in a class of arrangements or grants, as the case may be, specified in <lb/>the Regulations; or <lb/>• for the purposes of a program specified in the Regulations <lb/>by virtue of the inclusion of item 407.059 of pt 4 of sch 1AA of the Regulations. <lb/>Proposition 3: Section 32B(1) of the FF(SP) Act and item 407.059 in pt 4 of sch 1AA <lb/>of the FF(SP) Regulations are constitutionally valid. <lb/>Conclusion: Therefore, the CDDA Scheme has statutory support and does not fall <lb/>foul of the strictures of Williams No 1. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>95 <lb/>Ibid 293. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>71 <lb/></page>

			<body>Like Boughey, Rock and Williams we agree that proposition 3 above is <lb/>strongly arguable, employing a similar argument to the one used to secure the PGPA <lb/>Act. Specifically: <lb/>• The express incidental head of power allows the Parliament to enact laws <lb/>incidental to Commonwealth executive power conferred by the Constitution. <lb/>• Section 61 of the Constitution describes the Commonwealth executive&apos;s <lb/>power to execute and maintain the Constitution and the laws of the <lb/>Commonwealth. <lb/>• Consistently with the basic principle of statutory construction that legislation <lb/>should be interpreted to ensure compatibility with the Constitution if <lb/>reasonable constructional choices are open, s 32B(1) of the FF(SP) Act and <lb/>item 407.059 of pt 4 of sch 1AA of the FF(SP) Regulations should be read <lb/>down so as only to confer powers relating to the Commonwealth executive&apos;s <lb/>power to execute and maintain the Constitution and the laws of the <lb/>Commonwealth. <lb/>• Therefore, s 32B(1) of the FF(SP) Act and item 407.059 of pt 4 of sch 1AA <lb/>of the FF(SP) Regulations are sourced in s 51(xxxix) as laws incidental to <lb/>powers vested in the Commonwealth executive by the Constitution. <lb/>However, in contrast to Boughey, Rock and Weeks, we (like Sapienza it <lb/>appears 96 ) entertain grave doubts that a court would find that item 407.509 does refer <lb/>to the CDDA Scheme (proposition 2 above). Given that the purpose of insisting on <lb/>statutory authorisation in Williams No 1 was to ensure that the Commonwealth <lb/>Parliament (including the Senate as a &apos;states&apos; House&apos;) has a direct say on <lb/>Commonwealth executive spending -&apos;to ensure &quot;parliamentary control&quot; over the <lb/>executive and enforce the federal division of powers established by the Australian <lb/>Constitution&apos; 97 -it would seem unlikely that a court would reason that the vague <lb/>words of the item would be sufficient to put the Parliament on notice that the CDDA <lb/>Scheme is included in it. <lb/>Although the High Court in Williams No 2 may have subsequently set the bar <lb/>low, 98 the imprecise language of the item stands in stark contrast to the precision <lb/>with which other programs are included by name in the schedule (for example, the <lb/>Remote Youth Leadership and Development Corps, the Remote Jobs and <lb/>Communities Program, and the Productive Ageing Package). 99 Even more <lb/>significantly, the list of programs in pt 4 of sch 1AA is organised by reference to a <lb/>series of government departments and item 407.509 is part of a set of programs, all <lb/>beginning with the numbers &apos;407&apos;, which appears under the heading &apos;Department of <lb/>Education, Employment and Workplace Relations&apos;. That department (which no <lb/>longer exists, having been divided into two departments, the Department of <lb/>Education and the Department of Employment and Workplace Relations in 2022) <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>96 <lb/>Amanda Sapienza, Judicial Review of Non-Statutory Executive Action (Federation Press, 2020) 37 <lb/>n 205. <lb/>97 <lb/>W Bateman (n 20) 185. <lb/>98 <lb/>Ibid 187. <lb/>99 <lb/>FFLA Act No 3 (n 48) sch 2. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>72 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>

	<body>was not primarily responsible for oversight of the CDDA Scheme, nor are its two <lb/>successor departments; the Department of Finance has always occupied that <lb/>position. Moreover, as noted previously, the CDDA Scheme traverses all non-<lb/>corporate Commonwealth entities, not just the Department of Education, <lb/>Employment and Workplace Relations or its successor departments. <lb/>The item is possibly a reference to a proposal, which was current from 2010 <lb/>to 2015 but never enacted, to give Comcare (a Commonwealth statutory authority <lb/>for which the department was responsible) the statutory power to make discretionary <lb/>compensation payments for defects in its administration analogous to the CDDA <lb/>Scheme. 100 Or, at best, item 407 is a reference to the administration of the CDDA <lb/>Scheme within the department (and now its successor departments), but not in the <lb/>numerous other departments that make CDDA Scheme decisions. <lb/>On the assumption that we are correct in our misgivings, and that there is a <lb/>real risk that a court would find that item 407.509 does not refer to the CDDA <lb/>Scheme (or at least not to the extent that it is administered outside the Department <lb/>of Education and the Department of Employment and Workplace Relations), we will <lb/>now consider the CDDA Scheme&apos;s constitutionality on the assumption that it has no <lb/>statutory support. <lb/>Act of grace payments out of the bounty of the Crown originated as a <lb/>response to &apos;a lacuna in the rule of law&apos; 101 created by the Crown&apos;s legal immunity, <lb/>encapsulated in &apos;the legal apophthegm that the King can do no wrong&apos;. 102 They were <lb/>(and remain in the United Kingdom) premised on an unconstrained executive power <lb/>to spend, with the qualification -once the supremacy of Parliament over the Crown <lb/>was secured in the 17 th century -that the requisite funds are appropriated by <lb/>Parliament. 103 Hence the Australian constitutional conundrum post Pape and the <lb/>Williams cases: given that the High Court has decided that the United Kingdom <lb/>premise does not apply to the Commonwealth executive under the Constitution, is <lb/>the CDDA Scheme lawful if -as we have assumed -it has no statutory footing? <lb/>On the premise that &apos;[i]t is well settled that the [Commonwealth] Executive <lb/>can spend (with an available appropriation) where power to do so is conferred by <lb/>valid statute or by the Constitution itself&apos;, 104 the High Court in Williams No 1 <lb/>identified three exceptions to the general principle that, under the Constitution, the <lb/>Commonwealth executive cannot spend without legislation authorising that <lb/>expenditure. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>100 Review of Government Compensation Payments (n 23) 50 [3.42]; Safety, Rehabilitation and <lb/>Compensation Amendment (Improving the Comcare Scheme) Bill 2015 (Cth) cl 70C; Explanatory <lb/>Memorandum, Safety, Rehabilitation and Compensation Amendment (Improving the Comcare <lb/>Scheme) Bill (Cth) 27-8, 32-3. <lb/>101 Committee on Ministers&apos; Powers (UK), Report (Cmd 4060, 1932) 112. <lb/>102 Joseph Chitty, A Treatise on the Law of the Prerogatives of the Crown (Butterworth, 1820) 5. <lb/>103 Boughey, Rock and Weeks (n 28) 290-1. <lb/>104 Williams No 1 (n 5) 249 [193] (Hayne J) (emphasis added) (citations omitted). See also at 361 [558], <lb/>366 [569] (Kiefel J). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>
	  
	  <page>73 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <body>(a) <lb/>Nationhood Exception <lb/>The first exception (hereafter referred to as the &apos;nationhood exception&apos;) relates to the <lb/>so-called &apos;nationhood power&apos; 105 which derives &apos;from the character and status of the <lb/>Commonwealth as a national government&apos;. 106 It can be dealt with here briefly. <lb/>Although we would concede that the making of act of grace payments by the <lb/>Commonwealth without legislative support could come within the depth of the <lb/>nationhood power (as noted previously, the faculty to make such payments does not <lb/>interfere with the legal rights and duties of individuals because their receipt is non-<lb/>coercive and voluntary), we maintain that act of grace payments fall outside the <lb/>breadth of the nationhood power. 107 As expounded above, 108 the making of such <lb/>payments is not an activity &apos;peculiarly adapted to the government of a nation&apos;, 109 <lb/>nor &apos;appropriate to a national government&apos;, 110 nor an exercise of a power &apos;possessed <lb/>by the national government alone&apos;. 111 <lb/>(b) <lb/>Ordinary Functions Exception <lb/>The second exception is where the expenditure relates to &apos;the ordinary course of <lb/>administering a recognised part of the Government of the Commonwealth or with <lb/>the incidents of the ordinary and well-recognised functions of that Government&apos; <lb/>(hereafter referred to as the &apos;ordinary functions exception&apos;). 112 While this exception <lb/>provides significant assistance to the Commonwealth, it cannot cover the whole of <lb/>the CDDA Scheme: the Scheme purports to embrace compensation for &apos;defective <lb/>administration&apos; by all &apos;non-corporate Commonwealth entities&apos;, 113 without reference <lb/>to the exception. At the risk of stating the obvious, it would be specious to maintain <lb/>that making act of grace payments for defective administration relating to the non-<lb/>ordinary or not well-recognised functions of the Commonwealth government can be <lb/>characterised as incidental to the ordinary and well-recognised functions of the <lb/>Commonwealth government. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>105 Discussed above in Part II(C)(1)(iii). <lb/>106 AAP Case (n 1) 397 (Mason J); Williams No 1 (n 5) 249-52 [194]-[198], 267 [240] (Hayne J), 362 <lb/>[559], 370-3 [582]-[594] (Kiefel J), 346-9 [497]-[507], 357 [542] (Crennan J). See also at 180 [4], <lb/>184-5 [22], 188-91 [29]-[34], 216-17 [83] (French CJ), 230-1 [131], 234-5 [144]-[146] (Gummow <lb/>and Bell JJ), 272 [256] (Hayne J), 342 [485], 355 [535] (Crennan J), 361 [558] (Kiefel J). <lb/>107 For a discussion of the use of the concepts of breadth and depth to analyse Commonwealth executive <lb/>power, see Stephenson (n 4) 36-8. For a discussion of the limitations on the nationhood power framed <lb/>by those concepts, see at 59-70. <lb/>108 See above Part II(C)(1)(iii) for our discussion of the possible engagement of the nationhood power, <lb/>in combination with s 51(xxxix) of the Constitution, to provide constitutional support to s 65 of the <lb/>PGPA Act (n 13). <lb/>109 AAP Case (n 1) 397 (Mason J) (emphasis added). <lb/>110 Ibid 397 (Mason J) (emphasis added). <lb/>111 Hanks, Gordon and Hill (n 83) 214. <lb/>112 Williams No 1 (n 5) 233-4 [139]-[141] (Gummow and Bell JJ), 255-6 [208]-[209] (Hayne J), 342 <lb/>[484], 343 [487], 345 [493], 353-5 [525]-[534] (Crennan J). See at 370 [582] (Kiefel J). In Williams <lb/>No 1, the existence of the ordinary functions exception was not in dispute between the parties: <lb/>Williams No 1 (n 5) 233 [139] (Gummow and Bell JJ), 342 [482]-[484], 345 [493] (Crennan J), 370 <lb/>[582] (Kiefel J). <lb/>113 RMG 409 (n 35) [1]. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>74 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>(c) <lb/>Prerogative Exception <lb/>The third exception is where the expenditure is an exercise of the Commonwealth <lb/>executive&apos;s prerogative powers inherent in s 61 (hereafter referred to as the <lb/>&apos;prerogative exception&apos;). 114 The extent to which this exception can provide a <lb/>constitutional foothold for the CDDA Scheme depends on how act of grace <lb/>payments made in the absence of statutory authorisation are characterised. <lb/>The term &apos;prerogative&apos; can bear two meanings. In a narrow sense (commonly <lb/>associated with the writings of Blackstone) it refers to the unique or special powers <lb/>and privileges of the Crown which can interfere with the legal rights and interests of <lb/>others. However, in the broader sense (commonly, but perhaps erroneously, <lb/>associated with the writings of Dicey) 115 it encompasses additionally those legal <lb/>capacities that the Crown enjoys in common with its subjects, and which cannot be <lb/>used to interfere with the legal rights and interests of others without their consent. <lb/>When the High Court in Williams No 1 recognised the prerogative exception, it was <lb/>referring to the narrow &apos;true prerogative&apos;, 116 consistently with longstanding, <lb/>conventional Australian usage: 117 otherwise, the impugned contract between the <lb/>Commonwealth and Scripture Union Queensland to spend Commonwealth moneys <lb/>would have fallen within the prerogative exception and survived challenge. <lb/>Consequently, if act of grace payments made without legislative support are made in <lb/>the exercise of a broad executive capacity to spend, then payments under the CDDA <lb/>Scheme do not fall within the narrow, true prerogative exception and are unlawful, <lb/>unless they fall within the ordinary functions exception. <lb/>While acknowledging &apos;that the dividing line between special government <lb/>powers and mere legal capacities may not always be clear&apos; 118 we maintain that when <lb/>the Commonwealth makes an act of grace payment, it exercises a capacity derived <lb/>from its legal personality as a polity (which, following the usage of Gageler J in <lb/>Plaintiff M68/2015, we will hereafter refer to as a &apos;non-prerogative executive <lb/>capacity&apos;) 119 not a narrow, unique (Blackstonian) &apos;prerogative executive power&apos;. 120 <lb/>If we are right, then important constitutional consequences follow, so it is incumbent <lb/>upon us to explain why we have come to that conclusion. <lb/>First, as emphasised previously, when the Commonwealth makes an act of <lb/>grace payment to a subject, there is no legal coercion and no power &apos;exercisable over <lb/>individuals&apos;. 121 The prospective recipient is not compelled to take the money; they <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>114 Williams No 1 (n 5) 216 [83] (French CJ), 342 [484], 343 [487], 358 [544] (Crennan J), 373 [594] <lb/>(Kiefel J). See generally at 184-6 [22]-[25] (French CJ), 227-8 [123]-[124] (Gummow and Bell JJ). <lb/>The existence of the prerogative exception was not in dispute between the parties in Williams No 1: <lb/>Williams No 1 (n 5) 342 [482]-[484], 345 [493] (Crennan J); 370 [582] (Kiefel J). <lb/>115 L v South Australia (2017) 129 SASR 180, 188 [29]-[30] (Kourakis CJ). <lb/>116 Ibid 31 [107] (Kourakis CJ). <lb/>117 Ibid 30 [102] (Kourakis CJ). See also Stephenson (n 4) 21. <lb/>118 Hanks, Gordon and Hill (n 83) 214. <lb/>119 Plaintiff M68/2015 v Minister for Immigration and Border Protection (2016) 257 CLR 42, 98 [134] <lb/>(&apos;Plaintiff M68&apos;). <lb/>120 Ibid. <lb/>121 Chitty (n 102) 25. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>75 <lb/></page>

			<body>can refuse. It is therefore not &apos;an act which is capable of interfering with legal rights <lb/>of others&apos;: 122 <lb/>Such effects as the act might have on legal rights or juridical relations result <lb/>not from the act being uniquely that of the Executive Government but from <lb/>the application to the act of the same substantive law as would be applicable <lb/>in respect of the act had it been done by any other actor. 123 <lb/>In other words, an act of grace payment is relevantly analogous to a voluntary <lb/>payment by a subject to another subject based on a perceived moral obligation (in <lb/>contrast to a claim of legal right) and &apos;involves nothing more than the utilisation of <lb/>a bare capacity or permission, which can also be described as an ability to act or as <lb/>a &quot;faculty&quot;&apos;. 124 <lb/>Secondly, to apply the 1759 maxim from Finch&apos;s Law concerning the <lb/>prerogative: 125 it is the law in the case of a subject that she has the legal capacity to <lb/>make a payment to another based on a perceived moral obligation rather than claim <lb/>of legal right, and hence it is not the law unique to the Crown. It does not, therefore <lb/>ex hypothesi fall within the scope of a prerogative executive power. <lb/>Thirdly, there is no reference to any prerogative power to make act of grace <lb/>payments in Joseph Chitty&apos;s monumental 500-page A Treatise on the Law of the <lb/>Prerogatives of the Crown published in 1820, HV Evatt&apos;s famous 1924 doctoral <lb/>thesis, The Royal Prerogative, or the first edition of Halsbury&apos;s Laws of England <lb/>published in 31 volumes from 1907 to 1917. Moreover, both Chitty and Evatt make <lb/>it clear at the outset that their conception of the prerogative is entirely <lb/>Blackstonian: 126 if act of grace payments were an exercise of a prerogative power, <lb/>then it is astonishing that the power to make them is not mentioned in either. <lb/>Although there are some United Kingdom authorities on act of grace payments <lb/>which refer to such payments as &apos;under the prerogative powers of the executive&apos;, 127 <lb/>it needs to be borne in mind that the United Kingdom usage of the term &apos;prerogative&apos; <lb/>(in contrast to Australia) generally follows the Diceyan conception. 128 <lb/>Fourthly, a prerogative executive power must be a product of the common <lb/>law: it only exists if the common law historically recognises its existence. In the pre-<lb/>Federation era, both the government of the United Kingdom 129 and the Australian <lb/>colonial governments made act of grace payments from time to time, thus enhancing <lb/>&apos;the constitutional framework in which the claims of the citizen upon the state could <lb/>be resolved&apos;. 130 In the colony of New South Wales, for example, the established <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>122 Plaintiff M68/2015 (n 119) 98 [135] (Gageler J). <lb/>123 Stephenson (n 4) 64. <lb/>124 Plaintiff M68 (2016) 257 CLR 42, 98 [135] (Gageler J) (citations omitted). <lb/>125 &apos;You shall find it to be the law almost in every case of the King, that is law in no case of a subject&apos;: <lb/>Sir Henry Finch, Law or a Discourse Thereof in Four Books (Henry Lintot, 1759) 85. <lb/>126 Chitty (n 102) 4; HV Evatt, The Royal Prerogative (Law Book Company, 1987) 11-12. <lb/>127 R v Ministry of Defence; Ex parte Walker (2000) 2 All ER 917, 928 <lb/>128 Stephenson (n 4) 19-21. <lb/>129 See, eg, United Kingdom, Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons, 28 July 1896, 827. <lb/>130 Paul Finn, Law and Government in Colonial Australia (Oxford University Press, 1987) 75. See, eg, <lb/>Western Australia, Parliamentary Debates, Legislative Assembly, 20 February 1891; Western <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>76 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>

	<body>practice was for the aggrieved citizen to petition Parliament and then for Parliament <lb/>to &apos;appoint a select committee to inquire and report as to whether a recommendation <lb/>should be made to the Government for an ex gratia payment&apos;. 131 Therefore, if the <lb/>making of act of grace payments is an exercise of a prerogative executive power, <lb/>one would expect that Australian courts in the colonial period would have had <lb/>occasion to recognise it as such. But they did not. Although there is some curial <lb/>recognition of the practice, 132 act of grace payments were never described in terms <lb/>consistent with an exercise of a prerogative executive power. Instead, they were <lb/>described in terms consistent with our position that such payments are an exercise <lb/>of non-prerogative executive capacity. 133 <lb/>If our position is correct, then the Commonwealth must rely solely on the <lb/>ordinary functions exemption to secure the constitutional legality of CDDA <lb/>payments (on the assumption that, contra Boughey, Rock and Weeks, the CDDA <lb/>Scheme lacks statutory support). On that premise, any CDDA payments that fall <lb/>outside the scope of that exception are made in violation of the Constitution. <lb/>It is perhaps unduly cynical to observe that it is to the advantage of the <lb/>Commonwealth that no disappointed applicant for a payment under the CDDA <lb/>Scheme is likely to challenge the constitutionality of the Scheme itself. However, if <lb/>an applicant&apos;s CDDA Scheme application concerned defective administration <lb/>related to &apos;the ordinary course of administering a recognised part of the Government <lb/>of the Commonwealth, or with the incidents of the ordinary and well-recognised <lb/>functions of that Government&apos;, 134 and that relationship was not considered by the <lb/>CDDA decision-maker rejecting the application (and why would it be, given that the <lb/>language of the ordinary functions exemption does not appear in RMG 409), then <lb/>that applicant would have a compelling argument that the decision is infected with <lb/>jurisdictional error: the decision-maker has ignored a constitutionally mandated <lb/>precondition to the exercise of their power. And it is possible to envisage situations <lb/>where the fact that a person suffered a loss because of defective administration <lb/>related to the ordinary, well-recognised functions of the Commonwealth <lb/>government (as opposed to extraordinary, novel functions, where some diminution <lb/>of the standard and quality of administration might be anticipated and excused) <lb/>militates in favour of a moral obligation to make a payment. Think of Karen Green, <lb/>a 16-year-old school leaver who was denied unemployment benefits for some <lb/>months because of the Department of Social Security&apos;s defective administration of <lb/>an ordinary, well-recognised function of the Commonwealth relating to an entirely <lb/>foreseeable and ordinary event -that is, that a 16-year-old would choose to leave <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Australia, Parliamentary Debates, Legislative Assembly, 18 January 1892, 285; Western Australia, <lb/>Parliamentary Debates, Legislative Assembly, 19 December 1892, 447-8; Parliament of New South <lb/>Wales, Sessional Papers, 1899(3) 462-3, 870, 867. <lb/>131 Finn (n 130) 75. See also Parramatta River Steamers &amp; Tramway Co v Hixson (1895) 16 NSWLR <lb/>105, 109 (Martin CJ), 109-10 (Windeyer J), 110 (Innes J) (&apos;Parramatta River Steamers&apos;); Twaddell <lb/>v Driver [1877] Knox Reports 459 (&apos;Twaddell&apos;). <lb/>132 Finn (n 130) 75. <lb/>133 Parramatta River Steamers (n 131) 109 (Martin CJ), 109-10 (Windeyer J), 110 (Innes J). See <lb/>Twaddell (n 131). <lb/>134 See above n 112 and accompanying text. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>
	  
	  <page>77 <lb/></page>

			<body>school at the end of the school year and immediately start actively and genuinely <lb/>looking for full-time employment. 135 <lb/>However, even if we are wrong, and the Commonwealth does enjoy a <lb/>prerogative executive power to make act of grace payments without statutory support <lb/>under s 61 of the Constitution, there are still consequences for the legality of CDDA <lb/>Scheme decision-making. As a creature of the common law, any prerogative power <lb/>to make act of grace payments must be legally limited: it follows, therefore, that <lb/>CDDA payments can only lawfully be made within the legal limits of that <lb/>prerogative. 136 Moreover, and in contrast to the inapposite &apos;nationhood power&apos;, the <lb/>legal orthodoxy is that those limits on the prerogative are fixed by the common law <lb/>in aspic and determined retrospectively. 137 As Lord Diplock famously warned in <lb/>1964, &apos;it is 350 years and a civil war too late for the Queen&apos;s courts to broaden the <lb/>royal prerogative&apos;. 138 While it is conceded that the prerogative may be &apos;capable of <lb/>being adapted to &quot;new situations&quot;&apos;, 139 act of grace payments are an ancient practice <lb/>from time out of mind, not a &apos;new situation&apos;. Hence, if the Commonwealth executive <lb/>transgresses the historically determined limits of the posited prerogative in making <lb/>a CDDA decision which does not fall within the ordinary functions exception, then <lb/>it is vulnerable to judicial review. That raises a difficult question: what would be the <lb/>historically determined limits on any posited prerogative executive power to make <lb/>act of grace payments? <lb/>Although the Case of Proclamations in 1610 established that the authority to <lb/>determine the existence and extent of the prerogative belonged to the courts, not the <lb/>Crown, 140 traditionally &apos;the manner of exercise of a prerogative power was <lb/>considered unreviewable on any ground whatsoever&apos;. 141 This position was not <lb/>abandoned until the second half of the 20 th century, 142 hence &apos;there exists a modest <lb/>body of case law&apos; 143 only. However, we maintain that if such an executive <lb/>prerogative power exists, then it must have some qualities to make it distinguishable. <lb/>Specifically, we propose that it must be (1) predicated upon the existence of a <lb/>relevant appropriation by the legislature; (2) exercisable at the discretion of the <lb/>Crown &apos;out of grace&apos; or favour, without any legal duty or compulsion to make a <lb/>payment, usually as a remedy of last resort in the absence of another viable available <lb/>remedy; 144 and (3) exercised on the basis of some sense of a moral obligation to <lb/>make a payment in exceptional or special circumstances. 145 Of these qualities, it is <lb/>(3) that is the most distinctive: a sense of moral, in contrast to legal, obligation <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>135 Green v Daniels (1977) 13 ALR 1. <lb/>136 Sapienza (n 96) 177. <lb/>137 Ibid 141; Stephenson (n 4) 25. <lb/>138 British Broadcasting Corporation v Johns [1965] Ch 32, 79 (Diplock LJ). <lb/>139 Nicholas Condylis, &apos;Debating the Nature and Ambit of the Commonwealth&apos;s Non-Statutory <lb/>Executive Power&apos; (2015) 39(2) Melbourne University Law Review 385, 406, quoting George <lb/>Winterton, &apos;The Prerogative in Novel Situations&apos; (1983) 99 Law Quarterly Review 407, 408 <lb/>(emphasis in original). <lb/>140 Case of Proclamations (1610) 12 Co Rep 74; 77 ER 1352. <lb/>141 SA de Smith, Judicial Review of Administrative Action (Stevens &amp; Sons, 1959) 118. <lb/>142 Council of Civil Service Unions v Minister for the Civil Service [1985] AC 374. <lb/>143 Clement v Minister for Finance &amp; Deregulation [2009] FMCA 43, [32] (Neville FM) (&apos;Clement&apos;). <lb/>144 Ibid [25], [30], [38]; Hartigan v Treasurer (ACT) (2018) 228 FLR 324, 329 [29] (&apos;Hartigan&apos;). <lb/>145 See, eg, Toomer (n 30) [47]. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>78 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>imposed on the Crown would be the &apos;lodestar&apos; 146 of any posited act of grace <lb/>prerogative. <lb/>A problem: paragraphs 17 and 18 of RMG 409 explain, under the heading <lb/>&apos;What does the CDDA Scheme do?&apos;: <lb/>The CDDA Scheme provides that if a minister or an official authorised by the <lb/>minister forms an opinion that an official of the entity, acting, or purporting <lb/>to act, in the course of duty, has directly caused a claimant to suffer detriment, <lb/>or, conversely, prevented the claimant from avoiding detriment, due to: <lb/>• <lb/>a specific and unreasonable lapse in complying with existing <lb/>administrative procedures that would normally have applied to the <lb/>claimant&apos;s circumstances <lb/>• <lb/>an unreasonable failure to institute appropriate administrative procedures <lb/>to cover a claimant&apos;s circumstances <lb/>• <lb/>giving advice to (or for) a claimant that was, in all circumstances, <lb/>incorrect or ambiguous <lb/>• <lb/>an unreasonable failure to give to (or for) a claimant, the proper advice <lb/>that was within the official&apos;s power and knowledge to give (or was <lb/>reasonably capable of being obtained by the official to give) the minister <lb/>or the authorised official may authorise a payment to the claimant. <lb/>The CDDA Scheme is permissive, in that it does not oblige the decision-<lb/>maker to approve a payment in any particular case. However, the decision to <lb/>approve or refuse a payment must be publicly defensible, having regard to all <lb/>the circumstances of the matter. <lb/>All the above is undoubtedly very helpful for the staff member to whom RMG 409 <lb/>is directed, but nowhere in paragraphs 17 and 18, nor in the other 90 paragraphs of <lb/>the guide, is there any express reference to morality, nor indeed justice (in contrast <lb/>to repeated references to unreasonableness). Specifically, the guide does not <lb/>expressly advise the staff member that they need to consider whether the <lb/>Commonwealth is under a moral obligation to make a payment and if so, the size of <lb/>the payment that would be required to discharge that obligation. It is conceded that <lb/>the need to discern such an obligation may be implicit in RMG 409 but there are <lb/>dangers in not making the requirement explicit. 147 A staff member (frequently <lb/>without any legal qualifications) in ignorance of both the prerogative, and the <lb/>distinction between hard and soft law, might be misled by the guide into not giving <lb/>&apos;proper&apos; and &apos;due&apos; consideration 148 to the moral dimension of a CDDA Scheme <lb/>claim. 149 Indeed, government agencies have been criticised for &apos;adopting an overly <lb/>defensive and legalistic approach to CDDA decision-making&apos; 150 that &apos;is not in the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>146 Clement (n 143) [31] (Neville FM). <lb/>147 Sapienza (n 96) 151-2. <lb/>148 Tickner v Chapman (1995) 57 FCR 451, 455, 465. <lb/>149 The Commonwealth Ombudsman identified a similar problem with the way in which Centrelink&apos;s <lb/>Customer Compensation Handbook described the CDDA Scheme: Putting Things Right (n 37) 25-<lb/>7, 32. <lb/>150 Review of Government Compensation Payments (n 23) 52 [3.47], referring to concerns of the Acting <lb/>Commonwealth Ombudsman. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>79 <lb/></page>

			<body>spirit of the &quot;moral&quot; as opposed to &quot;legal&quot; obligation that is central to CDDA&apos;. 151 <lb/>Within that bureaucratic culture, one can envisage a staff member, dealing with an <lb/>emotive application for a CDDA payment, scrupulously following the guide and <lb/>falling into a crude legal positivist trap. She might reason, for example: <lb/>I note the repeated references in your application to the injustice of your <lb/>predicament and the Government&apos;s moral obligation to make a payment to <lb/>you, but ultimately my decision must be made according to the law, and I am <lb/>not satisfied that the Government acted unreasonably as set out in paragraphs <lb/>17 and 18 of RMG 409. <lb/>Although it concerns a statutory act of grace scheme, the 2018 decision of the ACT <lb/>Supreme Court in Hartigan illustrates this danger. <lb/>Hartigan concerned an Administrative Decisions (Judicial Review) Act 1989 <lb/>(ACT) application to review a decision of the Australian Capital Territory Treasurer <lb/>under the Financial Management Act 1996 (ACT) to refuse an act of grace payment <lb/>of $200,000. The plaintiff had been attacked as a six year old in 2010 by a pit bull <lb/>terrier when he was visiting a tenant in a house managed by the Australian Capital <lb/>Territory Commissioner for Social Housing, and had suffered significant facial, head <lb/>and leg injuries. 152 In 2015, he unsuccessfully sued the Commissioner in the <lb/>Australian Capital Territory Supreme Court in negligence for compensation. 153 He <lb/>subsequently, in 2017, sought an act of grace payment. 154 Section 130 of the <lb/>Financial Management Act 1996 required the Treasurer to be satisfied of &apos;special <lb/>circumstances&apos; before authorising any payment and, in refusing the application, the <lb/>Treasurer reasoned: <lb/>In reading the decision of the Supreme Court, I noted that Justice Penfold <lb/>found that the Commissioner for Social Housing was not liable for the dog <lb/>involved in the attack and breached no duty of care to prevent the dog attack <lb/>on your client. Her Honour found that there were no steps the Commissioner <lb/>might have reasonably taken that could have prevented the attack. <lb/>Accordingly, pursuant to s 130 of the Financial Management Act 1996 I am <lb/>not satisfied that there are special circumstances to warrant authorising a <lb/>payment to your client and it is for this reason that I am declining your request. <lb/>I am sympathetic to the serious injuries that your client sustained, but they are <lb/>not the Commissioner&apos;s or the Territory&apos;s responsibility. 155 <lb/>The Treasurer&apos;s decision, unsurprisingly, did not survive judicial review. The <lb/>Supreme Court found that he had misconstrued the nature of the power under s 130 <lb/>because he had focused solely on the lack of legal liability; he had thus missed the <lb/>&apos;whole premise of an act of grace payment [as] an appeal to the Treasurer&apos;s goodwill <lb/>and moral conscience&apos;. 156 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>151 Ibid, quoting Women&apos;s Legal Service NSW, Submission No 108 to Senate Legal and Constitutional <lb/>Affairs References Committee, Parliament of Australia, Review of Government Compensation <lb/>Payments (2010) 3. <lb/>152 Hartigan (n 144) 335-8 [76]-[93]. <lb/>153 Hartigan v Commissioner for Social Housing (ACT) (2017) 319 FLR 158. <lb/>154 Boughey, Rock and Weeks (n 28) 319-20. <lb/>155 Hartigan (n 144) 326 [4]. <lb/>156 Ibid 331 [47] (McWilliam AsJ). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>80 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>III State and Territory Schemes <lb/>A <lb/>States <lb/>The potential problem for the states is that all of them bar Queensland either rely <lb/>exclusively on an inherent executive power to make discretionary act of grace <lb/>payments (Victoria, Tasmania and South Australia) or assert such a power in <lb/>addition to their statutory arrangements (Western Australia and New South <lb/>Wales). 157 Thus, if the constraints on the Commonwealth executive&apos;s expenditure <lb/>identified in Williams No 1 apply wholly or in part to the states, it can be powerfully <lb/>argued that many of the act of grace payments made by the states without statutory <lb/>support are unlawful. This Part sets out why it is probable that the strictures of <lb/>Williams No 1 apply to the states and then identifies the possible suspect and non-<lb/>suspect categories of state non-statutory act of grace payments. <lb/>1 <lb/>Why It Is Probable that Williams No 1 Applies to the States <lb/>The High Court has emphasised that Williams No 1 did not consider the spending <lb/>powers of the state executives, 158 and academic opinion as to whether its constraints <lb/>on executive spending apply to the states is divided. 159 On the one hand, it can be <lb/>argued that the limits on Commonwealth executive power to spend identified in <lb/>Williams No 1 were anchored in the text and structure of the Constitution, 160 and that <lb/>they therefore do not apply to the states, as there are no state equivalents to s 61 of <lb/>the Constitution, nor to s 81. 161 Moreover, while the Commonwealth Parliament is <lb/>a legislature conferred with limited, express heads of power, the state parliaments <lb/>are not. 162 However, we maintain that it is possible, even probable, that the <lb/>constraints on Commonwealth executive expenditure identified in Williams No 1 <lb/>will be applied wholly or in part to the states for the following reasons: <lb/>(1) The application of the High Court&apos;s reasoning in Williams No 1 to the state <lb/>executives would be consistent with what has been described as an <lb/>&apos;undertone&apos; 163 in the High Court&apos;s jurisprudence -since its 2010 decision <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>157 Western Australia distinguishes between &apos;act of grace payments&apos; under the Financial Management <lb/>Act 2006 (WA) and &apos;ex gratia payments&apos; made &apos;under non-statutory executive power&apos;: &apos;Treasurer&apos;s <lb/>Instruction 319: Act of Grace Payments&apos; in Treasury (WA), Financial Administration Bookcase <lb/>(Update 92, November 2023) (&apos;WA Treasurer&apos;s Instruction&apos;). By contrast, in New South Wales the <lb/>two terms are treated as interchangeable: NSW Treasury Circular (n 11). <lb/>158 Williams No 2 (n 7) 464 [64] (French CJ, Hayne, Kiefel, Bell and Keane JJ). <lb/>159 See, eg, Hanks, Gordon and Hill (n 83) 220, 236-7; Selena Bateman, &apos;Constitutional Dimensions of <lb/>State Executive Power: An Analysis of the Power to Contract and Spend&apos; (2015) 26(4) Public Law <lb/>Review 255. <lb/>160 Williams No 1 (n 5) 254 [206] (Hayne J). <lb/>161 With the arguable exception of WA: see Constitution Act 1889 (WA) s 64. However, in contrast to s <lb/>81 of the Constitution which is entrenched (and binds the Commonwealth Parliament), s 64 of the <lb/>Constitution Act 1889 is not entrenched. <lb/>162 Anne Twomey, &apos;Post-Williams Expenditure: When Can the Commonwealth Spend Public Money <lb/>without Parliamentary Authorisation?&apos; (2014) 33(1) University of Queensland Law Journal 9, 25. <lb/>163 Kathleen Foley, &apos;What is the Relevance of Williams and Plaintiff M61 for the Exercise of State <lb/>Executive Power?&apos; (2013) 36(2) University of Western Australia Law Review 168, 179. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>81 <lb/></page>

			<body>in Plaintiff M61/2010E v Commonwealth 164 -of &apos;concern … about the <lb/>dangers of unconstrained executive power&apos;. 165 <lb/>(2) The High Court&apos;s reasoning in Williams No 1, where it is based on the <lb/>requirement of representative and responsible government &apos;that the <lb/>Parliament, as the directly elected representative of the people, must have <lb/>control over the expenditure of money by the Executive&apos;, 166 may be applied <lb/>equally to the states. 167 <lb/>(3) The High Court&apos;s reasoning in Williams No 1, insofar as it is based &apos;on the <lb/>need to … enforce the federal division of powers established by the <lb/>Australian Constitution&apos;, 168 may be applied to the states. 169 Although the <lb/>Constitution is structured such that the means of enforcement of its federal <lb/>division of powers upon the Commonwealth is different from the means of <lb/>enforcement of that federal division upon the states, 170 it remains the case <lb/>that the Constitution must require both the states and the Commonwealth to <lb/>comply with that division. <lb/>(4) Given that the High Court in Williams No 1 found the &apos;natural person&apos; <lb/>analogy advanced by the Commonwealth unhelpful in delimiting the power <lb/>of the Commonwealth executive, it is likely that the Court would find any <lb/>submission that a state executive&apos;s powers to spend can be ascertained by <lb/>reference to a natural person&apos;s powers to spend similarly unhelpful. 171 <lb/>(5) The High Court&apos;s reasoning in Williams No 1 may be applied to the state <lb/>Legislative Councils in so far as that reasoning is protective of the role of the <lb/>Senate as an integral component of a bicameral legislature (in contrast to the <lb/>Senate&apos;s role as a &apos;states&apos; House&apos;, a role which is inapplicable to the state <lb/>Legislative Councils). 172 A fortiori as the existence of the state Legislative <lb/>Councils in all states except Queensland has been effectively entrenched by <lb/>means of s 6 of the Australia Acts 1986 (Cth and UK). 173 <lb/>(6) The argument that Commonwealth executive spending should be supported <lb/>by legislation, in contrast to an appropriation Act only -because &apos;the Senate <lb/>has limited powers to deal with an Appropriation Bill, whereas it has much <lb/>greater powers with respect to general legislation which might authorise the <lb/>executive to spend money in specific ways&apos; 174 -can be applied with equal <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>164 Plaintiff M61/2010E v Commonwealth (2010) 243 CLR 319. <lb/>165 Foley (n 163) 179. <lb/>166 Appleby and McDonald (n 17) 270. See Williams No 1 (n 5) 241 [173] (Hayne J). <lb/>167 Appleby and McDonald (n 17) 253. <lb/>168 W Bateman (n 20) 185. See Williams No 1 (n 5) 192-3 [37] (French CJ); Williams No 2 (n 7) 468-9 <lb/>[79]-[83] (French CJ, Hayne, Kiefel, Bell and Keane JJ). <lb/>169 Appleby and McDonald (n 17) 280. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">170 For example, the Commonwealth&apos;s legislative powers are directly conferred by the Constitution, <lb/>whereas the states enjoy the &apos;unexpressed residuary&apos; of legislative power; and s 109 gives <lb/>Commonwealth laws paramountcy over inconsistent state laws. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>171 Foley (n 163) 176, 178. <lb/>172 Williams No 1 (n 5) 205 [60] (French CJ), 232 [136] (Gummow and Bell JJ). <lb/>173 S Bateman (n 159) 269-70. <lb/>174 Williams No 1 (n 5) 205 [60] (French CJ). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>82 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>force to the South Australian and Tasmanian Legislative Councils, and with <lb/>even greater force to the Victorian and New South Wales Legislative <lb/>Councils. The restrictions on the South Australian and Tasmanian Legislative <lb/>Councils in relation to appropriation Bills are analogous to those imposed on <lb/>the Senate by s 53 of the Constitution. 175 The restrictions on the Victorian <lb/>and New South Wales Legislative Councils in relation to appropriation Bills <lb/>are significantly greater than those imposed on the Senate by s 53 of the <lb/>Constitution: in Victoria and New South Wales, appropriation Bills for the <lb/>ordinary annual services of government, which can include appropriation for <lb/>capital works and new policies, can be enacted without the respective <lb/>Legislative Council&apos;s agreement. 176 <lb/>(7) The High Court&apos;s reasoning in Williams No 1 -where it draws on the <lb/>fundamental constitutional principle that the executive does not have the <lb/>power to impose taxation (that is, just as the executive cannot levy tax without <lb/>legislation, it cannot spend the money raised by taxation without <lb/>legislation) 177 -can be applied equally to the state executives. <lb/>(8) The High Court&apos;s reasoning in Williams No 1 -where it draws a distinction <lb/>between, on the one hand, a natural person spending their &apos;&quot;own&quot; moneys&apos; 178 <lb/>and, on the other hand, the spending of &apos;public moneys&apos; 179 by the <lb/>Commonwealth executive -can be equally applied to the spending of public <lb/>moneys by the state executives. 180 <lb/>(9) The application of the High Court&apos;s reasoning in Williams No 1 to the state <lb/>executives may be characterised as another instance of an uncontroversial <lb/>principle that the text and structure of the Constitution imposes limitations on <lb/>state legislative and executive power, including implied limitations, such as <lb/>the implied freedom of political communication. It is also consistent with the <lb/>Court&apos;s rejection of the term &apos;plenary&apos; as an accurate description of any <lb/>executive or legislative power under the Constitution. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>175 Section 62(1) of the Constitution Act 1934 (SA) provides that the South Australian Legislative <lb/>Council cannot amend any &apos;money clause&apos;, which is defined in s 60(4) as &apos;a clause of a Bill, which <lb/>clause appropriates revenue or other public money, or deals with taxation, or provides for raising or <lb/>guaranteeing any loan or for the repayment of any loan&apos;. The Legislative Council can, however, under <lb/>s 62(2), &apos;return to the House of Assembly any Bill containing a money clause with a suggestion to <lb/>omit or amend such clause or to insert additional money clauses, or may send to the Assembly a Bill <lb/>containing suggested money clauses requesting, by message, that effect be given to the suggestion&apos;. <lb/>However, s 62(3) provides that s 62(2) &apos;applies to a money clause contained in an appropriation Bill <lb/>only when such a clause contains some provision appropriating revenue or other public money for <lb/>some purpose other than a previously authorised purpose or dealing with some matter other than the <lb/>appropriation of revenue or other public money&apos;. In Tasmania, s 42(1) of the Constitution Act 1934 <lb/>(Tas) provides that the Legislative Council &apos;may not amend … a provision of a Bill for an <lb/>Appropriation Act … to meet the cost of the ordinary annual services of the Government&apos; although <lb/>it may, under s 43(1) &apos;request, by message, the amendment of the Bill&apos;. <lb/>176 Constitution Act 1975 (Vic) ss 62, 64, 65; Constitution Act 1902 (NSW) s 5A. <lb/>177 Williams No 1 (n 5) 352 [519] (Crennan J). <lb/>178 Ibid 236 [151] (Gummow and Bell JJ), 241 [173] (Hayne J). <lb/>179 Ibid 236 [151] (Gummow and Bell JJ), 241 [173] (Hayne J), 368 [577] (Kiefel J). <lb/>180 Twomey (n 162) 9. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>
	  
	  <page>83 <lb/></page>

			<body>(10) Just as the High Court has recognised that the Constitution impliedly <lb/>attributes certain essential, entrenched characteristics to state courts, it may <lb/>recognise that the textual references to the state executives and parliaments <lb/>in the Constitution imply certain essential, entrenched characteristics, <lb/>including the characteristics of democratic representative and responsible <lb/>government such as parliamentary control over executive spending. <lb/>2 <lb/>Some Constitutional Problems if the Constraints Imposed by <lb/>Williams No 1 Are Applied to the State Executives <lb/>If we accept that the constraints on Commonwealth executive expenditure identified <lb/>in Williams No 1 might apply wholly or in part to the states, then the states that <lb/>persist in making non-statutory act of grace payments (that is, all states except <lb/>Queensland) may find themselves in some difficulty in upholding their commitment <lb/>to spend public money lawfully. Specifically: <lb/>(1) The ordinary functions exception is unlikely to cover all non-statutory act of <lb/>grace payments made by the states. 181 Of those States that have soft law <lb/>instruments regulating such payments (South Australia, Victoria and New <lb/>South Wales), 182 no reference is made in those instruments to the exception; <lb/>it can thus be inferred that payments are made without reference to it. In <lb/>Tasmania and Western Australia, in the absence of soft law instruments <lb/>(Western Australia having a soft law instrument in relation to its statutory act <lb/>of grace payment scheme, but no such instrument relating to its assertion of <lb/>the prerogative), 183 one is left to assume that non-statutory payments are also <lb/>made without reference to the exception. <lb/>(2) The prerogative exception is more promising for the states that persist in <lb/>making non-statutory act of grace payments, but it is also not without similar <lb/>difficulties to those faced by the Commonwealth. To reprise: if state act of <lb/>grace payments made without legislative support are made in the exercise of <lb/>a non-prerogative executive capacity to spend, then non-statutory act of grace <lb/>payments do not fall within the prerogative exception and are unlawful, <lb/>unless they fall within the ordinary functions exception; all other payments <lb/>are, in constitutional principle, illegal. Moreover, as was the case with the <lb/>Commonwealth, any putative prerogative executive power will be subject to <lb/>legal limits, including most likely a requirement that the state is under a moral <lb/>obligation to make a payment. <lb/>(3) Of the existing state soft law instruments regulating non-statutory act of grace <lb/>payments (that is, in South Australia, Victoria and New South Wales), only <lb/>the Victorian instrument refers to morality; 184 the New South Wales and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>181 Ibid 27. <lb/>182 Those instruments are Treasury (SA), Ex Gratia Payments (Treasurer&apos;s Instruction 14, July 2020) <lb/>(&apos;SA Treasurer&apos;s Instruction&apos;); Treasury (Vic), Disclosure of Ex Gratia Expenses (Financial <lb/>Reporting Direction 11, April 2022) [6.1] (emphasis added) (&apos;Victorian Treasurer&apos;s Direction&apos;) and <lb/>NSW Treasury Circular (n 11). <lb/>183 WA Treasurer&apos;s Instruction (n 157). <lb/>184 Victorian Treasurer&apos;s Direction (n 182) 6.1 (emphasis added). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>84 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>South Australian instruments 185 are devoid of any reference to it. This <lb/>increases the risk that act of grace decisions in New South Wales and South <lb/>Australia (as well as in Tasmania and Western Australia where there is no <lb/>soft law guidance at all) will be made unlawfully, and without jurisdiction, <lb/>on the basis that a relevant consideration of act of grace decision-making was <lb/>not considered. 186 <lb/>Finally, should the post-Pape constitutional framework be applied to the states, it <lb/>should be noted that the one area where the position of the states is fundamentally <lb/>different from that of the Commonwealth is in relation to legislative power. As <lb/>detailed in the previous Part, the Commonwealth must grapple with the complexities <lb/>of s 51(xxxix) and s 61 of the Constitution to place its act of grace payment schemes <lb/>on a statutory footing. The legislative powers of the state parliaments are not <lb/>constrained by heads of legislative power, and thus placing their act of grace <lb/>payment schemes on a statutory footing is less legally complicated. 187 If Victoria, <lb/>New South Wales, South Australia, Tasmania or Western Australia is reluctant to <lb/>contain its act of grace payments within a comprehensive statutory scheme, one <lb/>possible solution may be the enactment of a provision in similar terms to s 51(1) of <lb/>the Constitution of Queensland Act 2001 (Qld) which provides: &apos;The Executive <lb/>Government of the State of Queensland … has all the powers, and the legal capacity, <lb/>of an individual.&apos; If act of grace payments in the absence of statutory support are an <lb/>exercise of the prerogative executive power, then such a provision is not needed and <lb/>would not affect such payments. But if we are right, and they are an exercise of the <lb/>non-prerogative executive capacity, then such a provision may arguably provide <lb/>those payments with sufficient statutory authorisation to satisfy the requirements of <lb/>Williams No 1. 188 <lb/>B <lb/>Territories <lb/>In contrast to the unclear position in the Australian states, we maintain that the <lb/>constraints imposed by Williams No 1 on the Commonwealth executive must also <lb/>apply to the exercise of executive power in the Australian territories. <lb/>Constitutionally speaking (and in stark contrast to the constitutional autonomy of the <lb/>state executives), 189 the source of any territory executive power is Commonwealth <lb/>executive power, and the stream cannot rise higher than its source. Fortunately, both <lb/>of the self-governing Australian territories (that is, the Australian Capital Territory <lb/>and the Northern Territory) have made statutory provision for act of grace payments. <lb/>As mentioned earlier in our discussion of Hartigan, 190 s 130(1) of the <lb/>Financial Management Act 1996 empowers the Australian Capital Territory <lb/>Treasurer to authorise an act of grace payment &apos;[i]f the Treasurer considers it <lb/>appropriate to do so because of special circumstances … although the payment of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>185 NSW Treasury Circular (n 11); SA Treasurer&apos;s Instruction (n 182). <lb/>186 Craig v South Australia (1995) 184 CLR 163, 179. <lb/>187 Foley (n 163) 178-9. <lb/>188 Twomey (n 162) 27. <lb/>189 R v Governor of South Australia (1907) 4 CLR 1497. <lb/>190 See above Part II(C)(2)(c). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">2024] <lb/>ACT OF GRACE PAYMENTS AND THE CONSTITUTION <lb/></note>

			<page>85 <lb/></page>

			<body>that amount … would not otherwise be authorised by law or required to meet a legal <lb/>liability&apos;. The Northern Territory equivalent is s 37(1) of the Financial Management <lb/>Act 1995 (NT), which empowers the Northern Territory Treasurer to authorise an <lb/>act of grace payment &apos;[i]f the Treasurer is satisfied that, by reason of special <lb/>circumstances, it is proper to do so&apos;. Given that the Australian Capital Territory and <lb/>Northern Territory Legislative Assemblies each have &apos;power to make laws for the <lb/>peace, order and good government of the Territory&apos;, 191 both s 130(1) of the <lb/>Australian Capital Territory Act and s 37(1) of the Northern Territory Act are almost <lb/>certainly valid and hence sufficient to place act of grace payments in the Australian <lb/>Capital Territory and the Northern Territory on a constitutionally secure statutory <lb/>footing. <lb/>There are also relevant soft law instruments in each jurisdiction, namely <lb/>section 2 in part 6 of the Treasurer&apos;s Directions in the Northern Territory, and the <lb/>Act of Grace Payments: Policy and Procedures Guide (&apos;ACT Guide&apos;) in the <lb/>Australian Capital Territory. The Northern Territory Directions are skeletal, and <lb/>hence of little help to decision-makers. By contrast, the ACT Guide is much more <lb/>detailed (running to eight A4 pages in its pdf version) and hence more helpful. <lb/>Unfortunately, however, two of its paragraphs may mislead. <lb/>First, paragraph 23 of the ACT Guide repeats the advice in paragraph 9 of <lb/>RMG 401 that &apos;&quot;special circumstances&quot; and &quot;appropriate&quot; are not defined in the <lb/>[Act] and are for … the decision-maker to assess and decide on&apos;. Paragraph 23 of <lb/>the ACT Guide is thus vulnerable to the same criticism that was made previously of <lb/>paragraph 9 of RMG 401: it pays insufficient heed to Australian judicial supremacy <lb/>in the interpretation of the law. <lb/>Secondly, paragraph 27(c) of the ACT Guide states: <lb/>Act of grace payments may not be approved, for example: … when a request <lb/>has arisen from private circumstances outside the sphere of ACT <lb/>administration, there has been no involvement of an agent or ACT <lb/>Government employee or entity and the matter is not related to the impact of <lb/>any ACT legislation … <lb/>Analogously with the criticism made previously of paragraph 13 of RMG 401, this <lb/>statement risks misrepresenting the legal position for its non-legal audience. It is <lb/>hardly likely that a court would find a payment falling within paragraph 27(c) of the <lb/>ACT Guide to be legal: the slightly ambiguous word &apos;may&apos; should therefore be <lb/>hardened to &apos;must&apos;. By contrast s 37(2) of the Financial Management Act 1995 (NT) <lb/>adds, with commendable clarity: &apos;Subsection (1) does not authorise a payment of <lb/>money ex gratia unless the special circumstances arose in the course of the business <lb/>of the Government of the Territory.&apos; <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>191 Australian Capital Territory (Self-Government) Act 1988 (Cth) s 22; Northern Territory (Self-<lb/>Government) Act 1978 (Cth) s 6. Section 22(2) of the former adds that &apos;power to make laws extends <lb/>to the power to make laws with respect to the exercise of powers by the Executive&apos;. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>86 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">SYDNEY LAW REVIEW <lb/>[VOL 46(1):55 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <body>IV Conclusion <lb/>In his detailed analysis of public finance law in the United Kingdom and Australia, <lb/>Will Bateman has argued that the Australian High Court&apos;s early 21 st century attempts <lb/>to police &apos;the authority possessed by treasury departments over public <lb/>expenditure&apos; 192 has &apos;resoundingly failed&apos;. 193 This article, albeit confined as it is to <lb/>one narrow and somewhat arcane area of public expenditure, would suggest that <lb/>Bateman&apos;s conclusion might be too pessimistic and sweeping. At the very least, it <lb/>may distract attention from some of the specific &apos;ripples of affection&apos; of Pape and <lb/>the Williams cases. <lb/>This article has sought to identify some of those ripples of affection for the <lb/>ancient Crown practice of act of grace payments, which has been imported from one <lb/>constitutional universe, comprising an unwritten, unitary constitution, to another <lb/>constitutional universe, comprising a written, federal constitution. It concludes that: <lb/>• the Commonwealth&apos;s general statutory act of grace provision, s 65 of the <lb/>PGPA Act, should be read down with reference to Commonwealth executive <lb/>power under s 61 of the Constitution to ensure that it is sufficiently connected <lb/>to a head of Commonwealth legislative power (that is, s 51(xxxix) of the <lb/>Constitution); <lb/>• an explicit and unambiguous reference to the Commonwealth&apos;s non-statutory <lb/>CDDA Scheme should be included in the FF(SP) Regulations; <lb/>• the States of Victoria, New South Wales, South Australia, Tasmania and <lb/>Western Australia should enact legislation to provide statutory support for <lb/>their general act of grace payment schemes; and <lb/>• all Australian jurisdictions, including the self-governing territories of the <lb/>Australian Capital Territory and the Northern Territory, should ensure that <lb/>they have soft law instruments on act of grace decision-making which alert <lb/>decision-makers to the constitutional constraints which must limit and inform <lb/>their decisions. <lb/></body>

	<listBibl>192 W Bateman (n 20) 179. <lb/>193 Ibid 195. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>