<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Being Differently Black</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Mbali</forename>
          <surname>Khoza</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="sandfort">Johanna Sandfort</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-12-22T21:43:08.984Z">22/12/2025 21:43:08</date>
        <title>Review Luca</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.30958__ajha.12-4-5</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Athens Institute for Education and Research ATINER</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2025</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.30958/ajha.12-4-5</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Mbali Khoza. (2025). Being Differently Black. Athens Journal of Humanities &amp;amp; Arts, 12(4), 439. DOI: 10.30958/ajha.12-4-5</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-28T14:00:19.752716Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-28T14:00:19.752716Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-11-28T14:22:11.984Z" status="draft" who="#sandfort">
      <desc>Corrections Zwischenstand</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-06T09:35:14.591Z" status="draft" who="#sandfort">
      <desc>Corrections finished</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-22" status="checked" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Review</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
      <front>Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts -Volume 12, Issue 4, October 2025 -Pages 439-454 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.30958/ajha.12-4-5 <lb/>doi=10.30958/ajha.12-4-5 <lb/>Being Differently Black <lb/>By Mbali Khoza  <lb/>Difference has always been an interest of mine -the different gestures, methods <lb/>and materials utilised by various post-colonial artists to question authorial identity <lb/>and to &quot;speak&quot;. In my art practice these ideas are interrogated in relation to the <lb/>question &quot;What difference does it make who is speaking?&quot;. This question is intended <lb/>to expose the invisible mechanism of power that exists within authorship, raising <lb/>questions such as who determines who gets to speak, how they speak, what is <lb/>spoken about and who speaks on behalf of whom. <lb/></front>
      
      <body>Introduction <lb/>In 2014 the concept of &quot;difference&quot; played an integral role in helping me <lb/>conceptualise a performance work that I titled What Difference Does It Make Who <lb/>Is Speaking? I began making the work out of my interest in the lived experience of <lb/>foreign blacks who had immigrated to South Africa in search for a better life and <lb/>education. Central to this body of work was the politics of language, particularly <lb/>how it became utilised by black South Africans to justify Afrophobic 1 attacks <lb/>against black immigrants. For instance, black South Africans addressed others in <lb/>isiZulu to gauge whether someone was an immigrant. Immigrants&apos; inability to <lb/>speak the language often culminated in gruesome attacks, some of which resulted <lb/>in death. This tension between black South Africans and black immigrants became <lb/>a catalyst for another question: How does it feel to be what Charles I. Nero <lb/>describes as &quot;differently black&quot;? 2 Nero characterises &quot;differently black&quot; blacks as <lb/>being &quot;different&quot; from native-born blacks, the difference being that &quot;differently <lb/>black&quot; blacks are seen as &quot;good blacks&quot; by non-black South Africans. 3 They are <lb/>perceived to be &quot;harder working, smarter, and/or &apos;better&apos; than native-born blacks&quot;. 4 <lb/>To help me answer the question &quot;What does it mean to be &apos;different&apos;?&quot;, I began <lb/></body>
      
      <front> <lb/>Lecturer, Rhodes University, South Africa. <lb/></front>
      
      <listBibl>1. Rothney Tshaka defines Afrophobia as the &quot;fear of a specific other -the black other&quot;. <lb/>R. Tshaka, &quot;Afrophobia versus Xenophobia in South Africa,&quot; Unisa News &amp; Media, 15 <lb/>November 2016, https://www.unisa.ac.za/sites/corporate/default/News-&amp;-Media/Articles/ <lb/>Afrophobia-versus-xenophobia-in-South-Africa#:~:text=%E2%80%9CXenophobia%20i <lb/>s%20fear%20of%20the,north%20of%20the%20Limpopo%20River (accessed 2024). <lb/>2. C. I. Nero, &quot;Differently Black: The Fourth Great Migration and Black Catholic Saints in <lb/>Ramin Bahrani&apos;s Goodbye Solo and Jim Sheridan&apos;s In America,&quot; in Migrating the Black Body: The <lb/>African Diaspora Visual Culture (Eds.) Leigh Raiford and Heike Raphael-Hernandez (Seattle: <lb/>University of Washington Press, 2017), 208. <lb/>3. Ibid. <lb/>4. C. M. Greer, Black Ethnics: Race, Immigration, and the Pursuit of the American Dream <lb/>(New York: Oxford University Press, 2013), 520. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Khoza: &quot;Being&quot; Differently Black <lb/></note>
      
      <page>440 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>impromptu conversations with black immigrants from various African countries 5 <lb/>living in the Johannesburg CBD, Alexandra Township and the urban areas of <lb/>Gauteng province who has migrated to South African in the hope for a better life. I <lb/>began the conversations purely out of interest for their lived experiences in South <lb/>Africa as many of them were friends, neighbours and shop owners whom I saw <lb/>every day. These conversations became my research interest when I began on <lb/>working an undergraduate project centred around language, particularly English, 6 <lb/>and how African writers have grappled and continue to grapple with the limitations <lb/>of the English language. 7 I then extended my study to how black foreign Africans <lb/>learn 8 what has become South Africa&apos;s most spoken language: isiZulu. I chose to <lb/>record my conversations with five participants. I thought that more formal interviews <lb/>would water down what had begun as organic conversations. 9 <lb/>During our conversations, participants spoke candidly to me about why being <lb/>seen as &quot;different&quot; affected the manner in which they could occupy certain spaces <lb/>in South Africa, and what it was like to travel and live while being black and foreign <lb/>in South Africa. What I was able to ascertain from our conversations is how difficult <lb/>it was for them to migrate to South Africa and why for some of them returning <lb/>home was never too far from their thoughts. In his essay Reflecting on Exile, Edward <lb/>Said describes exile (whether internal or external, forced or by choice) as an <lb/>&quot;unhealable rift forced between a human being and a native place, between the self <lb/>and its true home: its essential sadness can never be surmounted&quot;. 10 Those who <lb/>expressed their desire to stay in South Africa, either because they wanted to or <lb/>because there was no prospect of returning home, remained conflicted about the <lb/>tensions between them and black South Africans, whether these could be overcome <lb/>or whether they would continue to threaten their livelihood. <lb/>The 2020 Afrophobic attacks 11 have shown that the current South African state <lb/></body>
      
      <note place="footnote">5. Angola, Benin, Democratic Republic of Congo, Senegal, Zambia and Zimbabwe. <lb/>6. It is worth noting that there are various iteration of the English language. The one I <lb/>am referring to was the British English. <lb/>7. The inability of English to punctuate the African experience like African languages do. <lb/>8. Some by choice and other my force. I do think it is only appropriate to learn the <lb/>language of any community you chose to live in. Studies have shown that language can <lb/>help create a sense of community. <lb/>9. I also wanted the participants to feel relaxed and confident to speak freely, without <lb/>feeling surveilled or under some kind of imposition from me. <lb/></note>
        
      <listBibl>10. E. W. Said, Reflections on Exile, and Other Literary and Cultural Essays (London: Granta, <lb/>2000), 482. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="footnote">11. Between March 2000 and 2008, 67 black foreigners were murdered. These black-<lb/>on-black attacks were spurred on by what at the time was described as &apos;xenophobia&apos;. The <lb/>term was used to describe some black South Africans&apos; disdain and violence toward black <lb/>foreigners from the continent. But many were weary of this narrative fabricated by the <lb/>media, claiming that some attacks were the results of existing tensions amongst Zimbabwean <lb/>nationals from Shona and Ndebele ethic groups. Nevertheless, what was clear is that it was <lb/></note>
      
      <note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>
      
      <page>441 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>has not done enough to find out why Afrophobia continues to display itself within <lb/>the black community. Further, it has not tried to educate black South Africans about <lb/>the contribution of black Africans to the liberation struggle, which included <lb/>accommodating black South Africans during their years in exile. However, this does <lb/>not necessarily mean one should ignore what Nero has observed: that the conflict <lb/>between black foreigners and black South Africans has been exacerbated by how <lb/>black foreigners are perceived by non-black South Africans. Hence they are often <lb/>treated far better than native-born blacks: considered to have a better work ethic, <lb/>they are given first preference for employment. 12 <lb/>What Afrophobia in South Africa has brought to the fore is that blackness is <lb/>not monolithic but is a complex phenomenon. More importantly, it has shown that <lb/>racial solidarity is not a given. As such, it has forced black communities on the <lb/>continent and in the diaspora to think critically about what they share &quot;besides <lb/>colour&quot; and whether we could reach a point where there can be a racial coalition. 13 <lb/>The Power of Language and the Language of Power <lb/>My interest in the foreign black experiences, was particular, I was drawn to <lb/>conversations in and around language, as language was one of the many reasons <lb/>that some black South Africans offered to justify their Afrophobia. I began to <lb/>examine what black African foreigners thought about black South Africans who <lb/>insisted that if they wanted to live in South Africa then they should learn to speak <lb/>at least one of the eleven official languages, isiZulu being the operative language. This <lb/>prerequisite, ironically, is not enforced on white immigrants. In my conversations, <lb/>most immigrants expressed their desire to learn some South African languages but <lb/>wanted to do so on their own terms: they were willing to learn the language, <lb/>bearing in mind that doing so would make it easier for them to move around and <lb/>speak and relate to black South Africans. But others questioned why they were <lb/>being forced to learn isiZulu when there are ten other official languages, including <lb/>seTswana, Tshivenda, isiXhosa and Xitsonga, 14 available to them. Upon reflecting on <lb/>the individual dialogues I had with participants, I eventually came to the conclusion <lb/>that it is debatable whether language can solve Afrophobia. For instance, according <lb/>to the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, &quot;indigenous <lb/></body>
      
      <note place="footnote">black-on-black violence. The term &apos;Afrophobia&apos; specifies that it is conflict between black <lb/>Africans. <lb/>12. This plays a particular role considering that many black South Africans, especially <lb/>unskilled workers, receive very low wages and are often exploited by employers. For <lb/>example, domestic workers and farm workers, especially in rural areas, often receive wages <lb/>significantly lower than the minimum wage stipulated by the government. <lb/></note>
        
      <listBibl>13. Greer, Black Ethnics: Race, Immigration, and the Pursuit of the American Dream, 2. <lb/></listBibl>
        
      <note place="footnote">14. Others are seSotho, Afrikaans and English. <lb/></note>
      
      <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Khoza: &quot;Being&quot; Differently Black <lb/></note>
      
      <page>442 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>languages matter for development, peace building and reconciliation.&quot; 15 Although I <lb/>can see how community language learning can help reconcile native-born blacks <lb/>and foreign blacks, 16 Afrophobia as Tshaka has pointed out is much more <lb/>complicated than that. What does need to be addressed is what he calls the &quot;fear&quot; <lb/>of the &quot;black other&quot;, a by-product of Apartheid laws that restricted black South <lb/>Africans&apos; mobility across the continent, isolating them from other African nations <lb/>and by so doing cultivating a culture of fear towards black African foreigners. This <lb/>begs the questions: How can black South Africans overcome this fear? <lb/>Debates concerning language are not new in South Africa. They can be traced <lb/>back to the 1976 Soweto uprising when black students protested against the Bantu <lb/>Education Act of 1953. This act was deliberately designed to limit the socio-<lb/>economic status of black people by imposing Afrikaans as medium of instruction <lb/>for all South Africans. This unfinished conversation reared its head again in the <lb/>2015-2016 #AfrikaansMustFall protests spearheaded yet again by black students at <lb/>the universities of Stellenbosch and Pretoria. Part of the #RhodesMustFall movement, <lb/>which demanded the decolonization of university curricula, it insisted that Afrikaans <lb/>be replaced by English, British English to be extract, as a more accessible language <lb/>of instruction. However, the shift from one oppressive language to another rather <lb/>than the use of indigenous languages has shown that the project of black <lb/>emancipation remains unfinished. The British English language, I would like to <lb/>argue, performs a second erasure. <lb/>To help think about how British English has a visceral impact on black <lb/>Africans, I began researching black literature and scholarship, with the aim of finding <lb/>out how black authors were grappling with having to write and document black <lb/>lived experiences in British English. My research led to the novella The House of Hunger <lb/>(1978), written by the Zimbabwean author Dambudzo Marechera. For Marechera, The <lb/>House of Hunger is a metaphor for how what was then Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe) <lb/>manifested itself in a condition of alienation and double consciousness. 17 As Laurice <lb/>Taitz quotes Marechera, &quot;The House has now become my mind; and I did not like <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>15. K. Brits, R. Kaschula, and Z. Docrat, &quot;Integrating Languages Should Form Part of <lb/>South Africa&apos;s Xenophobia Solutions,&quot; The Conversation, 2 June 2020, https://theconversation. <lb/>com/integrating-languages-should-form-part-of-south-africas-xenophobia-solutions-137526. <lb/>16. Linguist Siti Nurhasanah&apos;s research on community language learning, a methodology <lb/>used by psychologists to improve &quot;communicative intent&quot; in classrooms, has shown that when <lb/>the teacher used the community language to &quot;propose[…] some topics then [the students] could <lb/>explore deeply, they felt enjoyable to express their ideas&quot;. Siti Nurhasanah, &quot;The Use of <lb/>Community Language Learning Method to Increase the Students&apos; Participation in Classroom <lb/>Conversation,&quot; Register, 8, no. 1 (2015), 84, 94). In a similar manner, learning a native language <lb/>can help foreigners immerse and integrate themselves into South African society. <lb/>17. . Taitz, &quot;Knocking on the Door of the House of Hunger: Fracturing Narratives and <lb/>Disordering Identity,&quot; in Emerging Perspectives on Dambudzo Marechera (Eds.) Flora Viet-Wild <lb/>and Anthony Chennelles (Trenton: African World Press, 1999), 2. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>
      
      <page>443 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>the way the roof is rattling&quot;. 18 By equating his mind to the &quot;House,&quot; to a metaphor <lb/>for not only Rhodesia but also the house in which he was raised, Marechera places <lb/>emphasis on his inability to escape it. He comes to the realization that the &quot;House&quot; <lb/>is not just physical but also psychological. <lb/>On his use of the British English language, Marechera writes: &quot;Shona was part <lb/>of the ghetto demon I was trying to escape […] This perhaps is in the undergrowth <lb/>of my experimental use of English, standing it on its head&quot;. 19 In agreement with <lb/>Marechera is African American writer Ntozake Shange who writes: &quot;I cant count the <lb/>number of times I have viscerally wanted to attack deform n maim the language <lb/>that I waz taught to hate myself in&quot;. 20 <lb/>In her essay &quot;Apostrophe, Animation and Abortion&quot;, Barbara Johnson proposes <lb/>the notion of the &quot;rhetorical figure&quot;. 21 She defines the &quot;rhetorical&quot; as &quot;language that <lb/>says one thing and means another&quot;. 22 She describes it as a &quot;device&quot; that is synonymous <lb/>with a voice, 23 which she then equates with the rhetorical device of the apostrophe. 24 <lb/>The apostrophe, according to the Merriam-Webster dictionary, is &quot;the addressing of a <lb/>usually absent person or a usually personified thing rhetorically&quot;. 25 Or in Johnson&apos;s <lb/>words, it is a &quot;direct address of an absent, dead, or inanimate being by a first-person <lb/>speaking&quot;. 26 If the apostrophe is a tool the writer uses to make inanimate objects <lb/>animate, like &quot;The House&quot;, Marechera and Shange metaphorically visualize the <lb/>British English language as an individual, which they can attack, disfigure, <lb/>dismember and reassemble to serve their own purpose. The perceptions of English <lb/>which Marechera and Shange share seem in line with Slavoj Zizek&apos;s definition of <lb/>the superego, which he defines as &quot;a traumatic voice, an intruder persecuting us <lb/>and disturbing our psychic balance&quot;. 27 <lb/>The choice to write in an African language is often a choice for obscurity and <lb/>a renunciation of the international limelight that writing in English, French or <lb/>Portuguese could offer the writer. 28 As cited in the introduction, the mother tongue <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>18. Ibid, 24. <lb/>19. Quoted in C. Hart, &quot;A Post-Modern at the Margin: Innovations in Dambudzo <lb/>Marecheraʼs Texts,&quot; in Moving Spirit: The Legacy of Dambudzo Marechera in the 21stCentury <lb/>(Eds.) Julie Cairnie and Dobrota Pucherova (Münster: LIT Verlag, 2012), 137. <lb/>20. Quoted in ibid, 137. <lb/>21. B. Johnson, &quot;Apostrophe, Animation and Abortion,&quot; Diacritics 16, no. 1 (1986), 28-47. <lb/>22. Ibid, 29. <lb/>23. In this context it is an aliterary voice which could either be the writer&apos;s, the narrator&apos;s <lb/>or the character&apos;s voice. <lb/>24. Johnson, &quot;Apostrophe, Animation and Abortion,&quot; 29. <lb/>25, Merriam-Webster Dictionary, &quot;Apostrophe,&quot; https://www.merriam-webster.com/ <lb/>dictionary/apostrophe, (accessed 2024). <lb/>26. Johnson, &quot;Apostrophe, Animation and Abortion,&quot; 30. <lb/>27. S. Zizek, The Metastases of Enjoyment: Six Essays on Women and Causality (London: <lb/>Verso, 2005), 57. <lb/>28. P. Mlama, &quot;Creating in the Mother Tongue,&quot; in The Mongue and Mother Tongue: <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Khoza: &quot;Being&quot; Differently Black <lb/></note>
      
      <page>444 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>serves as a constant reminder of one&apos;s culture, which Ngũgĩ wa Thiong&apos;o believes <lb/>the African writer risks losing as &quot;an image of their word&quot; if they choose to write <lb/>in the foreign tongue. 29 In Penina Mlama&apos;s opinion, writers who chose to do so <lb/>&quot;belong to a class of writers who are willing to take a risk, who respond to the <lb/>challenges posed by the realities of our African society today&quot;. 30 One of these <lb/>challenges is that the English, French and Portuguese have become legitimized as <lb/>languages of communication in most postcolonial countries in Africa, as is the case <lb/>in South Africa, where English is considered one of the official languages. This is no <lb/>coincidence, posits Neville Alexander, who highlights how the language of the <lb/>oppressor (English in addition to Afrikaans) &quot;became the language of aspiration and <lb/>eventually the language of national unity and of liberation for the black elite&quot;. 31 In <lb/>addition, Wa Thiong&apos;o observes that <lb/>
      
      European languages were seen as having a capacity to unite African peoples against <lb/>divisive tendencies inherent in the multiplicity of African languages with the same <lb/>geographic state. 32 <lb/>Once these European languages were accepted as languages of communication <lb/>the next step was the written format. This is how African writers began to write in <lb/>these European languages. However, Wa Thiong&apos;o finds this problematic in that <lb/>by writing in the &quot;foreign tongue&quot; the &quot;African writer&quot; enriches these languages <lb/>rather than enriching the mother tongue, leaving it to &quot;rot&quot;. In support of Wa <lb/>Thiong&apos;o, Frantz Fanon emphasizes the importance of language by stating: <lb/>To speak means to be in a position to use a certain syntax, to grasp the morphology of <lb/>this or that language, but it means above all to assume a culture, to support the weight <lb/>of a civilization. 33 <lb/>This implies that the African writer is forced to perform what Bill Ashcroft <lb/>describes as a &quot;linguistic structure or code which can be described by the colonial <lb/>distinction of &apos;standard&apos; and &apos;variant&apos;&quot;. 34 These are factors that are embedded or <lb/></body><listBibl>African Literature and the Perpetual Quest for Identity African (Eds.) Pamela J. Olubumi Smith <lb/>and Daniel P. Kunene (Trenton: World Press, 2002), 11. <lb/>29. N. Wa Thiongʼo, Decolonizing the Mind: The Politics of Language in African Literature <lb/>(Nairobi: East African Educational Publishers KL, 1986), 11. <lb/>30. Mlama, &quot;Creating in the Mother Tongue,&quot; 11. <lb/>31. N. Alexander, &quot;After Apartheid: The Language Question,&quot; in After Apartheid: <lb/>Reinventing South Africa? (Eds.) Ian Shapiro and Kahreen Tebeau (Charlottesville: University of <lb/>Virginia Press, 2011), 312. <lb/>32. Wa Thiongʼo, Decolonizing the Mind: The Politics of Language in African Literature, 285. <lb/>33. F. Fanon, Black Skin White Masks (Trans.) Charles Lam Markmann (London: Pluto <lb/>Press, 2008), 8. <lb/>34. B. Ashcroft, &quot;Constitutive Graphonomy,&quot; in The Post-colonial Studies Reader (Eds.) <lb/>Bill Ashcroft, Gareth Griffiths, and Helen Tiffin (New York: Routledge, 1995), 300. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>
      
      <page>445 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>carried within the language that the &quot;African writer&quot; can fall victim to. However, <lb/>what we see in Marechera&apos;s work is that the postcolonial African writers <lb/>appropriate the language as a strategy to escape these structures. Fanon supports <lb/>the claims of Mlama and Wa Thiong&apos;o that language is a carrier of the experience <lb/>of one&apos;s culture; and this is the power of language. But can this experience only be <lb/>expressed through one&apos;s mother tongue? What happens when thoughts cannot be <lb/>expressed in the mother tongue? Lewis Nkosi explains that whatever the language <lb/>of choice, the writer cannot escape this problem: <lb/>In a way, any writer always falls short of his true ideal: his struggle with his materials, <lb/>the attempt to wrestle from language the true meaning of the world he seeks to depict, <lb/>is always endless and incomplete. Incomplete, because in describing the true <lb/>lineaments of what the writer sees with his inner eye language can only approximate <lb/>the shapes and figures of his imagination. In this respect, therefore, the situation of the <lb/>African writer is not unique. It is the same struggle with language. 35 <lb/>The predicament of a bilingual writer is then how to express or evoke the <lb/>experience of the mother tongue when writing in the foreign tongue. James McGuire <lb/>proposes that for the bilingual writer to write, they must experience what he describes <lb/>as the &quot;freedom of linguistic exile&quot;, and only then can they truly write. 36 This <lb/>separation allows the writer room to express writing &quot;between a double existence&quot;, <lb/>that is, a characteristic of a postcolonial writer who is a &quot;self translator&quot;. 37 As self <lb/>translators, there is the opportunity for writers to become acquainted with the <lb/>abundance of English as a language or the various English&apos;s that can be spoken. It <lb/>is during this period that they can simultaneously experiment 38 with the language <lb/>while having to contend with the precarious sociopolitical nature of the language. <lb/>Writers can now begin to focus their attention on what is spoken; 39 or, as Nkosi <lb/>explains, they can become analytical about the &quot;shapes and figures of&quot; their <lb/>&quot;imagination&quot;. To achieve this style of writing, writes Njabulo Ndebele in his essay <lb/>&quot;Defining South African Literature for a New Nation&quot;, black writers would need <lb/>to free themselves from &quot;white writing&quot;. 40 A characteristic he uses to described <lb/>white South African writers is their tendency to write about &quot;what happened to the <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>35. L. Nkosi, Tasks and Masks: Themes and Styles of African Literature (Harlow: Longman, <lb/>1981), 6. <lb/>36. J. McGuire, &quot;Forked Tongues, Marginal Bodies: Writing as Translation,&quot; in The Tongue <lb/>and Mother Tongue: African Literature and the Perpetual Quest for Identity African (Eds.) Pamela J. <lb/>Olubumi Smith and Daniel P. Kunene (Trenton: World Press, 2002), 74. <lb/>37. McGuire, &quot;Forked Tongues, Marginal Bodies: Writing as Translation,&quot; 81. <lb/>38. By breaking it, as Shange and Marechera have demonstrated. <lb/>39. It can be stylized, as Shange has shown. <lb/>40. N. Ndebele, &quot;Defining South African Literature for a New Nation,&quot; in The Subversive <lb/>Imagination: Artists, Society and Social Responsibility (London: Routledge, 1994), 153. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Khoza: &quot;Being&quot; Differently Black <lb/></note>
      
      <page>446 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>&apos;Others&apos;&quot;. 41 And as a result they have produced &quot;a literature of what we have done <lb/>to others, how it has affected them, and how it may have affected us&quot;. 42 For <lb/>Ndebele, this was yet another method of white writers to exert their dominance <lb/>over the &quot;Others&quot;. Progressive artistic development for black writers, Ndebele <lb/>explains, needs to free itself from this &quot;crisis&quot;, 43 especially given that they are entering <lb/>a &quot;New world&quot;: the end of apartheid and the beginning of a post-apartheid South <lb/>Africa. The success of this &quot;new&quot; writing strategy, at least for Ndebele, could be <lb/>determined by writers&apos; abilities to demonstrate a deep understanding of the <lb/>intellectual and sociological condition of the new South Africa as well as its &quot;cultural <lb/>future&quot;. 44 <lb/>Differences that Matter <lb/>The solo exhibition What Difference Does It Make Who Is Speaking? (13 May-2 June <lb/>2016) at the Point of Order, University of Witwatersrand, was a rigorous extension <lb/>of my interest in language and difference that I began in 2011. I envisioned the <lb/>gallery as a studio space, one I could work in every day from Monday to Friday. In <lb/>it I produced work, took part in a series of interventions and held film screenings. <lb/>Each of these gestures was intentional. I spent my time thinking deeply about my <lb/>practice, the material that will be used to express my ideas through visual languages, <lb/>and what research-led practice could look like. I also used this time to reflect on the <lb/>question(s) I was posing. I created an environment where I could revisit art works <lb/>displayed in the space and rework them, or as the collective of the Center of <lb/>Historical Reenactments (CHR) would say, &quot;re-chew&quot; them. <lb/>Most of the artworks were text based, others were sonic or videos. There were <lb/>film works written and produced by me and collections of texts by other authors <lb/>that I remixed and made new. I considered many of the projects as collaborative <lb/>works with artists, scholars and creative practitioners who, knowing and <lb/>unknowing, contributed to the making of the artworks. This has always been my <lb/>approach to making, one that is in alignment with the conceptual art hypothesis of <lb/>the 1960s that was critical of traditionalist 45 ways of making. Salah M. Hassan and <lb/>Olu Oguibe describe the goals of conceptual art as &quot;intentional acts and interventions <lb/>in which artists elected or rejected certain forms or strategies in art making and in the <lb/>process revised received understandings of the nature and essence of art&quot;. 46 A <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>41. Ibid, 149. <lb/>42. Ibid. <lb/>43. Ibid, 152. <lb/>44. Ibid. <lb/>45. By that I mean painting, sculpture, drawing and printmaking. <lb/>46. S. M. Hassan and O. Oguibe, &quot;&apos;Authentic/Ex-Centric&apos; at the Venice Biennale: African <lb/>Conceptualism in Global Contexts,&quot; African Arts 34, no. 4 (2001), 10. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>
      
      <page>447 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>crucial part of these interventions was the ability to wrestle with a myriad of crises <lb/>as a bilingual art practitioner. Fundamentally, my concern was what was spoken <lb/>and for whom. With each intervention, I began to muse over the blues the English <lb/>language has induced in individuals whose mother tongue is not English. I became <lb/>interested in the strategies that one can employ to break and stretch the language for <lb/>my own personal use while still being critical of it is as a sociological phenomenon. <lb/>Each of these textual artworks was intentionally made to awaken provocations <lb/>about the condition of the English language with the hope that viewers/readers <lb/>would reflect on their relationship with the language. <lb/>Bilingual Blues: A Collaboration with Sujata Bhatt (Figure 1) examines how bilingual <lb/>speakers wrestle with living in two worlds, one in which they are expected to <lb/>prioritize speaking or writing the English language over their mother tongue. A <lb/>Yoruba Proverb (Figure 2) demonstrates how meaning can be in lost in translation. <lb/>The Slow Sound of the Tongue (Figure 3) explores the anxiety-educing feelings that <lb/>might be evoked when one tries to speak a new language or a language one is <lb/>expected to know. <lb/>Figure 1a. Mbali Khoza &quot;Bilingual Blues: A Collaboration with Sujata Bhatt&quot;, 2016. Paper <lb/>and magnifying glass, dimensions vary <lb/></body>
      
      <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Khoza: &quot;Being&quot; Differently Black <lb/></note>
      
      <page>448 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>Figure 1b. Mbali Khoza, &quot;Bilingual Blues: A Collaboration with Sujata Bhatt&quot;, 2016. Paper <lb/>and magnifying glass, dimensions vary <lb/>Figure 2. Mbali Khoza, &quot;A Yoruba Proverb&quot;, 2016. Ink on paper, 40 x 40 cm <lb/></body>
      
      <note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>
      
      <page>449 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>Figure 3. Mbali Khoza, &quot;The Slow Sound of the Tongue&quot;, 2016. Text on A4 paper <lb/>So You Want to Learn the Language? A Fanakalo Pronunciation Guide. A Collaboration <lb/>with Abri de Swardt (Figure 4) is an artwork in which alphabet cue cards are shown <lb/>to the viewer in a video accompanied by a voice-over by artist Abri de Swardt who <lb/>then explains to listeners how certain alphabets function and are pronounced in <lb/>Fanakalo language. The wall text Untitled (I Thought We Had This Conversation in 1976) <lb/>(Figure 5), written on the wall by a commissioned sign writer, makes reference to <lb/>signs made by students during the 2015 #FeesMustFall protests in South Africa. <lb/>My intentions was to create a parallel with the 1976 Soweto protest in an attempt <lb/>to spotlight what I perceived to be the failure of the Rainbow nation to decolonize <lb/>anti-black institutions. Context 4 and 4.1: A Collaboration with Adrian Piper (Figure 6) <lb/>invited viewers to respond to a series of questions as an attempt to shift their role <lb/>from spectators to participants and co-authors. Their responses facilitated a <lb/>dialogue between each other. More importantly, I hoped it would help dismantle <lb/>the long-standing hierarchical relationship between artist, space and audience. <lb/>Central to each work is the notion of difference, what it may look like and how <lb/>it may operate, and how in turn it may affect individuals&apos; perceptions of themselves, <lb/></body>
      
      <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Khoza: &quot;Being&quot; Differently Black <lb/></note>
      
      <page>450 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>others and their behaviour. Yet, at the same time how it may unify communities as <lb/>it is this encounter with difference that makes us realise how unique we are as a <lb/>society. That is why, in my opinion, we should be critical of myths and institutions <lb/>that want to eradicate these differences, replacing them with homogenous <lb/>identities. This is a mistaken effort to erase differences that matter. <lb/>
      
      Figure 4. Mbali Khoza, &quot;A Fanakalo Pronunciation Guide. A Collaboration with Abri de <lb/>Swardt&quot;, 2016. Video <lb/>Figure 5. Mbali Khoza, &quot;Untitled (I Thought We Had this Conversation in 1976)&quot;, 2016. <lb/>Text on wall <lb/></body>
      
      <note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>
      
      <page>451 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>Figure 6a. Mbali Khoza, &quot;Context 4 and 4.1: A Collaboration with Adrian Piper&quot;, 2016. <lb/>Dimensions variable <lb/>Figure 6b. Mbali Khoza, &quot;Context 4 and 4.1: A Collaboration with Adrian Piper&quot;, 2016. <lb/>Dimensions variable <lb/></body>
      
      <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Khoza: &quot;Being&quot; Differently Black <lb/></note>
      
      <page>452 <lb/></page>
      
      <body>Figure 6c. Mbali Khoza, &quot;Context 4 and 4.1: A Collaboration with Adrian Piper&quot;, 2016. <lb/>Dimensions variable <lb/>
      
      While the question of difference is a key component of this paper, another is <lb/>the shared kinship amongst English speakers whose mother tongue is not English. <lb/>I am interested in how these speakers exert power over the language and what it <lb/>means to come to terms with the language&apos;s imperial identity. From Marechera&apos;s, <lb/>Shange&apos;s, Nkosi&apos;s and my own explorations of the countless decolonial techniques <lb/>that can be deployed to alter the English language for our own needs I hope we can <lb/>take away that a language of power can not only manifest itself differently but that <lb/>it could be a crucial characteristic of black liberatory literary culture. <lb/></body>
      
      <listBibl>Bibliography <lb/>Alexander, Neville. &quot;After Apartheid: The Language Question.&quot; In After Apartheid: <lb/>Reinventing South Africa?, edited by Ian Shapiro and Kahreen Tebeau. Charlottesville: <lb/>University of Virginia Press, 2011, 311-331. <lb/>Ashcroft, Bill. &quot;Constitutive Graphonomy.&quot; In The Post-colonial Studies Reader, edited by Bill <lb/>Ashcroft, Gareth Griffiths and Hellen Tiffin. New York: Routledge, 1995, 298-302. <lb/>Fanon, Frantz. Black Skin White Masks. Translated by Charles Lam Markmann. London: <lb/>Pluto Press, 2008. <lb/>Greer, M. Christina. Black Ethnics: Race, Immigration, and the Pursuit of the American Dream. <lb/>New York: Oxford University Press, 2013. <lb/>Hart, Carolyn. &quot;A Post-Modern at the Margin: Innovations in Dambudzo Marecheraʼs <lb/>Texts.&quot; In Moving Spirit: The Legacy of Dambudzo Marechera in the 21st Century, edited <lb/>by Julie Cairnie and Dobrota Pucherova. Münster: LIT Verlag, 2012, 133-140. <lb/>Hassan, Salah M., and Olu Oguibe. &quot;&apos;Authentic/Ex-Centric&apos; at the Venice Biennale: <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Athens Journal of Humanities &amp; Arts <lb/>October 2025 <lb/></note>
      
      <page>453 <lb/></page>
      
      <listBibl>African Conceptualism in Global Contexts.&quot; African Arts 34, no. 4 (2001): 64-75. <lb/>McGuire, James. &quot;Forked Tongues, Marginal Bodies: Writing as Translation.&quot; In The <lb/>Tongue and Mother Tongue: African Literature and the Perpetual Quest for Identity African, <lb/>edited by Pamela J. Olubumi Smith and Daneil P. Kunene. Trenton: World Press, <lb/>2002, 75-86. <lb/>Mlama, Penina. &quot;Creating in the Mother Tongue.&quot; In The Tongue and Mother Tongue: <lb/>African Literature and the Perpetual Quest for Identity African, edited by Pamela J. <lb/>Olubumi Smith and Daneil P. Kunene. Trenton: World Press, 2002, 9-18. <lb/>Ndebele, Ndebele. &quot;Defining South African Literature for a New Nation.&quot; In The Subversive <lb/>Imagination Artists, Society and Social Responsibility. London: Routledge, 1994, 148-153. <lb/>Nero, Iames Charles. &quot;Differently Black: The Fourth Great Migration and Black Catholic <lb/>Saints in Ramin Bahrani&apos;s Goodbye Solo and Jim Sheridan&apos;s In America.&quot; In Migrating <lb/>the Black Body: The African Diaspora Visual Culture, edited by Leigh Raiford and Heiki <lb/>Raphael-Hernandez. Seattle: University of Washington Press, 2017, 207-220. <lb/>Nkosi, Lewis. Tasks and Masks: Themes and Styles of African Literature. Harlow: Longman, 1981. <lb/>Said, W. Eward. Reflections on Exile, and Other Literary and Cultural Essays. London: Granta, <lb/>2000. <lb/>Taitz, Laurice. &quot;Knocking on the Door of the House of Hunger: Fracturing Narratives <lb/>and Disordering Identity.&quot; In Emerging Perspectives on Dambudzo Marechera, edited <lb/>by F. Viet-Wild and A. Chennelles. Trenton: African World Press, 1999, 23-42. <lb/>Tshaka, Rothney. &quot;Afrophobia versus Xenophobia in South Africa&quot;. Unisa News &amp; <lb/>Media, 15 November 2016. https://www.unisa.ac.za/sites/corporate/default/News-<lb/>&amp;-Media/Articles/Afrophobia-versus-xenophobia-in-South-<lb/>Africa#:~:text=%E2%80%9CXenophobia%20is%20fear%20of%20the,north%20of% <lb/>20the%20Limpopo%20River (accessed 2024). <lb/>Wa Thiongʼo, Ngũgĩ. Decolonizing the Mind: The Politics of Language in African Literature. <lb/>Nairobi: East African Educational Publishers KL, 1986. <lb/>Zizek, Slavoj. The Metastases of Enjoyment: Six Essays on Women and Causality. London: <lb/>Verso, 2005. <lb/></listBibl>
      
      <note place="headnote">Vol. 12, No. 4 <lb/>Khoza: &quot;Being&quot; Differently Black <lb/></note>
      
      <page>454 </page>

	</text>

  </TEI>