<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Legal Aspects of Australia’s Commercial Relationship With Taiwan</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Andrew</forename>
          <surname>Godwin</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="sandfort">Johanna Sandfort</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T10:36:18.684Z">30/01/2026 11:36:18</date>
        <title>finalized</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.53300__001c.5220</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Bond University</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">1992</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.53300/001c.5220</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Andrew Godwin. (1992). Legal Aspects of Australia’s Commercial Relationship With Taiwan. Bond Law Review, 4(1), None. DOI: 10.53300/001c.5220</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T14:46:45.917425Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-19T14:46:45.917425Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-29T08:30:40.649Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-29T10:00:01.150Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-12T20:44:03.365Z" status="draft" who="#sandfort">
      <desc>Second pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-15T17:45:03.126Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-21T15:16:09.706Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T10:35:55.564Z" status="approved" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T10:36:35.584Z" status="approved" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Bond Law Review <lb/>Volume 4 | Issue 1 <lb/>Article 3 <lb/>1992 <lb/>Legal Aspects of Australia&apos; s Commercial <lb/>Relationship With Taiwan <lb/>Andrew Godwin <lb/>Follow this and additional works at: http://epublications.bond.edu.au/blr <lb/>This Article is brought to you by the Faculty of Law at ePublications@bond. It has been accepted for inclusion in Bond Law Review by an authorized <lb/>administrator of ePublications@bond. For more information, please contact Bond University&apos;s Repository Coordinator. <lb/>Legal Aspects of Australia&apos; s Commercial Relationship With Taiwan <lb/>Abstract <lb/>[extract] More difficult to comprehend, however, is the unconventional way in which the trading relationship <lb/>has developed and the low profile, at least on an official level, which Taiwan maintains in Australia. Moreover, <lb/>the difficulty increases when an attempt is made to understand the official view that Taiwan does not <lb/>constitute a &apos;country&apos; itself but forms a part of that country which is popularly known as China. How is this <lb/>view reconcilable with what appears to be objective reality, namely that Taiwan operates as an independent <lb/>sovereign state whose separate identity is reflected in the fact that it is referred to as Taiwan and not China? <lb/>This paper considers the legal aspects of Australia&apos;s commercial relations with Taiwan. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>commerce, Taiwan, Australia, international law <lb/>Cover Page Footnote <lb/>The writer wishes to acknowledge the kind assistance given by Professor Malcolm Smith and Professor <lb/>Michael Pryles in the preparation of this paper. <lb/>This article is available in Bond Law Review: http://epublications.bond.edu.au/blr/vol4/iss1/3 <lb/>LEGAL ASPECTS OF <lb/>AUSTRALIA&apos;S COMMERCIAL <lb/>RELATiONSHiP WiTH TA[WAN <lb/>By <lb/>Andrew <lb/>Article Clerk <lb/>Minter E[Jison <lb/></front>

			<body>As one of the &apos;four dragons&apos; of Asia, ~ Taiwan occupies an enviable position <lb/>as one of the strongest and wealthiest economies in the region. The amount <lb/>of its foreign reserves is second only to Japan and it has a formidable <lb/>spending power in the international market of trade and investment. That <lb/>Taiwan should have become such an important trading partner and source of <lb/>investment to countries such as Australia is not difficult to comprehend? <lb/>More difficult to comprehend, however, is the unconventional way in which <lb/>the trading relationship has developed and the low profile, at least on an <lb/>official level, which Taiwan maln~s in Australia. Moreover, the difficulty <lb/>increases when an attempt is made to understand the official view that <lb/>Taiwan does not constitute a &apos;country&apos; itself but forms a part of that country <lb/>which is popularly known as China. How is this view reconcilable with what <lb/>appears to be objective reality, namely that Taiwan operates as an <lb/>independent sovereign state whose separate identity is reflected in the fact <lb/>that it is referred to as Taiwan and not China? <lb/>This paper considers t_he legal aspects of Australia&apos;s commercial relations <lb/>with Taiwan. Three broad objectives are targetted. The f~rst objective is to <lb/>identify the historical reasons for the unofficial nature of relations between <lb/>Australia and Taiwan and the rationale behind the official view that Taiwan <lb/>is not a sovereign state but a province of China. This requires a consideration <lb/>of Taiwan&apos;s historical development and the status of Taiwan under <lb/>international law. This is the subject of the second part of this paper. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 <lb/>2 <lb/></note>

		<front>The writer wishes to acknowledge the kind assistance given by Professor Malcolm Smith <lb/>and Professor Michael Pryles in the preparafi~ of this paper. <lb/></front>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">The countries constituting the &apos;four dragons&apos; of Asia are South Korea, Hong Kong, <lb/>Singapore and Taiwan. <lb/>Trade between Austrafia and Taiwan has tripled in the last decade and is now worth <lb/>about $3.5 billien a year. This has made Taiwan Australia&apos;s sixth largest export market, <lb/>ahead of the United Kingdom, Hong Kong, Germany and the People&apos;s Republic of China. <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>Although the issue of Taiwan&apos;s status under international law has its roots <lb/>in historic!l events that occurred over forty years ago, it is also necessary to <lb/>consider the issue in light of recent pofifical developments in Taiwan. These <lb/>developments will have a major impact on the future of Taiwan and are <lb/>considered in part three. <lb/>The second objective of this paper is to identify the legal problems caused <lb/>by Taiwan&apos;s status as an u~ognized state. On an international level, this <lb/>requires a consideration of any restrictions which international law might <lb/>impose on Australia&apos;s dealings with Taiwan in view of the fact that Taiwan is <lb/>regarded as a territory of China. It also requires a consideration of the <lb/>foreign affairs policies that the Federal Government has adop~ with respect <lb/>to its relations with the People&apos;s Republic of China (PRC). This is the subject <lb/>of part 4. On a domestic level, the question of the legal problems caused by <lb/>Australia&apos;s non-recognition of Taiwan requires a consideration of the effect <lb/>of Taiwan&apos;s stares in domestic courts. This is the subject of part 5. <lb/>The third objective of this paper is to consider the measures that the <lb/>Australian Government has adopted to overcome the legal problems caused <lb/>by Taiwan&apos;s status as an unrecognized state. In this regard, the main focus <lb/>is on the enactment and operation of the Foreign Corporations <lb/>(Application of Laws) Ace 1989 (Cth). This Act is examined in part 6 and is <lb/>compared with the approach that other countries have adopted with respect <lb/>to Taiwan (part 7). <lb/>Although many of the legal issues raised in this paper are hypothetical in <lb/>the sense that they are not based on problems that have occurred in reality, it <lb/>is highly likely that such issues will arise in future in view of the exponential <lb/>growth in Australia&apos;s commercial relations with Taiwan. In some respects, <lb/>the success with which the Austral~n Government has managed to develop <lb/>commercial relations within the framework of nonrecognition has meant <lb/>that, up to this point in time, a direct consideration of many of these issues <lb/>has been conveniently postponed. However, on the assumption that many of <lb/>these issues will arise, it is appropriate to identify them and to consider the <lb/>best way in which they can be resolved. This is the main purpose of this <lb/>paper. <lb/>The Status Of Taiwan Under International taw <lb/>If the proposition that Taiwan is an independent sovereign state is to be <lb/>denied, it is necessary to determine the status of Taiwan under international <lb/>law and the impact of ~t status on its ability to operate in the international <lb/>forum. The issue of Taiwan&apos;s status under international law has been debated <lb/>for over forty years without any conclusive resolution. Many commentators <lb/>have participated in this debate and some differ radically in their views. <lb/>of the views hinge on various interpretations of historical events, the true <lb/>significance of which is often unclear. What is clear, however, is that <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Australia&apos;s CommerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>subsequent developments, in tx~th domestic and world affairs, are continually <lb/>undermining the premises on which these interpretations are based. <lb/>Before the views of these commentators are examined, it may be useful to <lb/>state the official view adopted by the rival governments of China and Taiwan <lb/>with respect to the status of Taiwan. The official view of these governments <lb/>a view that is reflected in the foreign affairs policies of virtually all <lb/>countries -is that Taiwan is a province of a greater China that comprises the <lb/>territory commonly referred to as &apos;mainland China&apos; and the territory <lb/>commonly referred to as &apos;Taiwan&apos;? Thus the debate between these two <lb/>governments centres not on the status of Taiwan but on the identity of the <lb/>government that has legitimate sovereignty over the greater China. <lb/>However, notwithstanding the wish of these governments to treat Taiwan <lb/>as an inseparable part of a greater China, the evidence that Taiwan <lb/>constitutes a part of Chinese territory is by no means conclusive under <lb/>international law o <lb/>Perhaps the easiest way to examine the diversity of views concerning t.he <lb/>legal status of Taiwan is to consider chronologically the historical events <lb/>upon which the various commentators have relied in reaching their <lb/>conclusions. Of essence is the tvae nature of the relationship between China <lb/>and Taiwan as territories and the validity of the claims of the effective <lb/>governments on those two territories. <lb/>Taiwan can only be said to have been a formal province of China for the <lb/>eight years between 1887, when it was officially made into a province by the <lb/>Qing Dynasty, and 1895 when it was ceded to Japan by the Treaty of <lb/>Shimonoseki? In the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries it was probably <lb/>regarded by the Chinese Emperor as a tributary sh-ailar to such countries as <lb/>Thailand and Burma ~ and it provided the destination for many dissidents <lb/>fleeing main~d China. In fact, eighteen years after the Qing Dynasty was <lb/>established in 1644, the son of the defeated ruler of the Ming Dynasty, <lb/>Koxinga, led the remnants of his forces to Taiwan and expelled the Dutch <lb/>who had established settlements there in the early years of the seventeenth <lb/>century. Although nominal Chinese authority over Taiwan was asserted in <lb/>1683, the Qing Court did v~mally nothing to govern or develop Taiwan. 6 In <lb/>fact, as far as Chinese officials were concerned, a posting on Taiwan was <lb/>tantamount to banishment or punishment for dereliction of duty. 7 In any <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">The rut1 area of q&apos;aiwan&apos; includes the island of Taiwan, the Pescad~res and the offshore <lb/>islands of Quemoy and Matsuo <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>The Treaty of Shimonoseki, by which Taiwan ~nd the Pescadores were ceded to Japan, <lb/>was signed by the government of the Ching Dynasty after the Sino-Japanese War of <lb/>1894. <lb/>See C~en LC m&apos;~d Reisman W H Who Owns Taiw~: A Search for International Title&apos; <lb/>(1972) 81 gale Law Journal 599, 608. <lb/>Poid. <lb/>See Leng S Taiwan. China&apos;s Last Frontier (1991) as quoted in Far Eastern Economic <lb/>Review (Heng Kong) 9 May 1991, 34. <lb/></listBibl>
		  
		  <page>43 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 E~ND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>event, regardless of the extent of China&apos;s sovereignty over Taiwan both <lb/>before and after 1887, it is clear that sovereignty passed to Japan in 1895. <lb/>In 1941, the year in which war was declared between China and Japan, the <lb/>Nationalist Government of the Republic of China (as it was then called) <lb/>unilaterally repudiated the Treaty of Shimonoseki. The present government <lb/>of China has relied on this action in asserting that sovereignty over Taiwan <lb/>reverted to China in 1941o&apos; This assertion has been widely criticised as an <lb/>incorrect interpretation of international law. Kirkham, for example, states <lb/>that under international law a state cannot merely by unilateral declaration <lb/>regain rights of sovereignty which it has formally ceded by Treaty? In <lb/>addition, the view that the provisions of Treaties concluded between states <lb/>are not ipso facto annulled by the outbreak of war is well supported by the <lb/>authorities. 1°T <lb/>he second event on which some commentators have relied to prove the <lb/>transfer of sovereignty from Japan to China was Japan&apos;s surrender at the end <lb/>of World War 11o By its instrument of surrender, Japan accepted the <lb/>provisions of the Potsdam Proclamation, made by the Allied Powers on 26 <lb/>July 1945. The Potsdam Proclamation was an affirmation of the Cairo <lb/>Declaration, made in 1943, under which the Allied Powers declared that it <lb/>was their intention, after Japan&apos;s defeat, to restore to China all territories <lb/>which Japan had stolen, such as Manchm~ia, Taiwan and the Pescadores. tl <lb/>2&quot;he argument is that t~he provisions of the Cairo and Potsdam declarations <lb/>operated either to transfer sovereignty over Taiwan from Japan to China 12 or <lb/>to estop the pa~es to the declarations from denying that sovereignty would <lb/>ultimately vest in China2 ~ The problem with this argument is that there is a <lb/>presumption under international law that the formal cession of territory after <lb/>war requires a Peace Treaty°&quot; Furthermore, the Japanese surrender was not a <lb/>definitive renunciation of the territories but a commitment to renounce them <lb/>in the Treaty of Peace? ~ Thus, there is a strong basis for the argument that <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>8 See Jain JP&quot;Tbe Legal Status of Formosa&apos; (1963) 57 American Journal of International <lb/>Law 16,44. See also CbJu H (ed)China and the Taiwan Issue (t979) 165. <lb/>9 See Kirkham D B &apos;The International Legal Status of Formosa&apos; (t968) 6 Canadian <lb/>Yearbook of lnterna¢ional Law 144, 147. <lb/>10 See Oppertheim L International Law (7th ed Lauterpacht H.) (1952) 304 as quoted in <lb/>Chiu op cit n 8 t66. <lb/>11 Upon Japan&apos;s surrender, the Allied Powers authorised the ROC Government to accept the <lb/>surrender of Taiwan a~nd the Pescadores. See Chert a~nd Reisman,op cit n 5,611. <lb/>12 This is the view that has previously been adopted by both the PRC and the ROC <lb/>govermnents. See Crawford J The Creation of States at International Law (1979) 14~5o <lb/>13 See Chiu op cit n 8 164. <lb/>14 See Crawford, op cit 147 and O&apos;Covme~l D P &quot;r~be Status of Formosa and the Chinese <lb/>Recognition Problem&apos; (1956) 50 American Jov,-nal of International Law 405, 407. Chiu <lb/>questions this viewpoint, arguing that unless there are stipulatiens in the Peace Treaty to <lb/>the contrary, conquered territory remains in the hands of the possessor. This, he argues, is <lb/>an application of the principle of Uti possidetis (as you possess, you shall continue to <lb/>possess): Chiu, op cit 162. <lb/>15 See Wright Q &apos;The Chinese Recognition Problem&apos; (1955) 49 American Journal of <lb/>International Law 320, 322. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s ComrnerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>Japan retained formal sovereignty over Taiwan until the Peace Treaty in <lb/>1951o 16 <lb/>The third event in which the question of sovereignty arises is the <lb/>Communist victory over the Nationa~sts in 1949 and the establishment of <lb/>the People&apos;s Republic of China on 1 October 1949. It was this event that <lb/>forced the Nationalists to retreat to Taiwan to establish a provisional <lb/>government of the RepuNic of China27 The contention made by the PRC <lb/>Government is that, as the successor government to the RepuNic of China, it <lb/>could lay claim to all of the territories occupied by the ROC Government, <lb/>including Taiwan. However, as has been explained above, formal Japanese <lb/>sovereignty over Taiwan was not relinquished until 1951 and it was only <lb/>then that occupation by another state for the purpose of acquiring <lb/>sovereignty over terra delicta becea~ne relevant. And, by t.his time, the PRC <lb/>could no longer claim succession through the ROC authorities on Taiwanol&apos; <lb/>Ironically, it was by no means certain in 1949 that a Peace Treaty with <lb/>Japan woutd be necessary to settle the question of sovereignty over Taiwan. <lb/>In January 1950, President Truman stated that the Allies had accepted the <lb/>exercise of Chinese authority over the island and there is evidence to suggest <lb/>that America intended to abandon the Nationalist regime to the planned <lb/>invasion of Taiwan by the PRCo 19 However, the situation changed radically <lb/>when the Korean war broke out in June 1950 and Traman dispatched the <lb/>Seventh Fleet into the Taiwan Strait, declaring the &apos;neutralization of <lb/>Formosa&apos; in order to stem the threat from Communist China. Aware of the <lb/>strategic importance of Taiwan, Truman stated that &apos;the determination of the <lb/>future status of Taiwan must await the restoration of security in the Pacific, a <lb/>peace settlement with Japan, or consideration by the United Nations? <lb/>°The <lb/>formal Peace Treaty between 48 Atlied Powers and Japan was <lb/>entered into on 8 September 1951 and came into force on 28 April 1952o 21 <lb/>By Article 2(6) of the Treaty, Japan renounced &apos;all right, title and claim to <lb/>Formosa&apos;. However, the Treaty was silent on the question of to whom <lb/>sovereignty passed and did not employ the &apos;usual terminology of <lb/>international conveyance&apos;o ~ In 1952, a similar treaty was concluded between <lb/>Japan and the Republic of China Government on Taiwan? 3 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>16 <lb/>The argument that Japan retained sovereignty until the Peace Treaty is disputed by one <lb/>writer who argues that since the sovereignty of the USSR over Sakhalin is undisputed, <lb/>the ROC&apos;s de facto sovereignty over Taiwan shoutd be sL~51arty undisputed: Chou D S <lb/>&apos;The International Status of the Republic of China&apos; (t986) Chinese Yearbook of&quot; <lb/>International Law and Affairs 161,162. The island of Sakhalin was one of the territories <lb/>that Japa~n relinquished along with Taiwan. <lb/>17 <lb/>On 8 December 1949, the Nationalists established the Republic of China (ROC) on <lb/>Taiwan. <lb/>18 <lb/>See Chiu op cit n 8, 615. <lb/>19 <lb/>See Kerr G H Formosa Betrayed (1976) 386. <lb/>20 Chert and Reisman op cit n 5, 615. <lb/>21 <lb/>136 United Nations Treaty Series 45. <lb/>22 O&apos;ConneLl op cit n 14 409. <lb/>23 <lb/>This treaty was also silent on the question of sovereignty. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>45 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>Whatever the ainty surrounding Taiwan&apos;s legal status under international lawo <lb/>Crawford suggests that a possible effect of Japan&apos; s relinquishment under the <lb/>Peace Treaty was to re-vest sovereignty in China as a &apos;state&apos; without <lb/>specifically determining the government entitled to exercise that <lb/>sovereignty o z The conclusion of this writer is that Taiwan&apos;s status is that of a <lb/>consolidated local &amp;facto government in a civil war situation. 26 <lb/>Other commentators argue that Taiwan became terra nullius upon Japan&apos;s <lb/>relinquishment of sovereignty and therefore susceptible of appropriation by <lb/>the ROC authorities on the basis of occupation. Kirkham, for example, <lb/>argues: <lb/>Because Taiwan became terra nullius only after the Peace Treaty of 1952, the <lb/>first authority to exercise contro! over Taiwan after the Peace Treaty was no <lb/>longer the gover~ment of China, notwithstanding its pretentions to that effect. <lb/>Thus Taiwan was not annexed to China and Chiang [Kai-shek] could not amnex <lb/>Taiwan in the name of Cbfina (because he did not represent China)..oChiang has <lb/>since shown his control over this independent territory to be effective and <lb/>permanent, and at least acquiesced in by the people of the islando Under such <lb/>circumstances, Chiang Kai-shek&apos;s government must be regarded (under <lb/>international law) as the govermn~ent of the sovereign state of Formosa? 7 <lb/>Kirksham further argues that because international law is concerned with <lb/>objective criteria, and not with unrealistic claims by various regimes, the <lb/>assertion by the Nationalist regime of sovereignty over mainland China <lb/>cannot change its legal status. In other words, the continued existence of <lb/>Taiwan as a_n independent territory, with its own de facto goverranent, has <lb/>converted Taiwan into a sovereign entity in the eyes of international law o <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>24 <lb/>It has been sugges~.d ~hat many states, adopting the correct legal position, assumed that <lb/>the mason bebSnd the omission was to afford an opportunity to deal with this question in <lb/>accordance with the UN Charter, taking into consideration the principle of self-<lb/>determination and the expressed desire of the inhabitants of Taiwan: Chert and Reisman <lb/>op cit n 5, 643. <lb/>25 <lb/>Crawford op cit n 12, 148. <lb/>26 [bid 151. <lb/>27 Kirkham op cit n 9, 153. See also O&apos;Connell op cit n 14, 414, who argues that the theory <lb/>of acquisition by occupation is the most imherently consistent in any anatysis of the <lb/>Taiwan situation. However, Crawford op cit n 12, 148, argues that the Japanese <lb/>relinquishment conld not have left Taiwan terra nullius since after 1952, as before, the <lb/>istand contined to be controlled by an effective, organised government. Chert and <lb/>Reisman, op cit n 5, 640, regard the issue as a moot question on the basis that peremptory <lb/>international norms (.ius cogens) would have termJnated the concept of terra nullius in <lb/>international law as regards any populated territory. <lb/>28 <lb/>Kiflcham op cit n 9, 154. On the other hand, O&apos;Co~meL!, op cit n 14, 4t5, argues that since <lb/>a government is only recognised for what it claims to be, the Nationgfist Government <lb/>cannot be recognised as the government of the independent State of Taiwan as it refuses <lb/>to be recognised as such. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s CommerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>In conclusion, it is submitted t~hat Taiwan must be regarded, at the very <lb/>least, as a de facto entity with international personality. ~ This view~oint <lb/>accords with the international taw definition of statehood as reflected in <lb/>Article 1 of the Montivideo Convention on the Rights and Duties of States <lb/>under which the qualifications for statehood are (a) a permanent population; <lb/>(b) a defined territory; (c) a government; and (d) capacity to enter into <lb/>relations with other states. ~ It also accords with the practice of many states <lb/>to regard Taiwan as a de facto sovereign state, notwithstanding the official <lb/>position that it is a province of China and the refusal to recognize the <lb/>government of Taiwan21 <lb/>However sound the above argument appears, the analysis of Taiwaffs true <lb/>status under international law would not be complete without mentioning the <lb/>view, persuasively argued by Chen and Reisman in 1972, that the <lb/>international legal title of Taiwan is suspended and that this position will <lb/>continue until there is substantial conformity to international norms of <lb/>territorial sovereignty¢ 2 The argument proceeds on the basis that the <lb/>Nationalist Government of Taiwan was itself an invading force which cannot <lb/>be regarded as representing the true wishes of the people of Taiwan until its <lb/>legitimacy is fully confirmed by democratic processes. However, the <lb/>political situation in Taiwan has changed drarnatically in the nineteen years <lb/>since Chen and Reisman wrote their article. These changes, and their <lb/>implications for Taiwan&apos;s future, are briefly examined in the next chapter. <lb/>Recent Political Developments <lb/>Whilst a detaited analysis of Taiwan&apos;s recent political development is beyond <lb/>the scope of this paper, this part will examine several political developments <lb/>in the last few years. These developments are significant because they have <lb/>important ramifications for Taiwan&apos;s future and the role t.hat international <lb/>law will play in resolving certain issues. They also demand a re-assessment <lb/>of many of the grounds upon which the above views concerning Taiwan&apos;s <lb/>status under international law are based. <lb/>Prior to 1986, Taiwan was a one-party state with political power firmly in <lb/>the hands of the Nationalist Party or Kuomintang (ICMT)o Opposition parties <lb/>were banned under martial law and political dissent was suppressed by <lb/>repressive anti-sedition laws which were collectively referred to as the <lb/>&apos;Temporary Provisions for the Suppression of Communist Insurgency&apos;, These <lb/>provisions were regarded as necessary in order to suppress both communist <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>29 This is supported by one writer who argues that this approach provides the best basis on <lb/>which Taiwan&apos;s future is to be determined: Li, V Ho &apos;The Legal Status and Political <lb/>Future of Taiwan after Normalisation&apos; in Starr JB (ed) The Future of US-China Relations <lb/>(1981) Ch 4, 225 and 247. <lb/>30 (1933) 49 Stat 3097 T S 881. <lb/>31 The refusal to recognise the Taipei Government is now even less relevant in Australia <lb/>due to the change in recognition policy. See text infra at n 73. <lb/>32 One of these norms is the principle of the rights of non self-goverefing peopteo See Chen <lb/>and Reisrnan op cit n 5 654. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>47 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 8OND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>sympathizers and also those who advocated an independent Taiwan -a <lb/>concept that was, and still is, anathema to the ruling K M T party2 3 A strict <lb/>policy prohibited official contact with the government of mainland China <lb/>and was known as the &quot;three Nos&apos; policy: no contact, no negotiations and no <lb/>compromise. The refusal of the Nationalist Government to have any contact <lb/>with Beijing, let alone recognize its existence, was a reflection of the official <lb/>state of war that existed between the two governments. <lb/>The first sign of change appeared in 1986 when the first opposition party <lb/>the Democratic Progressive Party o was formed and was allowed to <lb/>participate in the elections held in December of t~hat year. This was followed <lb/>by the lifting of martial Law in 1987 and the transfer of the Presidency to LeT <lb/>eng-hui, the first native Taiwanese to hold the position, after the death of <lb/>President Chiang Ching-kuo in 198824 On 1 May 1991, President Lee <lb/>signed a decree terminating the period of communist rebellion on the <lb/>mainland and repealed the &apos;Temporary Provisions&apos;. In doing so, Lee <lb/>acknowledged officially for the first time the existence of the communist <lb/>government in Beijing25 While the desire to facilitate indirect trade bevcceen <lb/>Taiwan and China, estimated at US$4 billion in 1990, ~ was clearly a factor <lb/>in the decision to repea! the &apos;Temporary Provisions*, an equally relevant <lb/>factor was the need to bring policy into line with reality? &apos; In addition, it was <lb/>an important step in the KMT&apos;s constitutional reform package, of which <lb/>constitutional democracy was seen as the ultimate goalo 3g These <lb/>developments are significant in two respects. Firstly, they strengthen Taipei&apos;s <lb/>claim to legitimacy against the argument that the Government has no <lb/>sovereignty over Taiwan because it does not represent the wishes of the <lb/>people2 ~ Secondly, to the extent that Taipei has abandoned its hopes of <lb/>unifying China by force, it is no longer appropriate to refer to Taipei as a <lb/>&apos;con~lidated local government in a civil war context&apos; <lb/>°The <lb/>recent political developments in Taiwan have had a signkficant impact <lb/>on the ways in which Taiwan is viewed by other countries. They also have <lb/>important ramifications for Taiwan&apos;s future. Most commentators, echoing the <lb/>official line in both Beijing and Taipei, have regarded the effects of the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>33 The desire of the valing KMT party to regain control of the malrdand is reflected in t~he <lb/>fact that the capital in Taipei was only ever established as a provisional capital. <lb/>34 President Lee was formally inaugurated in May 1990. <lb/>35 See Far Eastern Economic Review (Hong Keng), 9 May 1991, 8. <lb/>36 See the trade statistics in Far Eastern Economic Review (Hong Kong), 6 June 1991, 40. <lb/>37 See the Editorial Age (Melbourne), 2 May 1991. <lb/>38 The constitutional reforms provide a basis for the establishment of fully representative <lb/>government by catty !993. For a summary of these reforms, see Taiwan Update <lb/>(Canberra), May 1991. <lb/>39 TNs is the argument put forward by Chert and Reisman op cit n 5, 654. <lb/>40 This is the phrase used by Crawford op cit n 12 t51. Note, however, that Taiwan&apos;s <lb/>Premier, Hau Peitsun, has said that an official state of war v~A1 continue to exist between <lb/>China and Taiwan until a formal ceasefire agreement is signed with China: Far Eascern <lb/>Economic Review (Heng Kong), 28 February 199!, 13. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<body>developments as moving Taiwan closer to reunification with the mainland. &apos;1 <lb/>However, an equally plausible interpretation of the effect of these <lb/>developments is that the foundation is laid for an independent Taiwano <lb/>Although such an outcome conflicts with the avowed intentions of the KMT <lb/>Government, it cannot be discounted as a possibility in the future, a <lb/>possibility that becomes more likely when the difficulties associated with <lb/>reunification are taken into account. Both Taipei and Beijing have different <lb/>views about how reunification will take place. Beijing offers its &apos;one country, <lb/>two systems&apos; formula along the lines worked out for Hong Kong after 1997. <lb/>Taipei&apos;s response is that this is unacceptable because it relegates Taiwan to <lb/>the status of a local government and that reunification can only take place <lb/>wi~in a democratic framework. President Lee has reiterated that even direct <lb/>investment will not occur until Beijing meets certain conditions such as <lb/>democratization and economic liberalization on the mainland, the <lb/>renunciation of the use of force against Taiwan and the cessation of its <lb/>attempts to isolate Taiwan in international affairs? 2 However, it is highly <lb/>unlikely that Beijing will relax its pressure on Taiwan and dispense witch the <lb/>option of using force in the event that &apos;foreign interference&apos; occurs in <lb/>Taiwano &apos;3 Moreover, the calts for independence among supporters of the <lb/>opposition party and young people are becoming stronger.&quot; <lb/>Foreign Relations <lb/>On 22 December 1972, Australia announced that it had recognized the PRC <lb/>and severed relations wi~ the Republic of China on Taiwan? s The decisions <lb/>to recognize the PRC followed closely on the heels of the election of the <lb/>Australian Labor Party (ALP) on 4 December 1972. It was the culmination <lb/>of a review of Australia&apos;s China policy which had been initiated by the <lb/>previous government in 1971 after the PRC was admitted to the United <lb/>Nations, replacing the ROC as the China representative. The pressure to <lb/>recognize the PRC intensified in earty 1972 after President Nixon&apos;s visit to <lb/>China and the signing of a joint communique between China and the US in <lb/>Shanghai on 28 February 1972. This was the fLrst step in the normalization <lb/>of relations between China and the United States. Although the US did not <lb/>formally recognize the PRC until 1979, it acknowledged in the joint <lb/>communique that &apos;all Chinese on either side of the Taiwan Strait maintain <lb/>that there is but one China and that Taiwan is part of China. &quot;4 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 See q&apos;aiwan Visit to Beijing Breaks 43-Year Ice&apos; Age (Melbourne), 30 April 1991. In this <lb/>article, the writer cerements that &apos;It]he way is now open for talks between Taiwan and <lb/>China on direct ~-ade, and eventually, on reunification&apos;. <lb/>42 See &apos;Strait Talk&apos; Free China Review (Taipei), Januar~ 1991,t0. <lb/>43 By &apos;foreign interference&apos;, Beijing presumably means any foreign assistance that pushes <lb/>Taiwan towards kndependenceo <lb/>44 Recently, moves to amend the Constitution have been opposed by students demanding a <lb/>new Constitution that effectively renounces the Govermment&apos;s sovereignty over atl of <lb/>China except Taiwano See Fa~r Eastern Econorrdc Review (l-long Kong), 2 May 1991,20. <lb/>45 See &apos;Australia recognises China&apos; Canberra Times (Canberra), 23 December 1972, 1. <lb/>46 For the full text of the Shanghai Communique, see Lasater, ML, The Taiwan Issue in <lb/>S ino-American Strategic Relations (1984) 253. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 8OND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>The commitment of the Whitlam Government to recognize the PRC had <lb/>been part of the platform on which the ALP had run its election campaign in <lb/>1972. 47 The only factor which prevented the immediate establishment of <lb/>diplomatic relations after the election was the time needed to reach <lb/>agreement on the wording of the joint communique between Australia and <lb/>the PRC. The Chinese were keen to adopt a formula by which Australia <lb/>recognized the PRC&apos;s full sovereignty over Taiwan. The Australian <lb/>Government, on the other hand, was reluctant to make such a concession, <lb/>particularly in view of the firm relations which Australia had previously <lb/>maintained with the ROC and the importance of trade with Taiwan. In the <lb/>end, the following formula was adopted: <lb/>The Australian Goverm&apos;rtent recognizes the Government of the PRC as the sole <lb/>legal government of China and acknowledges the position of the Chinese <lb/>Government that Taiwan is a province of the PRCo <lb/>Such a formula is one of severn formulae that have been adopted by other <lb/>countries. At one end of the range, there is the formula that does not mention <lb/>Taiwan at all but merely recognizes Beijing as the sole legal government of <lb/>China ~ At the other end is the Maldives formula: <lb/>The Goverpanent of Maldives recognizes that the Govermn~ent of the PRC is the <lb/>sole legal government of China and that Taiwan is an inalienable part of the <lb/>territory of the PRC. <lb/>Between these extremes is the formula adopted by Australia and other <lb/>variations such as the Canadian formula by which Canada &apos;takes note of <lb/>Beijing&apos;s position that Taiwan is an inalienable part of the territory of the <lb/>PRC&apos;, and the Japanese formula by which Japan &apos;understands and respects&apos; <lb/>Beijing&apos;s position? 9 <lb/>With respect to the joint communique between Australia and the PRC, the <lb/>extent to which Australia recognizes Beijing&apos;s claim to sovereignty over <lb/>Taiwan clearly depends on an interpretation of the word &apos;acknowledges&apos;. <lb/>Furthermore, what is acknowledged is Beijing&apos;s &apos;position&apos; that Taiwan is a <lb/>province of China. Thus, a valid interpretation of the wording used is that <lb/>Australia neither accepts Beijing&apos;s position that Taiwan is a province of <lb/>China nor recognizes that Taiwan is a province of China. The only <lb/>commitment that Australia gives is to take into account Beijing&apos;s view of any <lb/>dealings between Australia and Taiwan in deference to its acknowledgment <lb/>of Beijing&apos;s position in this regard. ~ The Chinese version, however, uses the <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>47 <lb/>48 <lb/>49 <lb/>50 <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>50 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <listBibl>See Fung ESK and MacKerras C From Fear to Friendship-Australia&apos;s Policies toward <lb/>the PRC 1966-]982 (1985) 157. <lb/>This was the forrnula adopted by Austria and Ireland. <lb/>For a summary of the various formulae, see Shen L &apos;The Taiwan Issue in Peking&apos;s <lb/>Foreign Relations in the 1970&apos;s: A Systematic Review (1981) I Chinese Yearbook of <lb/>International Law and Affairs 74, 77. <lb/>~s is the view of the Deparkment of Foreign Affairs and Trade as revealed to the writer <lb/>of this paper in an interview in February 1991. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s CommerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>same word (chengren) for the translation of the words &apos;recognize&apos; and <lb/>&apos;acknowledge&apos;. &apos;1 Although &apos;chengren&apos; may mean either &apos;recognize&apos; or <lb/>&apos;acknowledge&apos;, the use of the word for &apos;acknowledge&apos; may arguably represent <lb/>a higher degree of acquiescence in the Chinese position that Taiwan is a <lb/>province of China than the English equivalent. Of significance in this regard <lb/>is the use of another Chinese word ~renshi&apos; to mean &apos;acknowledge&apos; in the <lb/>Shanghai Communique between China and the US2 ~ Whatever the reason <lb/>for the use of &apos;chengren&apos; to mean &apos;acknowledge&apos;, it is clear that its use in <lb/>conjunction with the Chinese word for &apos;position&apos; (lichang) indicates that there <lb/>is no outright acceptance by Australia that Taiwan is a province of Chinao 53 <lb/>Although the distinction may appear to be purely a semantic one, it has <lb/>provoked a certain amount of controversy in China&apos;s relations with the <lb/>United States. Chert Tiqiang, for example, argues that the use of &apos;chengren&apos; in <lb/>the 1979 SinooAmerican Communique was an intentional change from <lb/>&apos;renshi&apos; in the Shanghai Communique and that the US must be regarded as <lb/>accepting that Taiwan is a province of Chinao ~ This has been strongly <lb/>rejected by the US Governmento 5&apos; Chen gc~s on to argue that t~he joint <lb/>communique is an international agreement, binding on the parties, and that it <lb/>creates an obligation on the part of the US not to deal with Taiwan in a way <lb/>which constitutes intervention in Chings internal affairs. <lb/>The <lb/>PRC has often claimed a right to freedom from foreign intervention in <lb/>China&apos;s internal affairs, particularly with respect to Taiwano ~7 Political <lb/>obligations aside, an important question is whether, as Chert argues, the joint <lb/>communique between Australia and the PRC creates any legal obligation <lb/>under international law to avoid any dealings with Taiwan on the ground that <lb/>it constitutes interference in China&apos;s internal affairs. <lb/>It appears well established that, under international law, such a joint <lb/>communique does not have the status of a treaty so as to create legally <lb/>binding obligations between the party states. Article 2 of the Vienna <lb/>Convention on the Law of Treaties defines a treaty as an agreement whereby <lb/>two or more states seek to establish a relationship between themselves <lb/>governed by international lawo Starke has said that so long as an agreement <lb/>between states is attested and not governed by domestic national law, and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>51 For the Chinese text, see Renmin Ribao (People&apos;s Daily), 28 December 1972. <lb/>52 It is argued that this is the correct translation of &apos;acknowledge&apos;: Li op cit n 29 227. <lb/>53 See Fung and MacKerras op cit 160. <lb/>54 Chert T &apos;Some Legal Problems in Sino-US Relations&apos; (!983) 22 Columbia Journal of <lb/>Trans~ationa! Law, 41, 45. <lb/>55 See &apos;China-Taiwan: US Policy&apos;, Before the House Foreign Affairs Committee, 97th <lb/>Congress, 2d Session 6 (1982), Assistant Secretary of State Jobm H Holdridge. <lb/>56 Chert op cit n 54 45. <lb/>57 See, for example, China&apos;s strongly-worded protest over Australia&apos;s draft airline <lb/>agreement with Taiwan: q&apos;aiwan Air Deal Stirs Cb~ina&apos;s De&apos; Fi~ancial Revi~ (Sydney), <lb/>4 February 1991~ 1 . China&apos;s claim to freedom from foreign intervention in domestic <lb/>affairs has also been made with respect to Hong Kong, despite the fact that sovereignty <lb/>does nc~ pass to the PRC until 1997. Take, for example, the controversy in 1991 over the <lb/>attempts by the Hong Kong admLnistration to build a second airport. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>5~ <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>provided that it is intended to create a legal relationship, any kind of <lb/>instrument or d~ument may constitute a treaty. ~ However, a dividing line <lb/>is generally drawn between documents such as communiques and joint <lb/>statements, which establish political obligations between states, and those <lb/>instruments which are intended to be of treaty status. 5~ Moreover, it is <lb/>unlikely that the parties to such a joint communique would intend to create a <lb/>legal relationship as such an intention would exclude the possibility of <lb/>changing the nature of diplomatic relations in future. ~ In any event, the joint <lb/>communique is not regarded as a treaty under Australian law and practice, <lb/>and is no more than a formal record of agreement which is politically <lb/>binding on the two cotmtries¢ I <lb/>It is clear that the Australian Government does not regard the expansion of <lb/>mutually beneficial commercial relations with Taiwan as a cont~avention of <lb/>the one-China policy as reflected in the terms of the 1972 Joint <lb/>Communique 2 Although the Australian Government will not countenance <lb/>concessions of a diplomatic or political nature which imply recognition of <lb/>Taiwan as a separate political entity, it has taken important steps to <lb/>strengthen the unofficial and commercial relationship with Taiwan, <lb/>reflecting the &apos;positive, forward-looking and pragmatic approach in <lb/>Australia&apos;s unofficial relations with Taiwan. &apos;T <lb/>he new pragmatism which Canberra has adopted with respect to Taiwan <lb/>is undoubtedly due in part to Taiwan&apos;s increasing strength as a trading <lb/>partner and source of in~&apos;estment. It is also due to the realization that in the <lb/>present age, the lines between foreign policy and other policies with external <lb/>application are rarely neat. <lb/>The <lb/>folly of adopting a literal approach to the &apos;one-China&apos; poticy and <lb/>denying Australia the opportunity to pursue unofficial commercial contacts <lb/>with Taiwan is self-evident. Taiwan&apos;s economic strength in Asia cannot be <lb/>ignored and has commanded the attention of other countries despite the <lb/>political influence of the PRC Canberra has acknowledged the role that <lb/>Taiwan might play in regional dialogue and has recognized the strong <lb/>arguments for including Taiwan in such regional bodies as the Asia Pacific <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>58 Starke J .Introduction to International Law (t0th ed !989) 413. <lb/>59 See Myers DP &apos;The names and Scope of Treaties&apos; (1957) 51 American Journal of <lb/>Interna¢ional Law 574, 596. <lb/>60 Such an intention would render the suspension of diplomatic relations a breach of an <lb/>international obligation! <lb/>61 T~is is the v~iew of the Depamnent of Foreign Affairs and Trade as revealed to the writer <lb/>of this essay in an interview in Febnuary 1991. <lb/>52 &apos;Australia and China: Leaking Back -and Forward&apos; -Address by Senator Gareth Evans, <lb/>Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, to the Eighth China-Australia Senior Executive <lb/>Forum, Melbourne, 17 April 1991, 7. <lb/>63 Ibid. <lb/>64 &apos;AustraLia in Asia: the Integration of Foreign and Economic PoLicies&apos;-Address by <lb/>Senator Evans to the Seminar on AustraLia and the North East Asian Ascendancy, <lb/>Sy&amp;~ey, 22 November 1989. For the text, see The Monthly Record (Canberra) November <lb/>1989, <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>52 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s Commercial Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>Economic Cooperation Forum. 6Ĩ <lb/>n reality, however, the strengthening of economic ties between Australia <lb/>and Taiwan and Canberra&apos;s unofficial recognition of Taiwan as a separate <lb/>entity have made the &apos;one-China&apos; policy less tenable. The upgrading of <lb/>&apos;unofficial&apos; relations between the two countries, together with the enactment <lb/>of investment, protection legislation ~ and the establishment of direct air <lb/>links, make it difficult, if not impossible, to escape the conclusion that <lb/>Australia treats Taiwan as a separate political entity and not as a province of <lb/>China. <lb/>Of course, the formal recognition of Taiwan as a sovereign state in its own <lb/>right will remain unrealistic for as long as Beijing and Taipei insist that it is a <lb/>province of China. However, notwithstanding the belief that Taiwan should <lb/>property be part of greater China the de facto recognition of Taiwan as an <lb/>independent entity does not rule out the possibility of reunification in the <lb/>future. This is proved by the existence of multi-system nations in other parts <lb/>of the world such as Korea and pre-unification Germany. The concept of the <lb/>multi-system nation may allow &amp;facto recognition of the existence of states <lb/>within a greater state with the ultimate goal of reunification understood 7 <lb/>The obvious impediment to the operation of this concept with respect to <lb/>Taiwan is that both Beijing and Taipei insist on being recognized as the sole <lb/>legal government of both parts of the &apos;divided&apos; China, including that part over <lb/>which each has no effective control. However, such a claim by each <lb/>government should not prevent other states from treating Taiwan as a de <lb/>facto entity -an approach which is more in accord with reality than t~he <lb/>fiction that it is a province of China. <lb/>In view of the decision by the Australian Government to dispense with the <lb/>recognition of governments ~ and the willingness of both Taiwan and <lb/>Australia to pursue economic relations on an &apos;unofficial&apos; basis, it may be <lb/>pertinent to ask why it is necessary to consider the true status of Taiwan <lb/>under international law. In other words, does it matter ff the fictitious &apos;one-<lb/>China&apos; policy is maintained provided that it does not interfere with economic <lb/>objectives? <lb/>The answer is that does not really matter ff the present state of affairs is <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>65 The Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation Forum was initiated in January t989 by Prime <lb/>Minister Hawkeo For acknowledgement of Taiwan&apos;s possible participation, see &apos;Australia <lb/>and the &quot;Pacific Century&quot; -Address by Senator Evans to the Asia Society in New York <lb/>on 3 October 1989, The Monthly Record (Canberra), October t989, 566. <lb/>66 The legislation is considered infra under ~he Legislative Solution&apos;. <lb/>67 See C~.iu H &apos;The International Law of Recognition and Multi-system Nations -With <lb/>Special Reference to the Chinese (Mainland -Taiwan) Case&apos; (1981) Chinese Yearbook of <lb/>International Law and Affairs 1,4. Chiu contrasts Lhe exclusion of Taiwan from <lb/>international affairs with the accommodation of the two Korean states by the <lb/>international community and claims that t~he different treatment Lies in the relative <lb/>strength and size of the PRC over the ROC. <lb/>68 Discussed in text infra at n 73. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>53 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(t992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>maintained. The extent to which Canberra has upgraded its unofficial <lb/>relations with Taiwan, ostensibly within the framework of the &apos;one-China&apos; <lb/>policy, reflects the relative ease with which policy can be relegated to the <lb/>background. It matters, however, when future trends are taken into account. <lb/>As mentioned above, °~ Taiwan&apos;s reunification with China is by no means <lb/>certain, given the difficulties involved and the growing disparity between <lb/>Taiwan and mainland China. In addition, independence cannot be discounted <lb/>as a possibility. Even if the present regime in Taipei is sincere about <lb/>reunification with China, any attempts to isolate Taiwan and to stifle the <lb/>voice which it deserves in regional affairs is counter-productive. In fact, <lb/>Chiu has argued that only by allowing Taiwan the appropriate international <lb/>status will the PRC and Taipei be able to prevent two Chinas from emerging <lb/>and make unification more likely. TM <lb/>Unfortunately, given the PRC&apos;s uncompromising position with respect to <lb/>Taiwan, it is unlikely that Beijing will allow Taiwan a greater say in <lb/>international affairs without a struggle. Ironica!ly, it is in Beijing&apos;s interests <lb/>for Taipei to continue its claim to sovereignty over China. ~my concession <lb/>on the part of Taipei that it only has effective sovereignty over Taiwan <lb/>would be regarded by Beijing as a fumher step towards independence° In the <lb/>same way as Beijing claims sovereignty over Taiwan on the basis of the <lb/>unilateral repudiation of the Treaty of Shimonoseki by its predecessor <lb/>government, 71 Beijing clings to its own brand of historical irredentism under <lb/>which the PRC claims racial suzerainty over the people of Taiwan for <lb/>eternity. <lb/>The <lb/>question of Taiwan&apos;s trae status under international law also becomes <lb/>retevant in the event that Taiwan decl~es its full independence. The PRC <lb/>has always left open the option of using armed force against Taiwan should <lb/>Taiwan decide to &apos;break away&apos; from the mainlando The question which would <lb/>then arise is whether such action would constitute aggression against another <lb/>state and whether self-defence would be the right of Taiwan under <lb/>international law o ~ Obv.iously, the answer would depend on whether Taiwan <lb/>constitutes a state under international law or whether the PRC could claim <lb/>immunity from foreign intervention on the ground that it was an &apos;internal <lb/>affah-&apos;o To the extent that Australia&apos;s &apos;one-China&apos; policy would give credence <lb/>to the view t~hat it would be an internal affair, it is submitted that such a <lb/>policy is misguided. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>69 Supra in text at n 41. <lb/>70 Chiu op cit n 67, t 1. <lb/>71 Discussed in text at n 8. <lb/>72 Even though no such theory allows self-elected leaders of a &apos;race&apos; to clakrn t.he territory on <lb/>which their people happen to Live, an exception seems to have been granted to the PRC <lb/>with respect to such territories as Taiwan and Tibet. See Chert and Reisman op cit n 5, <lb/>65t. <lb/>73 The right to self-defence appears in Article 51 of the UN Charter. The argument that <lb/>Taiwan would have a right to self-defence under international law is put by Cheng DC <lb/>&apos;A Communist Chinese Armed Attack on Taiwan: Some Inquiries of International Law <lb/>and PoLitics&apos; (1987) Chinese Yearbook of lntematior, al Law and Affairs 182. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>54 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s CommerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>At this point, it may be relevant to consider briefly the recent change in <lb/>Australia&apos;s recognition policy and the way in which it may operate with <lb/>respect to a fully independent Taiwano <lb/>On 19 January 1988, the Federal Government announced a change in its <lb/>recognition policy. No longer would the Government extend formal <lb/>recognition -de facto or de Jure -to new governments overseas. Instead, the <lb/>decision would be whether to recognize t.he state. TM <lb/>The new policy obviously has a significant impact on the way in which <lb/>Australia can respond to new governments in existing states. This is reflected <lb/>in the greater ease with which Australia can maintain its relations with <lb/>unconstitutional governments such as the Fijian Government installed after <lb/>the coup in 19872 ~ However, it is not clear whet,her the change in policy <lb/>affects the criteria on which Australia might extend recognition to a new <lb/>state such as an independent state of Taiwan. In view of the fact that Taiwan <lb/>akeady possesses the qualifications for statehood under international law, it <lb/>may be anomolous to talk about a new state of Taiwan emerging. In theory, <lb/>the onty real obstacle to its being recognized as a state is the refusal of the <lb/>Taipei Government to be recognized as the government of Taiwan26 <lb/>However, to the extent that the new policy removes recognition of <lb/>government from the question of recognition of states, it may logically imply <lb/>that Taiwan should be recognized as a state since Taipei&apos;s claim to <lb/>sovereignty over mainland China would no longer be a relevant factor. <lb/>The Consequences Of Non-Recognition <lb/>Under traditional principles of private international law, the question of <lb/>recognition is regarded by the courts as antecedent to a determination of the <lb/>status of t.he acts or laws of a foreign state. In other words, the degree of <lb/>recognition accorded to a foreign state (or government) determines t~he effect <lb/>which the courts wi!l give to its punic acts and laws. A determination that a <lb/>foreign state or government is unrecognized by the forum government has <lb/>traditionally had the following consequences: (i) the foreign state has no <lb/>standing to sue in the forum courts; ~7 (ii) its acts cannot be given effect to by <lb/>the forum courts, TM and (iii) it cannot claim jm~sdictional immunity. ~ The <lb/>reason for these prohibitions has been attributed to the absence of comity <lb/>between the forum state and the foreign state or governmentY <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>74 Age (Melbourne), 20 January 1988. For a detailed anatysis of the new policy, see <lb/>Charlesworth H, q~he New Austrodian Recognition Policy in Comparative Perspective&apos; <lb/>(1991) 18 MVLR 1. <lb/>75 See Charlesworth op cit 2. <lb/>76 The main practical obstacle, of course, is the PRC&apos;s ctaim to sovereignty over Taiwan. <lb/>77 Lucher v Sagor [1921] 1 KB 456. Ln America, the principle is defined by Russian <lb/>Socialis¢ Federated Soviet Republic v Cibrario 139 NE 259 (t923). <lb/>78 Even acts that affected private rights were denied effect: Adams v.Adams [1971] P188. <lb/>79 C#y of Berne v Bank of England (1804) 9 Ves Jun 347; 32 AL! F~ 636. <lb/>80 Starke, op cit n 58, 142. Another factor was the need for the judiciary and executive to <lb/>speak with the same voice in matters invot,4ng recognition: The Arantzazu Mendi [1939] <lb/>AC 256. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>55 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>Since recognition is regarded as an executive act of government, the <lb/>courts have traditionally accorded judicial deference to the acts and <lb/>statements of the executive to determine whether a foreign state or <lb/>government is recognized. Often the courts have accepted executive <lb/>certificates as conclusive evidence of the fact of recognitionY <lb/>However, the question of whether a court will regard a certificate as <lb/>conclusive depends largely on the content of the certificate and the extent to <lb/>which the executive has provided a complete and unambiguous answer to the <lb/>question put to itY <lb/>In Anglo-Czechoslovak Credit Bank v Janssen, ~3 the question confronting <lb/>the Victorian Supreme Court was whether Germany&apos;s occupation and <lb/>administrative control of Czechoslovakia could be recognized for the <lb/>purpose of determining the existence of the plaintiff bamko The defendant <lb/>argued that the bank no longer existed since the German authorities had <lb/>enacted a decree dissolving the bank. At first instance, the tria! judge <lb/>O&apos;Bryan J requested mad obtained an executive certificate which stated that <lb/>the Australian Government had not recognized Germany&apos;s de facto <lb/>administrative control over Czechoslovakia. As a result, O&apos;Bryan J. felt <lb/>himself bound to deny recognition to the decree of dissolution. On appeal, <lb/>the Full Court held that the certificate was not conclusive evidence on the <lb/>question of whether Germany was exercising de facto control over <lb/>CzechoslovakiaY Furthermore, the Court stated that in cases where there <lb/>was no uncertainty as to who had effective control of a territory, de facto <lb/>occupation could be proved by other evidence or the fact may be &apos;notorious <lb/>as a matter of common public knowledgeW <lb/>The decision in Anglo-Czechoslovak indicates that the absence of <lb/>recognition on the part of the forum government does not preclude a court <lb/>from accepting that a foreign government has effective control of a disputed <lb/>territory. Indeed, a refusal to accept the existence of control in such a <lb/>situation would not accor.d with reality. In addition, the decision indicates <lb/>that an executive certificate does not have the same significance where <lb/>courts are concerned with questions of usurpation of sovereignty as it has <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>81 In some instances, the conclusiveness of the certificate has been stipulated in legislation. <lb/>See, for example, s 40 of the Foreign States Immunities Act 1985 (Cth). On the other <lb/>hand, the Foreign Corporations (Application of Laws) Act 1989 has the effect of <lb/>removing the executive certificate as a relevant factor in the determination of questions to <lb/>which the Act applies° This is discussed supra under Nemova! of Recognition as a <lb/>Factor&apos;. <lb/>82 See Edeson WR &apos;Conclusive Executive Certificates in AustraLian Law&apos; (1976) 7 <lb/>Australian Year Book of International Law 1, 5. <lb/>83 [19431] VLR 185. <lb/>84 Ln fa~t, the FuLl Court (Mann CJ, Lowe and Martin JJ) held that the drafter of the <lb/>cepdficate had misapprehended the nature of the information sought and was realty <lb/>dealing with the attitude of the Goverr~-nent towards the question of de jure sovereignty: <lb/>[1943] VLR 185, 198. <lb/>85 [1943] VLR 185, 197. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>56 <lb/></page>

			<body>when the courts are concerned with relations with foreign states?&apos; This is <lb/>particularly so when the question of de facto control relates to the <lb/>determination of private rights and not to the merits or demerits of the <lb/>occupying power. <lb/>The executive certificate also loses much of its significance where the <lb/>main issue is the interpretation of a term in a contract or a statute. In such a <lb/>case, it is clear that the question is one of interpretation of the terms used by <lb/>the parties, and therefore a matter of law for the court, rather than one to be <lb/>determined by executive certificate. &apos;7 There are a few cases involving <lb/>Taiwan which illustrate this point. In Luigi Monta of Ger~oa v Cechofracht <lb/>Co Ltd, ~ the English High Court (Queen&apos;s Bench Division) held that Taiwan <lb/>constituted a &apos;government&apos; under a charterparty clause, stating that the <lb/>criterion required of a government was the &apos;exercise of full executive and <lb/>legislative control over an established territory&apos;o &apos;9 In Rogers Attorney-<lb/>General v Cheng Fu Sheng et a!, ~ the District Court of Columbia held that <lb/>Taiwan was a &apos;country&apos; under the US Immigration and Nationality Act so as <lb/>to constitute a place to which the plaintiffs (illegal Chinese immigrants) <lb/>could be deported? i <lb/>The argument against the conclusiveness of an executive certificate is <lb/>particularly persuasive where the issue is the interpretation of the rules of <lb/>private international bodies. In Reel v Holder, ~ The English Court of Appeal <lb/>held that Taiwan was a &apos;country&apos; under the rules of the International Amateur <lb/>Athletic Federation so as to entitle it to continue its membership of the <lb/>association. The Court held that the word &apos;country&apos; was used in order to <lb/>delineate territorial areas of authority, not in the sense of recognized <lb/>sovereign states. This decision was reached despite a statement from the <lb/>Foreign Office at first instance that Taiwan was not recognized as a stated <lb/>The <lb/>Departure from the Strict Approach <lb/>Notwithstanding the strict approach adopted by courts in the past with <lb/>respect to non-recognition, the courts have sometimes been prepared to give <lb/>effect to the acts of an unrecognized state or government and to allow the <lb/>agents or corporate creatures of unrecognized governments standing to sue. <lb/>The exception appears to be based on an acceptance that recognition is <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>86 This was acknowledged by the Co,art L,~ Adams v Adams [ 197 !] 188. <lb/>87 See Ryan KW (ed), International Law in Australia (!984) 13!. <lb/>88 [19561 2 QB 552. <lb/>89 Ibid 564 per Sellers J. <lb/>90 280 F2a 663 (1960). <lb/>91 A similar interpretation of a statutory term arose in Re A!-Fin Corporation&apos;s Patem <lb/>[1970] Ch 160. tn this case, North Korea was held to constitute a &apos;foreign state&apos; under the <lb/>Patents Act 1949. <lb/>92 [19811 1 WLR 1226. <lb/>93 A simAlar problern was considered by the English Court of Appeat in Shen Fu Chang v <lb/>Stellan MoMin (unreported, 5 Juty 1977). In this case, the question concerned Taiwan&apos;s <lb/>membership of the International Badminton Federation. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>57 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>decisive if the foreign state or government is suing, or seeking immunity <lb/>from the process, but less decisive when the issue is simply one of applying <lb/>the appropriate foreign law to determine private rightsY Moreover, the <lb/>absence of comity, as a ground for denying standing to unrecognized <lb/>governments in the forum courts, is less relevant when the suit involves an <lb/>enterprise created by the foreign government to engage in trade and <lb/>commerce. In recognizing an exception to the rule, the courts have been <lb/>cognisant of the harsh, and often illogical, consequences of applying the <lb/>strict approach, particularly where private rights and commercial transactions <lb/>are involved. It is difficult for the courts to ignore the fact that, despite the <lb/>absence of recognition by the executive, there may still be a government <lb/>which is in effective control of a territory and that laws are in place which <lb/>regulate the day-to-day affairs of the people, such as marriage and other <lb/>private relationshipso ~ Moreover, to ignore the foreign law as it relates to <lb/>such things as marriage, ownership of assets and the legal status of <lb/>companies might lead to absurd results. <lb/>There is also the problem that arises if companies of the nonrecognizing <lb/>state are unable to sue to enforce commercial transactions entered into with <lb/>companies incorporated under the laws of the unrecognized state. The <lb/>problem is complicated by the fact that such transactions often involve <lb/>government enterprises. Due to their close relationship to the unrecognized <lb/>government, the prohibition against allowing the foreign government to sue <lb/>would conceivably apply with equal validity to the enterprises themselves. <lb/>The dilemma becomes acute when the government of the nonrecognizing <lb/>state allows, or even encourages, trade between the two countries. ~ One <lb/>case in which the question of the standing of state enterprises from <lb/>unrecognized states was considered is the American case of Upright v <lb/>Mercury Business Machines CoY Although this action involved an assignee <lb/>of a state-controlled enterprise, the US Supreme Court made some important <lb/>comments about the position of the statecontrolled enterprise itself. <lb/>In Upright, the assignee of a state-controlled enterprise of the <lb/>unrecognized German Democratic Republic (GDR) sued in New York to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>94 <lb/>95 <lb/>96 <lb/>97 <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>58 <lb/></page>
	  
	  <listBibl>See Greig DW &quot;Fhe Cart Zeiss Case and the Position of an Unrecognised Govenment in <lb/>English Law&apos; (1967) 87 Law Quarterly Review 96, 1 t7. <lb/>See the comanents of L~rd Denr~ng MR in Hesperides Hotels Lid v Aegean Turkish <lb/>Holidays Lid [t978] QB.205, 212. <lb/>In November 1990, the Federal Government completed a review of l~licy towards <lb/>Taiwan. Although deciding not to vary the &apos;One-China&apos; policy, the Government <lb/>avmounced its plans to &apos;develop a healthy commercial relationship with Taiwan&apos;. The <lb/>measures taken by the Government to encourage trade and investment between Australia <lb/>and Taiwan include the expansion in the unofficial representative office in Taipei, the <lb/>establishment of a visa facilitation service in this office, the encouragement of a <lb/>subsidiary of Qantas in its negotiations with the Taiwan aviation industry to operate a <lb/>dk~ect airtink between the two countries and efforts to open up market access in Taiwan <lb/>for Australian beef, wheat and fresh fruit: Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, <lb/>&apos;Australian Policy Toward Taiwaff News Retease 12 Novernber 1990. <lb/>213 NYS 2d 417 (1961). <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>recover money owed by the defendant under a trade acceptance. The trade <lb/>acceptance represented an obligation to pay for typewriters sold and <lb/>delivered to the defendant by the East German corporation and had been <lb/>assigned to the plaintiff prior to the action. The defendant argued that the <lb/>assignee had no standing to sue on the ground that the assignor, whose rights <lb/>it had been assigned, was a branch of an unrecognized goverm&apos;nent. Because <lb/>the East German corporation would not have had a right to sue on the trade <lb/>acceptance itself, it could not assign such a right to its assignee. <lb/>The Court decided that the de facto existence of the GDR was juridically <lb/>recognizable for the pmqmse of upholding the validity of the assignment. On <lb/>the question of the assignee&apos;s standing to sue, the Court held that the lack of <lb/>standing on the part of the GDR or its creature corporation did not render the <lb/>transaction unenforceable at the suit of the assignee, ~ Although stating <lb/>unequivocably that the GDR Government itself had no standing to sue in <lb/>American courts, the Court left open the possibility that the GDR <lb/>Corporation could have sued on the transaction. Steur J stated by way of <lb/>obiter that the prohibition against according standing to a branch of <lb/>government referred to a branch that performed governmental functions as <lb/>the alter ego of the government. ~ The implication was that an exception is <lb/>made for other &apos;branches&apos; such as government-controlled enterprises which <lb/>do not perform such functions. <lb/>Some writers have criticized the imposition of any restrictions on the <lb/>standing of corporations of unrecognized governments in the courts of the <lb/>non-recognizing state. The criticism is based on the argument that if <lb/>commercial transactions are permitted between the citizens of the non-<lb/>recognizing state and persons or entities subject to the authority of <lb/>unrecognized governments, it is anomolous to deny a forum in which <lb/>disputes arising from such transactions may be resolvedo 1°W <lb/>ith respect to the standing of unrecognized governments themselves, the <lb/>Anglo-American approach has been inconsistent. In England, the courts have <lb/>resorted to somewhat artificial means to overcome the consequences of <lb/>denying s~qdingo In two cases, this has involved treating the unrecognized <lb/>government as an agent of a recognized government in order to allow a <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>98 <lb/>99 <lb/>100 <lb/>rbid 421. <lb/>1-bid 424. <lb/>See Lubman S q-he Unrecogcnised Government in American Courts: Upright v Mercury <lb/>Business Machines&apos; (1%2) 62 Cdumbia Law Review 275,300; Greig op cit n 94, 153. In <lb/>Amtorg Trading Corporation v United States 71 F 2d 524 (1934), a New York <lb/>corporation used by the Russians as their state tradgng agency in tl~ US was atlowed <lb/>standing to sue. In Kinder v Everett 2 Brit ILC 15, an agent for an unrecognized <lb/>government was permitted to sue in his own name on the proviso that he had the <lb/>authority of the unrecognized govermment to draw on the funds in question. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>59 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>transaction to be enforcedo TM In America, the rule in Cibrario has been <lb/>eroded by the recent practice of relying on State Department statements as to <lb/>whether standing should be allowedo 1~ In addition, there appears to be a <lb/>trend towards according standing to unrecognized governments except where <lb/>foreign policy dictates otherwise. Fountain has proposed that courts should <lb/>begin with a presumption that all foreign governments have a right of <lb/>s~qding and that the presumption should be limited only where deference to <lb/>the foreign policy of the executive is proper. In language that reflects the <lb/>reasoning of such writers as Greig, Fountain argues that when the US <lb/>Government has itself entered into informal relations with an unrecognised <lb/>government, or sanctioned or facilitated intercourse between that <lb/>government and US citizens, it is inequitable to prevent the unrecognized <lb/>government from enforcing its rights arising from those relations2 <lb/>Ĩn <lb/>Australia, it is uncertain how the question of standing will be <lb/>approached by the courts in view of the change in recognition policy2 <lb/>Charlesworth <lb/>has suggested that there are three possibilities. The first is for <lb/>the court to interpret the dealings that Australia has with an unrecognized <lb/>state, using the executive certificate as a guide. The second is for the <lb/>Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade to supply information to a court <lb/>similar to the practice in the United States. The third is for the com&apos;ts to act <lb/>on a presumption that all effective foreign governments and their acts should <lb/>be accorded status in Australian courts o 1°W <lb/>ith respect to foreign corporations from unrecognized states, the <lb/>common law in Australia has now been supplanted by legislationo This <lb/>legislation is considered in the next chapter. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>101 Carl Zeiss Stifiung v Rayner &amp; Keeler [1967] ! AC 853; Gut Corporation v Trust Bank of <lb/>Aj~ica LM 3 WLR 583. This approach has been criticised by two writers: see Greig, op <lb/>cit; Beck A &apos;A South African Homeland Appears in the English Courts: Legitimation of <lb/>the Blegitimate?&apos; (1987) 36 International and Co~@arative Law Quarterly 350. Note that <lb/>these two writers, althongh agreeing on the ar~&amp;Ciciatity of such reasoning, take opposite <lb/>positions on whether unrecognized governments shontd have standing. Greig favours <lb/>according standing to unrecognized govermnents: op cit 98 and 136. Beck, on the other <lb/>hand, argues that to accord standing would undercut the policy of non-recognition. Ln <lb/>addition, Beck argues that commercial considerations should not be a factor in the <lb/>determination of standing, agreeing with the view of Steyn J at first instance in Gur that <lb/>persons who contract with unrecognised governments should sue them in their own <lb/>courts or bear the risk of being non-suited: op cit 360. <lb/>t02 For a discussion of cases in wb~ich the State Department has issued such a statement, see <lb/>Fountain EL &apos;Out From the Precarious Orbit of Politics: Reconsidering Recognition and <lb/>the StandLng of Foreign Governments to sue in US Courts&apos; (1989) 29 Virginia Journal of <lb/>tnternazionaI Law 473,494. <lb/>103 1bid 510o <lb/>104 The question of the standing of the Taiwan Goverm~nent to sue in Australian courts is <lb/>considered lumber infra under ~l&apos;he Standing of Taiwanese Corporations&apos;. <lb/>t05 Charlesworth, op cit 24. Cnarleswordi appears to favour the third possibility, arguing that <lb/>&apos;It]he presumption that the effective government should have full status in Australian <lb/>courts would be strengthened if there had been public and/or private contacts with the <lb/>regime in question&apos;: opcit 25. In the case of Taiwan, private contacts with the regk~e are <lb/>encouraged by the Australian Government and have been facilitated by measures adopted <lb/>by Canberra. See supra n 96. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>6O <lb/></page>
<!--Überschrift im Absatz fehlt "The Legislative Solution".-->
			<body>It is possible to identify two main objectives behind the enactment of the <lb/>Foreign Corporations (Application of Laws) Act 1989 (the &apos;Act). Both of <lb/>these objectives are interrelated in the sense that each one provides the <lb/>raison d&apos;etre for the other. The first objective, which may be defined as the <lb/>&apos;economic&apos; objective, is to facilitate and encourage investment from Taiwan. <lb/>In order to take full advantage of the potential which such investment offers, <lb/>it is necessary to treat Taiwanese investment in the same way as investment <lb/>from other foreign countries2 ~ The second objective, which may be defined <lb/>s the legal objective, is to remove any legal impediments to the recognition <lb/>of Taiwanese law as it applies to Taiwanese corporations and, consequently, <lb/>to provide for the security of their investments in Australia. As mentioned <lb/>above, the legal impediments would have arisen as a result of t.he non-<lb/>recognition of Taiwan and the possible refusal of courts to recognize <lb/>Taiwanese law as applying to matters involving Taiwanese corporations. <lb/>Such matters include the validity of their incorporation and their rights and <lb/>obligations2 <lb/>°7 <lb/>Although t~he Act does not refer specifically to Taiwan and applies with <lb/>equal validity to other non-recognized entities such as Northern Cyprus and <lb/>the Bantu homelands in South Africa, the economic context which <lb/>precipitated its enactment indicates that the major concern was investment <lb/>from Taiwan. <lb/>The catalyst for the drafting of the Act was the proposal by the China <lb/>Steel Corporation from Taiwan to construct a US$4 billion steel mill in <lb/>Australia. The project was expected to create 6,000 jobs and generate annual <lb/>export income for Australia of around AUS$400 milliono 1~ Although <lb/>Australia was a serious contender for the mill, ~ China Steel expressed <lb/>concerns al~out the security of its investment in view of the fact that it was a <lb/>state-owned corporation.,10 The main concern probably related to the threat <lb/>of expropriation by mainland China -a possibility that is ruled out by section <lb/>8 of the Act. m A related concern, although not specifically mentioned in the <lb/>course of negotiations, could have been the nonrecognition of China Steel in <lb/>Australia and its lack of standing in Australian courts. Under the common <lb/>law, there was no clear answer to the question of whether state-owned <lb/>enterprises from non-recognized states enjoyed standing to sue in the forum <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>106 Such a necessity has been acknowledged by Senator Evans: Commonweatt.h of Australia, <lb/>Parliamentary Debates. Senate, 4 December 1989, 3755. <lb/>107 The uncertainty of the previous common law approach was acknowledged by the <lb/>MivSster for Trade Negotiations, 1~,~-Duffy, in khe Second Reading Speech for t~he Bill: <lb/>Commonwealth of Australia, Parliamentary Debates, House of Representatives 21 <lb/>December 1989, 3480. <lb/>!08 See &apos;Australia in line-up for US$4 bilfion China Steel havestment&apos; Asia Today (Sydney), <lb/>October 1989, 23. <lb/>109 The investment ultimately went to Malaysia. <lb/>110 &apos;Australia in line-up etc&apos; supra n108. <lb/>t 11 Discussed ivA~ra under &apos;Protection from Expropriation by t.he PRC&apos;. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>courts. The apparent trend was to deny standing on the ground that it would <lb/>amount to the deemed recognition of the jural status of the unrecognized <lb/>state itself, t12 It is here that the Act represents the most significant <lb/>modification of the common law o <lb/>The Removal of Recognition as a Factor <lb/>The pivotal provision in the Act is section 9. It is this provision that removes <lb/>recognition or non-recognition as a relevant factor in the operation of the <lb/>Act. Section 9 provides as follows: <lb/>(1) It is the intention of the Parliament that the application of t.his Act is not to <lb/>be affected by the recognition or non-recognition, at any time, by Australia: <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/>of a foreign state or place; or <lb/>of the govermment of a foreign state or place; or <lb/>that a place forms part of a foreign state; or <lb/>of the entities created, organised or operating under the law <lb/>applied by the people in a foreign state or placeo <lb/>(2) Without limiting subsection (1), it is also the intention of the Parliament <lb/>that the application of this Act is not to be affected by the presence or <lb/>absence, at any time, of diplomatic relations between Australia and any <lb/>foreign state or place. <lb/>A consequential effect of bhis provision is that the executive certificate is <lb/>no longer relevant to the determkr~ation of questions to which the Act applies. <lb/>This is because the main purpose of t_he executive certificate has traditionally <lb/>been to convey the executive&apos;s attitude with respect to the existence of <lb/>certain facts. These facts include the exercise of sovereignty over foreign <lb/>territory and the existence of foreign states or governments. As indicated <lb/>earlier, 11~ the courts have often regarded an executive certificate as <lb/>conclusive evidence of these facts and serious consequences have flowed <lb/>from this. However, the effect of section 9 is t.hat the application of the Act <lb/>&apos;is not to be affected&apos; by various matters which would have traditionally <lb/>fallen within the purview of the executive certificate. The effect of this <lb/>section on matters relating to Taiwan is that the operation of the Act is not to <lb/>be affected by Australia&apos;s non-recognition of Taiwan and its government or <lb/>the official view of the executive that Taiwan is a part of China. <lb/>The Application of Foreign Law <lb/>Section 7, which applies where it is necessary to refer to foreign law in the <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>112 See, for example, the comments of the court in Uprigh¢ v Mercury B~iness Machines Co <lb/>213 NYS 2d 41 7, 421 (1961). Note, however, that Steuer J limited the process by <lb/>according a narrow defLnition to a branch of government, supra n 99. <lb/>113 Supra under q&apos;he Consequences of Non-Recognition.&apos; <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>62 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Australia&apos;s CommerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>determination of a question under Australian law (s7(1)), has the effect of <lb/>referring courts to Taiwanese law for the determination (where necessary) of <lb/>certain questions involving Taiwanese corporations. These questions include <lb/>the validity of their incorporation and their legal capacity and powers. <lb/>The provision avoids the necessity of referring specifically to <lb/>unrecognized states such as Taiwan by using the word &apos;place&apos; which is <lb/>defined in section 3 as &apos;a place that, in practice, applies a separate system of <lb/>law.&apos; Section 7(2), for exarnple provides that any question relating to whether <lb/>a body or person has been validly incorporated in a place outside Australia is <lb/>to be determined by reference to the law applied by the people in that place. <lb/>Section 7(3) applies the same formula with respect to a list of other matters <lb/>such as the status of a foreign corporation and the rights and liabilities of its <lb/>members, officers or shareholderso Thus, section 7 overcomes the traditional <lb/>common law approach by which the acts and laws of an unrecognized state <lb/>or government in matters involving corporations could not be referred to by <lb/>the courts. <lb/>Protection from E×propriation by the PRC <lb/>Section 8 of the Act has the effect of denying recognition to the act of a <lb/>foreign state where the act purports to affect a foreign corporation and is <lb/>based on the assertion of sovereignty over the place in which the foreign <lb/>corporation is incorporated. An exception is made where the act would be <lb/>given effect to by the people in the place in which the foreign corporation <lb/>was incorporated. This exception would clearly apply to the acts of the <lb/>Taiwanese Government for as long as it remained the effective authority in <lb/>Taiwano The main thrust of the provision is directed at any acts by the PRC <lb/>which purport to affect Taiwanese corporations (or their assets in Australia) <lb/>based on its assertion of sovereignty over Taiwano Such acts might include <lb/>decrees of the PRC expropriating or confiscating the assets of Taiwanese <lb/>corporations in AustraLia. TM <lb/>The Standing of Taiwanese Corporations to Sue or be Sued <lb/>:in Australian Courts <lb/>As mentioned above, section 7 of the Act directs courts to refer to Taiwanese <lb/>law in the determination of such questions as the legal capacity and powers <lb/>of Taiwanese corporations. A determination that a Taiwanese corporation is <lb/>validly formed under Taiwanese law would presumably confer on the <lb/>corporation the same legal capacity and powers that are enjoyed by a legal <lb/>person such as the capacity to sue or be sued. To the extent that it accords <lb/>standing in Australian courts to Taiwanese government corporations, the Act <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>114 is highly u.~,JJkely that AustraLian courts would recognise such decrees anyway because <lb/>of the well-established principle against the recognition of confiscatory laws having <lb/>extra-territorial effect: Williams &amp; Humbert Lzd v W &amp; H Trade Marks (Jersey,) Ltd <lb/>986] 2 WLR 24; Bank Voor Handel en Scheepvaar¢ v NV Slafford [ 1953] 1 QB 248. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>63 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>represents a significant advance on the previous position under the common <lb/>law. &apos;&apos;~ As mentioned earlier,&quot;&apos; the strict common law approach may have <lb/>denied standing to such corporations. <lb/>An interesting question, to which the Act does not appear to provide an <lb/>answer, is whether Australian courts would accord standing to the Taiwan <lb/>Government or its agent to sue on a commercial transaction° Although it may <lb/>only be in exceptional circumstances that such a question would arise, it is <lb/>not beyond the realms of possibility, particularly in view of the close <lb/>economic relationship that is being fostered between Australia and Taiwan. <lb/>It is conceivable that a situation could arise in which an Australian company <lb/>enters into a contract involving the Government of Taiwan for, say, the <lb/>construction of public works and attempts to sue on the contract in <lb/>Australian courts. <lb/>An analogous situation arose for determination in t~he Gut case &apos;&apos;7 which <lb/>involved an attempt by an English corporation to recover money under a <lb/>guarantee which it had made available to the Republic of Ciskeio Although in <lb/>this case, the Republic of Ciskei was accorded standing on the ground that it <lb/>was a subordinate body of South Africa, it has been suggested that the Com-t <lb/>was influenced by the commercial implications in refusing standing.&apos;&quot; The <lb/>same commercial implications would arise in retation to Taiwan. Although <lb/>an argument may be put that persons who contract with unrecognised <lb/>governments should sue them in their own com~s or bear the risk of being <lb/>non-suited,&apos;&quot; it seems anomalous for such a result to prevail when the non-<lb/>recognizing government actively encourages and promotes such commercial <lb/>transactions with the foreign state or government. <lb/>When compared with the approach of other countries concerning t~he laws of <lb/>non-recognized states, the Foreign Corporations (Application Of Laws) Act <lb/>1989 is quite unique. Its uniqueness is due to the fact that it overcomes the <lb/>common law problems without mentioning Taiwan by name. It thus achieves <lb/>the intended result without making any diplomatic concessions to which the <lb/>PRC could object2 ~ In tfiis regard, it may be useful to consider briefly the <lb/>approach adopted by other countries in dealing with legal problems <lb/>involving Taiwan. The next chapter considers the various approaches <lb/>adopted by three countries o the United Kingdom, Japan and the United States. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 !5 The Act&apos;s conferral of locus standi on state-owned corporations is particularly relevant <lb/>with respect to Taiwan as major sectors such as finance, steel, shipbuilding, u~ties, <lb/>transportation and petrochemicals have traditionally been dominated by state-run <lb/>enterprises. <lb/>116 Supra in text at n 96. <lb/>117 [1986] 3 WLsR 583. <lb/>1t8 SeeBeck~pcitn 101 354. <lb/>119 See supra n 101. <lb/>120 Ironically, the main objections to the enactment of the Foreign Corpora ions <lb/>(Application of Laws) Act 1989 (Cth) have come from the Taiwan Government which <lb/>argues that the legislation does not go far enough! See &apos;Concessions urged for Taiwan air <lb/>agreement&apos; Financial Review 31 January 1991. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>64 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s CommerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>The Approac}~ Of Other Countries <lb/>In the United Kingdom, confusion over the legal status of corporations <lb/>incorporated in unrecognized states has led to the enactment of the Foreign <lb/>Corporations Act 1991 (UK). The Act appears to have the same effect as the <lb/>Foreign Corporations (Application of Law) Act 1989 (Cth). In other words, <lb/>the Act enables b~2 courts to recognize the legal capacity of corporations <lb/>incorporated under the laws of territories which are not recognized as states <lb/>by the UK. As a result, issues such as the capacity of a company to enter into <lb/>a particular transaction and the powers of its directors wi!l be decided by <lb/>courts in the same way as would be the case had the corporation come from a <lb/>recognized state. <lb/>The approach adopted by the Act differs from the approach under the <lb/>Australian Act. Whereas the Australian Act refers courts to the question of <lb/>whether a corporation was formed in a &apos;place that, in practice, applies a <lb/>separate system of law&apos;, the U-K Act refers courts to the question of whet,her a <lb/>corporation was established by laws &apos;recognized by the courts of a settled <lb/>legal system in the territory&quot; concerned&apos;. <lb/>The formulation adopted by the UK Act appears to be nm~wer than the <lb/>Australian Act as it requires the existence of a settled legal system. Thus, <lb/>stability is obviously a factor which the courts wi!l have to take into account. <lb/>The Act itself does not provide a definition of &apos;settled&apos; and so the scope of its <lb/>meaning will have to await judicial interpretation. 1= <lb/>Japan normalized relations with the PRC in September 1972, approximately <lb/>three months before t~he estab!ishment of diplomatic relations between the <lb/>PRC and Australia. Since 1972, Japan has c!osely adhered to the spirit of the <lb/>Sino-Japanese Communique by which diplomatic relations with the PRC <lb/>were established. However, Japan&apos;s status as one of Taiwan&apos;s leading trading <lb/>partners and its control of Taiwan prior to 1945 have made the PRC <lb/>&apos;suspicious of Japan&apos;s relations with Taiwan&apos;. m One of the most <lb/>controversial aspects of Japan&apos;s relationship with the PRC is the !ong-<lb/>standing Kokaryo case, a case that reflects the approach of Japanese courts to <lb/>the problem of recognition under private international law. <lb/>The Kokaryo case involved a dispute over ownership of a student <lb/>dormitory in Kyoto called Kokaryo that the Republic of China bought in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>121 The Foreign Corporations Ace 1991 (UK) came Lnto for~ on 25 September 1991. <lb/>122 For further comment on the Act, see New Law Journal (UK) 3 May 1 991,602 and <lb/>Business Law Brief (UK) May 1991,!0. <lb/>123 Newby L Sino-Japanese Relations -China&apos;s Perspective (1988) 57. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>85 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>1952 for Chinese students studying in Kyoto. In 1977, the ROC brought an <lb/>action to evict a group of leftist students who were occupying the dormitory <lb/>and refusing to leave on the ground that the ownership of the property <lb/>belonged to Beijing as a result of Japan&apos;s recognition of the PRC in 1972. At <lb/>first instance, TM the Kyoto District Court, while recognizing the ROC&apos;s <lb/>standing to sue, dismissed the action on the ground that the land and building <lb/>were public property and that the ownership therein had been transferred to <lb/>Beijing after Japan recognized the PRC in 1972. This finding arose as a <lb/>result of the operation of the doctrine of government succession. However, <lb/>on appeal, the Osaka High Court reversed the judgment of the lower court, <lb/>holding that the fact that the ROC had de facto sovereignty over Taiwan <lb/>made the succession of government from the ROC to the PRC as a result of <lb/>Japan&apos;s switch in recognition an incomplete succession. The theory of <lb/>incomplete succession of government was reiterated by the full bench of the <lb/>Osaka High Court to which a second appeal was brought in 1987J z~ After <lb/>recognizing the fact that the ROC had exercised exclusive and continuous <lb/>control over Taiwan since the establishment of the PRC and that Japan had <lb/>sustained trade relations with the ROC after 1972, the High Court observed: <lb/>In international law it is reasonable to consider that when a goverranent has <lb/>completely gone out of power and a new government replacing it has become <lb/>established (complete succession of government), all the assets owned by the <lb/>former shall succeed to the latter. On the other hand, when the old government <lb/>has not completely terminated and is still dominating part of the territory <lb/>effectively (incomplete succession of government), only the assets of the <lb/>former that are located in the territory dominated by the latter shall succeed to <lb/>the latter. <lb/>Ĩn <lb/>the judgment of the Court, the only exception to the principle outlined <lb/>above was the situation where the issue involved diplomatic assets or assets <lb/>used for the exercise of state powers. The dormitory building did not fall <lb/>within this exception and, accordingly, ownership remained in the ROC. <lb/>The ruling of the Osaka High Court that the ROC had de facto sovereignty <lb/>over Taiwan reflects the willingness of Japanese courts to deal with matters <lb/>involving foreign governments without being influenced by questions of <lb/>recognition. Despite strong objections from the PRC, the Japanese <lb/>Government has refused to interfere with the ruling, citing the doctrine of the <lb/>separation of powers as the reason behind its refusal. <lb/>Õne <lb/>Japanese writer, although agreeing with the outcome of the case, is <lb/>critical of the basis on which the decision was made. Instead of dealing with <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>t24 For the decision of the Kyoto District Court, see Japanese Annual of International Law <lb/>22 (1978) 151. <lb/>125 For the decision of the Osaka High Court, see Japanese Annual oflnternational Law 31 <lb/>(1988) 201. <lb/>!26 Ibid 203. <lb/>127 Newby op cit n 123, 60. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s CommerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>the matter in accordance with public international law concepts such as <lb/>incomplete succession, the Osaka High Court, it is argued, should have <lb/>determined title in accordance with the private international law concept of <lb/>&apos;effective&apos; law. In other words, the courts should have recogvJzed the title of <lb/>the ROC on the sole ground that it possessed de facto sovereignty over <lb/>Ta~wan and was thus able to acqtfire property in its own name. &apos;~&apos; <lb/>In 1979, Washington established diplomatic relations with the PRC and <lb/>terminated its formal diplomatic relations with Taipeio However, Washington <lb/>was anxious to ensure that the recognition of the PRC Government did not <lb/>affect, in practical terms, the relationship which had previously existed <lb/>between Taiwan and the US The continuation of the close relationship with <lb/>Taiwan was guaranteed by the enactment of the Taiwan Relations Act 1979 <lb/>(the &apos;TRA&apos;)2 <lb/>The <lb/>effect of the TRA is, inter alia, to treat Taiwan as a recognized state <lb/>for the purpose of applying the laws of the United States. Section 4 provides <lb/>as follows: <lb/>(a) The absence of diplomatic relations or recognition shall not affect the <lb/>application of the laws of the UvJted States with respect to Taiwan, and the <lb/>laws of the United States shall apply with respect to Taiwan in the manner <lb/>that the laws of the United States applied with respect to Taiwan prior to <lb/>January 1, t979 [the date on which diplomatic relations were terminated]. <lb/>The section goes on to provide that whenever US Iaws refer to foreign <lb/>comqtries, nations, states, governments, or similar entities, such terms shall <lb/>include, and such laws shall apply with respect to Taiwan (s 4(b)(1))o <lb/>Furthermore, whenever a question arising under US Iaw refers to the law in <lb/>Taiwan as the applicable law, the law applied by the people on Taiwan shall <lb/>be considered the applicable law for that purpose (s 4(4))° Except in so far as <lb/>this provision mentions Taiwan by name, its effect is similar to the Foreign <lb/>Corporations (Application of Laws) Act 1989o <lb/>Unlike the Australian Act, the TRA specifically provides that the capacity <lb/>of Waiwan&apos; to sue and be sued in American courts shall not be affected by <lb/>the absence of diplomatic relations or recognition (s 4(7))° Section 15 <lb/>provides that: <lb/>(2) The term &apos;Taiwan ° includes, as the context may require, the islands of <lb/>Taiwan and the Pescadores, the people on those islands, corporations and <lb/>other entities and associations created or organised under the laws applying <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>128 Tsutsui, &apos;Subjects of International Law in the Japanese Courts&apos; (1988) 37 International <lb/>and Comparative Law QuarteHy 325, 329. <lb/>t29 Public Law 96-8, 93 Stat 14 (10 Apr;J 1979). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">(~992) 4 BOND k <lb/></note>

			<body>~q <lb/>on those islands, and the goverrSng authorities on T~w~ re~g~s~ by <lb/>~e <lb/>United States as the Republic of China prior to 3~u~ 1, 1979, <lb/>~d <lb/>successor govem~g au~ofifi~ (~clud~g ~hfic~ su~iv~io~, agencies, <lb/>~d ~men~fies hhereo~. <lb/>Thus it goes further than the Australian Act in terms of specifically <lb/>conferring standing to sue and be sued on both government corporations and <lb/>also the government of Taiwan itself. Although the TRA places relations <lb/>between the US and Taiwan on an unofficial and commercial basis, courts in <lb/>the US have applied the TRA in a manner that treats Taiwan as a sovereign <lb/>entity. In a series of cases, courts have applied sovereign immunity concepts <lb/>and the &apos;act of state&apos; doch~ine to Taiwan, and have regarded Taiwan as having <lb/>a government with authority to promulgate laws and capacity m engage fin <lb/>external relations. 1Õ <lb/>ne of the clearest examples of the tendency of US com~.s to treat Taiwan <lb/>as a sovereign entity is Millen Industries v Coordination Council for North <lb/>American Af_fairso TM In Millen, the plaintiff company established a <lb/>manufacturing plant in Taiwan, allegedly in reliance on representations made <lb/>by the defendant (CCNAA), an organization that operated as the agent of the <lb/>ROC government in the US. The plaintiff claimed that the CCNAA induced <lb/>it to invest in Taiwan by promising, inter alia, that the plaintiff would be <lb/>able to import its supplies into Taiwan on favourable terms. When the plant <lb/>turned out to be a money-losing operation, the plaintiff closed it and sued <lb/>CCNAA in the US. Although from one angle, the transaction could have <lb/>been viewed as an ordinary commercial one between a US company and a <lb/>Taiwan &apos;association&apos;, the Court regarded it as involving an exercise of the <lb/>~sovereign prerogative&apos; to regulate exports and imports to and from Taiwan. 132 <lb/>Thus, the CCNAA could claim immunity under the Foreign Sovereign <lb/>Immunities Act on the ground that the representations had been made in a <lb/>&apos;sovereign&apos; capacity and were not purely commercial. In addition, the &apos;act of <lb/>state&apos; doctrine was applied so as to prevent the Court from inquiring into acts <lb/>by the sovereign power within the territory of Taiwan2 <lb/>~3 <lb/>The factual circumstances in Mitten could easily arise in Australia. <lb/>Although the ROC Government, through its unofficial agent in Australia, <lb/>could not claim sovereign immunity under the Foreign States Immunities <lb/>Act 1985 (Cth), it is uncertain how an Austra~an court would deal witch a suit <lb/>by an Australian company against an unofficial ROC agency such as the <lb/>Taipei Economic &amp; Cultural Office (TECO). As an incorporated <lb/>associations, the TECO can sue or be sued on any commercial transaction <lb/>into which it has entered. However, even though it is not entitled to claim <lb/>sovereign immunity in Australia, it is difficult to conceive of a situation <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>130 For a surm-nary of these cases, see Damrosch LF ~he Taiwan Retafions Act Mter Ten <lb/>Years&apos;Journal of Chinese Law 3 (1989) t57, 174. <lb/>131 855 F 2A 879 (1988). <lb/>132 855 F2d 879, 885. <lb/>133 See further Damrosch op cit 175. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>68 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s Commercia~ Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>where an Australian court would entertain an action against it where matters <lb/>of sovereign prerogative, such as the regulation of exports and imports, were <lb/>involved. The decision in Anglo-Czechoslovak Credit Bank v Janssen TM <lb/>appears to suggest that a court might look beyond the executive certificate <lb/>and accept that an unrecognized foreign government has effective control of <lb/>a disputed territory. Consequently, the court might refuse to intervene in <lb/>matters of sovereign prerogative. However, the difficulties would be <lb/>compounded by the fact that, unike the CCNAA in the US which enjoys <lb/>statutory recognition under the TRA as the agent of the governing authorities <lb/>in Taiwan, the TECO is not officially recognized as the agent of the Taiwan <lb/>Government in Australia. Any move by the court to accord such recognition <lb/>would clearly run counter to the policies of the executive. <lb/>Although the size and influence of the US have enabled it to preserve its <lb/>relationship with Taiwan without jeopardising its diplomatic relations with <lb/>the PRC, the operation of the TRA has provoked much opposition from the <lb/>government in Beijingo The main criticism is that it violates international law <lb/>and constitutes intervention in China&apos;s internal affairs. The alleged violation <lb/>of international law is based on the view that the TRA is contrary to the US -<lb/>China Joint Communique of 1979 under which diplomatic relations were <lb/>established° The argument is that the joint communique establishes legal <lb/>obligations under international law and that the US cannot plead its own law <lb/>as an excuse for nonperformance of its international obligations? <lb/>~5 <lb/>As discussed earlier, 1~&apos; there is strong authority for the contention that <lb/>such a joint communique does not create legally binding obligations under <lb/>internationa! law. Thus, the recognition of Taiwan by US domestic law <lb/>cannot be regarded as violating international law. Nevertheless, although the <lb/>Taiwan Relations Act may be a valid means of overcoming problems relating <lb/>to Taiwan&apos;s status under the domestic law of the US, it still does not answer <lb/>the question of how Taiwan should be regarded under international law? <lb/>~7 <lb/>For the US, the question of Taiwan&apos;s status under international law may not <lb/>be of immediate relevance in view of the operation of the TRA. For <lb/>Australia, however, the question will still be relevant with respect to those <lb/>matters not covered by the provisions of the Foreign Corporations <lb/>(Application of Laws) Act 1989. Such matters include the standing of the <lb/>Taiwan Government in Australian courts and the role which Taiwan should <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>134 <lb/>135 <lb/>136 <lb/>137 <lb/>[1943] VLR 185. This case was discussed in text supra at n 38. <lb/>For a,n explanation of this argument, see Chen op cit n 54, 46; Hsia T &quot;The PRC&apos;s Attitude <lb/>Toward the Taiwan Relations Act; in Chert F (ed), China Policy &amp; National <lb/>Security(1984) Ch 9, 195. <lb/>Supra in text at n 59. <lb/>Section 4(c) of the TRA &apos;approves the continuation in force of all treaties and other <lb/>international agreements, including multilateral conventions&apos; that had previously been in <lb/>effect between the US and the Republic of China. However, the Act avoids recognizing <lb/>Taiwan as a state for the purpose of continuing the mutual obligations under such <lb/>agreements by establisbJng an agency structure as the substitute for inter-governmental <lb/>relations. The agencies for the US and Taiwan are the American Institute on Taiwan <lb/>(ART) and the Coordination Council for North American Affairs (CCNAA) respectively. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>69 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>be able to perform in regional bodies. In addition, the strengthening of <lb/>economic ties between Australia and Taiwan, as evidenced by the <lb/>establishment of a dfi-ect aiflink, will increase the likelihood that Australia <lb/>will one day have to deal with Taiwan on an official level. Consider, for <lb/>example, the situation that would arise if an accident occurred on the <lb/>Australia-Taiwan air route or if one of the airplanes were hijacked. Would <lb/>the Australian Government be prepared to recognize the Taiwan Government <lb/>for the purpose of direct negotiations in accordance with international <lb/>practice or would negotiations have to take place through unofficial <lb/>channels? <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In the four decades since the 1949 revolution on mainland China, Taiwan has <lb/>established itself as an independent territory witch full capacity to perform the <lb/>international duties of a sovereign state. That many states have not <lb/>recognized it as such is due to Taipei&apos;s refusal to be recognized as the <lb/>government of the sovereign state of Taiwan, and the mutually exclusive <lb/>claims to sovereignty over a greater China by Taipei and Beijing. It is <lb/>certainly not due to any disabilities arising outside the realm of politics. <lb/>Politics, however, will continue to play a determinative role in the shaping <lb/>of Taiwan&apos;s future. Whatever international law has to say about the criteria <lb/>for statehood, the question of recognition is still dependent on policy <lb/>considerations rather than objective reality. For as long as Beijing and Taipei <lb/>insist on being regarded as the sole legitimate government of all of China, <lb/>including Taiwan, their coexistence will present problems in international <lb/>affairs. <lb/>On the subject of legitimacy, there is no doubt that Beijing has earnt the <lb/>right to be regarded as the successor government to the Republic of China <lb/>government that existed on the mainland prior to 1949. To the extent that the <lb/>ROC Government re-established itself on Taiwan as a government-in-exile <lb/>after 1949, there have certainly been valid questions as to its legitimacy over <lb/>Taiwan, even if Taiwan never reverted to Chinese sovereignty after Japan&apos;s <lb/>defeat in 1945. However, as this essay has revealed, &apos;~9 recent political events <lb/>in Taiwan have changed the ethos of society in Taiwan and it is now less <lb/>valid to reject the legitimacy of the government in Taipei on the ground that <lb/>it does not represent the true wishes of the peopte of Taiwano As democratic <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>138 Such a scenario occurred in !984 when a British Airways jetlkner on route to Shanghai <lb/>was diverted to Taipei. Both Taipei and London were parties to the 1970 Hague Anti-<lb/>I~Ajacking Convention and as such, they cooperated to solve the problem: see Ma Y <lb/>Ma~or Legal Issues Relating to the International Status of the ROC (t986) Chinese <lb/>Yearbook of International Law and Affairs 171,t76, n24. Ma points out that even though <lb/>Beijing regards the ROC&apos;s signatures, ratifications and accessions to a given treaty null <lb/>and void, Beijing could hardly have requested London to negotiate with it instead of <lb/>Tail~i in this case. <lb/>139 See Supra Recent Political Developments. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>70 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AustrNia&apos;s CommerciN Relationship with Taiwan <lb/></note>

			<body>reforms begin to take hold in Taiwan, it is inevitable that Beijing&apos;s claim to <lb/>sovereignty over Taiwan will weaken. This in turn will raise questions about <lb/>the validity of Chinese irredentism, as reflected in the &apos;One-China&apos; policy, <lb/>under which Taiwan is regarded as an inseparable part of China. <lb/>In countries such as Australia, the inconsistencies caused by the &apos;One-<lb/>China&apos; policy will become more apparent as economic ties with Taiwan <lb/>become stronger and gradually force an acknowledgment of objective <lb/>reality. Such objective reality is implicit in the ways in which Australia has <lb/>upgraded its unofficial relations with Taiwan arid in the effect of the Foreign <lb/>Corporations (Application of Laws) Act 1989. Furthermore, the changes in <lb/>recognition policy, although not of immediate relevance to Taiwan, will <lb/>obviously have an effect on the ways in which t_he Australian Government <lb/>might respond to the question of Taiwan&apos;s status in future. <lb/>With respect to the Act, the change in recognition policy is relevant to the <lb/>extent that the standing of the government of an unrecognised state is no <lb/>longer a factor in the determination of legal questions involving foreign <lb/>corporations from that state. However, a contradiction is caused by, on the <lb/>one hand, the Australian Government&apos;s official adherence to the notion that <lb/>Taiwan is a province of China and, on the other hand, its enactment of the <lb/>legislative basis for a determination by the courts that it is, in effect, a <lb/>sovereign state. The contradiction is clearly avoided by section 9 of the Act <lb/>and the consequential elimination of the executive certificate as a <lb/>determinative factor in the pr~ess. However, the contradiction still remains <lb/>and demonstrates the extent to which policy lags behind economic, and legal, <lb/>reality. <lb/>The purpose of this essay has been to demonstrate that there is no legal <lb/>impediment to Australia&apos;s treatment of Taiwan as a de facto independent <lb/>state and to identify certain areas in which problems still remain, even after <lb/>the enactment of the Foreign Corporations (Application o_fLaws) Act 1989. <lb/>These problems include the standing of the Taiwanese Government in <lb/>Australian courts and the inconsistencies caused by the &apos;One-China&apos; policy. <lb/>With respect to the operation of the Act, the Australian Government has been <lb/>forthright in its view that &apos;as a matter of public policy, the foreign relations <lb/>considerations should not normally be the overriding factor in the <lb/>determination of private legal rights, particularly those involving commercial <lb/>transactions&apos;. 14° On this basis, it would appear logical for the courts to accord <lb/>standing to the Taiwanese Government in cases involving commercial <lb/>transactions. As noted earlier, the courts may be closer to according standing <lb/>to unrecognised governments in view of the new recognition policy. <lb/>However, there is still uncertainty as to how the new policy will operate. To <lb/>the extent that the courts will be able to look at Australia&apos;s unofficial <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>140 Mr Daffy in the Second Reading Speech for the Bill: Commonwealth of Australia, <lb/>Parliamentary Debaces, House of Representatives, 21 December !989, 3480. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>71 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">(1992) 4 BOND L R <lb/></note>

			<body>relations with Taiwan to determine whether there has been implied <lb/>recognition, there will obviously be greater flexibility than was allowed by <lb/>the previous situation in which the executive certificate played a dominant <lb/>roleo The strong trading relationship between the two countries and <lb/>Canberra&apos;s policies for the development of economic ties would obviously <lb/>lend weight to the contention that standing should be accorded in appropriate <lb/>circumstances. Such a result would appear consistent with the policy of <lb/>separating foreign policy considerations from matters involving private <lb/>rights. However, the &apos;One-China&apos; policy might still present a dilemma for the <lb/>Government if the courts were to adopt the American practice of seeking <lb/>guidance from the executive as to whether standing should be accorded in <lb/>the circumstances of a particular case. Any overt support from the <lb/>Government that standing should be accorded in appropriate circumstances <lb/>would clearly fall foul of the &apos;One-China&apos; policy <lb/>In the debate following the Second Reading of the Bill, one of the <lb/>members of the Opposition expressed the opinion that the China policy was <lb/>due for review and that the Bill was a step towards the recognition of Taiwan <lb/>which was long overdueJ 41 Although formal recognition of Taiwan depends <lb/>on the occurrence of certain events over which Australia has no control, <lb/>there are certainly means by which Australia can encourage the <lb/>strengthening of economic relations with Taiwan. The Foreign Corporations <lb/>(Application of Laws) Act 1989 is one example of the means available to the <lb/>Australian Government and will hopefully lay the foundation for further <lb/>growth in Australia&apos;s commercial relationship with Taiwano <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>141 Mr Smith (Liberal Party, Bass): Commonwealth of AustraLia, Parliamentary Debates, <lb/>House of Representatives, 21 December 1989, 3482. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <page>72 <lb/></page>


	</text>

</TEI>