<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">A Decade after the Global Financial Crisis: New Regulatory Challenges to Financial Stability</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Mohammed</forename>
          <surname>Khair alshaleel</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Johana</forename>
          <surname>Hoekstra</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T07:29:19.164Z">30/01/2026 08:29:19</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.54648__eulr2021006</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Kluwer Law International BV</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2021</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.54648/eulr2021006</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Mohammed Khair alshaleel, Johana Hoekstra. (2021). A Decade after the Global Financial Crisis: New Regulatory Challenges to Financial Stability. European Business Law Review, 32(Issue 1), 117-156. DOI: 10.54648/eulr2021006</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-01-02T12:20:28.308967Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2026-01-02T12:20:28.308967Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-09T07:43:30.686Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>First pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-11T21:16:00.308Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith second pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T09:09:45.938Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-25T11:51:49.349Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T07:29:38.205Z" status="candidate" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>A Decade After the Global Financial Crisis: New Regulatory Challenges to Financial <lb/>Stability <lb/>Dr Mohammed Khair Alshaleel &amp; Dr Johanna Hoekstra * <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Since the global financial crisis in 2008 regulatory measures have been taken to strengthen the <lb/>international financial sector. There are however regulatory challenges that have the potential <lb/>to destabilise the international financial sector. This article examines three of these challenges: <lb/>Fintech, Brexit, and Emerging Markets Economies. There is currently no significant analysis <lb/>of these issues in relation to their effect on global financial stability. This article addresses this <lb/>gap and analyses why these issues form a threat to financial stability. Fintech is modest but <lb/>growing exponentially and there is little regulation in place, Brexit is characterised by <lb/>prolonged uncertainty and potentially significant negative effects on the economy, and <lb/>Emerging Markets Economies now occupy a far larger part of the international financial sector <lb/>than in 2008 and their potential effects on global financial stability are also significantly <lb/>stronger. The analysis leads to the conclusion that the common threat emerging from these <lb/>challenges is policy uncertainty which leads to increased wariness from investors, which in <lb/>turn leads to sudden changes in capital flows. This can potentially affect international financial <lb/>stability. To mitigate these effects a more internationally harmonised approach to policy and <lb/>regulation is key. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>It has been over a decade since the eruption of the global financial crisis (GFC) in 2008. The <lb/>GFC was characterised by the failure of large financial institutions, important contagion <lb/>between financial institutions, and the spread of adverse consequences from the financial <lb/>system to the real economy. The crisis has had significant ramifications for public finances, <lb/>cross-border capital flows, trade, the world economy, and people&apos;s living standards. In fact, its <lb/>effects are still being felt. The severity of the GFC has revealed the main weaknesses in the <lb/>international architecture for financial regulations. This includes preventing, managing, and <lb/></body>

			<front>* Dr Mohammed Khair Alshaleel is a lecturer in law at the University of Essex (email: mkalsh@essex.ac.uk ) <lb/>Dr Johanna Hoekstra is a lecturer in law at the University of Essex (email: jhoeks@essex.ac.uk ) <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>resolving crises in the global financial system. The global financial regulatory community <lb/>recognised that there were major deficiencies in the way financial institutions and markets had <lb/>been regulated. This was sufficiently demonstrated by the failure of large banks to manage risk <lb/>and the unregulated expansion of a shadow banking system. 1 Therefore, in order to rectify the <lb/>fault lines of the financial system, financial regulators have sought to enact a fundamental set <lb/>of financial reforms. The reforms are built on the four key elements, which were the main <lb/>causes of the crisis: making the over-the-counter (OTC) derivatives markets safer; making <lb/>financial institutions more resilient; ending the problem of financial institutions being too-big-<lb/>to-fail; and transforming shadow banking into resilient market-based finance. 2 The financial <lb/>regulators acknowledged that financial stability is the key objective of these reforms, so they <lb/>aimed at building a more robust and resilient global financial system. In achieving the financial <lb/>stability objective, they adopted a system-wide approach, which is based on the key elements <lb/>of the financial system. 3 <lb/>The evidence shows that reforms since the crisis have boosted the resilience of the financial <lb/>system by making banks safer, reducing the risk of runs due to maturity transformation. 4 <lb/>Significantly, financial regulators have been given new legal powers to effectively monitor and <lb/>address risks that could emerge outside the regulatory boundary and manage a crisis. 5 <lb/>While the post crisis reforms have been designed to fix the abovementioned roots and causes <lb/>of the GFC, they do not consider emerging regulatory challenges that might threaten the <lb/>stability of the global financial system and be potential causes of a future financial crisis. This <lb/>article makes a novel contribution by analysing three potential regulatory challenges to <lb/>financial stability, namely financial technology (fintech), the UK leaving the European Union <lb/>(Brexit), and issues arising from emerging market economies (EME). While these emerging <lb/>challenges have been addressed from different legal, financial and economic aspects, this <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 See Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas, Understanding the Risks Inherent in Shadow Banking: <lb/>A Primer and Practical Lessons Learned (November 2012) at &lt;https://www.dallasfed.org/~/media/ <lb/>documents/research/staff/staff1203.pdf&gt; accessed 25 April 2020. <lb/>2 The G20, &apos;Global Plan for Recovery and Reform&apos; (2009) <lb/>http://www.g20.utoronto.ca/2009/2009communique0402.html accessed 26 August 2019. <lb/>3 Mohammed Alshaleel, Money Market Funds Reforms in the US and the EU: The Quest for Financial Stability,&apos; <lb/>31 EBLR 303 -335 (2020). <lb/>4 See, FSB, Implementation and Effects of the G20 Financial Regulatory Reforms ,4th Annual Report (2018) <lb/>https://www.fsb.org/2018/11/implementation-and-effects-of-the-g20-financial-regulatory-reforms-fourth-<lb/>annual-report/ accessed 6 September 2019. <lb/>5 FSB, Supra n.4 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>article uniquely analyses them from a financial stability perspective. Fintech, for example, has <lb/>been subject to various discussions such as innovations and services offered by fintech start-<lb/>ups, whether fintech industry should be regulated and the way it should be regulated. 6 The <lb/>effects of Brexit on the financial market have been addressed from two different perspectives: <lb/>effect on the UK and effects on the EU. However, the effects of Brexit on global financial <lb/>stability have not been analysed in depth. 7 In addition, the relationship between EME and the <lb/>financial market are usually discussed by economists and are addressed from the perspective <lb/>of ensuring domestic financial stability on EME markets. 8 In contrast here we look at the effect <lb/>of EME on global financial stability. <lb/>Further when it comes to work on global financial stability, analysts and policy makers have <lb/>mainly concentrated on addressing the causes of the 2008 crisis; particularly issues related to <lb/>financial institutions and financial markets. 9 They have not focussed on newer issues that could <lb/>in the future represent a challenge to global financial stability. The three issues addressed here <lb/>do not emerge from financial institutions and financial markets as such; but they nevertheless <lb/>have the potential to destabilise global finance. <lb/>This article argues that what links all three issues (Brexit, fintech and EME) is policy <lb/>uncertainty: because policy makers are not currently addressing these matters from a global <lb/>financial perspective there is a risk of gaps in legislation. These gaps can be exploited by <lb/>(financial) institutions and lead to uncertainty for actors on the international financial market. <lb/>This uncertainty leads to more volatile markets caused by sudden changes in capital flows <lb/>which are the result of financial actors taking reactive ad hoc decisions. <lb/>This article analyses the arguments as to why these three issues could form a potential threat <lb/>to global financial stability and builds up the argument as to how these risks are currently <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>6 See for example, Christopher Bradley, FinTech&apos;s Double Edges, Chi.-Kent L. Rev 61 (2018); Christopher Odinet, <lb/>Consumer Bitcredit and Fintech Lending, 69 Ala. L. Rev. 781 (2018); Charles Mooney, Fintech and Secured <lb/>Transactions Systems of the Future, 81 Law &amp; Contemp. Probs. 1 (2018); and Chris Brummer and Yesha Yadav, <lb/>Fintech and the Innovation Trilemma, 107 Geo. L.J. 235 (2019). <lb/>7 See for example, Jeremy Cape, Brexit and Taxes, 47 Intertax 345 (2019); Christopher McCorkindale, Brexit <lb/>and Human Rights, 22 Edinburgh L. Rev 126 (2018); and Giorgio Sacerdoti and Paulo Mariani, Brexit and Trade <lb/>Issues&apos; 11 Eur. J. Legal Stud 187 (2019). <lb/>8 See for example, Anne Krueger, The Rise of the Emerging Markets ,18 Law &amp; Bus. Rev. Am 445 (2012); Claire <lb/>Hill, Whole Business Securitization in Emerging Markets, 12 Duke J. Comp. &amp; Int&apos;l L. 521 (2002); and Ayuli <lb/>Jemide, More Appetite for Emerging Markets, 27 Int&apos;l Fin. L. Rev.70 (2008). <lb/>9 The G20, Supra n.2 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>underregulated. The article contributes to the literature first by analysing the nature of the <lb/>stability risks to global finance emanating from Brexit, fintech and EME (e.g. ….). Second it <lb/>contributes by examining the commonalities that emerge from these issues to better understand <lb/>how these should be addressed. Whilst this article does not aim to provide the regulatory <lb/>solutions that should be implemented it makes a key contribution by identifying these <lb/>commonalities. The below paragraphs briefly explain why these three issues specifically <lb/>represent a risk to global financial stability. <lb/>Financial technology or fintech indicate technological innovations that influence financial <lb/>services. Fintech industry has the potential to make substantial changes to the current structure <lb/>of the financial system and this might have implications for financial stability. The article <lb/>argues that compared to the exponential growth of fintech, the policy measures are still <lb/>insufficient. This article investigates the potential risks that fintech could pose to financial <lb/>stability such as the growth of fintech businesses that offer financial services but fall outside <lb/>the regulatory boundary, cyber risk and the rise of third-party reliance within the financial <lb/>system that could cause systemic risk. <lb/>Another potential regulatory challenge to financial stability is Brexit. More than three years <lb/>after the 2016 Referendum it is still not clear what shape the legal relationship of the UK and <lb/>the EU will be in the future. Given the importance of the UK financial sector on both a <lb/>European and a global scale, any disruption of the sector could threaten international financial <lb/>stability. This is because of the imbalance between the financial market in the UK and the other <lb/>Member States which make it particularly vulnerable to significant changes in the legal <lb/>framework as well as the policy gaps that are likely to emerge following a hastily negotiated <lb/>treaty, for instance the loss of passporting rights which will see UK financial institutions treated <lb/>as third state institutions. This is especially aggravated by the lack of planning and the threat <lb/>of a chaotic Brexit (which is a risk if the EU and the UK cannot agree on future relations during <lb/>the transition period.) <lb/>Finally, because EME play a more significant role in the global economy due to their growth, <lb/>threats to financial stability now flow from EME to advanced economies and that could <lb/>threaten global financial stability. In 2008 the role of EME in the financial market was smaller <lb/>and therefore they were greatly affected by the financial crisis but the influence of those effects <lb/>on the global financial market was less significant. Now that EME play a more important role <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>any major disturbance to their domestic markets are much more likely to affect the international <lb/>financial market. Such disturbances are more frequent in EME because their domestic policy <lb/>is often (perceived to be) less stable which creates uncertainty for financial actors, and this <lb/>leads to a more volatile market. <lb/>The analysis of these three issues leads to an understanding of the underlying commonalities. <lb/>First, these issues are currently not addressed from a global financial stability perspective <lb/>which leads to legislative gaps. Secondly, in particularly Brexit and EME are subject to a <lb/>politicised process which means that either issues are not addressed, or they are used as political <lb/>leverage. This then leads to policy uncertainty which leads to a more unpredictable response <lb/>from the financial market which causes volatility in capital flows and this in turns affects global <lb/>financial stability. <lb/>The remainder of the article is divided into five parts. First, because this article considers the <lb/>potential threat of the three emerging regulatory challenges to financial stability, Part 2 lays <lb/>out the background to the subject and examines the concept of financial stability and the shift <lb/>from micro-prudential regulations to macro-prudential. It also explains regulatory responses to <lb/>achieve global financial stability post-the GFC. The purpose of this part is to ensure an <lb/>understanding of the current international financial market in order to understand why these <lb/>new regulatory challenges have emerged and why so far these have not been sufficiently <lb/>acknowledged and addressed in financial regulations. Part 3 discuss the risks that fintech could <lb/>pose to financial stability, highlighting the regulatory approaches that have been so far emerged <lb/>as a response to the development of fintech. Part 4 analyses the factors related to Brexit that <lb/>threaten financial stability, investigating the short-term issues such as the loss of passporting <lb/>rights and the long-term consequences coming from diverging regulations which are enhanced <lb/>by the significant role that the UK plays on the global financial market. Part 5 explores the key <lb/>issues in EMEs that could threaten global financial stability, focusing on abrupt changes in <lb/>trade policy which is often used as a political tool which leads to volatility on the financial <lb/>market due to sudden changes in capital flows. Part 6 concludes by summarising key points <lb/>and identifying the commonalities between these threats. <lb/>2. Financial Stability and Macro-Prudential Regulation <lb/>In order to understand the potential impact of the three new regulatory challenges on financial <lb/>stability, this section discusses the concept of financial stability and its importance post the <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>GFC. It also sheds light on the failure of micro-prudential rules and the move to macro-<lb/>prudential policy to achieve the financial stability objective before examining the key <lb/>regulatory responses to achieve global financial stability post the GFC, which are based on <lb/>macro-prudential approach. <lb/>Over a decade has passed since the beginnings of the GFC that resulted in the most severe <lb/>financial panic in the global financial markets since the Great Depression. It is recognised that <lb/>financial crises can have devastating effects on the broader economy. 10 The failure of large <lb/>financial institutions and the crash of financial markets can cause problems in accessing credit, <lb/>leading to an intense recession. The root causes of the 2008 GFC were summarized by G20 as <lb/>follows: <lb/>During a period of strong global growth, growing capital flows, and <lb/>prolonged stability earlier this decade, market participants sought higher <lb/>yields without an adequate appreciation of the risks and failed to exercise <lb/>proper due diligence. At the same time, weak underwriting standards, <lb/>unsound risk management practices, increasingly complex and opaque <lb/>financial products, and consequent excessive leverage combined to create <lb/>vulnerabilities in the system. Policy makers, regulators and supervisors, in <lb/>some advanced countries, did not adequately appreciate and address the <lb/>risks building up in financial markets, keep pace with financial innovation, <lb/>or take into account the systemic ramifications of domestic regulatory <lb/>actions. 11 <lb/>Major failures in the financial regulation and supervision were fundamental causes of the crisis. <lb/>Particularly, the GFC showed many deficiencies in the pre-crisis approach to financial stability <lb/>regulation. 12 The economic and social costs of the crisis showed that the theory of the self-<lb/>correcting nature of capital markets is not anymore adequate. 13 To illustrate, in the self-<lb/></body>

			<listBibl>10 See, Robert W. Kolb, Lessons from the Financial Crisis: Causes, Consequences, and Our Economic Future, 135 <lb/>(New Jersey; John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2010). <lb/>11 The G20, G20 Special Leaders Summit on the Financial Situation Washington DC (2008). Available at <lb/>http://www.g20.utoronto.ca/summits/2008washington.html accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/>12 Hilary Allen, A New Philosophy for Financial Stability Regulation 45 Loy. U. Chi. L. J. 174-230 (2013). <lb/>13 Jeffrey Friedman &amp; Wladimir Kraus, Engineering the Financial Crisis: Systemic Risk and the Failure of <lb/>Regulation, 119 (Pennsylvania; University of Pennsylvania Press, 2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>correction process, the market price either rises or decreases in response to a deficiency or an <lb/>excess to restore the balance between quantity demanded and quantity supplied. 14 This process <lb/>works automatically to adjust from disequilibrium to equilibrium without the need for <lb/>government intervention to regulate the market. This process assumes that market actors are <lb/>rational, and they act efficiently for the most part. However, the collapse of the financial system <lb/>in 2008 demonstrated that this assumption is false. As a result, the enhancement of financial <lb/>regulation was placed as a core position to strengthen financial system and regulatory regimes <lb/>and to avoid future crises. remarkably, since the GFC, the goal of financial stability has become <lb/>the dominant idea of any financial reform nationally or internationally. 15 Further, since the <lb/>stability of the financial system has become a pre-condition to any reform after the GFC, it is <lb/>essential to define financial stability. In spite of the increased focus on the importance of <lb/>financial stability issues, there is, as yet, no generally accepted agreement on what financial <lb/>stability precisely means. Reviewing the financial stability literature, two schools of thought <lb/>are manifestly discernible. While the first school focusses on defining financial instability, the <lb/>second school&apos;s representatives attempt to define financial stability. <lb/>In the first school of thought, Chant, for example, characterised financial instability as <lb/>&apos;…conditions in financial markets that harm or threaten to harm an economy&apos;s performance <lb/>through their impact on the working of the financial system&apos;. 16 The definition proposes that <lb/>financial instability should be evaluated with regard to the potential impact of changes in <lb/>financial conditions on the real economy. Further, Mishkin suggested that &apos;financial instability <lb/>occurs when shocks to the financial system interfere with information flow so that the financial <lb/>system can no longer do its job of channeling funds to those with productive investment <lb/>opportunities&apos;. 17 The definition affirms the substantial role of information failures in causing <lb/>financial instability. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>14 Ismael Hossein-zadeh, Beyond Mainstream Explanations of the Financial Crisis: Parasitic Finance Capital, 12 <lb/>(New York; Routledge, 2014). <lb/>15 Niamh Moloney, The legacy Effects of the Financial Crisis on Regulatory design in the EU&apos; in The Regulatory <lb/>Aftermath of the Global Financial Crisis, 118 (New York; Cambridge University Press, 2012). <lb/>16 Bank of Canada, Essays on Financial Stability, Technical Report No. 95 (2003) available at <lb/>http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.172.8150&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf accessed 16 June <lb/>2019. <lb/>17 Frederic S. Mishkin, Global Financial Instability: Framework, Events, Issues 13 Journal of Economic <lb/>Perspectives 3-20 (1999). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the second school of thought, Schinasi defined financial stability as &apos;A financial system is in <lb/>a range of stability whenever it is capable of facilitating (rather than impeding) the <lb/>performance of an economy and of dissipating financial imbalances that arise endogenously <lb/>or as a result of significant adverse and unanticipated events&apos;. 18 While the definition does not <lb/>view financial stability as a single or static condition, it stresses that financial stability is a <lb/>continuum. Further, Crockett stated that financial stability requires &apos;that the key institutions in <lb/>the financial system are stable, in that there is a high degree of confidence that they continue <lb/>to meet their contractual obligations without interruption or outside assistance; and that the <lb/>key markets are stable...&apos;. 19 The definition focuses only two components of the financial <lb/>system: financial institutions and markets. However, it does not include the third main element <lb/>of the financial system which is financial infrastructure. <lb/>In 2012, the European Central Bank (ECB) defined financial stability as: <lb/>A condition in which the financial system-comprising of financial <lb/>intermediaries, markets and market infrastructures-is capable of <lb/>withstanding shocks and the unraveling of financial imbalances, <lb/>thereby mitigating the likelihood of disruptions in the financial <lb/>intermediation process which are severe enough to significantly <lb/>impair the allocation of savings to profitable investment <lb/>opportunities. 20 <lb/>The significance of the ECB definition comes from the fact that it considers financial stability <lb/>as a broad concept, encompassing the three core components of the financial system: financial <lb/>institutions, markets and infrastructure. Considering the close interlinkages between all of these <lb/>components, expectations of disruptions in any of the individual elements can impact the <lb/>overall stability. To illustrate, disruptions may initially arise and develop in a single institution <lb/>and subsequently spread to other elements of the financial system. Therefore, the regulatory <lb/>intervention to attain financial stability should be comprehensive, addressing the three key <lb/>components. Leaving any gap in these elements will result in the instability of the financial <lb/>system. This approach is called the macro-prudential approach. In the aftermath of the GFC, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>18 Garry J. Schinasi, Defining Financial Stability IMF Working Paper No. WP/04/187, (2004) available at <lb/>https://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/wp/2004/wp04187.pdf accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/>19 Andrew D. Crockett, Why is Financial Stability a Goal of Public Policy? 6 Economic Review 5-22 (1997). <lb/>20 European Central Bank, Financial Stability Review (2012) available at <lb/>https://www.ecb.europa.eu/pub/pdf/other/financialstabilityreview201212en.pdf?f73875a2aa7884337314f4f1 <lb/>c4db5a7d <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>there seems to be a consensus among regulators and academics that financial regulation needs <lb/>to follow the macro-prudential approach. <lb/>Prior to the GFC, the presumption that the resilience of individual financial institutions is both <lb/>an essential and adequate condition to guarantee the resilience of the whole financial system <lb/>was incorrect because events during the GFC have demonstrated that the resilience of <lb/>individual institutions is insufficient to avoid instability in the financial system. 21 Micro-<lb/>prudential rules failed to consider the influence of individual financial institutions&apos; risk-taking <lb/>on the broader financial system and economy, and how the interconnectedness of financial <lb/>institutions could largely spread systemic risks across the financial system. 22 For instance, in <lb/>times when risk is recognised to be high, selling an asset might be seen as a prudent response <lb/>by an individual financial institution. But if many financial institutions apply this approach, <lb/>there will be collapse in asset prices, which in turn could lead to huge volatility in asset markets. <lb/>Therefore, to achieve the financial stability objective, it was necessary to focus on the resilience <lb/>and robustness of the financial system as a whole. This holistic approach adopted by many <lb/>financial regulators is called macro-prudential policy. The European Systemic Risk Board <lb/>(ESRB) states that &apos;the ultimate objective of the macro-prudential policy is to contribute to the <lb/>safeguard of the stability of the financial system as a whole, including by strengthening the <lb/>resilience of the financial system and decreasing the build-up of systemic risks, thereby <lb/>ensuring the sustainable contribution of the financial sector to economic growth&apos;. 23 It is <lb/>significant to mention that macro-prudential policy has become one of the main features of the <lb/>post-crisis international financial regulatory reform agenda. <lb/>Further, macro-prudential policy uses a range of tools to achieve its ultimate objective because <lb/>applying a single tool is unlikely to be sufficient to address the different sources of systemic <lb/>risk. 24 This can include mandatory capital buffers, liquidity fees, suspension of redemption and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>21 See, Rainer Masera, CRR/CRD IV: The Trees and the Forest, 67 PSL Quarterly Review 381-422(2014). <lb/>22 See, Andreas Krause, Systemic Risk, in Investment Risk Management, 189 (New York; Oxford University <lb/>Press, 2015). <lb/>23 European Systemic Risk Board, Recommendation of The European Systemic Risk Board of 4 April 2013 On <lb/>Intermediate Objectives And Instruments of Macro-Prudential Policy (ESRB/2013/1), C 170/1. (2013) Available <lb/>at https://www.esrb.europa.eu/pub/pdf/recommendations/2013/ESRB_2013_1.en.pdf accessed 16 June <lb/>2019. <lb/>24 Systemic risk is defined by the OECD as &quot;the risk that the inability of one institution to meet its obligations <lb/>when due will cause other institutions to be unable to meet their obligations when due. Such a failure may cause <lb/>significant liquidity or credit problems and, as a result, could threaten the stability of or confidence in markets&quot;. <lb/>OECD, Glossary Of Statistical Terms (2004) available at https://stats.oecd.org/glossary/detail.asp?ID=6796 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>stress tests. Stress tests play an important role in assessing the vulnerability of the financial <lb/>system to adverse shocks. 25 Mandatory capital buffers are another important tool that macro-<lb/>prudential authorities can use to address specific vulnerabilities. These require financial <lb/>institutions, in addition to minimum capital requirements, to maintain higher capital to asset <lb/>ratios to ensure that they continue to operate in the event of adverse shocks in the financial <lb/>markets without the need to shrink assets. 26 <lb/>2.1 Regulatory Responses to Achieve Global Financial Stability Post-the Global Financial <lb/>Crisis <lb/>The GFC that began in the US had a direct spill over to the rest of the world financial markets. <lb/>Immediately in the aftermath of the GFC, political leaders recognised that there were critical <lb/>deficiencies in the way financial markets and institutions had been regulated. 27 In response, in <lb/>April 2009 in London, the G20 announced a comprehensive global reform agenda to tackle the <lb/>causes of the crisis. 28 The G20 agenda was initially agreed in the 2008 G20 Washington Action <lb/>Plan and developed in subsequent key summits, including the April 2009 London Summit and <lb/>the September 2009 Pittsburgh Summit. The reform Agenda aimed at establishing a more <lb/>robust and resilient global financial system that can promote the real economy in times of stress <lb/>and diminishing the chance and costs of future financial crises in the most effective way. <lb/>Further, to achieve financial stability and implement its agenda, the G20, in April 2009, <lb/>established the Financial Stability Board (FSB) as the successor to the Financial Stability <lb/>Forum (FSF). The FSB was delegated a variety of tasks including: (1) monitoring and advising <lb/>on market developments and their implications for regulatory policy; (2) promoting <lb/>information-sharing among supervisors; (3) supporting contingency planning for cross-border <lb/>crisis management; (4) identifying and assessing the problems in the global financial system; <lb/>and (5) collaborating with the International Monetary Fund (IMF) to conduct Early Warning <lb/>Exercises. 29 <lb/>In addition, the G20 reform programme, coordinated by the FSB, is built on the four pillars of: <lb/>making financial institutions more resilient; ending the problem of financial institutions being <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>25 Damodaran Krishnamurti &amp; Yejin Carol Lee, Macroprudential Policy Framework: A Practice Guide, 50 <lb/>(Washington; World Bank Publications, 2014). <lb/>26 See, Matthias Haentjens &amp; Pierre Gioia-Carabellese, European Banking and Financial Law, 102 (New York; <lb/>Routledge, 2015). <lb/>27 The G20, Supra n.2 <lb/>28 The G20, Supra n.2 <lb/>29 FSB tasks available at https://www.fsb.org/about/ <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>too-big-to-fail; making over-the-counter (OTC) derivatives markets safer; and transforming <lb/>shadow banking into resilient market-based finance. A complete discussion and analysis of <lb/>these pillars is beyond the scope of this article, but brief discussion of the key elements is <lb/>necessary to assess whether the global financial system is stable. <lb/>A. Making financial institutions more resilient <lb/>One of the core elements of the post-crisis reform was making financial institutions more <lb/>resilient, with higher capital and liquidity requirements and more efficient supervision. <lb/>Therefore, the central banking and supervisory community, coordinated with the FSB, <lb/>recognised that reforming banking regulation was essential. At the heart of this pillar is the <lb/>Basel III initiative to boost the existing regulatory framework for internationally active banks, <lb/>by increasing the quantity and quality of bank capital. 30 The crisis demonstrated that previously <lb/>permitted capital levels were inadequate given the maturity transformational nature of <lb/>banking. 31 In December 2010, the Basel Committee on Banking Supervision (BCBS) released <lb/>Basel III. In December 2017, BCBS finalized Basel III, after agreeing on rules that restrict the <lb/>potential for unwarranted variability of internal model-based risk weights across countries so <lb/>the capital ratios might be applied more equally across jurisdictions. For instance, Basel III <lb/>also introduced two elements of liquidity regulation: the liquidity coverage ratio and the net <lb/>stable funding ratio. 32 While the liquidity coverage ratio aims at promoting the short-term <lb/>resilience of the liquidity risk profile of banks, the main aim of the net stable funding ratio is <lb/>to reduce funding risk over a longer time. 33 Another important initiative to make financial <lb/>institutions more resilient is the International Association of Insurance Supervisors (IAIS) lead <lb/>to develop a global risk-based Insurance Capital Standard (ICS) for internationally active <lb/>insurance groups and strengthening supervisory effectiveness, through its ComFrame project. 34 <lb/>B. Ending too-big-to-fail <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>30 FSB, Supra n.4. <lb/></listBibl><note place="footnote">31 The term maturity transformation refers to the difference in the residual contractual maturity between <lb/>assets and liabilities. <lb/></note><listBibl>32 Basel Committee on Banking Supervision, Basel III: The Liquidity Coverage Ratio and Liquidity Risk <lb/>Monitoring Tools (2013). Available at www.bis.org/publ/bcbs238.htm accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/>33 Basel Committee on Banking Supervision, Progress Report on Implementation of the Basel Regulatory <lb/>Framework (2013). Available at http://www.bis.org/publ/bcbs247.pdf accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/>34 See, Georges Ugeux, International Finance Regulation: The Quest for Financial Stability, 65 (New Jersey; <lb/>John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>The phrase &quot;too big to fail&quot; indicates the threat to the real economy of a tragic failure of a <lb/>financial institution. The GFC showed that national authorities were not able to deal with the <lb/>failures of large cross-border financial institutions safely and without recourse to public funds. <lb/>For instance, the failure of Lehman Brothers was bailed out using public funds. 35 As a result, <lb/>in 2011, the G20 endorsed a set of policy rules to address the risks to the global financial system <lb/>from systemically important financial institutions (SIFIs), with a specific focus on global SIFIs <lb/>(G-SIFIs) 36 to manifest the greater risks that these institutions pose to the global financial <lb/>system. 37 In November 2018 the FSB published an updated list of global systemically <lb/>important banks (G-SIBs) using an assessment methodology designed by BCBS. 38 <lb/>C. Making derivatives markets safer <lb/>The OTC derivatives markets is one of the most internationally active markets, allowing the <lb/>transmission of risks across markets, institutions, and cross-borders. Prior to the GFC, <lb/>deficiencies in OTC derivatives markets contributed to the increase in systemic risk and the <lb/>damage caused by the crisis. 39 As a consequence, improvements to OTC derivatives markets <lb/>are a key pillar of the G20 reform agenda. These improvements aim at mitigating systemic risk, <lb/>reducing market abuse and increasing transparency. The reforms, for example, include trade <lb/>reporting, exchange or platform trading of standardised contracts, central clearing of all <lb/>standardised OTC derivatives contracts, and margining standards and higher capital <lb/>requirements for non-centrally cleared contracts. The majority of FSB jurisdictions-which <lb/>cover more than 90% of OTC derivative transactions-now have in force frameworks for <lb/>determining when standardised OTC derivatives should be centrally cleared. 40 <lb/>D. Transforming shadow banking into resilient market-based finance <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>35 See, Eric. Posner, Last Resort: The Financial Crisis and the Future of Bailouts, 35 (Chicago; University of <lb/>Chicago Press, 2018). <lb/></listBibl>
				
				<note place="footnote">36 A systemically important financial institution or systemically important bank is a bank, insurance company, <lb/>or other financial institution whose failure might trigger a financial crisis. <lb/></note>
				
				<listBibl>37 See, FSB, Global Systemically Important Financial Institutions (G-SIFIs), (2019). Available at <lb/>https://www.fsb.org/work-of-the-fsb/policy-development/addressing-sifis/global-systemically-important-<lb/>financial-institutions-g-sifis/ accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/>38 FSB, 2017 list of global systemically important banks (G-SIBs), (2018). Available at <lb/>https://www.fsb.org/2018/11/2018-list-of-global-systemically-important-banks-g-sibs/ accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/>39 FSB, Supra n.4 <lb/>40 See, FSB, OTC Derivatives Market Reforms: Twelfth Progress Report on Implementation, (2017). Available at <lb/>https://www.fsb.org/2017/06/otc-derivatives-market-reforms-twelfth-progress-report-on-implementation/ <lb/>accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>The GFC revealed many systemic problems arising from so called shadow banking activities. <lb/>In 2012, the FSB defined shadow banking as &quot;credit intermediation involving entities and <lb/>activities (fully or partially) outside the regular banking system&quot;. 41 Unlike traditional banks, <lb/>shadow banks are outside the scope of traditional banking regulation. The shock caused by the <lb/>exploding of the housing bubble and sub-prime mortgage crisis caused a run on the shadow <lb/>banking system. However, shadow banks did not have the traditional deposit insurance to <lb/>protect them from this run. 42 In 2011, the FSB announced a comprehensive framework -the <lb/>Shadow Banking Roadmap -to strengthen regulation and oversight of shadow banking, <lb/>including strengthening money market funds, improving securities financing markets, reducing <lb/>interconnectedness between banking and nonbank sectors and improving securitization <lb/>markets. The most significant achievement in the area of shadow banking is the new set of <lb/>rules governing money market funds (MMFs). In the US, on July 23, 2014, the Securities and <lb/>Exchange Commission (SEC) adopted a substantial reform to the regulatory framework <lb/>governing MMFs. 43 The reform came into force on October 2016. The main components of the <lb/>reform are the introduction of the floating net assets value (FNAV), and the liquidity fees and <lb/>redemption gates. In the EU, the new European MMFs regulation was published in the EU <lb/>Official Journal on 30 June 2017 and came into force on 21 July 2017. 44 The EU reform follows <lb/>the US reform in adoption of liquidity fees and redemption gate; however, the distinctive <lb/>attribute of this reform is the introduction of Low Volatility NAV (LVNAV) MMFs. Further, <lb/>In January 2017 the FSB finalised its recommendations to address structural vulnerabilities and <lb/>reduce liquidity mismatches associated with asset management. 45 <lb/>Remarks on the post-crisis reforms <lb/>The foregoing discussion demonstrates that the post GFC reforms have made significant <lb/>progress. They have principally addressed the fault lines that caused the crisis. Banks are <lb/>considerably better capitalised, more liquid and less leveraged. Reforms to the OTC derivatives <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>41 See, FSB, Strengthening Oversight and Regulation of Shadow Banking, (2013). Available at <lb/>https://www.fsb.org/wp-content/uploads/r_130829b.pdf accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/>42 See, IMF, Shadow Banking and Market Based Finance (2017). Available at <lb/>https://www.imf.org/en/News/Articles/2017/09/13/sp091417-shadow-banking-and-market-based-finance <lb/>accessed 25 April 2020. <lb/>43 See, SEC, SEC Adopts Money Market Fund Reform Rules (2014) available at <lb/>https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2014-143 <lb/>44 See, Regulation (EU) 2017/1131 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 14 June 2017 on money <lb/>market funds [2017] OJ L 169/8. <lb/>45 Available at https://www.fsb.org/2017/01/policy-recommendations-to-address-structural-vulnerabilities-<lb/>from-asset-management-activities/ accessed 16 June 2019. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>markets have created a more transparent and robust system, and implementation of too-big-to-<lb/>fail (TBTF) reforms is advancing. The elements of shadow banking that contributed to the <lb/>financial crisis have declined significantly. In general, the financial system is more resilient <lb/>and diversified. However, it is significant to highlight two key points. First, while the benefits <lb/>from the post-crisis banking regulatory framework are obvious, extensive regulations have had <lb/>a key impact on the shrinkage of bank&apos;s profitability. Since the global financial crisis, bank <lb/>profitability has declined across countries. 46 At least partially, this reflects lower leverage <lb/>created by the regulatory reforms. Further, International bank lending has dropped since the <lb/>crisis and its business structure has shifted from cross-border towards more stable regionally-<lb/>funded lending. 47 Secondly, the post GFC framework focuses on established business models <lb/>that caused the GFC whether in conventional or shadow banking and was, therefore, <lb/>unprepared for disruption by explosion in the application of different technologies in financial <lb/>services by both regulated and unregulated fintech businesses offering niche financial products. <lb/>3. Fintech and Financial Stability <lb/>This section examines the exponential growth of fintech and the potential benefits of fintech <lb/>for the financial system. However, it then goes on to provide original analysis as to specific <lb/>risks posed by fintech that might threaten the global financial stability: namely unregulated <lb/>fintech businesses, cyber risk and the rise of third-party reliance within the financial system <lb/>that could cause systemic risk. It also discusses the regulatory responses to fintech and how <lb/>these responses are still insufficient given the rapid growth of the fintech sector. <lb/>What is Fintech? <lb/>Financial technology or fintech refers to technological innovations that affect financial <lb/>services. The term &quot;fintech&quot; has become widely used within the past few years. The potential <lb/>of reducing costs, increasing efficiency, improving access to financial services makes fintech <lb/>so attractive. 48 There is no industry-wide consensus about the definition of fintech. <lb/>Nonetheless, the FSB&apos;s definition for fintech is very useful in light of the development of the <lb/>fintech industry. The FSB defines fintech as &apos;technologically enabled financial innovation that <lb/>could result in new business models, applications, processes, or products with an associated <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>46 Bank for International Settlements, Structural changes in banking after the crisis, (2018) CGFS Papers No 60 <lb/>available at https://www.bis.org/publ/cgfs60.htm accessed 24 February 2020. <lb/>47 Bank for International Settlements, Supra n.46. <lb/>48 See, Pranay Gupta &amp; T. Mandy Tham, Fintech: The New DNA of Financial Services, 39 (Berlin; Walter de <lb/>Gruyter GmbH &amp; Co KG, 2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>material effect on financial markets and institutions and the provision of financial services&apos;. 49 <lb/>Further, the fintech industry encompasses a variety of tech-fuelled innovations. Many of these <lb/>innovations tend to be start-ups that usually focus on applying a specific technology to promote <lb/>or transform a particular process or financial service. Examples include smart contracts, robo-<lb/>advice, distributed ledger technology, big data applications and peer-to-peer (P2P) lending. <lb/>Generally, the fintech sector can be categorized into five broad areas: (1) payments; (2) <lb/>financing (lending/crowdfunding); (3) asset management services; (4) insurance; and (5) other <lb/>fintechs such as security, and data and analytics. 50 Robo-advisors, for example, are automated <lb/>interfaces that provide investment advice and investment management services without any <lb/>human intervention by using algorithms and asset allocation models which are advertised as <lb/>being tailored to each individual&apos;s investment needs. 51 Because human intervention is <lb/>eliminated, robo-advisors services are substantially cheaper than those of traditional <lb/>management companies. <lb/>Fintech has grown rapidly in recent years. A KPMG report shows that, in 2018, global venture <lb/>investment in fintech companies reached $111.8 billion across 2,196 deals, up from $50.80 <lb/>billion in 2017 and $ 25 billion in 2016. 52 This rapid growth is driven by different factors such <lb/>as technological advances, higher customer expectations for cost, convenience and speed, and <lb/>the substantial changes in the financial regulations post the GFC. 53 This exponential growth <lb/>raises an important question about the impact of fintech on financial stability. It might be <lb/>argued that fintech sector is still too small relative to the overall financial system to present a <lb/>compelling risk to financial stability. However, the industry&apos;s fast-paced development means <lb/>that financial regulators should consider this sector in their financial stability risk assessment <lb/>to guard against future risks. In order to identify the potential implications of fintech for <lb/>financial stability, it is necessary to assess fintech&apos;s potential benefits and risks. Fintech holds <lb/>great promise for the financial system because it has the potential to transform the financial <lb/>system across a great variety of products and services. This variety in the financial services can <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>49 See, FSB, Financial Stability Implications from FinTech, Supervisory and Regulatory Issues that Merit <lb/>Authorities&apos; Attention (2017) available at https://www.fsb.org/wp-content/uploads/R270617.pdf <lb/>50 FSB, Supra n.49. <lb/>51 Ihy Chiu, Fintech and Disruptive Business Models in Financial Products, Intermediation, and Market-Policy <lb/>Implications for Financial Regulators, 21 J. TECH. L. &amp; POL&apos;Y 55-112 (2016). <lb/>52 KPMG, The Pulse of Fintech 2018 (2018). Available at <lb/>https://assets.kpmg/content/dam/kpmg/xx/pdf/2019/02/the-pulse-of-fintech-2018.pdf accessed 26 June <lb/>2019. <lb/>53 See, Gregor Dorfleitner, Lars Hornuf, Matthias Schmitt &amp; Martina Weber, FinTech in Germany, 1 (Berlin; <lb/>Springer, 2017). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>create a more efficient and resilient financial system. Applying productivity enhancing <lb/>technologies, such as robo-advice, could enhance business models of incumbent financial <lb/>institutions. 54 Adoption of machine learning and artificial intelligence (AI) could also promote <lb/>improvements in decision-making processes, by enhancing the models that financial <lb/>institutions and investors use. Fintech has also the potential to support growth by enabling more <lb/>individuals to access financial services. For instance, robo-advisory services have the potential <lb/>to increase access to wealth management for households who could not obtain similar <lb/>traditional asset management services due to different reasons such as high fees paid to <lb/>professional management. 55 <lb/>At the same time, it is undeniable that the development of fintech outside the boundaries of <lb/>the supervisory and regulatory framework can pose risks to financial stability. Fintech <lb/>businesses that offer financial services but fall outside the regulatory boundary or are subject <lb/>to minimum regulatory standards may not be subject to the same level of monitoring of their <lb/>governance to which regulated financial institutions are subject. 56 The growth of these <lb/>businesses could become a risk to the financial system. Fintech businesses could develop risky <lb/>investment practices to generate more profits and if these practices are not subject to risk <lb/>management regulations, they might pose serious risk to financial stability. <lb/>Another important risk that fintech can pose to financial stability is cyber risk. When the <lb/>systems of different institutions are connected to each other and there is a weak link, the <lb/>vulnerability of financial activities to cyber-attacks is likely to be higher. 57 Reliance of fintech <lb/>firms on technology could also increase numbers and the range of entry points into the financial <lb/>system, which hackers could attack. The case of Dwolla in the US is a clear example of the <lb/>cyber risk. Dwolla is a fintech start up that offered payment and money transfer solutions. <lb/>Dwolla confirmed to its customers that their personal data will be safe and secure. Nonetheless, <lb/>because its cybersecurity system was outdated, the firm faced a cyberattack that put their <lb/>customers&apos; data privacy in danger. Therefore, the US Consumer Financial Protection Bureau <lb/>(CFPB) undertook a &quot;data security enforcement action&quot; against Dwolla, which then led to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>54 For further information about robo-advice see, Paolo Sironi, FinTech Innovation: From Robo-Advisors to Goal <lb/>Based Investing and Gamification, 51 (Chichester, John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2016). <lb/>55 Sironi, Supra n.45, 50. <lb/>56 FSB, Supra n.49. <lb/>57 See, Douglas Arner, Janos Nathan Barberis &amp; Ross Buckey, FinTech, RegTech, and the Reconceptualization of <lb/>Financial Regulation 37 Nw. J. Int&apos;l L. &amp; Bus. 371-414 (2017). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Dwolla being fined with $100 thousand. 58 It is significant to know that from 2013 to 2018 <lb/>cyber-attacks on Fintech firms resulted in at least $1,450 Million in losses due to fraud. 59 While <lb/>most jurisdictions address cyber -resilience through the lens of IT and general operational risk, <lb/>there is typically a lack of explicit references to cybersecurity risk. A survey by the <lb/>International Monetary Fund (IMF) shows that although awareness of cybersecurity risks is <lb/>generally high and most countries have frameworks in place to protect the resilience of the <lb/>financial system, gaps in mapping cyber risks are common, particularly among emerging <lb/>markets and developing economies (EMDE). 60 Further, another survey conducted by the <lb/>European Banking Authority (EBA) on supervisory practices around cybersecurity in the EU <lb/>financial sector demonstrates that there are many differences in the process of testing of <lb/>regulated entities&apos; vulnerability and resilience to cyber risk and the cross-border cooperation <lb/>with regards to such testing. 61 <lb/>Further, some activities offered by fintech firms could increase third-party reliance within the <lb/>financial system. Third-party service providers to financial institutions are rapidly becoming <lb/>more important and vital, especially in the areas of cloud computing and data services. Cloud <lb/>computing services, for example, could be provided by a small number of parties. Robo-advice, <lb/>for instance, may rely on a set of third-party data providers that might be extremely <lb/>concentrated. 62 Disruptions to these third-party services, maybe due to operational issues, are <lb/>more likely to pose systemic risks, which in turn could destabilise the financial system. To <lb/>illustrate, systemic risk is best characterized by connectedness. When financial institutions <lb/>become more connected, the systemic risk increases. The more points of connectedness <lb/>between financial institutions there are, the more points of vulnerability to the financial system. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>58 Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, Administrative Proceeding, (2016). Available at <lb/>https://files.consumerfinance.gov/f/201603_cfpb_consent-order-dwolla-inc.pdf. <lb/>59 IMF Working Paper, Cyber Risk for the Financial Sector: A Framework for Quantitative Assessment, (2018) <lb/>available at https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/WP/Issues/2018/06/22/Cyber-Risk-for-the-Financial-Sector-<lb/>A-Framework-for-Quantitative-Assessment-45924 accessed 25 April 2020. <lb/>60 International Monetary Fund and World Bank Group, Fintech: The Experience So Far, (2019) available at <lb/>https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/Policy-Papers/Issues/2019/06/27/Fintech-The-Experience-So-Far-47056 <lb/>accessed 25 February 2020. <lb/>61 The European Supervisory Authorities, Joint Advice on the Costs and Benefits of a Coherent Cyber Resilience <lb/>Testing Framework for Significant Market Participants and Infrastructures, (2019) available at <lb/>https://eba.europa.eu/sites/default/documents/files/documents/10180/2551996/d229589f-a855-45f2-ad5a-<lb/>411792792e60/JC%202019%2025%20(Joint%20ESAs%20Advice%20on%20a%20coherent%20cyber%20resilien <lb/>ce%20testing%20framework).pdf accessed 26 February 2020. <lb/>62 Sironi, Supra n.54, at 51. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Therefore, the failure of a cloud provider could be disastrous to the financial system and the <lb/>economy. <lb/>The foregoing discussion about the benefits and risks of fintech raises a question about how <lb/>fintech industry should be regulated to mitigate the financial stability risks. In order to answer <lb/>this question, it is important to discuss how fintech fits within existing regulatory frameworks. <lb/>As discussed earlier, the financial regulatory reforms enacted since the GFC has focused on <lb/>traditional financial institutions. Particularly, they have been premised on addressing the roots <lb/>of the crisis caused by the traditional financial institutions. Taking into consideration the fact <lb/>that majority of the fintech firms are not regarded as traditional financial institutions, the <lb/>reforms have failed to consider the rise of fintech and its potential to alter financial service <lb/>attributes and market structure. This implies that, generally, the current regulatory frameworks <lb/>concerning financial institutions&apos; operations and activities do not apply to all fintech firms&apos; <lb/>activities and that may exert a negative effect on the stability of the entire financial system. <lb/>For instance, a recent survey by the European Securities and Markets Authority (ESMA) shows <lb/>that the main area where regulatory gaps and issues have been identified by National <lb/>Competent Authorities (NCAs) and where fintech firms do not fit neatly within the existing <lb/>rules is related to crypto-assets, Initial Coin Offering (ICOs) 63 and Distributed Ledger <lb/>Technology (DLTs). 64 In these areas, many NCAs have asked for clarification of EU regulatory <lb/>requirements. NCAs, for instance, claim that there is a lack of clarity in relation to the definition <lb/>of financial instruments and the legal nature of crypto assets. <lb/>Another important survey by IMF and World Bank Group (WBG) reviewing fintech <lb/>developments across the membership finds that nearly two-thirds of the countries responding <lb/>to the survey identified gaps in which fintech issues are not adequately addressed by their <lb/>current legal frameworks, especially the legal framework for financial sector related to peer-<lb/>to-peer lending, crypto-assets, robo-advisory services, mobile money, algorithmic trading, and <lb/>lending activities using AI. 65 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">63 An Initial Coin Offering is a method of raising funds using cryptocurrencies. It is often a form of <lb/>crowdfunding <lb/></note>
				
		<listBibl>64 The European Securities and Markets Authority, Report on the Licensing of FinTech Business Models, (2019) <lb/>available at https://www.esma.europa.eu/sites/default/files/library/esma50-164-<lb/>2430_licensing_of_fintech.pdf accessed 25 February 2020. <lb/>65 International Monetary Fund and World Bank Group, Supra n.60. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>It is also significant to emphasise that traditional regulatory frameworks and regulatory <lb/>institutions might be too slow and inflexible to properly regulate fintech. A careful balance, <lb/>therefore, needs to be struck between enabling fintech and addressing challenges to financial <lb/>stability. This balance is necessary not only to preserve financial stability but also to avoid <lb/>stalling the development of fintech. <lb/>Three regulatory approaches have so far emerged as a response to the development of fintech. <lb/>The first approach is &quot;wait and see&quot; or doing nothing and this approach could be characterised <lb/>as a laissez-faire approach. 66 While adopting this lenient regulatory approach may be beneficial <lb/>for the development of fintech, it entails different risks. Since reforming financial regulations <lb/>after the GFC, traditional financial institutions work under strict regulatory requirements and a <lb/>&apos;wait and see approach&apos; for fintech would give fintech firms an unfair competitive advantage. <lb/>This regulatory approach may also drive financial intermediation into a sector where financial <lb/>regulators only have limited influence. The second regulatory approach is a formal approach, <lb/>where financial regulators reform the existing regulations or enact new regulations in order to <lb/>provide a more proper and effective framework for new fintech firms and new activities. 67 For <lb/>instance, Mexico enacted Fintech Law in 2018 to promote financial inclusivity and <lb/>technological innovation. In the EU, the Payment Services Directive (PSD2), which entered <lb/>into application on 13 January 2018, facilitates innovative financial technology companies, <lb/>competition and efficiency. The PSD2 sets the rules on what type of organisations can provide <lb/>payment services within the European Economic Area (EEA). 68 <lb/>The third approach is the experimentalist approach, which involves introducing innovation <lb/>facilitators such as accelerators, innovation hubs and regulatory sandboxes. 69 Accelerators aim <lb/>at supporting particular tasks of policy relevance with funding support. 70 An innovation hub is <lb/>a platform established by the regulatory authority where the developers of fintech start-ups <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>66 See, Douglas Arner, Janos Nathan Barberis, Dirk A. Zetzsche &amp; Ross Buckey, FinTech and RegTech: Enabling <lb/>Innovation While Preserving Financial Stability, 18 Geo. J. Int&apos;l Aff. 47-58 (2017). <lb/>67 See, European Securities and Markets Authority, Financial Technology: ESMA&apos;s Approach, 4th Luxembourg <lb/>FinTech Conference (2018). Available at https://www.esma.europa.eu/sites/default/files/library/esma71-99-<lb/>1051_speech_on_cryptoassets_-_pa.pdf accessed 8 July 2019. <lb/>68 Available at https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32015L2366 accessed 8 July <lb/>2019. <lb/>69 See, FSB, Regulatory and Supervisory Issues from FinTech, (2017) available at https://www.fsb.org/wp-<lb/>content/uploads/Cambridge-Centre-for-Alternative-Finance-Regulatory-and-Supervisory-Issues-from-<lb/>FinTech.pdf accessed 9 July 2019. <lb/>70 Gupta and Tham Supra n.48, at 27. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>receive guidance from the regulator and, sometimes, from each other. The main function of <lb/>innovation hub is to promote innovations and to provide advice to newly established firms for <lb/>a fixed period. 71 In Australia, for example, an Innovation Hub was introduced in 2015, with <lb/>the aim of making it easier for the creators of fintech innovations to understand the regulatory <lb/>framework of financial intermediation. 72 A sandbox creates a testing environment or safe place <lb/>for fintech innovations to test products with less risk of being punished by the regulator. The <lb/>main aim of sandbox is to remove unnecessary regulatory barriers to innovations by allowing <lb/>them to test their financial product or business model for a predetermined period on real <lb/>consumers. 73 In the UK, the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) first introduced the sandbox <lb/>concept through an initiative called &quot;Project Innovate&quot;. The Project Innovate aimed at allowing <lb/>fintech firms to introduce their innovative services, products, and business models to the <lb/>financial market, without subjecting them to the full set of regulatory restrictions imposed by <lb/>the FCA. 74 The FCA also minimized costs and administrative barriers to fintech firms and new <lb/>entrants. In order to ensure the success of the project, the FCA established &quot;sandbox unit&quot; to <lb/>deal with sandbox applications and supervise the testing process by the fintech companies. <lb/>Inspired by the success of the FCA&apos;s sandbox in the UK, many other countries around the <lb/>world, such as, Canada, Thailand, Australia, Malaysia, Bahrain, UAE, US, Hong Kong, and <lb/>Singapore, have developed similar forms of a regulatory sandbox. 75 <lb/>Further, while some jurisdictions have taken or plan to take policy measures on fintech, the <lb/>scope and scale of changes or planned changes vary substantially. Generally, these measures <lb/>are still insufficient given the rapid growth of the fintech sector and its potential threat to global <lb/>financial stability and most of these measures do not take into account the fact that majority of <lb/>the fintech companies are not regarded as traditional financial institutions. This can be <lb/>attributed to the lack of the regulators knowledge about Fintech industry. It is also necessary <lb/>to emphasise the fact that the majority of the countries adopt &quot;do nothing&quot; approach to the <lb/>development of fintech either intentionally or otherwise. 76 Even in the countries that have taken <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>71 Magyar Nemzeti Bank, Innovation and Stability Overview of Fintech in Hungary, consultation document <lb/>(2017) available at https://www.mnb.hu/letoltes/consultation-document.pdf accessed 8 July 2019. <lb/>72 Australian Securities and Investments Commission, &apos;ASIC&apos;s Innovation Hub and our approach to regulatory <lb/>technology&apos; (2017) available at https://download.asic.gov.au/media/4270022/rep523-published-26-may-<lb/>2017.pdf accessed 8 July 2019. <lb/>73 See, Christopher G. Bradley, FinTech&apos;s Double Edges, 93 Chi.-Kent L. Rev. 61-95 (2018). <lb/>74 For further information see, FCA, Regulatory sandbox, (2019) available at <lb/>https://www.fca.org.uk/firms/regulatory-sandbox accessed 8 July 2019. <lb/>75 <lb/>Magyar Nemzeti Bank, Supra n. 71. <lb/>76 European Securities and Markets Authority, Supra n.67. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>important steps in regulating fintech, there are still some regulatory gaps that should be <lb/>addressed. The EU, for example, has introduced two key regulations in the form of the General <lb/>Data Privacy Regulation (GDPR) and PSD2, both of which came into force in 2018. While the <lb/>GDPR aims at protecting individual privacy by regulating the processing and transfer of <lb/>personal data, the PSD2 compels banks to give third-party providers access to customers&apos; bank <lb/>accounts, if requested by the customer. This would foster competition and innovation in <lb/>financial services. Nonetheless, as mentioned above, certain fintech services and products <lb/>offered in the EU such as crypto-assets, ICOs and DLTs are still not regulated. <lb/>Since the fintech growth presents a global challenge in financial regulation, a dynamic, <lb/>proactive, and responsive regulatory response might be supported by close international <lb/>cooperation. Because financial regulators in most of the countries do not currently necessarily <lb/>have appropriately experience to develop effective and comprehensive regulation in the fintech <lb/>sector, international cooperation led by international bodies-especially FSB-is crucial for the <lb/>development of fintech regulation and ensuring the global financial stability. On June 27, 2017, <lb/>the FSB published a report that examines the potential impacts of fintech on financial <lb/>stability. 77 The report concluded that given the small size of fintech sector, there were no <lb/>compelling financial stability risks from emerging fintech innovations. On February 14, 2019, <lb/>the FSB published another report about fintech developments and potential financial stability <lb/>implications. 78 Although the FSB&apos;s report demonstrates the same findings of the 2017 report, <lb/>it suggests that fintech has the potential to change the current structure of the financial system <lb/>and as a result it may have implications for financial stability. However, experience shows that <lb/>risks can emerge quickly if left unchecked. The role of unregulated shadow banking sector <lb/>during the GFC in amplifying the crisis is a clear evidence of how risks can evolve very quickly. <lb/>Therefore, the FSB approach should be proactive rather than reactive to mitigate the potential <lb/>risks that fintech could have on financial stability. <lb/>Further, given the lack of precise data and information about fintech and the small size of the <lb/>industry, financial stability has never been cited as an objective for recent regulatory measures <lb/>or reforms around fintech. Other than the financial stability, which is the main perspective of <lb/>analysing the implications of fintech in this article, relevant lenses for policymakers and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>77 See, FSB, Supra n.49. <lb/>78 FSB, FinTech and market structure in financial services: Market developments and potential financial stability <lb/>implications, (2019) available at https://www.fsb.org/wp-content/uploads/P140219.pdf accessed 8 July 2019. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>academics such as: (1) market integrity; (2) consumer and investor protection; (3) financial <lb/>inclusion; and (4) competition are at the fore. However, it is important to emphasise that the <lb/>article does not undermine the significance of these regulatory lenses, but rather it goes beyond <lb/>these concerns to demonstrate the significance of the financial stability when considering the <lb/>implications of the fintech industry. In fact, there might be overlaps and trade-offs between <lb/>those regulatory lenses and financial stability concern. Therefore, a careful balance needs to be <lb/>struck between financial stability and other policy concerns. <lb/>In sum, as explained above, fintech innovations bear various features of systemic risk, and the <lb/>level of such risk is more likely to increase as the size of the fintech activities grows, although <lb/>there is no clear evidence of such an effect at present. The post GFC reform of the financial <lb/>industry has focused on different sectors of the market and has largely ignored the unique risks <lb/>and problems associated with fintech. As a consequence, financial regulators have neither the <lb/>tools nor the expertise necessary to deal with fintech risks and challenges to financial stability. <lb/>4.Brexit and Financial Stability <lb/>This section analyses the potential effects of Brexit on global financial stability. Its main <lb/>conclusion is that the continuing uncertainty is potentially disruptive for global financial <lb/>stability as it does not leave institutions the time to properly prepare for changes in regulation. <lb/>Furthermore, there is a risk that the UK will either leave with no treaty after the transition <lb/>period or with a hastily agreed treaty that leaves significant issues to be decided in the future. <lb/>This will lead to several challenges with regards to global financial stability, which are analysed <lb/>in this section. <lb/>This section discusses first the important position of the UK on the global financial market. It <lb/>then analyses the loss of passporting rights which is an issue of immediate concern as this will <lb/>immediately affect financial firms and limit their operations. The third issue this section <lb/>analyses is the long-term effects of a diverging legislative framework between the UK and the <lb/>EU. The fourth part looks at several auxiliary issues which are likely to have an impact such <lb/>as financial firms moving to other Member States and the position of the UK as a clearing <lb/>house for euros. The concluding part analyses the importance that the agreement on the <lb/>financial framework continues to champion harmonised legislation. <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Overall, it points to the political uncertainties that dominate Brexit and which could influence <lb/>international financial stability due partly to sudden changes in capital flow in the short term <lb/>and divergent regulations between the EU Member States and the UK in the long term. It is <lb/>argued below that these issues are closely connected with the overarching issue of policy <lb/>uncertainty which represents a risk for global financial stability. Global legal harmonisation <lb/>can counter policy uncertainty as it would limit the effect that Brexit has on the international <lb/>financial market. This is of course a long-term solution and in the short-term governments <lb/>might need to implement domestic legislation to counter the effects of Brexit on domestic <lb/>financial stability. <lb/>4.1 The Key Position of the UK Financial Sector <lb/>The UK financial sector is one of the most internationally intertwined and globally competitive. <lb/>It represents nearly one fifth of the global banking sector. 79 The banking sector is the most <lb/>Europeanised and internationalised of the EU Member States 80 and it is the largest financial <lb/>sector in the EU 81 and the largest financial exporter in the world. 82 Assets held by the banking <lb/>sector were nearly 450% of UK GDP in 2013. 83 The sector is heavily international with about <lb/>half of those assets held by foreign banks. 84 Half of the assets of the banking sector consist of <lb/>loans to non-banks which highlights the important role the UK banking sector plays in <lb/>intermediating global capital. 85 EU banks have concentrated most of their wholesale activities <lb/>in the UK. 86 The financial sector in the UK is thus significant on both a European and a global <lb/>scale and any disruption to the sector threatens international financial stability. Furthermore, <lb/>the overrepresentation of the financial sector in the UK economy in comparison to the rest of <lb/>the EU means that in the other EU Member States the financial sector is underrepresented <lb/>compared to the size of the economy. This has caused a reliance in these states on larger banks <lb/>for investments and this makes their financial stability more dependent upon a smaller number <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>79 Jakob Miethe &amp; David Pothier, Brexit: What&apos;s at Stake for the Financial Sector? 6 DIW Economic Bulletin, <lb/>364,364 (2016). <lb/>80 David Howarth &amp; Lucia Quaglia, Brexit and the Single European Financial Market, 55 J. Common Mark. Stud. <lb/>149, 155 n.1 (2017). <lb/>81 Howarth,Supra n.80 at 152. <lb/>82 David Howarth &amp; Lucia Quaglia Brexit and the battle for financial services, 25 J. Eur. Public Policy, 1118, 1118 <lb/>n.8 (2018) <lb/>83 Miethe,Supra n.79, at 364. <lb/>84 Miethe,Supra n.79, at 367. <lb/>85 Miethe,Supra n.79, at 369. <lb/>86 John Springford &amp; Philip Whyte, the Consequences of Brexit for the City of London, Centre for European <lb/>Reform (2014) <lb/>https://www.cer.eu/publications/archive/policy-brief/2014/consequences-brexit-city-london <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>of large financial institutions. 87 Thus financial risks are concentrated in a limited number of <lb/>players which makes the market more vulnerable should there be any (potential) bankruptcy of <lb/>one of these institutions. <lb/>The above means that Brexit is likely to disrupt the financial stability in both the UK and the <lb/>other EU Member States, which in turn could pose a threat to global financial stability. This is <lb/>especially aggravated by the lack of clarity. Over three years after the referendum a transition <lb/>deal was concluded for one year, ending on the 1 st of January 2021. There currently is no deal <lb/>for beyond that date and negotiations are ongoing. Serious doubts have been raised on whether <lb/>is possible to conclude a trade agreement in this period. 88 The European Commission President <lb/>has warned that one year will not be enough to conclude an agreement on every area and any <lb/>special arrangements for the financial sector will have to wait until beyond 2020. 89 Both the <lb/>IMF and the World Bank have identified the no-deal scenario as a threat to financial stability <lb/>as the uncertainty could lead to risk aversion which will affect capital flows in the market. 90 <lb/>This would lead to political tensions, trade disruptions, volatile currencies, and damage <lb/>investors&apos; confidence. 91 Until a trade agreement is concluded the relationship between the UK <lb/>and the EU will be characterised by policy uncertainty. It is precisely this uncertainty that the <lb/>IMF warns about as it makes the market more volatile. <lb/>4.2 Loss of Passporting Rights <lb/>The key immediate concern for the financial market following Brexit would be the loss of <lb/>passporting rights. The effect of this will be felt immediately and is therefore the first issue of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>87 John Armour, Brexit and financial services,33 Oxf. Rev. Econ. Policy 54,56 n1 (2017) <lb/>88 See for instance: Jennifer Rankin, Get Brexit Done&apos;? The reality will be far more difficult and tortuous, The <lb/>Guardian, (25 November 2019). <lb/>https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2019/nov/25/get-brexit-done-reality-far-more-difficult-tortuous-<lb/>european-union <lb/>Stephen Bush, How limiting EU trade deal negotiations to one year may cause problems for Boris Johnson New <lb/>Statesman (17 December 2019). <lb/>https://www.newstatesman.com/politics/brexit/2019/12/how-limiting-eu-trade-deal-negotiations-one-year-<lb/>may-cause-problems-boris <lb/>89 Kate Proctor, Peter Walker and Daniel Boffey, Brexit: Boris Johnson will amend bill to outlaw extension, The <lb/>Guardian, (17 December 2019) <lb/>https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2019/dec/16/boris-johnson-will-amend-brexit-bill-to-outlaw-extension <lb/>90 IMF, Global Financial Stability Report: Vulnerabilities in a Maturing Credit Cycle, April 2019, XI <lb/>Available online at: https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/GFSR/Issues/2019/03/27/Global-Financial-Stability-<lb/>Report-April-2019 <lb/>91 IMF, Supra n.90, at 10 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>major concern for financial stability. A passport is a licence for a financial institution to conduct <lb/>business in any other Member State without need for further regulations. 92 Around 5,500 UK <lb/>firms rely on these passporting rights. Through passporting UK firms can access the Single <lb/>Market. These require for the Member States to ensure application of the EU &apos;single rulebook.&apos; <lb/>Passporting rights are especially important for the wholesale financial market which covers <lb/>derivatives, foreign exchange trading, private and public bond trading, equity trading, and <lb/>commodities trading. 93 The EU can grant regulatory equivalence which would allow UK <lb/>financial firms to continue to operate in the same way. The Financial Stability Board (FSB) has <lb/>promoted global regulatory equivalence as a tool to achieve financial stability. 94 This process <lb/>is not automatic; it takes time and is often politicised. This raises uncertainty for UK financial <lb/>firms as they cannot yet anticipate when and how regulatory equivalence will be agreed. <lb/>Passporting rights would not be carried over following Brexit. Only if the UK remains in the <lb/>Single Market would passporting rights be maintained. Passporting rights are important for the <lb/>UK financial sector but loss of these will also affect the global financial market. For instance, <lb/>the EU investment fund, &quot;Undertakings for the Collective Investment in Transferable <lb/>Securities&quot; (UCITS), which is worth around 8,000 billion euros is managed from the UK and <lb/>half of the world&apos;s financial firms have based their EU headquarters in the UK. 95 <lb/>Third country institutions must apply for admission in each Member State and are subject to <lb/>both the legislation of their home state and the host state. 96 This is costly and burdensome. <lb/>There are some exceptions to this rule in the form of regulatory equivalence. Regulatory <lb/>equivalence would give UK financial firms some access to the Single Market. The rights are <lb/>not as extensive as passporting rights and do no not affect all financial services. For instance, <lb/>the scope for retail and commercial banking and primary insurers is limited. 97 It is therefore <lb/>not a perfect solution and it will leave uncertainty unless these services are covered in <lb/>additional agreements between the UK and the EU. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>92 Based on two EU Directives: Capital Requirements Directive (CRD; 2013/36/EU) and the Markets in Financial <lb/>Instruments Directive (MiFID; 2004/39/EC). <lb/>93 Dirk Schoenmaker, The UK Financial Sector and EU Integration after Brexit: The Issue of Passporting 9 (N <lb/>(2016) ( Nauro Campos &amp; Fabrizio Coricelli ed., Palgrave MacmIllian 2016). <lb/>94 Matthias Lehmann &amp; Dirk Zetzsche, How Does it Feel to be a Third Country? The Consequences of Brexit for <lb/>Financial Market Law, Brexit: the International Legal Implications, Paper No.14 Brexit: The International Legal <lb/>Implications 5-6 (2018). <lb/>95 Michael McMahon, The implications of Brexit for the City 80 The CAGE Background Briefing Series 2 (2017). <lb/>96 Lehmann, Supra n.94, at4. <lb/>97 Armour, Supra n.87, at 65. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>The decision on whether to grant regulatory equivalence is taken by the EC. The EC has the <lb/>right to withdraw equivalence at a short notice (30 days) if regulations diverge too much. The <lb/>interpretation of &apos;too much&apos; lies with the EC and is a political decision. As financial legislation <lb/>is currently aligned the main issue for the UK will be that regulatory equivalence can easily be <lb/>used as a political negotiation tool as happened for instance when Switzerland did not receive <lb/>clearing system equivalence when it restricted the free movement of EU workers. 98 The EC <lb/>takes into account the wider circumstances, including policy concerns when making a decision <lb/>on granting equivalence. 99 This means that it is not only whether a third state meets the <lb/>legislative criteria but also whether this decision promotes the coherence and integrity of the <lb/>Single Market. Given that this is a political decision no legal appeal against the decision is <lb/>possible. 100 <lb/>The UK would still need to follow the &apos;single rulebook&apos; (much of which is based on <lb/>international financial agreements). 101 Currently, there are 39 regulatory equivalences under 14 <lb/>different laws. 102 These would all need to be followed and they are subject to change with new <lb/>rules added on a regular base. 103 Following Brexit, the UK would lose its influence on shaping <lb/>the single-rulebook. This means that the financial interests of the City will not be represented <lb/>within the law-making process. 104 An example is that in 2011 the European Central Bank <lb/>(ECB) decided that Euro dominated transactions should be cleared in the Eurozone. At the time <lb/>the UK successfully appealed this policy in the European Court of Justice (ECJ). Following <lb/>Brexit, the UK will have no influence if the EU decided to implant this policy (or any others.) 105 <lb/>In principle there should not be a legal issue in granting the UK regulatory equivalence, given <lb/>the current regulatory convergence. There is a risk that the equivalence process will be <lb/>politicised in the course of the trade agreement negotiations, especially if these are not <lb/>straightforward (and events of the last three years have proven that these negotiations are <lb/>anything but easy). 106 Given the seemingly complete lack of absence of any planning for Brexit <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>98 Lehmann, Supra n.94, at 7. <lb/>99 Lehmann, Supra n.94, at 7. <lb/>100 Lehmann, Supra n.94, at 17. <lb/>101 Niamh Moloney, Financial Services, the EU, and Brexit: An Uncertain Future for the City? , 17 German Law <lb/>Journal 75, 80 (2016). <lb/>102 Armour, Supra n.87, at 61. <lb/>103 Armour, Supra n.87, at 61. <lb/>104 Moloney, Supra n.101. at 81. <lb/>105 Armour, Supra n.87, at 62. <lb/>106 Armour, Supra n.87, at 62. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>in the UK there is a risk that regulatory equivalence would not be agreed and implemented in <lb/>time before the end of the transition agreement. For instance, for Australia, Hong Kong and <lb/>Singapore it took two years for the legislation to come into force. 107 <lb/>The financial sector argues that loss of passporting rights will result in higher costs and higher <lb/>risks for customers and investors 108 Investment becomes more expense but also riskier because <lb/>the flexibility of financial institutions decreases as more requirements are placed on these with <lb/>regards to location (need to establish a presence in an EU Member State), requirements to clear <lb/>assets in euros, and a limited access to the Single Market. <lb/>The period between loss of passporting rights and regulatory equivalence is specifically a risky <lb/>period. UK financial institutions will face significant upheaval during that time. As stated <lb/>above the IMF warns of risk aversion from investors which leads to a more volatile financial <lb/>market. The global significance of the UK financial market means that the effects of the higher <lb/>risks and costs will not be restricted to the UK or even the EU but will also be globally felt. <lb/>The longer that this uncertainty last the greater this effect will be on the financial market that <lb/>will seek to compensate for that uncertainty through charging higher costs and a loss of <lb/>investment. <lb/>It should also be noted that EU and non-EU financial firms could also have potential difficulty <lb/>accessing the UK financial market depending on what policies the UK will implement <lb/>following Brexit. Therefore, firms from Member States and third countries will also face <lb/>uncertainty as to their position in the UK financial market which is also a risk for global <lb/>financial stability. <lb/>It is unlikely that the UK will choose to throw up significant barriers for access as this would <lb/>affect their own financial institutions disproportionally. However, there is no guarantee that no <lb/>new rules will be adopted. Furthermore, due to the difficulties of negotiating the overarching <lb/>Brexit framework less attention is paid by the Government and Parliament to specific sections <lb/>of that legal framework. This means that whilst regulations that blocks access might not be <lb/>likely, there will be regulatory gaps as there will have been no time to vote in new legislation <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>107 Armour, Supra n.87, at 63. <lb/>108 Howarth, Supra n.82, at 1122 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>to fill these gaps. This risk can of course be addressed by immediately starting the process for <lb/>regulatory equivalence, but that cannot be done until there is further clarity on the future legal <lb/>framework between the UK and the EU. The main risk factors from loss of passporting rights <lb/>are therefore the uncertainty as to the future relationship between the EU and the UK, the gaps <lb/>to regulatory equivalence, and the politicisation of the equivalence process which means that <lb/>there could be a delay before any legal solutions are adopted. <lb/>4.3 The Financial Legal Framework <lb/>Following the GFC, the EU introduced a significant amount of new regulations, including for <lb/>previously unregulated organisations such as credit rating agencies and activities such as over <lb/>the counter derivates. 109 There is now a near complete legal European framework that regulates <lb/>financial institutions, and this will not be automatically transposed following Brexit. This <lb/>means that there will be regulatory gaps, and this creates significant policy uncertainty which <lb/>is a cause of financial volatility and can thus destabilise the financial market. 110 . When the UK <lb/>leaves the EU, all financial firms in the UK will be treated as located in a third country. 111 This <lb/>means that they will then be subject to the EU financial laws that apply to firms from third <lb/>countries. This represents a significant shift for UK based financial firms and they will need to <lb/>adjust to the changes. <lb/>As discussed, most of the current legislative framework in the financial sector in the UK is part <lb/>of the EU legal framework. 112 Much of this is international in nature and based on standards <lb/>set by International Standard Setting Bodies (ISSBs). 113 Therefore, the UK is unlikely to make <lb/>significant changes to the regulatory framework in the short term, but will roll over these <lb/>measures as they stand. EU financial law will continue to be relevant for the UK financial <lb/>sector after Brexit, given that financial institutions will continue to operate on both the EU and <lb/>the UK financial market. This could enhance the regulatory burdens on companies who will <lb/>now have to contend with EU law requirements as well as potentially divergent UK law. If UK <lb/>law remains aligned with EU law and the law is thus harmonised there is a greater potential for <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>109 Howarth, Supra n.80 at 153. <lb/>110 Ansgar Belke, Irina Dubova &amp; Thomas Osowski (2018) Policy uncertainty and international financial <lb/>markets: the case of Brexit, 50 Applied Economics 3759 n.34-35 (2018). <lb/>111 Lehmann, Supra n.94, at 16. <lb/>112 Moloney, Supra n.101. at 75. <lb/>113 Moloney, Supra n.101. at 75 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>financial stability. Legal harmonisation is key in combatting policy uncertainty. 114 The effects <lb/>of this policy uncertainty on the financial market can already be seen. The Financial Times <lb/>reported that $4.2b has been withdrawn from UK equity funds since May 2019 and that total <lb/>capital outflow since the referendum is already $29.7bn and with experts agreeing that the <lb/>uncertainty of a Brexit deal is the major contributor to this capital outflow. 115 Investors are <lb/>worried that if the UK leaves without a deal or only a perfunctory deal that leaves most policies <lb/>to be negotiated at a later point, there will be no clarity on whether UK and EU financial law <lb/>will continue to develop in a harmonised manner, or whether divergence will arise and if so <lb/>what that would look like. <lb/>UK financial law is thus largely composed of EU law, some of this based on transnational <lb/>regulations. Following Brexit, it will be a monumental task to decide which obligations to carry <lb/>over. There is a risk that regulatory gaps will appear. 116 This is especially the case when one <lb/>considers the law beyond Regulations and Directives which have been incorporated in UK <lb/>statutory law. The EU has emitted a vast number of guidelines, notes, and other documents, <lb/>many of which are followed by the UK or at least hold some legal authority because of their <lb/>provenance from the EU institutions. 117 When the UK leaves the EU, this legal authority <lb/>diminishes (and their position will be less clear) and as these rules are not part of statutory law, <lb/>they cannot be rolled over as easily. This could lead to legislative gaps. Legislative gaps and <lb/>the diminished legal authority of EU transitional financial rules which carry no direct legal <lb/>obligations are again a cause of policy uncertainty. <lb/>The UK financial sector has sometimes raised issues with (in their eyes) the overregulation of <lb/>EU financial service. This reflects the difference of philosophies between the more liberalised <lb/>viewpoint of the UK and the more market regulatory viewpoint of some of the other Member <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>114 On issues related to legal harmonisation and uncertainty see for instance: <lb/>A. Claire Cutler, Unification and Harmonisation of Private International Trade Law 13 Global Society 25 (199) <lb/>Steve Maguire &amp; Jaye Ellis, Uncertainty, Precaution and Global Interdependence: Implications of the <lb/>Precautionary Principle for State and Non-state Actors, 256 (Biermann et all. ed. Global Environmental Change <lb/>and the Nation State, Proceedings of the 2001 Berlin Conference on the Human Dimensions of Global <lb/>Environmental Change (2001) <lb/>José Angelo Estrella Faria, Future Directions of Legal Harmonisation and Law Reform: Stormy Seas or <lb/>Prosperous Voyage?, 14 Uniform Law Review 5 (2009). <lb/>115 Chris Flood &amp; Shioban Riding, Investors pull billions from UK on prospect of no-deal Brexit, Financial Times, <lb/>31 Aug. 2019 <lb/>116 Moloney, Supra n.101. at 82 <lb/>117 Moloney, Supra n.101. at 82 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>States (including Germany and France). 118 The UK often advocates for less mandatory <lb/>regulation. 119 The UK has been able to influence the financial legal framework as a member of <lb/>the EU but will no longer be able to do so in the same capacity when outside the EU. <lb/>Furthermore, it will be able to draft legislation reflective of its philosophies. This could lead to <lb/>more regulatory divergence in the future. 120 The ECB has expressed its concerns that <lb/>divergence could lead to a regulatory race to the bottom. 121 Whilst deregulation could boost <lb/>aspects of the financial sector in the short run as it will attract financial institutions, such a <lb/>competition could in the long run affect international financial stability considerably and would <lb/>encourage other states (in particular the EU) to limit access to their markets. 122 Due to the need <lb/>for regulatory equivalence between the UK and the EU there will likely be no significant <lb/>divergence in the short term. 123 However, due to the different approaches as discussed above <lb/>and the difficulty of rolling over the soft law framework in its entirety it is likely that divergence <lb/>will occur in the medium to long term. Financial stability in a globalised market requires <lb/>coherency between national laws 124 as international financial stability is dependent upon <lb/>international cooperation. 125 The FSB has identified legal fragmentation as a key risk to <lb/>financial stability. 126 <lb/>Therefore, there is a need to ensure that agreements following Brexit ensure close regulatory <lb/>equivalence. This agreement, whatever shapes it takes, will not deal with the complete myriad <lb/>of guidelines, rules, and other forms of soft law. This body of law cannot be harmonised as <lb/>easily. Financial institutions could play a leading role by ensuring they institute harmonised <lb/>rules and guidelines to fill in any gaps. The market can play an important role in legal <lb/>harmonisation if this is seen as beneficial for growth. If institutions feel they can benefit from <lb/>divergence and competition, there will be less incentive for ensuring this harmonisation. It is <lb/>thus important that states have a strong globally harmonised regulatory framework and that no <lb/>major gaps arise in the legislation. This also encourages institutions to cooperate so that a <lb/>harmonised soft law framework continues to exist and develop beyond Brexit. These are long-<lb/></body>

			<listBibl>118 <lb/>Howarth, Supra n.80 at 158 <lb/>119 Armour, Supra n.87, at 56 <lb/>120 Howarth,Supra n.80 at 158 <lb/>121 Howarth, Supra n.82, at 1125 <lb/>122 Springford, Supra n.86, at 7 <lb/>123 Michael Randall, Brexit and Financial Services: What Comes next, 22 Edinburgh L. Rev. 149, 154 (2018) <lb/>124 Springford, Supra n.86, at 6 <lb/>125 Armour, Supra n.87, at 60. <lb/>126 Lehmann, Supra n.94, at 5. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>term solutions and the work on these can only start after the future relationship between the <lb/>UK and the EU is defined. There will thus likely be an uncertain period where issues have not <lb/>been regulated and this will likely be followed by divergence in the legal framework between <lb/>the UK and EU. This means financial firms are likely to need to adapt several times to new <lb/>regulations which would cause further disruption. <lb/>4.4 Additional Disruptive Issues <lb/>Financial firms will need to further expand their operations to the EU Member States and <lb/>therefore Brexit will lead to additional costs for the sector. 127 Financial services could decide <lb/>to relocate to other EU Member States. 128 There is also a possibility that some firms will seek <lb/>to relocate some of their services outside of the EU, for instance to the US. 129 The EU Member <lb/>States are not a monolith and there will be competition between states on attracting financial <lb/>operations in an attempt to become the main financial hub of the eurozone. This is coupled <lb/>with the risk of competitive legislation, a race to the bottom (as discussed above), whereby <lb/>different states will try to attract as many services as possible. 130 This all leads to an unstable <lb/>situation and this could affect the confidence of investors. Risk aversion could lead to <lb/>disinvestment in the short term as investors are likely to wait until the situation stabilises. 131 <lb/>The UK is the main clearing hub for euros. It is unclear whether the EU will impose legislation <lb/>that will limit the position of the UK, but it is likely there will be changes. The ECB as well as <lb/>the French and German governments have already made statements discussing the need to <lb/>ensure that the Eurozone should be the main clearing area for euros. 132 This means that UK <lb/>financial institutions will face restrictions on certain transactions and that they will have to shift <lb/>operations to the Single Market. This leads to an upheaval in the market and additional costs. <lb/>Whilst most of this section focused on the effects of the UK financial sector on international <lb/>financial stability there is also the issue of how the changes will affect the EU. Research <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>127 McMahon, Supra n.95, at 3 <lb/>128 Douglas J. Cumming &amp; Shaker A. Zahra, International Business and Entrepreneurship Implications of Brexit, <lb/>27 Br. J. Manag, 687, 689 (2016). <lb/>129 André Sapir, Dirk Schoenmaker, &amp; Nicolas Véron, Making the Best of Brexit for the EU27, 1 Bruegel Policy <lb/>Brief 6 (2017) <lb/>130 Sapir, Supra n.129, at 6 <lb/>131 Randall, Supra n.123, at 150. <lb/>132 Howarth, Supra n.82, at 1124 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>indicates that the EU banking sector could be hit even worse than that of the UK. 133 This is <lb/>because of a decline in investment firms in the EU (with banks not being able to support the <lb/>investments in the firm) and a decrease in total deposits in EU banks which makes the banking <lb/>sector in the EU more vulnerable. 134 This means that negative economic consequences of <lb/>Brexit will be felt within the EU banking sector and lead to the EU banking sector not carrying <lb/>the real weight of the economy, given that this will no longer be supported by the UK banking <lb/>sector, which now plays a disproportionally large role. 135 If there is no deal this will likely <lb/>cause financial instability which will impact national economies. 136 <lb/>4.5 Future Planning <lb/>In 2016 the US Treasury Department warned that Brexit could be a threat to the stability of the <lb/>US financial sector given that there will be a long period of uncertainty about the rules that <lb/>would now govern transactions. 137 In 2020 there is still the same uncertainty and a quick <lb/>resolution seems far away. This article has not discussed the impact of Brexit on the economy <lb/>as a whole as this is beyond its scope. It is clear that the economy of both the UK and the <lb/>Member States could be severely impacted by Brexit. 138 This would also affect the financial <lb/>sector. <lb/>Not all sections of the financial sector will be equally affected by Brexit. Most at risk are the <lb/>sections which are the most globalised. These would include wholesale banking, investment <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>133 Aristeidis Samitas Stathis Polyzosb &amp; Costas Siriopoulosa, Brexit and Financial Stability: An Agent-based <lb/>Simulation, 69 Economic Modelling 1 (2018). <lb/>134 Samitas, Supra n.133, at 29. <lb/>135 Samitas, Supra n.133, at 31. <lb/>136 Randall, Supra n.123, at 150. <lb/>137 Douglas, Supra. n.128, at 689 <lb/>138 UNCTAD has warned of the strong effects of a non-deal Brexit on the economy and predicts this could lead <lb/>to a 7% drop in exports from the UK to the EU (which is $16 billion dollars) and that 20% of the UK exports to <lb/>non-member states are at risk because these non-member states have preferential access to the EU market <lb/>through trade deals. <lb/>(Pamela Coke &amp; Alessandro Nicita, The trade cost of a no-deal Brexit to the United Kingdom, 3 Sept. 2019 <lb/>https://unctad.org/en/pages/newsdetails.aspx?OriginalVersionID=2176 ) <lb/>Research from UNCTAD also analyses how a no-deal Brexit would hit especially the economies of the UK, the <lb/>EU, but could also affect non-member states that have strong trading links with the UK (such as for instance <lb/>Turkey) <lb/>(Alessandro Nicita, Ksenia Koloskova &amp; Mesut Saygili, Brexit. Implications for Developing Countries, UNCTAD <lb/>Research Paper No.31 (2019) <lb/>See also for the effects of Brexit on the economy: <lb/>Patrick Minford, The effects of Brexit on the UK economy, 42 The World Economy, 57 n.1 (2019) <lb/>Gabriel Felbermayr, Clemens Fuest, Jasmin Katrin Gröschl &amp; Daniel Stöhlker, Economic Effects of Brexit on the <lb/>European Economy, Economic Policy Reports 4(2017) <lb/>John van Reenen, Brexit&apos;s Long-Run Effects on the U.K. Economy, Brookings Papers on Economic 367 (2016) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>banking, and derivatives clearing. 139 At risk are especially non-EU headquartered banks that <lb/>have a UK subsidiary to ensure EU passporting rights (around 14% of the UK banking <lb/>sector). 140 These would no longer have a reason to be in the UK and would likely relocate to a <lb/>Member State. 141 The banking sector would thus be impacted, especially given the limited <lb/>regulatory equivalence that exists for retail and commercial banking. 142 For other sectors such <lb/>as wholesale financial transactions there likely will be more intensive competition from for <lb/>instance the United States. 143 <lb/>The UK and the EU have already taken some specific measures to avoid disruption to the <lb/>financial market such as the recent activation of currency swap arrangements between the Bank <lb/>of England and the ECB to underpin market liquidity. The EU has adopted time-limited <lb/>equivalence decisions for UK central counterparties and central securities depositaries. These <lb/>types of solutions should be further encouraged but it would be important to ensure these fit in <lb/>an overarching legal framework and are not just temporary stopgaps. <lb/>This section discussed the potential effects of Brexit on global financial stability. These effects <lb/>are closely linked to uncertainty. The key short-term risk is the loss of passporting rights <lb/>(especially if there is not immediately a lack of regulatory equivalence) and the key long-term <lb/>risk is legal divergence which works against financial stability as the latter benefits from legal <lb/>harmonisation. Policy uncertainty is a net contributor to financial instability, even to eclipse <lb/>the actual financial volatility event itself. 144 In the UK this effect could be observed following <lb/>the Brexit referendum and is likely to continue, even in the medium term. 145 The Withdrawal <lb/>Agreement only concerns the transition period and a further trade deal still needs to be <lb/>negotiated. 146 Therefore, the continued uncertainty represents a risk to international financial <lb/>stability. This is aggravated by the politicisation of the process which leads to further delays in <lb/>establishing long term policy. The UK and the EU will need to come to an agreement on the <lb/>financial sector as soon as possible and it is important that such an agreement is comprehensive, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>139 Howarth, Supra n.82, at1123 <lb/>140 Armour, Supra n.87, at 65. <lb/>141 <lb/>Armour, Supra n.87, at 65. <lb/>142 Armour, Supra n.87, at 67. <lb/>143 Armour, Supra n.87, at 67. <lb/>144 Belke, Supra n.110, at 3759. <lb/>145 Belke, Supra n.110, at 3762. <lb/>146 EU (Withdrawal Agreement) Bill Available on: https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/eu-<lb/>withdrawal-agreement-bill <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>in alignment with international developments, focused not just on the EU and the UK but also <lb/>taking into account the global financial market in order to foster stability, and is aimed at <lb/>maintaining legal harmonisation. <lb/>5. Emerging Market Economies -Key Issues for Financial Stability <lb/>5.1 Introductory Issues <lb/>This final part analyses key risks in emerging market economies (EME) that could threaten <lb/>global financial stability, and which have not yet been sufficiently recognised by policy makers <lb/>and analysts. The literature has concentrated mainly on the effects of global financial markets <lb/>on EME and has not analysed how key issues that specifically affect EME would affect global <lb/>financial stability. This section analyses several of these other issues: specifically, unstable <lb/>trade policies from major players like the USA, (a perception) of domestic policy uncertainty <lb/>leading to sudden changes in capital flow, and high foreign currency debts leaving the market <lb/>more vulnerable to changes in international financial markets. Whilst the effects of these issues <lb/>on the domestic financial markets in EME have been discussed, there is no in-depth analysis <lb/>on how in turn this could affect global financial stability. This section will thus analyse how <lb/>these issues destabilise domestic financial markets in EME from the perspective of how this <lb/>affects global financial stability. <lb/>EME can be defined as low income countries that have a fast pace of development and a <lb/>government favouring economic liberalisation policies. 147 They have diverse economic <lb/>environments, but instability is a common factor. 148 As the economies develop further, they <lb/>become more entwined with the international financial market. The ECB has stated that <lb/>compared to two decades ago, EME play a significantly more prominent role in the global <lb/>economy. 149 They now account for more than half of global GDP (at purchasing power parity) <lb/>and gross capital flows. 150 Thus there now more risk of EME affecting global financial stability <lb/>because of their larger role in the international economy. EME and advanced economies share <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>147 Robert E. Hoskisson, Lorraine Eden, Chung Ming Lau &amp; Mike Wright, Strategy in Emerging Economies, 43 <lb/>Acad. Manag. J. 249, 249 n.3 (2000). <lb/>148 Klaus Meyer &amp; Mike Peng, Theoretical Foundations of Emerging Economies Business Research, 47 J. Int. Bus. <lb/>Stud. 3, 10. n.1 (2016) <lb/>149 Livia Chitu &amp; Dominic Quint, Emerging market vulnerabilities -a comparison with previous crises, ECB <lb/>Economic Bulletin, n.8 (2018) <lb/>https://www.ecb.europa.eu/pub/economic-bulletin/focus/2018/html/ecb.ebbox201808_01.en.html <lb/>150 <lb/>Chitu, Supra n.148 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>many similar vulnerabilities that could put international financial stability at risk. EME are <lb/>highly volatile and investment in EME is characterised as high risk by financial institutions. 151 <lb/>This means that EME are more vulnerable to policy uncertainty and this can potentially have a <lb/>rippling effect on the global financial market. <lb/>Whereas previously a financial crisis affecting advance economies would strongly affect <lb/>emerging economies but far less so the other way around, this is no longer the case. Because <lb/>of the economic growth of EME threats to financial stability now also flow from EME to <lb/>advanced economies and it is important that policy makers worldwide have appropriate tools <lb/>to monitor and understand these risks. 152 This is especially so in relation to those risks to which <lb/>EME are especially vulnerable in comparison to advanced economies. <lb/>Obviously, the topic of EME is vast and this article does not include a complete discussion on <lb/>all issues related to financial stability and EME. It only seeks to highlight several key issues <lb/>that could affect global financial stability. Furthermore, EME are a diverse group of countries <lb/>all over the world. It is clear that different factors are at play in each of these economies. This <lb/>section thus concentrates on several risks common to EME that could threaten international <lb/>financial stability. <lb/>5.2 Trade Policy <lb/>Both the World Bank and the IMF have identified trade tensions with the US as a potential risk <lb/>to worldwide financial stability. 153 US trade policy is important for the global financial market <lb/>because of the size of its economy and the role of the dollar as the global reserve currency. <lb/>Growth of global trade has slowed significantly in recent years. 154 This is mainly due to <lb/>changes in trade policy. The overall rise in protectionism has led to the integration of <lb/>international trade slowing down. 155 In itself this does not necessarily threaten financial <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>151 Ashoka Mody, What is An Emerging Market? IMF Working Papers, N. 04/177, 3 (2004). <lb/>https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/WP/Issues/2016/12/31/What-is-An-Emerging-Market-17598 <lb/>152 Etienne Lepers &amp; Antonio Sánchez Serrano, Decomposing financial (in)stability in emerging economies, 9 <lb/>Working Paper Series European Systemic Risk Board (2017) <lb/>153 IMF, Global Financial Stability Report: A Decade after the Global Financial Crisis: Are We Safer?, 5 (2018). <lb/>:https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/GFSR/Issues/2018/09/25/Global-Financial-Stability-Report-October-<lb/>2018 <lb/>154 IMF, Supra n.90, at IX <lb/>155 Vanessa Gunnella &amp; Lucia Quaglietti, The economic implications of rising protectionism: a euro area and <lb/>global perspective, 3 ECB Economic Bulletin (2019) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>stability. However as discussed in previous sections, for the financial market to be stable, policy <lb/>certainty is key. Whilst this is a global threat it is more likely to affect EME because they are <lb/>less shock-resistant to policy uncertainties because of domestic policy uncertainty and they are <lb/>more vulnerable to sudden changes in capital flow. 156 <lb/>The trade policy of the US has become more volatile in recent years. Policies of the current <lb/>administration are difficult to predict and anticipate. This could affect stability because it is <lb/>hard for financial institutions to predict effects of a policy if there is no clarity on what that <lb/>policy will be. Especially the trade tensions between the US and China have the possibility of <lb/>affecting financial stability given the size of the Chinese economy. This is even more of an <lb/>issue because of the financial fluctuations in China&apos;s economy and the currently less <lb/>predictable and more unstable growth of the Chinese economy. 157 The lack of a consistent trade <lb/>policy makes it difficult to adjust and this creates uncertainty among both states and businesses. <lb/>Whilst the exact effects are difficult to predict, the financial market reacts to changes in trade <lb/>policy. For instance, the optimism about negotiations between China and the US were one of <lb/>the causes of the rebound of the financial market at the start of 2019. 158 <lb/>Under the current US administration led by President Trump, the approach to global trade is <lb/>characterised by further protectionism and frequent policy changes that are more political than <lb/>economic in nature. This has, for instance, resulted in the imposition of higher trade tariffs on <lb/>an assortment of goods (including steel and aluminium) and on goods from certain states <lb/>(notably China). Of course, trading partners respond to these changes by levying their own <lb/>tariffs. Trade policy is used as a political tool. In June 2019 the Trump Administration <lb/>threatened to impose 5% tariffs on Mexican imports unless Mexico stopped migrants from <lb/>crossing the US southern border. If Mexico did not respond the tariffs would go up to 25% by <lb/>October 2019. 159 Clearly, these tariffs serve no economic purpose and were meant as a political <lb/>tool to pressure the Mexican government in compliance. Using trade policy in this way is likely <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>https://www.ecb.europa.eu/pub/economic <lb/>bulletin/articles/2019/html/ecb.ebart201903_01~e589a502e5.en.html <lb/>156 IMF, Supra n.90, at IX <lb/>157 <lb/>IMF, Supra n.90, at IX <lb/>158 <lb/>IMF, Supra n.90, at IX <lb/>159 Sarah Nassauer &amp; Heather Haddon, Tariffs on Mexican Imports Would Hit More Than Avocados in Grocery <lb/>Stores, 1 Jun. 2019, The Walls Street Journal <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>to cause unrest on the market as the decisions are unpredictable and there is no economic logic <lb/>behind them. <lb/>The attitude of the Trump Administration towards international trade is that of a zero-sum, <lb/>adversarial approach, where there is a winner and a loser. 160 As evidenced by the refusal of <lb/>the Trump Administration to nominate candidates to the appellate dispute resolution body of <lb/>the World Trade Organisation (WTO) and the attacks on the North America Free Trade <lb/>Association (NAFTA) and the support of Brexit there is a mistrust within the Administration <lb/>for the organisations that seek to regulate international trade. If the US operates mainly outside <lb/>of the confines of the international institutions their policy becomes less predictable. The US <lb/>could use the size of its economy to push for more advantageous, less balanced trade deals with <lb/>other states which could diminish the flow of capital between states, and states with emerging <lb/>markets are more vulnerable to this. 161 The operation of the Trump Administration outside <lb/>institutional confines threatens economic stability because these organisations provide <lb/>mechanisms to limit the effect on shocks to the financial market. 162 This could also weaken the <lb/>position of the IMF which is an institution that promotes economic growth and financial <lb/>stability. 163 Trading outside the bounds of international institutions which are characterised by <lb/>a rule-based approach to trade means a less structured, more volatile, and less predictable <lb/>approach to international trade. This could particularly affect EME who on average have less <lb/>financial resilience to cope with changing policies and who have on average weaker domestic <lb/>institutions that could not take over the role that international institutions currently fulfil. <lb/>Haley discusses how trade agreements (bilateral and multilateral) often have currency <lb/>manipulation clauses which push out IMF policy and how these clauses put smaller economies <lb/>at a disadvantage as they would have more to lose in case of a dispute that threatens the flow <lb/>of trade. 164 Possible effects could include businesses deciding to diminish their exports or not <lb/>entering foreign markets at all. 165 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>160 James A Haley, Trump Trade Policy, Exchange Rate Surveillance and the IMF: Back to the Future?, Centre for <lb/>International Governance Innovation, No. 224 CIGI Papers 1 (2019) <lb/>https://www.cigionline.org/sites/default/files/documents/no.224web.pdf <lb/>161 Haley, Supra n.160, at 1. <lb/>162 Haley, Supra n.160, at 11. <lb/>163 Haley, Supra n.160, at 10. <lb/>164 Haley, Supra n.160, at 9. <lb/>165 Gunnella, Supra n.157. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Information asymmetry is a key obstacle for well-functioning and stable financial system as <lb/>information flows interfere with the financial system and this &apos;can then no longer perform its <lb/>function of mobilising savings, facilitating the exchange of goods and services, reducing risks <lb/>and allocating resources to productive sectors.&apos; 166 This points to the importance of reliable <lb/>information to inform state policy and to inform decisions made by financial firms. A volatile <lb/>trade policy encourages information asymmetry and would thus be a risk factor for states <lb/>(which cannot predict changes in trade policy as easily) and for financial firms (which have no <lb/>reliable information to inform their decisions). <lb/>If trade tensions escalate further this could lead to eroding confidence in the global economy. 167 <lb/>Model based simulations from the IMF and the ECB indicate that the escalation of trade <lb/>tensions causes additional financial stress on the market. 168 The market cannot predict the <lb/>changes in policy and risk aversive investors will be slower to invest and quicker to withdraw <lb/>funds. Depending on how predicable and sudden the changes are this can affect international <lb/>financial stability. EME are more vulnerable to these sudden changes because of several <lb/>factors: they have less ability to cope with changes in trade policy as their infrastructure is less <lb/>developed, their financial markets are characterised by high foreign currency debts which <lb/>makes them more vulnerable to changes in the global economy, and investors are already more <lb/>risk averse when it comes to EME. If trade policy tensions destabilise the financial market this <lb/>disproportionally affects EME which in turn can affect global financial stability. <lb/>5.3 The Flow of Capital <lb/>A second important risk to financial stability in EME is a sudden change in capital flows. To <lb/>further develop the financial market in EME capital flow across borders is encouraged. <lb/>However, capital flow also brings risk to financial stability. 169 It leaves the economy more <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>166 Enowbi Batuo, Kupukile Mlambo &amp; Simplice Asongu, Linkages between financial development, <lb/>financial instability, financial liberalisation and economic growth in Africa, African Governance and <lb/>Development Institute, No. 82641 MPRA Pape, 7 (2017). <lb/>https://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/82641/1/MPRA_paper_82641.pdf <lb/>Roger Gordon &amp; A. Lans Bovenberg, Why is capital so mobile internationally? Possible explanations and <lb/>implications for capital income taxation, 86 Am. Econ. Rev 1057 n.5 (1996). <lb/>167 Gunnella, Supra n.155. <lb/>168 Gunnella, Supra n.155. <lb/>169 Ulrich Volz (ed.), Financial Stability in Emerging Markets: Dealing with Global Liquidity, German <lb/>Development Institute 4 (2012) <lb/>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/256017592_Financial_Stability_in_Emerging_Markets_-<lb/>_Dealing_with_Global_Liquidity <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>vulnerable to external shocks and this can have a cumulative effect on global financial <lb/>stability. 170 If an economy has limited exposure to international capital flows the economy is <lb/>less at risk to external shocks and volatility is low. 171 The lack of integration with the wider <lb/>financial market ensures a cushion against global financial instability and provides a barrier <lb/>against domestic financial instability affecting the international financial market. As the capital <lb/>flows across borders with EME have grown these have become more vulnerable to financial <lb/>instability. EME are particularly vulnerable to changes in capital flow if they also have low <lb/>reserves, high leverage, or high foreign currency exposures. 172 The liberalisation of the <lb/>financial markets in EME has led to their further integration in the international financial <lb/>market. 173 The merits of this further integration have been analysed and there is no clear definite <lb/>answer on how beneficial this is. 174 This discussion falls beyond the scope of this article but <lb/>suffice to say that the further liberalisation and integration of EME has led to increased capital <lb/>flows and that this creates a greater risk to global and domestic financial stability. <lb/>In 2011 the flow of capital to EME was $910 billion compared to $149 billion in 2002. 175 This <lb/>means the markets are now closer linked and therefore an internal financial crisis risks affecting <lb/>other financial markets. The IMF identified that concerns about policy credibility of EME <lb/>could cause significant capital outflow which is a risk to financial stability. 176 Policy credibility <lb/>means that investors trust that the domestic policies of a country are designed to protect their <lb/>investments. Investors can perceive EME financial policies as arbitrary and not necessarily <lb/>working for their best interest. 177 This is partly due to the high volatility of the economy and <lb/>partly because of the transitional state of EME which means that the political and economic <lb/>landscape is perpetually changing and policy is thus in a constant state of flux. 178 Investors <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>170 E Han Kim &amp; Vijay Singal, The Fear of Gobalizing Capital Market, 1 Emerg. Market. Rev. 183 (2000). <lb/>171 Batuo, Supra n.166, at 4. <lb/>172 IMF, Supra n.90, at VIII. <lb/>173 Batuo, Supra n.166, at 4. <lb/>174 See for instance: <lb/>S.A Asongu, Liberalisation and Financial Sector Competition: A Critical Contribution to the Empirics with an <lb/>African Assessment&apos; 83 South African Journal of Economics 425 (2015). <lb/>Geert Bekaert, Campbell R. Harvey, Christian Lundblad, Growth Volatility and Financial Liberalisation. <lb/>Journal of international Money and Finance, 25 J. Int. Money Finance 370 n.3 (2006) <lb/>Norman Loayza &amp; Romain Ranciere, Financial Development, Financial Instability and Growth, CESifo Working <lb/>Paper No. 684 (2002) <lb/>175 Volz, Supra n.169, at 4. <lb/>This is a continuing trend apart from the 2008-2009 period when the flow of capital was down and the pre-<lb/>crisis year 2007 which spiked at USD 1,244 billion. <lb/>176 IMF, Supra n.153, at 4,5. <lb/>177 Mody, Supra n.151, at 6. <lb/>178 Mody, Supra n.151, at 6. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>cannot anticipate the policies in an effective manner, and this increases investment risks. This <lb/>is coupled with the perception that policies are more corrupt in EME which decreases <lb/>transparency, raises business costs, and makes investors wary. 179 This can especially <lb/>discourage long-term investments. 180 This makes the economy and the financial market of <lb/>EME more unstable. The high volatility of EME is partly caused by this domestic policy <lb/>instability which can hamper economic growth and lead to more abrupt changes in capital <lb/>flow. 181 <lb/>A financial crisis can suddenly diminish the flow of capital to the affected country and even <lb/>the whole region. 182 Whilst there is a significant linkage between capital flows and financial <lb/>stability there is no conclusive evidence on how this linkage works. 183 Not all capital flows are <lb/>as vulnerable to external factors during financial crises: dollar debts are more vulnerable than <lb/>local currency debts and equity portfolio investments for instance. 184 The influence on banking <lb/>flows and portfolios is also much stronger than on Foreign Direct Investment. 185 Drivers of <lb/>capital flow vary across components and should therefore be categorised to understand where <lb/>the economy is particularly vulnerable. 186 This makes it difficult to have effective regulation <lb/>to counter the risks. Some of the financial factors that play a role in this linkage: the size of the <lb/>banking sector, the credit to deposit ratio, and the liquid assets to deposit ratio, and macro-<lb/>economic factors such as real GDP per capital, trade openness, rate of inflation, and the <lb/>exchange rate regime. 187 The effects also vary per country so there is a risk if EME are treated <lb/>as an entity that the regulations are not effective given the different concerns that exist in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>179 Chi Keung Marco Lau, Ender Demir &amp; Mehmet Huseyin Bilgin, Experience-based corporate corruption and <lb/>stock market volatility: Evidence from emerging markets 17 Emerg. Markets Rev., 1 (2013) <lb/>180 Beata S Javorick &amp; Shang-Jin Wei, Corruption and cross-border investment in emerging markets: Firm-level <lb/>evidence, 28 J. Int. Money Finance 605 (2009). <lb/>181 Mody, Supra n.151, at 6. <lb/>182 Marcel Förster, Markus Jorra &amp; Peter Tillmann, The comovement of international capital flows: evidence <lb/>from a dynamic factor model, 19 (Volz (ed.) German Development Institute (2012) <lb/>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/256017592_Financial_Stability_in_Emerging_Markets_-<lb/>_Dealing_with_Global_Liquidity <lb/>183 Christopher F Baum, Madhavi Pundit &amp; Arief Ramayandi, Capital Flows and Financial Stability in Emerging <lb/>Economies, 522 ADB Economics Working Paper Series 16 (2017). <lb/>184 Anton Korinek, Regulating Capital Flows to Emerging Markets: An Externality View J. Int. Econ 61, 65 (2018). <lb/>185 Robin Koeke, What Drives Capital Flows to Emerging Markets? A Survey of the Empirical Literature, MPRA <lb/>Paper No. 75887, 6 (2015) <lb/>https://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/75887/15/MPRA_paper_75887.pdf <lb/>186 Koeke, Supra n.185, at 6. <lb/>187 Baum, Supra n.183, at 10. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>individual states. 188 The lack of trust in the resilience and policy of EME (discussed above) <lb/>encourages further capital flow to advanced economies if these are perceived as more stable. 189 <lb/>Risk aversion and policy uncertainty play a key role in decisions to invest. 190 EME are <lb/>especially vulnerable to this as EME assets are generally seen as high-risk investments. 191 Thus <lb/>in times of a (potential) crisis investors are more likely to divest and search lower risk <lb/>investments elsewhere (even if these have a lower return) and this makes capital flows more <lb/>volatile. <lb/>Benchmark driven investors are more sensitive (three to five times compared to other investor <lb/>streams) to changes in global financial conditions. 192 An investment fund is benchmark driven <lb/>when &apos;portfolio allocation across countries is guided by the country weights in a benchmark <lb/>index.&apos; 193 As benchmark driven investors now have a larger share of the portfolio market (this <lb/>quadrupled in the past ten years) this could lead to sudden changes in capital flow. 194 The <lb/>inclusion of EME in the benchmark indices gives them accessibility to more and more diverse <lb/>finance but EME are also more vulnerable to the common factors included in the indexes, <lb/>which tend to treat EME as a class rather than being country specific. 195 The result is that the <lb/>flow of capital can change drastically regardless of how well the internal economy is doing. <lb/>EME are more vulnerable to changes in capital flow because they are more dependent on the <lb/>availability of foreign capital than advanced economies. 196 If the flow of capital diminishes this <lb/>undermines the banking system and industries which affects the economy. 197 This thus leaves <lb/>the country at risk to financial destabilisation. Given the further integration of the EME with <lb/>the global financial market this could have a knock-on effect on financial stability worldwide. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>188 Baum, Supra n.183, at 14. <lb/>189 IMF, Supra n.153, at 13. <lb/>190 IMF, Supra n.153, at 17. <lb/>191 Koeke, Supra n.185, at 10. <lb/>192 IMF, Supra n.90, at 30. <lb/>193 IMF, Supra n.90, at 31. <lb/>194 IMF, Supra n.90, at 30. <lb/>195 IMF, Supra n.90, at 32. <lb/>196 Maurice Obstfeld, Financial Flows, Financial Crises, and Global Imbalances, 31 J. Int. Money Finance 469 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>197 Batuo, Supra n.166, at 4. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>Short-term foreign currency debt is another issue that leaves EME vulnerable. 198 Exchange <lb/>rates and interest rates can diverge which creates a more volatile market. The use of risky <lb/>external finance instruments such as foreign currency denominated debts create a risk to <lb/>stability. 199 Individual investors take the risk to the economy as a given because of the short-<lb/>term profits these instruments engender. There is little reason for an individual investor to not <lb/>use these instruments if everyone else does. This would thus ask for international regulatory <lb/>intervention that leads to more harmonised law across states. 200 High external debt and weak <lb/>reserve coverage levels cause vulnerability to external shocks which has an effect on global <lb/>financial stability. 201 This risk is diminished because few countries have a high public debt and <lb/>a high foreign currency debt (Lebanon, Tunisia, Ukraine are examples of countries which do) <lb/>and most countries with high public debt (including large economies such as Brazil and India) <lb/>have a low foreign currency debt. 202 This is thus less likely to represent a risk to global financial <lb/>stability. The countries that are especially vulnerable are smaller economies and any internal <lb/>crisis is not likely to have a significant effect on the global financial market. <lb/>5.4 Building Policy <lb/>Compared to twenty years ago, many EMEs have reduced their external vulnerabilities and <lb/>improved their policy frameworks significantly. A large proportion of EMEs have adopted <lb/>inflation-targeting monetary policy frameworks, which help to anchor inflation expectations <lb/>and stabilise business cycles. The domestic banking sector in EME has grown so there is more <lb/>domestic credit available. 203 The IMF recommends that EME implement policies that provide <lb/>further resilience against changes in the capital flow, but warns against the extensive use of <lb/>capital flow management except in times of a (near) crisis as this can lead to the exclusion <lb/>from certain benchmark indices which would also affect the (domestic) financial market. 204 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>198 IMF, Supra n.153, at 19. <lb/>199 Anton Korinek, Emerging market economies after the crisis: trapped by global liquidity? 35 <lb/>(Volz (ed.) German Development Institute (2012). <lb/>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/256017592_Financial_Stability_in_Emerging_Markets_-<lb/>_Dealing_with_Global_Liquidity <lb/>200 Korinek, Supra n.201, at 35. <lb/>201 IMF, Supra n.153, at 20. <lb/>202 IMF, Supra n.153, at 20. <lb/>203 Lepers, Supra n.152, at 2. <lb/>204 IMF, Supra n.90, at 45. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>Whilst because of the regulatory changes EME are more resilient against a global financial <lb/>crisis their further integration in the international financial market also means that they can <lb/>affect the global financial market more. EME markets are more volatile, and this is a risk for <lb/>global financial stability. EME are more vulnerable to changes in capital flows because of their <lb/>dependence on foreign currency and because investment in EME is considered more high risk. <lb/>Thus, the capital flows are more volatile and sudden changes can affect the (domestic) financial <lb/>market. <lb/>Uncertainty in trade policy and flow of capital are directly linked. If trade policy is uncertain <lb/>and especially in a political climate where a trade war does not seem far away, firms could <lb/>make the choice to shift their portfolios to &apos;safer&apos; currencies and investments. 205 The current <lb/>trade tensions might escalate further, but this is difficult to predict and this will make investors <lb/>more careful. These tensions could thus have a direct effect on capital flows and would <lb/>disproportionally affect EME. <lb/>The heightened interconnectedness between the national and the global financial market for <lb/>EME means that it is key to stabilise domestic financial markets to ensure international <lb/>financial stability. Therefore, the goal should be the stabilisation of capital flow to a similar <lb/>degree as in advanced economies. To do so investment must be considered to have the same <lb/>risk as in advanced economies. One of the key elements for this stability is whether the country <lb/>is perceived as willing and capable to repay its debts. 206 Furthermore, policy certainty that <lb/>promotes transparency and clarity for investors is important to reduce the high-risk investment <lb/>perception. This encourages investment and ensures less volatile capital flows. To accomplish <lb/>this further international legal harmonisation focusing on certainty and transparency should be <lb/>considered. <lb/>6. Conclusion <lb/>Ten years after the GFC the international regulatory financial framework is far more robust <lb/>and resilient to shocks due to the introduction of new legislation. It was identified that failures <lb/>in supervision and lack of regulation were an important cause of the crisis. This led to a <lb/>significant amount of legislation which all supported the goal of furthering financial stability <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>205 Gunnella, Supra n.155. <lb/>206 Suk-Joong Kim, Sovereign credit ratings, capital flows and financial sector development in Emerging <lb/>markets, 9 Emerg. Markets Rev.17, 20 (2008). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<body>so that a global financial crisis will be less likely to occur. Nevertheless, different factors could <lb/>threaten this financial stability. This article has highlighted three of these factors: fintech, <lb/>Brexit, and emerging markets. These risks are addressed from different perspectives, but the <lb/>perspective of global financial stability is lacking in the literature. Whilst all three of these <lb/>factors have different causes and potential effects, they also share some key commonalities. <lb/>They all three arose post the financial crisis and are thus new factors that are underregulated <lb/>and cause significant policy uncertainty that could lead to changes in the financial landscape, <lb/>including sudden shifts in capital flow. All three of these risks are currently modest but have <lb/>the potential to evolve very quickly and therefore a legal response is needed, in order to be <lb/>proactive rather than reactive. Policy made to address these issues should take into <lb/>consideration the importance of global financial stability and factor in how any regulation <lb/>would affect this. <lb/>The fintech sector is still small but is experiencing exponential growth. It will therefore <lb/>increasingly become a significant factor on the international financial market. Currently, there <lb/>is only minimal regulation in place. The existing laws are domestic and there is no international <lb/>harmonisation. The lack of a coherent international legal framework forms a potential threat to <lb/>financial stability. The lack of legal harmonisation leads to policy uncertainty and gaps in the <lb/>legislation that can be exploited by financial operators. The quick growth of the sector could <lb/>quickly aggravate the risks to international financial stability as this could lead to unpredictable <lb/>changes in the international financial market. <lb/>The process of the UK exiting the EU does not need to lead to an instable financial market in <lb/>and of itself. However, the continued uncertainty regarding the future agreements between the <lb/>EU and the UK, and the influence of (party) politics which makes decisions less predictable <lb/>could cause significant issues on the global financial market. Regulatory equivalence will be <lb/>an ongoing process, legal divergence will occur in the longer term, and the lack of policy <lb/>certainty and transparency can lead to sudden changes in the financial market and in capital <lb/>flows. <lb/>EME are a diverse group of countries but share a more volatile economy which is more <lb/>vulnerable to sudden shifts in capital flows. This is coupled with policy uncertainty and a <lb/>perception of corruption and lack of transparency. Investors therefore regard EME as high-risk <lb/>investments and fuelled by uncertainty are more likely to move capital when there are tensions <lb/></body>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body>on the market, such as the tensions surrounding international trade policy, especially with <lb/>regards to the unpredictability of US trade policy. As EME have grown they have become more <lb/>important for the global economy and more entwined with the international financial market. <lb/>Therefore, fluctuations on domestic markets are likely to affect the global financial market. <lb/>From the above the conclusion can be made that a pattern emerges whereby policy uncertainty <lb/>leads to more wariness from investors which could lead to sudden changes in capital flows <lb/>which further destabilise the markets. Gaps in regulation regarding changes in the structure of <lb/>the financial market can aggravate risks to international financial stability. This article <lb/>contributed to understanding why fintech, Brexit, and EME threaten global financial stability <lb/>and why it is therefore key that this aspect is taken into account when policy is drafted. Whilst <lb/>the concrete solutions for all three of these risks would differ it is clear that further legal <lb/>harmonisation leading to a unified global legal framework for the financial market is necessary. <lb/>Legal harmonisation counters policy uncertainty, diminishes regulatory gaps between <lb/>countries, diminishes the risks for investors, counters sudden significant changes in capital <lb/>flow, and allows for more policy transparency. Therefore, ideally these risks would be <lb/>addressed at the international level with input from different stakeholders, including banks and <lb/>other financial institutions. At the very least domestic policy makers should take into account <lb/>international developments when drafting legislation that addresses these challenges. <lb/>From the analysis it becomes clear that smaller legislative issues can have a potentially <lb/>destabilising effect on the global financial market and that it is therefore important to address <lb/>these issues early on. As can be observed from these three issues there is a tendency for policy <lb/>makers and politicians to address other more immediate needs first and only focus on financial <lb/>stability once the potential threat emerges and is no longer only potential. Furthermore, there <lb/>is a real risk that new policy is politicised. Examples mentioned in this article include how the <lb/>European Commission has handled passporting rights by using it to gain leverage and how the <lb/>US is using trade policy to gain concessions in other areas. This makes policy less predictable <lb/>for financial institutions which leads to a more volatile market that is reactive instead of pro-<lb/>active. Therefore, a case can be made for more technical law making at the international level, <lb/>involving financial institutions and actors, international organisations, and other experts that <lb/>can draft conventions and other legislation. This would ensure more predictable policy that <lb/>responds better to the needs of the financial market. <lb/></body>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>
				
	<body>Whilst this article concentrated on fintech, Brexit, and EME, it also leads to a broader <lb/>understanding on how policy issues affect global financial stability. The commonalities of the <lb/>regulatory challenges discussed here have a more universal application: as policy uncertainty <lb/>emerges as a root cause it is important that legislators address issues of global financial stability <lb/>early on to ensure that no legislative gaps emerge, and new policy is predictable for financial <lb/>actors. </body>


	</text>

</TEI>