<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Towards a Collective Regulatory System of Private Equity Funds in China: Legislative Progress and Political Challenges</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Chi</forename>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-28T09:45:20.594Z">1/28/2026 10:45:20 AM</date>
        <title>review</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.54648__eulr2019007</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Kluwer Law International BV</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2019</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.54648/eulr2019007</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Chi Zhang. (2019). Towards a Collective Regulatory System of Private Equity Funds in China: Legislative Progress and Political Challenges. European Business Law Review, 30(Issue 1), 183-197. DOI: 10.54648/eulr2019007</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-01-02T12:28:21.213256Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2026-01-02T12:28:21.213256Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-06T16:34:12.897Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Annotation completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T14:54:42.867Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith second pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T09:08:48.038Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-28T13:06:20.959Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Zhang, C. (2019) Towards a collective regulatory systems of private equity <lb/>funds in China: Legislative progress and political challenges. European <lb/>Business Law Review, 30(1), pp. 183-198. <lb/>There may be differences between this version and the published version. <lb/>You are advised to consult the publisher&apos;s version if you wish to cite from <lb/>it. <lb/>http://eprints.gla.ac.uk/195018/ <lb/>Deposited on: 09 September 2019 <lb/>Enlighten -Research publications by members of the University of <lb/>Glasgow <lb/>http://eprints.gla.ac.uk <lb/>1 <lb/>Towards a Collective Regulatory System of Private Equity Funds in China: Legislative <lb/>Progress and Political Challenges <lb/>Chi Zhang* <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Private equity investment funds have been playing an increasingly significant role in the <lb/>Chinese economy. Owing to the fragmented financial regulatory regime of the country, <lb/>however, both the official supervision and self-regulation of private equity funds in China are <lb/>still problematic, which has increased the potential risk in the market. This article investigates <lb/>the political logic of the ongoing legislative and regulatory reform of private equity funds in <lb/>China. It also explores a proposal for the legal reform of the Chinese private equity industry <lb/>with reference to the experience of the United Kingdom and the European Union. It is <lb/>suggested that a unified financial regulatory system as a fundamental institutional arrangement <lb/>is a pre-requisite for establishing an effective and efficient regulatory regime for private equity <lb/>funds in China. This can only be achieved when the political conflict between different <lb/>regulators in the Chinese bureaucratic system is removed. <lb/></front>
    
    ____________________________ <lb/>

			<front>* Chi Zhang, Lecturer of Law, School of Law and Humanities, China University of Mining and Technology <lb/>(Beijing); Ph.D. in Law, 2017, University of Glasgow; LL.M., 2013, Tsinghua University; LL.B., 2011, <lb/>Tsinghua University. E-mail: thuzhangchi@163.com. The author acknowledges with gratitude Professor Iain G. <lb/>MacNeil, Dr John MacLeod and Dr Konstantinos Sergakis from the University of Glasgow, and Associate <lb/>Professor Carsten Gerner-Beuerle from the London School of Economics and Political ScienceUniversity <lb/>College London for their insightful comments on this research. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. <lb/>Introduction <lb/>Ever since the global financial crisis in 2008, it has been widely accepted that external <lb/>protection of investors in private equity 1 funds is indispensable and it has also been proven that <lb/>excessive regulatory exemption of private investment funds, including PE funds, may lead to <lb/>serious market risk. 2 Chinese regulators have recently emphasized the need for enhancing both <lb/>the official and industry regulation of the PE industry. The supreme authority of the country <lb/>was made particularly aware of and appreciates the more industry-oriented proposal for <lb/>financial reform proposed by the Fifth National Conference for Financial Reform held by the <lb/>State Council of China from 14 to 15 July 2017. 3 This implies that direct investment in Chinese <lb/>industry companies will be encouraged more than financial trading in the secondary markets. <lb/>Against this social background, the development of the legal and regulatory systems of PE <lb/>funds in China is being promoted significantly. <lb/>In China, the regulatory system of the PE industry currently comprises two forms: (i) official <lb/>regulation and (ii) self-regulation. The securities investment fund industry of China underwent <lb/>comprehensive regulatory reform during 2012-2014, resulting in a new regulatory model for <lb/>PE funds. However, owing to the political and departmental interests of different regulators, <lb/>the effectiveness of such regulatory approach is problematic. On the one hand, a functional <lb/>regulatory system has not yet been established in China and different regulatory bodies operate <lb/>official regulation over private investment funds. Thus, the compliance cost is very high. On <lb/>the other hand, although a self-regulatory system of PE has been established in China, however, <lb/>due to the inadequate reputational mechanism in the market, further reform of the self-<lb/>regulation of PE funds is also necessary. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;PE&apos;.<lb/></note> 
    
    <listBibl>2 US Department of the Treasury, &apos;Agreement Among PWG and US Agency Principals on Principles and <lb/>Guidelines regarding Privet Pool of Capital&apos; (Feb 2007), &lt; https://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/fin-<lb/>mkts/Documents/hp272_principles.pdf &gt; accessed 19 June 2017; Financial Services Authority, Private Equity: A <lb/>Discussion of Risk and Regulatory Engagement (Discussion Paper 06/6, 2006). <lb/>3 Zhifeng Xu, Qiuyu Wu and Jie Ouyang, A Comprehensive Report of the Fifth National Conference of <lb/>Financial Reform (16 July 2017), &lt; http://finance.people.com.cn/n1/2017/0716/c1004-29407471.html&gt; accessed <lb/>19 July 2017. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>This article reflects the research conducted into the political pattern in the development path <lb/>of the official regulatory and self-regulatory systems of the Chinese PE industry, which <lb/>revealed the detail of the existing problems in this field and their political roots. This article <lb/>is organized as follows: <lb/>Firstly, the risk of the Chinese PE industry is overviewed in a general sense. The section that <lb/>follows sheds light on the recent legal and regulatory reforms of the Chinese investment fund <lb/>industry and the substantive influence on the Chinese PE industry is discussed. The landscape <lb/>of the self-regulatory system of PE funds in China is sketched and the drawbacks are analysed. <lb/>In order to provide a reasonable reform proposal for the Chinese PE industry, the regulatory <lb/>regimes of PE in the United Kingdom (UK) and European Union (EU) respectively are <lb/>examined. A possible reform directive for Chinese PE funds is proposed and its limitation in <lb/>the light of the political issues in the country is reviewed. In the concluding section, the <lb/>suggestion is made that although the ongoing reform of a collective and unified regulatory <lb/>regime of PE in China is greatly encouraged, its substantial progress and effectiveness, <lb/>however, still depend on the political compromise and co-operation between the different <lb/>regulatory bodies in the Chinese government. <lb/>2. <lb/>The Risk in the Chinese Private Equity Investment <lb/>Private equity as one of the most mysterious sectors of the global financial market is <lb/>continually making huge profits in mysterious ways. However, the fact that PE investment is <lb/>highly risky is often ignored. Briefly, regulators have identified the following risks in PE <lb/>funds: first, the excessive leverage used by PE funds may be a severe burden on PE-owned <lb/>companies, which may give rise to a series of public problems, including corporate distress <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>and massive layoff. 4 Second, owing to the long-term lockup period of PE funds, lenders will <lb/>be motivated to transfer their exposure to other market participants by means of, for example, <lb/>credit derivatives, which means that the unregulated financing activities of PE funds may also <lb/>significantly spread the risk to the public. In this regard, the lesson learnt from the global <lb/>financial crisis in 2008 has shown that the over-use of credit derivatives can make it hard to <lb/>identify and judge the ownership of the risk of underlying assets. 5 As a consequence, default <lb/>events of some individual transactions may result in the fall of the market. Third, the <lb/>exemption of the disclosure requirement of PE funds may also harm PE investors: the <lb/>asymmetry of information between the fund managers and investors can be serious. Hence, it <lb/>is quite difficult for PE investors to monitor fund managers&apos; investment decisions effectively. 6 <lb/>In terms of the Chinese markets, the PE investment is more risky and immature than the PE <lb/>markets in developed countries. The main legal issues in relation to the Chinese PE market can <lb/>be summarized as follows: first of all, the limited partnership (LP) structure is the primary but <lb/>not the only organizational structure of PE funds in China. In fact, there are ten percent around <lb/>of the PE funds in China are established as business trusts. 7 From a functional perspective, <lb/>however, both of the trust and LP-structured PE funds play the same function in the Chinese <lb/>economy, the lack of collective regulatory system has given rise to the waste of social <lb/>resources. The PE funds organized in the form of investment trust presently are exclusively <lb/>regulated by the China Banking and Insurance Regulatory Commission 8 , the limited <lb/>partnership funds, however, fall in the regulatory scope of the China Securities Regulatory <lb/>Commission 9 . Therefore, the regulatory systems of the two regulatory bodies, for instance, the <lb/>market entry policies, transparency rules and internal governance rules are quite different from <lb/>each other and the severe regulatory arbitrage remarkably increase transaction cost of PE <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>4 Financial Services Authority, Private Equity: A Discussion of Risk and Regulatory Engagement (Discussion <lb/>Paper 06/6, 2006) 89-90. <lb/>5 Ibid., at 90. <lb/>6 Iain G. MacNeil, Private Equity: The UK Regulatory Response 3 Capital Markets Law Journal 18, 22 (2008). <lb/>7 Zhi Zheng, Wentao Wang, Decoding the Trusts, 294 (Citic Press 2014). <lb/></listBibl><note place="footnote">8 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;CBIRC&apos;. <lb/>9 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;CSRC&apos;. <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>practitioners 10 . Secondly, the PE limited partnership funds were not regulated by a specialized <lb/>regulator, therefore, the regulatory strategies are not really reasonable nor efficient. <lb/>In a nutshell, the professionalization and unification of the PE regulation in China are both <lb/>necessary and important. The current wave of regulatory reform of the Chinese PE industry <lb/>that started from 2012 mainly focuses on establishing a collective regulatory system of PE <lb/>funds, however, the complex political conflicts of the financial regulators is the focal point in <lb/>the reform. <lb/>3. <lb/>Contending for the Regulatory Power of Private Equity in China: The National <lb/>Development and Reform Committee versus China Securities Regulatory <lb/>Committee <lb/>Basically, the official regulatory system of PE funds in China is structured on two levels: (i) <lb/>the regulation of venture capital funds led by the National Development and Reform <lb/>Committee 11 and (ii) the general regulatory system of private investment funds controlled by <lb/>the CSRC. Nonetheless, owing to the political conflict between the NDRC and CSRC in <lb/>financial regulation, the Chinese regulatory regime of the private equity industry actually fails <lb/>to protect the economic interests of fund investors effectively. Fortunately, reform of the <lb/>regulation over PE funds was launched in 2012 and further reform is expected. <lb/>Before discussing the implementation of the regulatory power, the legal status of the NDRC <lb/>within China&apos;s economic and political regimes should be considered briefly. The predecessor <lb/>of the NDRC was the National Planning Commission, 12 which was established in 1952. The <lb/>main functions of the NPC were (i) to create macro-economic policy for different industries <lb/>and (ii) to supervise the implementation of Chinese government&apos;s national economic plans at <lb/>all the levels. From a legal perspective, before the institutional reform of the Chinese economy <lb/>was launched in the late 1970s, the legal status of the NPC was such that it was, in effect, the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>10 The details of the CBIRC&apos;s regulatory framework of private equity investment trusts are available in: Chi Zhang, <lb/>Venture Capital Investment Trusts in China: Legal Framework, Challenges, and Reform 23 (7) Trusts &amp; Trustees <lb/>806 (2017).<lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">11 Hereinafter referred to as the &apos;NDRC&apos; <lb/>12 Hereinafter referred to as the &apos;NPC&apos;. <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>most powerful department of the State Council of China. Almost any proposed economic or <lb/>industrial activities (e.g., industrial planning, foreign investment, price control, financial <lb/>activities and infrastructure) had to be approved by the NPC; in other words, historically, the <lb/>nature of the NPC was that of an extremely general social administrative body but not a <lb/>professional regulator of specific economic activities. With the liberalization of the economy, <lb/>however, the over-broad administrative power of the NDRC has been a barrier to Chinese <lb/>economic reform. To reduce administrative intervention in the market economy, two waves of <lb/>reform of the NPC led by the State Council were launched in 1998 and 2003 respectively. 13 At <lb/>present a series of the most substantive approval powers associated with financial regulation <lb/>are still in the hands of the NDRC. Accordingly, the NDRC&apos;s regulation over the PE industry <lb/>is also not specialized and the protection of investors is also insufficient. <lb/>Since the promulgation of the Interim Provisions for the Administration of Start-up Investment <lb/>Enterprises (2005), 14 the domestic PE funds in China have been regulated by the NDRC 15 <lb/>which obtains the power to examine and supervise the operation of PE funds at any time. In <lb/>the situation where a PE firm does not comply with the law, the NDRC has the power to revoke <lb/>its licence. 16 However, the Interim Provision (2005) does not clarify any legal liability or <lb/>substantive punishment imposed on fund managers who display inappropriate behaviour. In <lb/>such a loose policy circumstance, many unqualified fund management firms were motivated to <lb/>raise funds from unqualified investors and invested in risky projects. 17 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 During the 2000s, the State Council of China cancelled or simplified 2,614 administrative approvals and the <lb/>further simplification of the administrative approval power of the NDRC was proposed. For more detail, see <lb/>Youliang Yan, &apos;A Leviathan? The NDRC is Being Powerful Again&apos; Sina Finance News (Beijing, 30 May 2013). <lb/>&lt;http://finance.sina.com.cn/china/20130530/082015636012.shtml&gt; accessed 22 April 2017. <lb/>14 Hereinafter referred to as the &apos;Interim Provisions (2005)&apos;. <lb/>15 According to the Interim Provisions (2005), all PE and VC funds shall be filed with the NDRC or other <lb/>related administrative departments of the provinces (s 4) and registered with the State Administration for <lb/>Industry and Commerce (SAIC) or local departments of the SAIC (s 8). <lb/>16 Section 27, the Interim Provisions (2005). <lb/>17 For instance, the so-called First Judicial Case of China&apos;s PE Funds was adjudicated by the First Intermediate <lb/>People&apos;s Court of Shanghai in 2010, in which a twenty-eight-year-old fund manager, Hao Huang, was accused of <lb/>fraud in the financing industry and finally sentenced to fifteen years in prison. In this case, Hao Huang the general <lb/>partner of the PE funds, raised around RMB 0.178 billion from as many as 720 natural persons in China. This <lb/>kind of unregulated PE scandal has been more common since China&apos;s Alternative Investment Market was <lb/>launched in October of 2010. Yonggang Liu, &apos;The First Private Equity Case in China: A Chinese Ponzi Scheme?&apos; <lb/>China Economy Weekly (Beijing, 29 June 2010) &lt;http://finance.people.com.cn/GB/12001069.html&gt; accessed 23 <lb/>April 2017. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>However, the CSRC has been actively competing with the NDRC in regulating PE funds since <lb/>2012. The revision of the Securities Investment Fund Law of China was completed by the end <lb/>of December 2012. One of the key debates in the process of amending this legislation was <lb/>whether PE funds should be officially regulated by the Securities Investment Fund Law of <lb/>China (2012 Revision). 18 <lb/>According to the first version of the Consultation Draft issued by the Standing Committee of <lb/>the National People&apos;s Congress, 19 the new law tries to regulate PE funds formed as limited <lb/>liability companies or limited partnerships. 20 It is evident that if this Consultation Draft can be <lb/>successfully enacted into a statute, the regulator of PE funds will be changed, which means that <lb/>the CSRC and courts will be able substantially to share the regulatory power over PE funds. <lb/>More importantly, because the legal status of statutes issued by the National People&apos;s Congress <lb/>enjoys top priority in the Chinese legislative system, both the legal force of the Provisions <lb/>(2005) and the NDRC&apos;s regulatory authority of PE may be ended in the short term. 21 As a <lb/>result, the NDRC was dissatisfied with this Consultation Draft. In the process of the second <lb/>and final rounds of discussion on revising the SIFL, as a consequence, the NDRC and the <lb/>twenty-five professional associations in the PE industry across the country jointly signed a <lb/>statement addressed to the SCNPC, arguing that the high-level regulation over PE funds would <lb/>cripple the development of the Chinese PE industry. 22 As a result of the departmental <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">18 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;SIFL&apos;. <lb/>19 Hereinafter referred to as the &apos;SCNPC&apos;. <lb/></note>
    
    <listBibl>20 In this early version of the Consultation Draft (July 2012), private investment funds (excluding investment trusts <lb/>which have been regulated by the CBIRC since 2007) was proposed to be regulated by the CSRC, according to <lb/>Arts 106 and 107 of the Consultation Draft, the investment funds whose fund managers shall bear unlimited <lb/>liability will be regulated by the law and the content of the term &apos;securities&apos; includes all the stocks, bonds and any <lb/>other types of financial derivatives that can legally be exchanged or circulated in China. This means that the equity <lb/>of private companies that can be transacted privately is also expected to be regulated by the revised SIFL; in other <lb/>words, not only public investment funds, but also privately raised investment funds, including hedge funds, PE <lb/>and VC funds, will also be regulated by the new SIFL. The official version of this interim legislative document is <lb/>available at: <lb/>http://www.npc.gov.cn/npc/xinwen/lfgz/flca/2012-07/06/content_1729072.htm. <lb/>21 Clifford Chance LLP, &apos;The Amended Securities Investment Funds Law&apos;: Significant Changes but More <lb/>Expected&apos; (25 January 2013) <lb/>&lt;http://www.cliffordchance.com/briefings/2013/01/the_amended_securitiesinvestmentfundslaw.html &gt; accessed <lb/>28 April 2017; Dongying Wang, &apos;The Regulatory Power of PE/VC Funds: NDRC PK CSRC&apos;, South Weekly <lb/>(2013) &lt;http://www.nbweekly.com/news/business/201306/33414.aspx &gt; accessed 28 April 2017. <lb/>22 Supra note, Dongying Wang; Dong Liu, &apos;The New Law of Securities Investment Funds: Private Equity and <lb/>Venture Capital Funds Are Still Free from Regulation&apos; China Business News (Beijing, 25 December 2012) &lt; <lb/>http://finance.people.com.cn/fund/n/2012/1225/c201329-20003436.html&gt; accessed 17 April 2017; Sha Xiao, <lb/>&apos;The Rent-seeking Behind the Legislative Activities Regarding Private Equity Funds: The Intense Competition <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>competition in the jurisdiction in the final revision of SIFL (2012 Revision), PE funds were <lb/>eventually excluded from the regulatory ambit of SIFL (2012 Revision). 23 <lb/>In the above circumstances, driven by the competition between the NDRC and CSRC, further <lb/>regulatory reform of China&apos;s PE funds continued. In June 2013, the State Commission Office <lb/>for the Public Sector Reform of China 24 clarified the division of powers in the PE regulatory <lb/>affairs between the NDRC and CSRC as follows: (i) the NDRC should be in charge of making <lb/>macro-industry policies for the development of PE funds, and coordinate the relationship <lb/>between the government and PE market; and (ii) the CSRC should be responsible for the <lb/>regulation of PE firms and the protection of PE investors. 25 Based on this administrative order, <lb/>the most important regulatory reform of PE funds went further in 2014. On the one hand, the <lb/>NDRC has stated that the annual review of PE funds with the NDRC was no longer required. 26 <lb/>On the other hand, more importantly, the Interim Measures for the Supervision and <lb/>Administration of Privately Raised Investment Funds (2014), 27 which is the first detailed <lb/>administrative regulation of PE funds issued by the CSRC, came into force in August of the <lb/>same year. <lb/>According to the Interim Measures (2014), the CSRC is the general regulator of all kinds of <lb/>private investment funds in China with the exception of investment trust funds, which are <lb/>regulated by the China Banking Regulatory CommissionCBIRC. 28 However, because the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Between Administrative Departments&apos; The Rule of Law Weekends (Beijing, 22 August 2012) <lb/>&lt;http://finance.sina.com.cn/money/smjj/20120822/153112922035.shtml&gt; accessed 17 April 2017. <lb/>23 The material compromising the final version of the law is reflected in Art. 95 of the SIFL (2012 Revision): the <lb/>term securities therein refers to any publicly issued stocks, bonds and any other types of financial derivatives that <lb/>can legally be exchanged or circulated in China. It is evident that the adjustment of the definitive scope of <lb/>&apos;securities&apos; through the legislative procedure of the law makes PE funds free from the CSRC&apos;s high level of <lb/>regulation &lt;http://www.pkulaw.cn/fulltext_form.aspx?Gid=191978&gt; accessed 10 May 2017. <lb/>24 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;SCOPSR&apos;. <lb/>25 The Notice of the Division of Regulatory Functions Regarding Private Equity Funds issued by SCOPSR, June <lb/>2013 &lt; http://www.scopsr.gov.cn/bbyw/qwfb/201306/t20130627_227855.html&gt; accessed 10 June 2017. <lb/>26 The Notice of the Issues Regarding Further Development of Venture Capital Investment Enterprises issued by <lb/>the General Office of NDRC (May 2014) http://www.ndrc.gov.cn/zcfb/zcfbtz/201405/t20140514_611509.html&gt; <lb/>accessed 10 June 2017. <lb/>27 Hereinafter referred to as the &apos;Interim Measures (2014)&apos;. CSRC, Interim Measures for the Supervision and <lb/>Administration of Privately Raised Investment Funds (2014) <lb/>&lt; http://www.amac.org.cn/cms/article/preview?ID=386993&gt; accessed 10 June 2017. <lb/>28 According to s 2 of the Interim Measures (2014), the assets of a &apos;private investment fund&apos; includes, but is not <lb/>limited to, stocks, equities, bonds, futures, options and fund units, in consideration of the separated financial <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>administrative hierarchy of the NDRC and CSRC is at the same level and the Provisions (2005) <lb/>are still legally valid, currently any PE funds registered in China have to comply with the <lb/>requirements issued by the two regulators, namely (i) the CSRC and (ii) NDRC. Obviously, <lb/>such a dual-level regulatory system has reduced the efficiency and unnecessarily increased PE <lb/>practitioners&apos; compliance costs. Further regulatory reform of PE funds is expected to simplify <lb/>the compliance requirement of PE funds reasonably by enhancing the CSRC&apos;s regulatory <lb/>power in the PE market and, finally, remove the unprofessional regulatory power of the NDRC. <lb/>4. <lb/>Industry Self-regulation of Private Equity Funds in China: Unification in Process <lb/>The above analysis indicates that due to the lack of a coherent and unified regulatory system <lb/>of PE funds in China, the enforceability of the law and the effectiveness of the protection of <lb/>investors in PE funds are unsatisfactory. Although a collective regulatory system of the <lb/>investment fund industry is being built up, in order to enhance investor protection and to <lb/>promote market practice of PE in China, the self-regulatory system of the PE industry is also <lb/>important. <lb/>Generally speaking, the self-regulatory system of PE in China is organized on both the national <lb/>and provisional levels. One the one hand, pursuant to the Interim Measures (2014), the Asset <lb/>Management Association of China, 29 founded and led by the CSRC in June 2012, is the unified <lb/>self-regulatory body of private investment funds with a nationwide scope. 30 As a self-<lb/>regulatory body in the financial market, the primary function of the AMAC is improving <lb/>information transparency and normalising the managerial conduct of the Chinese asset <lb/>management industry. As a subset of private investment funds, PE funds are also required to <lb/>register with the AMAC, which means that any violation of laws or regulations by the fund <lb/>manager (mostly general partners) or individual practitioners may be punished by the AMAC. <lb/>At present, the AMAC has developed a system of information sharing on its official website <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>regulatory system, investment trusts that are exclusively regulated by the CBIRC are excluded from the regulatory <lb/>scope of the Interim Measures (2014). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">29 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;AMAC&apos;. <lb/></note>
    
    <listBibl>30 It is provided in Chapter 6 of the Interim Measures (2014) that &apos;AMAC is obliged to make self-regulatory rules <lb/>and examine the performance of its member institutions and related practitioners (s 29); in the circumstance where <lb/>any member institutions or related practitioners violate the laws, administrative regulations or self-regulatory <lb/>rules, AMAC is entitled to take actions and publish the violations to the public via its website (s 29); AMAC shall <lb/>establish a complaint-handling mechanism to accept investor complaints and mediate disputes (s 30).&apos; <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>where the public can directly access all information on violations, punishment, and blacklisting <lb/>of members and individuals who have failed to comply with the laws, regulations or self-<lb/>regulatory rules. 31 <lb/>On the other hand, the industry associations of PE supervised and led by the NDRC also play <lb/>a role in self-regulating Chinese PE funds. By the end of March 2017, there were two main <lb/>national-level self-regulators 32 and twenty-two local-level self-regulators of the PE industry in <lb/>China. 33 Most of these industry associations serve as information-sharing platforms for <lb/>investors and financial regulators. In terms of the self-regulation, it is obvious that a single and <lb/>separated reputational mechanism of self-regulation is insufficient for protecting PE investors. <lb/>For example, most articles of association of the industry regulatory bodies only provide that in <lb/>the circumstances where a member violates the law or the articles of association, the association <lb/>may permanently revoke the membership of the non-compliant member. 34 In most cases, the <lb/>PE associations are reluctant to expose any illegal, inappropriate or immoral behaviour of their <lb/>members; in other words, the reputational deterrence of the members of PE associations is still <lb/>weak. <lb/>Although the two nation-wide self-regulatory bodies of the Chinese PE and VC industries were <lb/>founded in 2001 and 2002 respectively, the standardization of industry-wide self-regulation is <lb/>imperfect; for instance, the China Association of Private Equity 35 released the Principle <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>31 Up to March 2017, AAMAC has blacklisted four fund management firms and five individuals who failed to <lb/>comply with the laws, regulations and self-regulatory rules &lt;http://www.amac.org.cn/xxgs/hmd/&gt; accessed <lb/>15 June 2017. <lb/>32 China Venture Capital and Private Equity Association (CVCA) and China Association of Private Equity <lb/>(CAPE). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">33 The following provinces have established their local self-regulatory associations of the PE and VC industry: <lb/>Hunan Province, Hubei Province, Henan Province, Guangdong Province, Zhejiang Province, Shanxi Province, <lb/>Jiangsu Province, Anhui Province, Jilin Province, Sichuan Province, Yunnan Province, Liaoning Province, Inner <lb/>Mongolia Province and Fujian Province. The following big cities have also established local associations for PE <lb/>or VC: Beijing, Shanghai, Shenzhen, Tianjin, Chongqing, Suzhou and Haerbin. Moreover, Beijing established <lb/>ZhongGuanCun Private Equity and Venture Capital Association (ZPEVCA) in 2013. Shanghai also established a <lb/>special professional association, namely the Shanghai Private Equity Association (SHPEA) in 2004, the goal of <lb/>which is to enhance collaboration with international PE firms. <lb/></note>
    
    <listBibl>34 For instance, s 13 of the Articles of Association of Suzhou Association of Private Equity <lb/>&lt;http://www.szape.org/CompanyConstitution.aspx&gt; accessed 17 June 2017; s 12 of the Articles of Association <lb/>of Beijing Association of Private Equity &lt; http://www.bpea.net.cn/article/ljxh/xhzc/&gt; accessed 17 June 2017. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">35 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;CAPE&apos;. <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Guidelines for China&apos;s PE and VC industry 36 in November 2011, which is regarded as an <lb/>official standard of the Chinese PE and VC industry. However, this guideline only provides a <lb/>series of very general principles regarding the self-regulatory issues, without detailed and <lb/>practical rules. It is evident that an effective reputational mechanism of the market may hardly <lb/>be established in this way. <lb/>5. <lb/>International Experience: The Collective Regulation of Private Equity in the <lb/>United Kingdom and European Union <lb/>5.1 The Regulatory Regime of Private Equity Funds in the United Kingdom: A Market-<lb/>Based Model <lb/>In the existing financial regulatory framework of the UK, PE and VC funds as unauthorized <lb/>investment funds are unregulated by the Financial Conduct Authority. 37 In consideration of its <lb/>risky nature, especially the excessive leverage used by PE funds, however, the FCA is also <lb/>inclined to emphasise the regulation of the conduct of PE firms in the UK market. 38 However, <lb/>most of such requirements have been satisfied by the existing corporate law and takeover <lb/>rules; 39 that is, the official regulatory regime of the PE industry mostly focuses on the <lb/>application of the existing laws regarding business organizations, 40 as in most cases private <lb/>equity funds are involved in corporate governance issues by exercising their voting right as <lb/>shareholders of investee companies, but less directly influence public markets. <lb/>By contrast, the industry association of PE and VC in the UK has moved much more quickly <lb/>in this area. The British Private Equity and Venture Capital Association, 41 which has been the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>36 China Association of Private Equity (CAPE), &apos;The Principle Guidelines for China&apos;s Private Equity and Venture <lb/>Capital Industry&apos; (2011) &lt;http://files.cbex.com.cn/bpea/201111/20111111133220846.pdf&gt; accessed 18 June <lb/>2017. <lb/></listBibl>
    
<note place="footnote">^37 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;FCA&apos;. <lb/>38 For example, before Brexit is completed, the authorization and on-going information transparency of PE firms <lb/>in the UK are required as a compliance of Alternative Investment Fund Manager Directive of the EU which will <lb/>be discussed in the following subsection. <lb/>39 These mostly refer to the Companies Act 2006 and the Takeover Code of the City. <lb/>40 For instance, investor protection for limited partners in PE funds is subject to the provisions under the Limited <lb/>Partnership Act 1907, the restriction on the conduct of PE funds as shareholders in corporate governance is subject <lb/>to the provisions under the Companies Act 2006 and the constraints on those buyout funds as bidders lie within <lb/>the regulatory remit of the Listing Rules of London Stock Exchange and the Takeover Codes of the City of <lb/>London. <lb/>41 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;BVCA&apos;. <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>leading self-regulatory body of PE and VC funds in the UK, was established in 1983. Its <lb/>membership comprises over 500 influential firms, including VC firms, professional <lb/>consultancies and international associations. 42 The primary mission of the BVCA is to promote <lb/>integrity and transparency in the UK&apos;s PE and VC market, and to enhance communication <lb/>between members internationally. In response to the public disquiet over the PE industry after <lb/>the global financial crisis, the BVCA has been playing an increasingly important role in <lb/>mitigating the risks in PE transactions. In terms of the regulatory functions of the BVCA, the <lb/>Regulatory Committee of the BVCA plays an important role in the self-regulation of PE and <lb/>VC firms in the UK, whose responsibility it is to ensure that all members can keep abreast of <lb/>any changes of the regulatory and policy environment in a timely manner. 43 In order to <lb/>guarantee the consistency between the practices of the PE and VC practitioners and authorities, <lb/>regularly publishing consulting research reports for the regulators or policymakers is another <lb/>key function of the Regulatory Committee of the BVCA. 44 <lb/>In November 2007, under the leadership of Sir George Walker, the Guidelines for Disclosure <lb/>and Transparency in Private Equity 45 were published which outlined the self-regulatory <lb/>approach of PE funds in the UK. In the first place, PE and VC firms should timeously publish <lb/>the details of their (i) investment strategies; and (ii) background of professional staff; and (iii) <lb/>a description of UK portfolio companies in the portfolio of PE firms on their website, which <lb/>should be accessible to the public and investors. 46 PE firms are also obliged to report on the <lb/>records of the investment of their portfolios to the association, by which the BVCA is able to <lb/>assess the performance of each PE firm both on an annual and industry-wide basis. 47 In the <lb/>second place, portfolio companies are required to disclose the composition of their board, <lb/>including the representatives of the PE firms on the board, 48 which is in support of mitigating <lb/>the information asymmetry between general partners and limited partners. In order to keep the <lb/>flexibility and adaptability of the soft law regulatory system, the BVCA tends to regulate the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>42 See the official website of the BVCA: http://www.bvca.co.uk/AboutUs.aspx. <lb/>43 See the official website of the BVCA: <lb/>http://www.bvca.co.uk/AboutUs/CouncilCommitteesAdvisoryGroups/RegulatoryCommittee.aspx. <lb/>44 Ibid. <lb/>45 Hereinafter referred to as the &apos;Walker Guidelines (2007)&apos;. BVCA, Guidelines for Disclosure and Transparency <lb/>in Private Equity (November 2007) <lb/>&lt;http://walker-gmg.co.uk/sites/10051/files/wwg_report_final.pdf&gt; accessed 21 May 2017. <lb/>46 Ibid., at 26. <lb/>47 Ibid., at 27. <lb/>48 Ibid., at 24. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>PE funds on a &apos;comply or explain&apos; basis, which means that the PE or VC firms who do not <lb/>comply with the above rules must provide the BVCA with an acceptable and reasonable <lb/>statement. 49 <lb/>After the publication of the Walker Guidelines 2007, the Guidelines Monitoring Group 50 was <lb/>established as an independent monitoring committee. The main task of the GMG is to <lb/>implement the rules in the UK PE market effectively. In practical terms, the effectiveness of <lb/>the self-regulation by the BVCA mainly works on the basis of a market reputation mechanism; <lb/>for instance, the GMG annually publishes a Review of Conformity with the guidelines that will <lb/>name the non-compliers for the public. In this scenario, both the limited partners and any other <lb/>parties in the PE market can directly judge the reputation of the non-complying firms; 51 in other <lb/>words, this market reputation deterrence can provide incentives for the PE management <lb/>corporations who are covered by the Walker Guidelines 2007 to comply with the requirements <lb/>of disclosure and transparency in the PE market. <lb/>5.2 The Regulatory System of the Private Equity Firms as Fund Managers in the <lb/>European Union: An Interventionist Model <lb/>As a response to the 2008 global crisis, in June 2011, the parliament of the EU promulgated a <lb/>unified regulation on alternative investment funds, namely the Alternative Investment Fund <lb/>Managers and Amending Directives. 52 Most private investment funds, including PE funds, fall <lb/>within the regulatory scope of the AIFMD. In comparison with the regulatory system of PE <lb/>funds in the UK, the regulatory strategy of the EU focuses more on the conduct of the fund <lb/>managers of PE funds, as the definition or legal nature of the so-called investment fund may <lb/>vary from country to country. Instead, a relatively unified definition of fund manager may be <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>49 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;GMG&apos;. Joseph A. McCahery and Erik P. M. Vermeulen, Private Equity Regulation: <lb/>A Comparative Analysis 16 Journal of Management &amp; Governance 197, 222 (2012). <lb/>50 MacNeil (n 6) at 30. <lb/>51 According to the Review of Conformity with the Guidelines 2014, two PE firms, namely Camelot (Ontario <lb/>Teachers&apos; Pension Plan) and Viridian Group (Arcapita) who failed to comply with the requirement of the Walker <lb/>Guidelines (2007) have been disclosed. Guidelines Monitoring Group, Seventeenth Report, December 2014, 24. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">52 The full name of the regulation is &apos;Directive 2011/61/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of <lb/>8 June 2011 on Alternative Investment Fund Managers and amending Directives (2003/41/EC and 2009/65/EC <lb/>and Regulations (EC) No. 1060/2009 and (EU) No. 1095/2010), hereinafter referred to as the &apos;AIFMD&apos;. <lb/></note> 

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>easier to understand for all the EU member states. The following detailed requirements under <lb/>the AIFMD regime are closely related to the regulation of PE fund managers in the EU: <lb/>First, fund managers are obliged to disclose detailed information in relation to the PE funds, <lb/>including, but not limited to, a list of shareholders of the Alternative Investment Fund <lb/>Managers, 53 organizational structure of the funds, the information in relation to the persons <lb/>who are responsible for the fund management. 54 In addition, the AIFMs of all the member <lb/>states of the EU are also required to provide information on the funds as regards the (i) rate and <lb/>sources of leverage; (ii) fundamental strategies of investment; (iii) decision-making procedure <lb/>of altering the investment strategies; (iv) detailed description of conflicts of interest; and the <lb/>(v) valuation of underlying assets of the funds and other information of potential risk. 55 It can <lb/>be seen that under the EU regulatory regime, the disclosure and transparency of portfolio <lb/>managers are clarified in detail, which will facilitate the regulator with supervising the level of <lb/>risk of the macro market in real time. Transparency is particularly significant for the PE <lb/>industry, as the most PE funds involving leveraged buyouts 56 may generate high risk <lb/>throughout the chain of debt, which may eventually give rise to systematic crises in financial <lb/>markets. The existing EU regulator is making a particular effort to deal with information <lb/>asymmetry and to improve the coherence in the unified financial market of the EU. <lb/>Second, in terms of fund management, the AIFMD requires that all fund managers have <lb/>responsibility to ensure that the internal control mechanism of the fund, such as accounting <lb/>procedures and electronic technology system, is adequate to identify, trace and control the <lb/>records of the transactions by its employees throughout the entire process of investment. 57 <lb/>More importantly, in order to manage and measure the risk in leveraged investment effectively, <lb/>the AIFMD especially requires fund managers to (i) set a maximum level of leverage and (ii) <lb/>restrict the use of collateral and guaranties in portfolio investment, among other things. 58 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">53 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;AIFM.&apos; <lb/></note>
    
    <listBibl>54 Art. 7 of the AIFMD. <lb/>55 Arts 7 and 23 of the AIFMD. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">56 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;LBOs&apos;. <lb/></note>
    
    <listBibl>57 Art. 18 of the AIFMD. <lb/>58 Art. 15 of the AIFMD. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>For those fund managers of specific types of alternative investment funds that may directly <lb/>control the corporate governance of target companies, the AIFMD imposes particular <lb/>restrictions on their conduct; for instance, the fund managers of those alternative investment <lb/>funds that acquire control of unlisted companies by exercising their voting rights are obliged <lb/>to comply with a series of special requirements: (i) standardized calculation methods of the <lb/>voting rights attached to the shares held by the funds; (ii) timely notification of the acquisition <lb/>of major holdings and control of non-listed companies; (iii) statutory annual report of <lb/>exercising control of non-listed companies and (iv) strict restraints on asset stripping of target <lb/>companies and so forth. 59 Obviously, such investment funds mainly refer to private equity <lb/>funds, especially those public-to-private buyouts vehicles (PTP funds). The AIFMD makes an <lb/>effort to normalize management of the EU-registered PE funds and to protect the interest of <lb/>not only shareholders, but also other stakeholders (such as the employees and creditors) of the <lb/>investee companies. <lb/>Compared to the relatively much looser regulatory environment of PE funds in the UK, the EU <lb/>parliament intends to impose higher levels of obligation on the fund managers of alternative <lb/>investment funds for the purpose of reducing systematic risk in the EU financial markets. One <lb/>reasonable understanding of this difference is that there is much more inconsistency in <lb/>domestic legislation in each of the EU member states than there is in the UK. Hence, a better <lb/>approach to regulate PE or other alternative investment funds effectively is to clarify a shared <lb/>standard of organizational management of the funds, instead of leaving too much leeway to the <lb/>member states. It would otherwise be difficult to identify the risk of the funds and <lb/>responsibilities of each fund manager across the EU. <lb/>6. <lb/>The Prospect of Private Equity Regulation in China: A Reform Proposal <lb/>6.1 Developing a Unified and Practical Guideline for Private Equity Fund Managers <lb/>As discussed above, the essential problem of the ineffective regulation of the Chinese PE <lb/>market is rooted in the political conflicts of various administrative bodies. In March 2016, the <lb/>State Council of China launched a specific reform proposal as regards the establishment of a <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>59 See details from Chap. V of the AIFMD. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>collective regulatory regime of the entire financial market in China. 60 In a general sense, it can <lb/>be predicted that the supreme-level regulatory arrangements will gradually be establishing a <lb/>comprehensive regulatory body aimed at identifying and controlling systematic risk in the <lb/>entire Chinese financial market. 61 This initiative by the central government of China can be <lb/>regarded as a possible and feasible direction of the regulatory reform of the entire investment <lb/>fund industry, including PE and VC, because the rapidly emerging industry of buyout funds in <lb/>China has been increasing the risk of leverage in the Chinese financial market. <lb/>In terms of the regulatory reform of PE funds, it is obvious that an effective and timely <lb/>information-sharing mechanism across different sub-markets can facilitate the control of <lb/>systematic risk in the PE industry. As a phased achievement of the reform, a collective <lb/>regulatory regime that is uniformly led by the State Council is recommended as a proper way <lb/>of improving the effectiveness of financial regulation. It has been recently proposed that a so-<lb/>called Central Committee of Financial Stability be established by the State Council, the core <lb/>responsibility of which is to comprehensively and continually control the systematic risk in the <lb/>Chinese financial markets, and also to coordinate with the People&apos;s Bank of China, CSRC, <lb/>CBIRC and China Insurance Regulatory Commission 62 to enhance supervision of the conduct <lb/>of market participants. 63 In a macro sense, it is expected that the supervision of, and restriction <lb/>on, over-risky transactions of Chinese PE funds could be improved in future. <lb/>By contrast, in a micro sense, however, a unified and detailed practical guideline for the PE <lb/>industry is still lacking. As already discussed, the existing Law of Securities Investment Funds <lb/>(2012 Revision) has not yet covered PE funds. Private equity funds are only roughly regulated <lb/>by the Interim Measures (2014). More formal and detailed legislation on all kinds of private <lb/>investment funds in China is desired. Provisional improvement of the CSRC&apos;s regulation is to <lb/>encourage the CSRC to promulgate specific administrative rules as guidelines for PE <lb/>practitioners. The existing regulations created by the NDRC may be advocated when the <lb/>political interests and relationship of the CSRC and NDRC are well coordinated, by which PE <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>60 State Council of P. R. China, &apos;The Opinion on the Significant Issues as regard Deepening Economic Reform of <lb/>2016&apos; (31 March 2016). <lb/>61 Lingyan Xu, Comparative Study on Legal System of Financial Supervision: Global Financial Legal System <lb/>Reform and China&apos;s Choice, 49-50 (Law Press 2016). <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">62 Hereinafter referred to as &apos;CIRC&apos;. <lb/></note>
    
    <listBibl>63 Supra note 3. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>funds will be regulated more coherently and efficiently. The last step in the reform process is <lb/>to revise the Law of Securities Investment Law of China and accept PE and VC funds as <lb/>regulated objects. A longer period of regulatory practices of the CSRC may someday provide <lb/>more insightful and useful experience for such a legislative reform. This is so because detailed <lb/>legislation on private investment funds needs more knowledge and experience and not merely <lb/>an indiscriminate legal transplant from other jurisdictions. <lb/>6.2 Strengthening the Reputation Mechanism in the Chinese Private Equity Market <lb/>With reference to the regulatory experience of the UK, it is recommended that the further <lb/>reform of the industry regulation of the PE market in China should focus on the establishment <lb/>of a nationwide reputation system, by which public investors can access information on any <lb/>violations and immoral behaviour of fund managers and PE firms, as it has been proven and <lb/>acknowledged that reputational records of PE firms have a remarkable correlation with not <lb/>only the scale of fundraising, 64 but also the bargaining ability of fund management firms. 65 <lb/>Specifically, owing to the existence of the dual-level system of self-regulation, the functions <lb/>of industry associations and the AMAC should be differentiated, by which the efficiency of <lb/>self-regulation of PE funds can be improved. At a national level, the AMAC should play a <lb/>leading role in the self-regulation of PE funds with a nationwide scope. According to sections <lb/>7 and 8 of the Interim Measures (2014), all private investment funds are required to register <lb/>with the AMAC and (i) file main legal documents, including the articles of associations, of <lb/>corporate funds or limited partnership agreements, the basic information of senior managers; 66 <lb/>(ii) disclose the key information of the investment targets and prospectus (if applicable). 67 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>64 Ching-Yi Chang et al, Analysis of the Factors that Influence Venture Capital Fundraising: An Empirical Study <lb/>in China 5 (12) African Journal of Business Management 4765 (2011). <lb/>65 Lee Harris, A Critical Theory of Private Equity 35 (1) Delaware Journal of Corporate Law 1 (2010). <lb/>66 Section 7 of the Interim Measures (2014) provides that: <lb/>&apos;A manager of Privately-raised Funds of any type shall, in accordance with the provisions of the AMAC, apply <lb/>for registration to the AMAC and submit the following basic materials: (1) Photocopies of the originals and <lb/>duplicates of its industrial and commercial registration certificate and business license; (2) Its articles of <lb/>association or partnership agreement; (3) The list of its major shareholders or partners; (4) Profiles of its senior <lb/>management personnel; and (5) Other materials required by the AMAC.&apos; <lb/>67 Section 8 of the Interim Measures (2014) provides that <lb/>after the fund-raising of a Privately-raised Fund of any type is completed, the manager of the Privately-<lb/>raised Fund shall, in accordance with the provisions of the AMAC, go through the record-filing procedures <lb/>for the Privately-raised Fund, and submit the following basic materials: (1) Information on the main <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Therefore, AMAC is able to collect the substantive information of each PE fund and will be in <lb/>the advantageous position of being able to identify the potential risk in the market, and judge <lb/>the violations of laws and regulations or inappropriate behaviour of PE fund managers. <lb/>At an industry level, the existing industry associations of PE and VC should play a more <lb/>important role in boosting reputational pressure on fund managers and practitioners of the <lb/>Chinese PE and VC market. First, it is advisable that a co-operation mechanism between the <lb/>industry associations and AMAC be established, by means of which all information regarding <lb/>the performance of industry associations&apos; members are accessible on websites or other public <lb/>information platforms. In such a way, the reputational mechanism in the private investment <lb/>fund market can be enhanced. Second, in a technical sense, more detailed and practical <lb/>guidance such as model rules for profit distribution, the recommended practices of limited <lb/>partnership agreements 68 and the standards for judging the managing partner&apos;s behaviour in <lb/>fund management should be advised and developed by PE industry associations in China, <lb/>which may make a contribution to the standardization of legal practice. 69 <lb/>7 Conclusion <lb/>The Chinese economy is experiencing a crucial period in which the macro-economic policies <lb/>are shifting from encouraging financial and real estate investment to supporting industry <lb/>economic development. Against this background, it is possible to see this another &apos;golden era&apos; <lb/>of PE in China. The recent legal and regulatory reform of the Chinese PE industry has shown <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>investment direction of the Privately-raised Fund and its fund category indicated according to the main <lb/>investment direction; (2) The fund contract and the articles of association or partnership agreement of the <lb/>company. The fund prospectus shall also be submitted if it has been provided for investors during fund-<lb/>raising. Where the Privately-raised Fund is established in the form of an enterprise, such as a company or <lb/>partnership, the industrial and commercial registration and photocopies of the original and duplicate of the <lb/>business license shall also be submitted; (3) Where the Privately-raised Fund is placed under entrusted <lb/>management, the agreement on entrusted management shall be submitted. Where the properties of the <lb/>Privately-raised Fund are entrusted to a custodian, the agreement on custody shall also be submitted; and <lb/>(4) Other materials required by the AMAC. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">68 Referred to as &apos;LPAs&apos;. <lb/>69 Actually, ever since the establishment of the AMAC in 2012, some professional training programmes have been <lb/>launched in each local and nationwide PE/VC association, the officers of the AMAC are regularly accredited to <lb/>the PE/VC associations at provincial level. Attending a given number of hours of training courses is commonly <lb/>required for each member of those local associations. Moreover, such regular communication may facilitate <lb/>information sharing of the self-regulators and different practitioners of PE and VC market. Such activities will be <lb/>beneficial for developing a series of coherent and widely applicable standards for PE and VC investment in China. <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>
    
    <body>that the authority is making concerted efforts to build up a collective and more professional <lb/>regulatory regime of PE funds. In reality, however, the tension between different regulatory <lb/>departments (mainly the NDRC and CSRC) has increased the difficulty and costs associated <lb/>with such an institutional transformation. Moreover, a multi-level and weak industry regulatory <lb/>system is also being reshaped in the current wave of reform. However, the collaboration <lb/>between the nation-wide self-regulator (mainly AMAC) and the many local industry <lb/>associations in the PE industry across China is still problematic. This is also closely related to <lb/>the political conflicts between the regulators at the top level of the Chinese bureaucratic system. <lb/>In sum, a more cost-efficient regulatory approach to Chinese PE can be expected, which should <lb/>be an important part of a unified and functionalized regulatory reform of the Chinese financial <lb/>market in the years to come. </body>


	</text>

</TEI>