<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Money Market Funds Reforms in the US and the EU</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Mohammed K.</forename>
          <surname>Alshaleel</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="sandfort">Johanna Sandfort</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="cboulanger">Christian Boulanger</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-24T08:55:34.278Z">1/24/2026 9:55:34 AM</date>
        <title>review</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.54648__eulr2020013</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Kluwer Law International BV</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2020</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.54648/eulr2020013</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Mohammed K. Alshaleel. (2020). Money Market Funds Reforms in the US and the EU: The Quest for Financial Stability. European Business Law Review, 31(Issue 2), 303-335. DOI: 10.54648/eulr2020013</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-01-02T12:22:04.329772Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2026-01-02T12:22:04.329772Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-12T09:23:24.539Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith first pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-12T09:23:49.323Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith first pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-13T07:21:45.933Z" status="draft" who="#sandfort">
      <desc>second pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-15T17:45:58.943Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-24T09:27:42.269Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Money Market Funds Reforms in the US and the EU: the Quest for Financial Stability <lb/>Mohammed K. Alshaleel * <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>This article considers the impact of money market funds (MMFs) reforms in the US and the <lb/>EU on the money market fund industry and global financial stability. The 2008 financial <lb/>crisis proved that MMFs are a source of considerable instability to the global financial <lb/>system, and highlighted their susceptibility to runs. The shareholders&apos; incentive to redeem <lb/>their shares before others do when there is a perception that the MMFs might suffer a loss <lb/>makes MMFs vulnerable to runs. Given this reality, the article argues that the emphasis of the <lb/>financial regulators on achieving the stability of the entire financial system after the 2008 <lb/>financial crisis necessitates the strictness of the new reforms. <lb/>Divided into six parts, the article outlines the attributes and classification of MMFs, the <lb/>definition of financial stability, and the run and systemic risk posed by MMFs during the <lb/>financial crisis, before assessing the MMFs&apos; reforms in the US and the EU and the impacts of <lb/>these reforms on the MMFs industry and global financial stability system. The major <lb/>component of the US reform is the introduction of the floating net asset value (FNAV), where <lb/>an MMF&apos;s share price will fluctuate to reflect the daily market value of the fund assets. In the <lb/>EU the new regulation provides investors with a high degree of optionality for investing by <lb/>introducing Low Volatility Net Asset Value (LVNAV) MMFs. The article concludes that <lb/>despite that, the reforms are likely to jeopardize the viability of some categories of MMFs, <lb/>they enhance global financial stability, and the complexity of the reforms has made MMFs <lb/>more appropriate products to financial institutions&apos; investors than retail investors. <lb/>* Lecturer, University of Essex (mkalsh@essex.ac.uk). <lb/></front>
	  
	  <page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>It has been a decade since the beginnings of the 2008 global financial crisis. This global crisis <lb/>hit the US and EU financial markets and economy heavily and revealed many fragilities in the <lb/>pre-crisis financial regulations. Money market funds (MMFs) were at the heart of the 2008 <lb/>financial crisis. MMFs are mutual funds whose main objectives are to maintain the principal <lb/>value of the funds and offer a return in accordance with money market rates. They are an <lb/>important source of short-term funding for corporations, governments, and financial <lb/>institutions. The 2008 financial crisis highlighted the serious systemic risk and susceptibility <lb/>of MMFs to runs. A run occurs when the value of an MMF&apos;s shares falls below their standard <lb/>$1.00 or €1.00 value, so the shareholders &quot;run&quot; to the fund to redeem their shares and get the <lb/>full value of their shares. 1 Indeed, MMFs proved to be a significant source of instability to the <lb/>global financial system. As explained below, in September 2008, the Reserve Primary Fund <lb/>&quot;broke the buck&quot;, where the value of its shares fell below its standard $1, leading to heavy <lb/>investor redemptions. This spread to other MMFs, resulting in a run on the MMF industry. <lb/>Because of the run on the MMF industry, the impact MMFs have on the stability of the global <lb/>financial system has received attention from financial regulators in the US and the EU. To <lb/>preserve the stability of the financial system, it was essential to address the susceptibility of <lb/>MMF to runs. Since the 2008 global financial crisis, MMFs have been the subject of ongoing <lb/>and intensive regulatory debate. Determining the appropriate and final form of the reforms <lb/>has been problematic because of the potential impact that the reforms might have on the <lb/>commercial viability of these instruments. <lb/>In the US, on July 23, 2014, the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) adopted a <lb/>substantial reform to the regulatory framework governing MMFs. This reform is considered <lb/>the most significant structural changes to MMFs in the US history. The reform came into <lb/>force on October 2016. As discussed below, the main components of the reform are the <lb/>introduction of the floating net assets value (FNAV), and the liquidity fees and redemption <lb/>gates. <lb/>In the EU, the new European MMFs regulation was published in the EU Official Journal on <lb/>30 June 2017 and came into force on 21 July 2017. Existing MMFs will have to comply with <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 Mark Perlow, Money Market Funds -Preserving Systemic Benefits, Minimizing Systemic Risks 8 Berkeley Bus. <lb/>L.J 80 (2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>the new regulation by 21 January 2019. The EU reform follows the US reform in adoption of <lb/>liquidity fees and redemption gate; however, the distinctive attribute of this reform is the <lb/>introduction of Low Volatility NAV (LVNAV) MMFs. <lb/>In the EU, the new reform has not been addressed yet, so this article takes the initiative in <lb/>documenting and analysing the changes to the MMFs legal framework. In the US, the <lb/>academic literature has largely focused on criticising the 2014 reform, arguing that the move <lb/>from stable NAV to floating NAV and granting MMFs the authority to apply the liquidity fees <lb/>and redemption gates threaten to destroy the value of this industry. For instance, Brown <lb/>(2013) argued that the rules that were implemented by the SEC in 2010 had adequately <lb/>strengthened the perceived weaknesses of the MMF industry, so the new rules proposed by <lb/>the SEC were unnecessary. 2 She found that extensive changes are likely to result in investor <lb/>flight from the fund industry to other unregulated industries, thereby increasing systemic <lb/>risks. In 2014, Peirce and Greene found that the proposed changes are not sufficient to address <lb/>the vulnerabilities of MMFs to runs, so they discussed an alternative method that relies on the <lb/>MMFs boards to freeze redemptions whenever and for as long they determine is in the best <lb/>interests of the fund. 3 Similarly, in 2015, Fisch criticised the 2014 reform and argued that <lb/>mandatory sponsor support offers a novel and simple regulatory solution to MMF fragility. 4 <lb/>Price, in 2015, examined the impact that the 2014 reform will have on the financial products <lb/>industry, and specifically, on banks that offer money market deposit accounts. He concluded <lb/>that the reform presents opportunities for banks to become an alternative investment vehicle <lb/>to MMFs, and banks might serve as an alternative source of funding for entities which have <lb/>typically relied on MMFs. 5 <lb/>Reviewing the relevant academic literature shows that scholars have focused in their analysis <lb/>of the new reform on the potential impact of the reform on the MMF industry without <lb/>considering its core role in enhancing the stability of the financial system. In other words, <lb/>scholars did not link the reform to any comprehensive reforms of the main components of the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>2 Latoya Brown, The Regulation of U.S. Money Market Funds: Lessons from Europe 9 Int&apos;l L. &amp; Mgmt Rev 203 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>3 See, Hester Peirce and Robert Greene, Opening the Gate to Money Market Fund Reform 34 Pace L. Rev. <lb/>1093-1168 (2014). <lb/>4 Jill Fisch, The Broken Buck Stops Here: Embracing Sponsor Support in Money Market Fund Reform 93 N.C. L. <lb/>Rev. 979(2015). <lb/>5 See, Carlton Price, What Money Market Mutual Fund Reform Means for Banks and Money Market Deposit <lb/>Accounts 19 N.C. Banking Inst 257(2015). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>financial system after the disastrous consequences of the 2008 financial crisis on the financial <lb/>markets and the economy. <lb/>In analysing and evaluating the US and EU reforms and their implications, this article makes <lb/>a novel contribution by adopting a completely different approach that links MMFs&apos; reforms to <lb/>any broader plans to reform the financial system. This approach is essentially based on two <lb/>main elements. The first element is the substantial change in financial regulations objectives <lb/>after the global financial crisis 2008, where the goal of financial stability has become the <lb/>dominate idea of national and international financial reforms. The second element is the shift <lb/>from micro-prudential regulation policy to macro-prudential policy 6 , which fundamentally <lb/>focuses on the resilience and robustness of the financial system as a whole rather than relying <lb/>on individual institutions to secure the stability of the global financial system. The <lb/>susceptibility of MMFs to runs proved to have such destabilizing implications for the whole <lb/>financial system that reforming the financial system cannot be complete and efficient without <lb/>addressing the risks posed by the structural vulnerabilities of MMFs, and this justifies the <lb/>strictness of the new laws. It is worth mentioning that after the enforcement of the new reform <lb/>in the US in 2016, no literature has been written about MMFs, so this article will benefit from <lb/>the statistics published by the SEC and other relevant institutions after the enforcement to <lb/>show the real impact of the new reform on the MMF industry. <lb/>The remainder of the article is divided into five parts. First, because scholars do not make a <lb/>clear differentiation between the different types of MMFs, this article attempts to clearly <lb/>classify all types of MMFs in the US and the EU. To accomplish this Part 2 explains the <lb/>nature, attributes and classifications of MMFs. Part 3 examines the concept of financial <lb/>stability, and other relevant concepts such as systemic risk and the core components of the <lb/>financial system, such as the financial institutions, markets and infrastructure that are <lb/>necessarily a part of any stable system of finance. It also discusses the failure of Reserve <lb/>Primary Fund and the phenomenon of runs in the MMF industry, highlighting how runs on <lb/>MMFs differ from runs on banks and mutual funds. Part 4 evaluates the 2014 US reform, <lb/>categorizing the changes into 4 main groups. It also scrutinizes the EU reform, comparing the <lb/>EU regulators&apos; approach to address MMFs&apos; vulnerability to runs with the US approach. Part 5 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">6 The shift from micro-prudential regulation policy to macro-prudential policy will be discussed later (5. <lb/>Analysing MMF&apos;s Reforms from financial stability perspective). <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>analyses MMF&apos;s reforms and their implications from financial stability perspective. Part 6 <lb/>concludes with practical recommendations to address certain gaps in the reforms. <lb/>2. Background <lb/>In order to understand MMFs&apos; reforms in the US and the EU and their impact on MMF <lb/>industry, it is necessary to define MMFs and understand their structure, financial and <lb/>economic attributes, and classification. <lb/>2.1 Definition, Characteristics and Structure <lb/>MMFs are a type of mutual fund that invest in short-term debt instruments. 7 They are <lb/>collective investment vehicles where money is raised by issuing shares or units to the public. 8 <lb/>MMFs are open-ended funds where the funds undertake to buy back their shares or units on <lb/>any regular business day. 9 Thus, MMFs provide financing for financial institutions, <lb/>corporations and governments. Further, MMFs typically invest in certificate of deposits (CD), <lb/>commercial paper (CP), asset-backed commercial papers (ABCP), short-term bonds issued by <lb/>private issuers, repurchase agreements, shares of (other) money market funds and government <lb/>securities. 10 MMFs diversify their investment portfolio to mitigate investment risks, so the <lb/>impact of a decline in the value of one of the fund holdings is offset by the other holdings. <lb/>The term &quot;diversification&quot; indicates the process of spreading risk over a number of different <lb/>investments, and probably across different markets (reflecting the maxim that you should not <lb/>put all your eggs in one basket). 11 Moreover, MMFs are managed by competent managers <lb/>(figure 1). Professional management means that the assets of an MMF are invested and <lb/>managed by professional fund managers with the experience, resources and expertise to <lb/>manage the fund effectively. 12 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>7 Jonathan Lim, Untangling the Money Market Fund Problem: A Public-Private Liquidity Fund Proposal 19 Stan. <lb/>J.L. Bus. &amp; Fin 71 (2013). <lb/>8 Nicholas Broke, Money Market Funds and Systemic Risk: A Critique of the SEC&apos;s 2014 Reforms 14 Geo. J.L. &amp; <lb/>Pub 290 (2016). <lb/>9 See, Frank Fabozzi, Capital Markets: Institutions, Instruments, and Risk Management 648 (5 th edn MIT Press, <lb/>Cambridge 2015). <lb/>10 See, Jeff Madura, Financial Markets and Institutions 627 (11 th edn Cengage Learning, Stamford 2014). <lb/>11 Charles Jones, Mutual Funds: Your Money, Your Choice: Take Control Now and Build Wealth Wisely 47 (FT <lb/>Press, New Jersey 2003). <lb/>12 John Haslem, Mutual Funds: Portfolio Structures, Analysis, Management, and Stewardship 43 (John Wiley &amp; <lb/>Sons, New Jersey 2009). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>The nature and purpose of MMFs distinguish them from other financial services or market <lb/>actors, including mutual funds and banks. Unlike mutual funds, whose NAV can fluctuate <lb/>daily, MMFs seek to maintain a stable NAV, typically $1.00 per share in the US and €1 in <lb/>the EU. This means mutual funds&apos; NAV fluctuates with the value of the assets in the fund&apos;s <lb/>portfolio. The per share NAV of a mutual fund is the aggregate value of the fund assets <lb/>minus the aggregate liabilities of the fund divided by the number of units outstanding. 13 For <lb/>instance: <lb/>The aggregate value of the assets £3,000,000 <lb/>The aggregate liabilities <lb/>£400,000 <lb/>The aggregate NAV <lb/>£2,600,000 <lb/>Number of share outstanding £1,000,000 <lb/>Net asset value per share <lb/>£ 2.6 <lb/>Figure (1): MMF structure. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 Herbert Mayo, Financial Institutions Investments and Management ) 337 (8 th edn Thomson South-Western <lb/>USA 2004. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>In fact, MMFs&apos; ability to maintain a stable share price is considered the key reason for their <lb/>popularity. 14 Investors have often viewed MMFs as bank equivalents and invest their money <lb/>in MMFs because MMFs offer features analogous to bank deposits: stability of value of the <lb/>principal invested and instantaneous access to liquidity. 15 Although banks and MMFs are <lb/>similar in some respects they differ in others, especially in terms of their legal structure and <lb/>economic function. MMFs do not create liquidity for their investors, rather they manage <lb/>liquidity by investing in short-term debt instruments. 16 Banks are deemed highly leveraged <lb/>institutions and use borrowed funds to provide credit to individuals and businesses needing <lb/>access to credit 17 and use borrowed funds to provide credit to individuals and businesses <lb/>needing access to credit. 18 Further, MMFs regulations clearly specify the types and <lb/>proportions of the assets that MMFs can invest in, and the investors have the right to know the <lb/>funds&apos; holdings through the compulsory disclosure which is not the case for the bank <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>14 See, Fabozzi, (n 9) 648. <lb/>15 See, Qingmin Yan and Jianhua, Regulating China&apos;s shadow banks 2 (Routledge, New York 2015). <lb/>16 Fernando J. Cardim de Carvalho, Liquidity Preference and Monetary Economies 89 (Routledge, New York <lb/>2015). <lb/>17 See, Investment Company Institute, Money Market Funds in 2012: Money Market Funds Are Not Banks <lb/>(2012) available at https://www.ici.org/pdf/12_mmf_mmfs_are_not_banks.pdf accessed 5 August 2017. <lb/>18 See, Ross Cranston, Principles of Banking Law 5 (3 rd edn, Oxford University Press, Oxford 2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>depositors. 19 Banks typically hold short-term and long-term securities which are illiquid. <lb/>Holding illiquid long-term and non-diversified portfolios has demonstrably failed to provide <lb/>stability for the banking industry. 20 On the contrary, MMFs hold short-term highly liquid, safe <lb/>and transparent securities. Another significant difference is that the notion of MMFs is based <lb/>on the idea of pooling money from investors by offering their shares to the public. This means <lb/>that unlike bank depositors, MMFs&apos; investors buy shares from the funds and do not deposit <lb/>their money. Therefore, investors acquire ownership interests in the fund&apos;s assets and shares in <lb/>the fund&apos;s profits and losses. <lb/>It is significant to mention that due to their popularity in the financial markets, MMFs assets <lb/>have grown dramatically over time. One of the main reasons of this growth is that MMFs <lb/>offer higher yield relative to banks&apos; savings accounts. 21 The global MMF industry (measured <lb/>by assets under management) is dominated by the U.S. In Europe, more than 95% of the <lb/>MMFs industry is concentrated in Luxembourg, Ireland and France. 22 In its first quarter 2017 <lb/>report, the Investment Company Institute reported that assets in MMFs had reached nearly <lb/>$5,157 billion during the first quarter of 2017 compared to $42.77 trillion of the mutual funds <lb/>worldwide assets at the end of the first quarter of 2017. 23 This means that MMFs accounted <lb/>for an estimated 12% of all mutual funds globally. In the US, according to the American <lb/>Investment Company Institute Fact Book 2017, MMFs net assets exceeded $2.7 trillion at the <lb/>end of 2016. 24 <lb/>2.2 A Classification of Money Market Funds <lb/>Different types of MMFS around the world exists to cater to the investors&apos; needs such as risk <lb/>tolerance and returns expectations. This flexibility makes MMFs a preferred option to a wide <lb/>range of investors in the financial market. Since this paper addresses MMFs in the US and the <lb/>EU, the focus will be on the classification of MMFs in these jurisdictions. As mentioned <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>19 See, Jones, (n 11) 47. <lb/>20 See, Investment Company Institute (n 17). <lb/>21 See, International Monetary Fund, Global Financial Stability Report, March 2002: Market Developments and <lb/>Issues 46 (2002). <lb/>22 See, IOSCO, Peer Review of Regulation of Money Market Funds: Final Report (2015) available at <lb/>https://www.iosco.org/library/pubdocs/pdf/IOSCOPD502.pdf accessed 6 August 2017. <lb/>23 See, Investment Company Institute, Worldwide Assets and Flows for Regulated Open-End Funds First <lb/>Quarter 2017 available at https://www.ici.org/research/stats/worldwide/ww_q1_17 accessed 6 August 2017. <lb/>24 See, American Investment Company Institute, 2017 Investment Company Fact Book (57th Edition, 2017). The <lb/>American Investment Company Institute (ICI) publishes every year a Fact Book which updates the statistics of <lb/>the mutual funds industry in the USA and around the world. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>above, there is no clear classification of MMFs, so this article strives to distinctly classify <lb/>them. Based on assets valuation methodology, MMFs can be classified into constant (or <lb/>stable) NAV MMFs and variable NAV MMFs. They can also be classified by the investor <lb/>type into two types: institutional and retail MMFs. According to their portfolio investments, <lb/>MMFs can be classified into government and prime MMFs. This section investigates these <lb/>types and their fundamental features (figure 2). <lb/>Figure (2): types of MMFs <lb/>A-Constant Versus Variable MMFs <lb/>Depending on the assets valuation methodology applied, MMFs either offer their shares at a <lb/>constant net asset value (CNAV) or a variable or floating net asset value (VNAV). 25 CNAV <lb/>MMFs use amortized cost accounting method to value their assets. 26 Amortized cost method <lb/>is an accounting valuation method where securities are valued at acquisition cost, as adjusted <lb/>for amortization of premium or accretion of discount. 27 This means that the valuation is not <lb/>based on current market factors. Using this method enables MMFs to maintain a constant <lb/>share price of $1, €1 or £1. By using the amortized cost method, the MMF makes incremental <lb/>adjustments to the amortized cost of a security each business day, so the amortized cost of <lb/>that security equals its face value when the security matures. For example, MMFs invest in <lb/>short-term securities such as commercial paper and repurchase agreements. Most of these <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">25 CNAV is also called Stable NAV (SNAV) and VNAV is also called Floating NAV (FNAV). <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>26 Daniel Levin, Breaking the Buck: The End for Money Market Mutual Funds as We Know Them 28 Rev. <lb/>Banking &amp; Fin. L 751 (2009). <lb/>27 Lim, (n 7). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <body>Types of MMFs <lb/>Assets Valuation <lb/>Method <lb/>Constant <lb/>MMF <lb/>Variable <lb/>MMF <lb/>Investors <lb/>Base <lb/>Institutional <lb/>MMF <lb/>Retail MMF <lb/>Assets Type <lb/>Government <lb/>MMF <lb/>Prime MMF <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>securities are discount securities where they are typically sold for less than face value (the <lb/>discount). Discount securities do not pay explicit interest, rather the interest is implicit. 28 <lb/>When the securities mature, the investor receives the face value. The difference between what <lb/>the investor paid and the amount received at maturity is the implicit interest. For instance, an <lb/>MMF may pay € 99.50 for a security that will return €100 in 50 days. The face value of the <lb/>security is €100 and the purchase price of the security is € 99.50. The discount is € 0.50. The <lb/>MMF records the security in its portfolio at an initial amortized cost of € 99.50. By applying <lb/>the amortized cost method, the MMF can increase the amortized cost value of the security <lb/>each business day by the amount of the daily interest accrual. This is generally calculated as <lb/>the difference between the security face value and the purchase price divided by the <lb/>remaining maturity of the security. In our example, the daily accrued interest would be one <lb/>cent ([€100 -€99.50]/50). The amortized cost method allows MMFs to increase the <lb/>amortized cost of securities-the purchase price plus accrued interest-at a predictable rate <lb/>each business day. 29 Consequently, a money market fund can maintain a stable €1.00/$ 1.00 <lb/>NAV. The accrued interest, in our example the daily one cent increment, is the daily dividend <lb/>declared to the MMF shareholders. When the accrued interest is offset by the dividend paid to <lb/>the shareholders, the MMF manages, from day to day, to maintain a stable NAV. <lb/>Obviously, the rationale of permitting MMFs to use the amortized cost method lies in the <lb/>nature of the securities that MMFs are required to hold. As mentioned above, MMFs hold <lb/>short-term and highly liquid debt securities. The amortized cost method usually provides a <lb/>good approximation to the real market value of MMF portfolio assets. That could only be true <lb/>if financial market conditions remain exactly as they were when the MMF purchased the <lb/>security because both the security&apos;s amortized cost and its market value increase every <lb/>business day by the amount of interest accrued. Nonetheless, it is rare that financial market <lb/>conditions remain the same. For instance, interest rates change from day to day and that <lb/>might affect the market values of the securities that an MMF holds. Therefore, MMFs value <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>28 For further information about discount securities see, Julian Walmsley, The Foreign Exchange and Money <lb/>Markets Guide 147 (2 nd edn John Wiley &amp; Sons, New Jersey 2000). <lb/>29 See, Institutional Money Market Funds Association, The use of amortised cost accounting by money market <lb/>funds (2013) available at <lb/>https://www.immfa.org/assets/files/IMMFA%20The%20use%20of%20amortised%20cost%20accounting%20b <lb/>y%20MMF.pdf accessed 17 August 2017. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>their securities at amortized cost to avoid fluctuations in the market value in the interim and <lb/>maintain a stable NAV. 30 <lb/>VNAV MMFs, on the other hand, use the mark-to-market accounting method to value their <lb/>portfolio. The mark-to-market method is a valuation method where securities are valued at <lb/>their current market value in order to reflect the regular fluctuations in the value of the <lb/>MMF&apos;s portfolio assets. 31 Therefore, the MMF&apos;s NAV might float from day to day. For <lb/>instance, if an MMF invests its entire portfolio assets in A&apos;s company shares, at the close of <lb/>each business day the MMF manager computes the fund&apos;s NAV by multiplying the closing <lb/>value of the A share price by the number of the MMF&apos;s A shares. When there is no readily <lb/>available market quotation for entire or some of the MMF&apos;s securities the MMF manager uses <lb/>the fair valuation method to value those securities. 32 The fair value is the price that the MMF <lb/>may reasonably expect to receive upon a current sale. The main objective of the mark-to-<lb/>market method is to compute a timely and accurate value of the MMF&apos;s assets. <lb/>It is important to know that prior to the 2014 reform, CNAV MMF was the only type of <lb/>MMFs in the US. 33 In Europe, MMFs could feature either CNAV or VNAV; however, the <lb/>new MMF reforms, as will be discussed later, have produced a new type of MMF: the low <lb/>volatility MMF (LVNAV). <lb/>B-Institutional Versus Retail MMFs <lb/>MMFs can be classified by the targeted investor group into retail and institutional. A retail <lb/>MMF usually designs its policies and procedures to limit the ownership to natural persons. <lb/>An institutional MMF is a fund that targets institutional and sophisticated investors. 34 <lb/>Institutional investors use money market funds to manage liquidity and these act as important <lb/>alternatives to cash accounts. On aggregate, institutional investors account for around 65 per <lb/>cent of the total assets under management in the US MMF industry. 35 In Europe, MMFs are <lb/>widely used by institutional investors at approximately 75 per cent of the total asset under <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>30 Brown, (n 2). <lb/>31 William Birdthistle, Breaking Bucks in Money Market Funds 2010 Wis. L. Rev 1165 (2010). <lb/>32 Levin, (n 26). <lb/>33 Brown, (n 2). <lb/>34 Robert Pozen and Theresa Hamacher, The Fund Industry: How Your Money is Managed 203 (2 nd edn John <lb/>Wiley &amp; Sons, New Jersey 2015). <lb/>35 See, American Investment Company Institute, (n 24). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>management. 36 The significance of classifying MMFs into institutional and retail derives <lb/>from the differences in shareholder behaviour, especially in difficult situations in the <lb/>financial market. Retail investors are presumed to be passive investors which means that in <lb/>the case of any potential change in the risk characteristics of the MMF retail investors react <lb/>slowly to that risk. 37 Institutional investors, on the other hand, are sophisticated investors, and <lb/>because they have their own experienced research team, they react quickly to any potential <lb/>risk. 38 This exposes MMFs to different degrees of liquidity risk. The degree of the risk might <lb/>be greater when the MMFs assets are owned by fewer large sophisticated investors. <lb/>Therefore, institutional investor-oriented MMFs preserve a high level of available liquidity to <lb/>avoid the risk of investor run, which in turn might affect the stability of the financial market <lb/>generally and the MMFs particularly. <lb/>C-Government Versus Prime MMFs <lb/>A prime MMF is a fund that invests in securities issued by corporate entities. Prime MMFs <lb/>typically invest in short-term corporate notes, repurchase agreement, banks&apos; certificates of <lb/>deposits and commercial paper. 39 MMFs that invest in securities issued or guaranteed by state <lb/>governments are known as government MMFs. 40 Government and prime MMFs can be found <lb/>in both the US and Europe. Because government MMFs principally invest in government <lb/>securities, they are not exposed to credit risk. Therefore, unlike prime MMF, they are <lb/>considered safe investments. It is significant to know that in the US the MMF industry has <lb/>produced another type of MMF: a tax-exempt MMF. This fund invests exclusively in <lb/>securities issued by the US local governments and tax-exempt municipal securities. 41 A tax-<lb/>exempt MMF is a good option for retail investors who are seeking a tax-exempt investment <lb/>to their income; however, a tax-exempt MMF is the smallest MMF category regarding the <lb/>size of the assets under management. <lb/>3. MMFs and Financial Stability <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>36 See, Institutional Money Market Funds Association IMMFA Assets Under Management (2017) available at <lb/>https://www.immfa.org/market-statistics/immfa-aum.html accessed 17 August 2017. <lb/>37 Jorge A Chan-Lau and Li L Ong, U.S. Mutual Fund Retail Investors in International Equity Markets: Is the Tail <lb/>Wagging the Dog? (2005) International Monetary Fund Working Paper 05/162, 3 <lb/>http://www.imf.org/en/Publications/WP/Issues/2016/12/31/U-S-18227 accessed 22 March 2018. <lb/>38 Jason Kravitt, Securitization of Financial Assets 17-112 (Aspen Publishers Online, 2012). <lb/>39 Birdthistle, (n 31). <lb/>40 Pozen and Hamacher, (n 34) 203. <lb/>41 Lim, (n 7). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>This section is divided into two parts. While the first part defines financial stability, the <lb/>second part discusses financial instability caused by MMFs runs during the 2008 financial <lb/>crisis. <lb/>3. 1 Defining Financial Stability <lb/>Since this article analyses MMFs&apos; reforms from a financial stability perspective, it is essential <lb/>to examine the concept of financial stability and define its core elements. However, before <lb/>examining financial stability, it is useful to appropriately define the relevant concepts such as <lb/>the financial system, and systemic risk. <lb/>What is a financial system? <lb/>Generally, a financial system comprises of three main components: financial institutions, <lb/>financial markets, and financial infrastructure. 42 Financial institutions, such as pension funds <lb/>and mutual funds, also provide a wide range of services, including investment and market <lb/>brokering. A financial market is a platform that matches savers and investors under some <lb/>established rules of conduct. 43 Financial infrastructure consists of set of institutions that <lb/>enable efficient operation of financial intermediaries such as payment systems and credit <lb/>information offices. 44 <lb/>What is systemic risk? <lb/>Despite the fact the term &quot;Systemic risk&quot; is widely used, it is difficult to define and quantify. 45 <lb/>In its Report on financial consolidation and risk, the Group of Ten (G-10) proposed the <lb/>following definition: <lb/>&quot;Systemic financial risk is the risk that an event will trigger a loss of <lb/>economic value or confidence in, and attendant increases in uncertainly <lb/>about, a substantial portion of the financial system that is serious enough <lb/>to quite probably have significant adverse effects on the real economy.&quot; 46 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>42 International Monetary Fund, Compilation Guide on Financial Soundness Indicators (2004) available at <lb/>https://www.imf.org/external/np/sta/fsi/eng/2004/guide/index.htm accessed 20 June 2018. <lb/>43 See, Madura, (n 10) 3. <lb/>44 Garry Schinasi, Safeguarding Financial Stability: Theory and Practice 107 (International Monetary Fund, <lb/>washington 2006). <lb/>45 International Monetary Fund, Responding to the Financial Crisis and Measuring Systemic Risks (2009) <lb/>available at http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/gfsr/2009/01/ accessed 20 June 2018. <lb/>46 Group of Ten, Report on Consolidation in the Financial Sector (2001) available at <lb/>https://www.bis.org/publ/gten05.pdf accessed 20 June 2018. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>The definition shows the key characteristics of systemic risk. Systemic risk must affect a <lb/>&quot;substantial portion&quot; of the financial system, so it is a risk to the financial system as a whole. <lb/>What is financial stability? <lb/>Despite the increased focus on the significance of financial stability issues, there is, as yet, no <lb/>widely accepted agreement on what financial stability precisely means. In the financial <lb/>stability literature, two schools of thought are distinctly discernible. While the first school <lb/>prefers to define financial instability, the representatives of the second school attempt to <lb/>define financial stability. <lb/>In the first school of thought, Mishkin, for example, stated that &quot;financial instability occurs <lb/>when shocks to the financial system interfere with information flow so that the financial <lb/>system can no longer do its job of channeling funds to those with productive investment <lb/>opportunities&quot;. 47 The definition emphasizes the essential role of information failures in <lb/>causing financial instability. Further, Chant described financial instability as &quot;…conditions in <lb/>financial markets that harm or threaten to harm an economy&apos;s performance through their <lb/>impact on the working of the financial system&quot; The definition suggests that financial <lb/>instability should be examined with regard to the potential impact of changes in financial <lb/>conditions on the real economy. 48 <lb/>In the second school of thought, Crockett pointed out that financial stability requires &quot;that the <lb/>key institutions in the financial system are stable, in that there is a high degree of confidence <lb/>that they continue to meet their contractual obligations without interruption or outside <lb/>assistance; and that the key markets are stable...&quot;. 49 The definition considers only two <lb/>components of the financial system: financial institutions and markets. Nonetheless, it does <lb/>not include the third main element of the financial system which is financial infrastructure. <lb/>In his paper &quot;Defining Financial Stability&quot;, Schinasi defined financial stability as &quot;A financial <lb/>system is in a range of stability whenever it is capable of facilitating (rather than impeding) <lb/>the performance of an economy and of dissipating financial imbalances that arise <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>47 Frederic Mishkin, Global Financial Instability: Framework, Events, Issues 13 Journal of Economic <lb/>Perspectives 7 (1999. <lb/>48 John Chant, Financial Stability as a Policy Goal 3 (2003) in Essays on Financial Stability, Technical Report No. <lb/>95, Bank of Canada, available at <lb/>http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.172.8150&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf accessed 19 June <lb/>2018. <lb/>49 Andrew Crockett, Why is Financial Stability a Goal of Public Policy? 82 Economic Review 6 (1997). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>endogenously or as a result of significant adverse and unanticipated events&quot;. 50 Interestingly, <lb/>the definition does not view financial stability as a single or static condition but instead it <lb/>emphasizes that financial stability is a continuum. <lb/>In 2012, the European Central Bank (ECB) defined financial stability as: <lb/>&quot;a condition in which the financial system-comprising of financial <lb/>intermediaries, markets and market infrastructures-is capable of <lb/>withstanding shocks and the unraveling of financial imbalances, <lb/>thereby mitigating the likelihood of disruptions in the financial <lb/>intermediation process which are severe enough to significantly <lb/>impair the allocation of savings to profitable investment <lb/>opportunities&quot;. 51 <lb/>The ECB definition is significant because it emphasizes that financial stability is a broad <lb/>concept, encompassing the three core components of the financial system: financial <lb/>institutions, markets and infrastructure. Considering the close interlinkages between all of <lb/>these components, expectations of disturbances in any of the individual elements can impact <lb/>the overall stability. To illustrate, disturbances may initially arise and develop in a single <lb/>institution and subsequently spread to other elements of the financial system. Therefore, the <lb/>regulatory intervention to achieve financial stability should be comprehensive, addressing the <lb/>three key components. Leaving any gap in these elements will result in the instability of the <lb/>financial system. This approach is called the macro-prudential approach. In the aftermath of <lb/>the 2008 financial crisis, there seems to be a consensus among regulators and academics that <lb/>financial regulation needs to follow the macro-prudential approach. In analysing MMFs&apos; <lb/>reforms in the EU and the US, this article will apply this holistic approach. The events during <lb/>the 2008 financial crisis demonstrated that the vulnerability of MMFs to runs is a source of <lb/>instability of the whole financial system, so any attempt to stabilize the financial system will <lb/>most likely be incomplete without addressing this susceptibility. <lb/>3.2 The 2008 Financial Crisis: Breaking the Buck and the Phenomenon of Runs <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>50 Garry Schinasi, Defining Financial Stability (2004) IMF Working Paper No. WP/04/187, available at <lb/>https://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/wp/2004/wp04187.pdf accessed 20 June 2018. <lb/>51 European Central Bank, Financial Stability Review (2012) available at <lb/>https://www.ecb.europa.eu/pub/pdf/other/financialstabilityreview201212en.pdf?f73875a2aa7884337314f4f1 <lb/>c4db5a7d accessed 20 June 2018. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>The financial crisis of 2008, often referred to as the Great Recession, affected every single <lb/>aspect of the economy. The September 2008 run on some MMFs alerted financial regulators <lb/>to the systemic relevance of MMFs. Even though MMFs did not cause the financial crisis, <lb/>their performance during the crisis demonstrated their potential to spread or even expand a <lb/>crisis. 52 An MMF &quot;breaks the buck&quot; when the value of its shares falls below their standard <lb/>$1.00 or €1.00 value. This could occur when the number of shares redeemed in a short period <lb/>of time is huge, so the liquidity of the fund cannot support the $1.00 valuation. 53 In this case, <lb/>MMF&apos;s shareholders are not able to redeem their shares for the $1.00 that they primarily <lb/>invested, so they &quot;run&quot; to the MMF to redeem their shares. A run on an MMF could cause <lb/>contagion in the MMF industry where a wave of redemptions spread from one MMF to <lb/>another. 54 In US history, only two MMFs have broken the buck where their NAV fell below <lb/>$1.00. 55 The most recent example was in 2008 when the Reserve Primary Fund reduced the <lb/>NAV of its shares to $0.97. 56 The Reserve Primary Fund was one of the largest MMF in the <lb/>US and had a good reputation among the investors because it generated above average <lb/>returns. Interestingly, the Reserve Primary Fund increased its commercial paper holdings by <lb/>59% within one year. Reserve Primary Fund assets under management were $62 billion, of <lb/>which it had invested around 1.2%, $785 million, in commercial paper issued by Lehman <lb/>Brothers. 57 On September 16, 2008, Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc declared bankruptcy. <lb/>Consequently, the Reserve Primary Fund lost $785 million in value, and that caused a <lb/>decrease in its NAV per share from $1.00 to $0.97. One day later, Reserve Primary Fund <lb/>broke the buck leading to a run by its shareholders. The shareholders requested redemptions <lb/>of approximately $40 billion in just two days. 58 The run contagion quickly spread to other <lb/>prime MMFs and within one-week investors withdrew approximately $310 billion from <lb/>prime MMFs. 59 In order to meet investors&apos; redemption requests, MMFs were forced to sell <lb/>their portfolio securities, which in turn lead to declines in the prices of short-term <lb/>instruments. However, only the Reserve Primary Fund broke the buck because many MMF <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>52 See, Viral V. Acharya, Thomas F. Cooley, Matthew P. Richardson and Ingo Walter, Regulating Wall <lb/>Street: The Dodd-Frank Act and the New Architecture of Global Finance 308 (John Wiley &amp; Sons, New Jersey <lb/>2010). <lb/>53 See, Gary Gorton, Misunderstanding Financial Crises: Why We Don&apos;t See Them Coming 49 (OUP USA, New <lb/>York 2012). <lb/>54 Perlow, (n 1). <lb/>55 Price, (n 5). <lb/>56 Ibid. <lb/>57 Lim, (n 7). <lb/>58 Ibid. <lb/>59 Evanoff Douglas and Moeller William, Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act: <lb/>Purpose, Critique, Implementation Status and Policy Issues 128 (World Scientific, Singapore 2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>sponsors provided fundamental financial support to avoid breaking the buck (sponsor support <lb/>will be discussed in detail later). 60 <lb/>Further, in order to understand MMFs runs it is necessary to compare MMFs with banks and <lb/>mutual funds. The phenomenon of runs is commonly associated with the banking industry. 61 <lb/>The main source of funds for banks is deposits; money that depositors deposit to the bank for <lb/>safekeeping and use in their transactions. The depositors reserve the right to withdraw the full <lb/>amount of their deposits upon demand. Banks use deposits to lend borrowers. Banks usually <lb/>have liquidity to meet normal withdrawal demands. Nonetheless, if a large quantity of <lb/>depositors withdraw their money at the same time, the bank will not be able to honour its <lb/>obligation and meet those demands. 62 And as a result, the bank will experience a run. The <lb/>depositors who withdraw their money first are able to receive their deposit in full, while those <lb/>who run slowly to the bank will most likely not receive their full deposits. This is known as <lb/>the first-mover advantage. 63 In contrast, a &quot;first-mover advantage&quot; in MMFs enables those <lb/>investors who redeem their shares first to do so at the standard NAV share price of $1.00, <lb/>even if the fund&apos;s assets are worth less. The redemption at $1.00 will decrease the MMF&apos;s <lb/>assets because those investors receive more than their actual entitlement. Consequently, the <lb/>subsequent investors will receive less than the first movers. Here, it is important to emphasise <lb/>the fact that in normal market conditions small variations between the standard $1.00 and the <lb/>MMF&apos;s actual NAV do not result in decreasing the MMF&apos;s assets because these variations are <lb/>offset by the purchases that also take place at $1.00 per share at the same time. <lb/>In a mutual fund, the first-mover advantage is not possible because the mutual fund does not <lb/>undertake to pay out anything more than each share&apos;s NAV which represents the aggregate <lb/>value of the fund assets minus the aggregate liabilities of the fund divided by the number of <lb/>shares outstanding. 64 To illustrate, if a mutual fund&apos;s NAV dropped by 20 per cent the <lb/>shareholders who run first to the fund will receive the same as those who ask for redemption <lb/>later. In other words, each shareholder in the mutual fund would receive only 80 percent of <lb/>the original invested value. Thus, the phenomenon of run in mutual funds is not possible. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>60 See, Hal Scott, Connectedness and Contagion: Protecting the Financial System from Panics 72 (MIT Press, <lb/>Cambridge 2016). <lb/>61 For further information about bank&apos;s run see, Gurbachan Singh, Banking Crises, Liquidity, and Credit Lines: A <lb/>Macroeconomic Perspective 24 (Routledge, New York 2012). <lb/>62 Ibid, 24. <lb/>63 Fisch, (n 4). <lb/>64 Mayo, (n 13) 337. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>In addition, breaking the buck might have serious and harmful impacts not only on the <lb/>investors, but also on the MMF industry and the financial market. To explain the threat, when <lb/>an MMF breaks the buck some investors might lose part or all of their share value. The <lb/>impact would be bigger on institutional investors because they usually hold large quantities <lb/>of shares and some MMFs shares might be held by few institutional investors. Further, <lb/>breaking the buck could also have a serious impact on the MMF industry. An MMF promise <lb/>to redeem its shares at stable $1.00 NAV per share is a main attribute that encourages <lb/>investors to invest in the fund. Failure of an MMF to honour its promise could result in losing <lb/>the confidence of not only the investors of the fund that broke the buck but also other MMFs <lb/>investors, so they either withdraw their money or stop investing in MMFs in the future. This <lb/>impact was clearly demonstrated by the huge number of redemptions that took place when <lb/>the Reserve Primary Fund broke the buck in both the US and European financial markets. <lb/>According to the Institutional Money Market Funds Association (IMMFA) the huge number <lb/>of redemptions in the US MMFs market affected the European CNAV MMFs to such an <lb/>extent that around 25 per cent of their total assets were redeemed in a very short time <lb/>period. 65 <lb/>Moreover, the adverse impact of breaking the buck could extend to the financial market and <lb/>economy. As explained above, when an MMF breaks the buck its investors will quickly run <lb/>to the fund to redeem their shares. A run on an MMF could lead to runs on other MMFs and <lb/>the huge number of redemptions will cause liquidity problems to MMFs. To overcome these <lb/>problems, MMFs will attempt to sell their portfolio assets to get cash. A forced sale of the <lb/>MMFs assets that occurs simultaneously might lead to price declines in the market or in a <lb/>specific sector. This most likely will affect all other institutions that hold these assets and <lb/>ultimately the stability of the financial market. The interventions of the US government to <lb/>stabilise the financial market after the Reserve Primary Fund broke the buck is clear proof of <lb/>this potential impact. To illustrate, on September 19, 2008, the Board of Governors of the <lb/>Federal Reserve System and the Treasury launched two unprecedented market interventions <lb/>to provide additional liquidity to MMFs and stabilize the financial markets. 66 These programs <lb/>successfully slowed the run on prime MMFs. Although the government interventions were <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>65 See, European Commission, Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on <lb/>Money Market Funds available at http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-<lb/>content/EN/TXT/PDF/?uri=CELEX:52013SC0315&amp;from=da accessed 21 August 2017. <lb/>66 See, Michael Brandl, Money, Banking, Financial Markets and Institutions 196 (Cengage Learning, Boston <lb/>2016). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>vital at that stage, the financial crisis alerted the financial regulators to the necessity of <lb/>reforming the MMFs&apos; regulations as a prerequisite to stabilising the financial market. <lb/>4. Regulatory reform of MMFs <lb/>After the global financial crisis, there was a consensus that the financial market&apos;s instability <lb/>was global, and international cooperation to enhance the financial legal framework needed to <lb/>be strengthened. Under the guidance of the Financial Stability Board (FSB), some initiatives <lb/>to improve financial stability were made, including recommendations to promote oversight of <lb/>shadow banking activities, the Basel III Accords and certain provisions for the &quot;globally <lb/>systemic important banks&quot;. 67 Along with securitization and repurchase agreement, improving <lb/>MMFs&apos; regulatory framework is considered an essential part of enhancing the shadow <lb/>banking system. The FSB, in 2011, defined shadow banking as &quot;credit intermediation <lb/>involving entities and activities (fully or partially) outside the regular banking system.&quot; 68 The <lb/>FSB tasked the International Organization of Securities Commissions (IOSCO) to develop <lb/>guidelines for MMFs and on October 9, 2012, the IOSCO issued their Policy <lb/>Recommendations (Final Report) for reforming MMFs. 69 The IOSCO Report outlined 15 <lb/>recommendations to be the basis for common standards for MMFs regulations across <lb/>jurisdictions. The recommendations, generally, are articulated around key principles for <lb/>disclosure to investors, liquidity management, maturity, credit, valuation, use of ratings and <lb/>repurchase agreements. The IOSCO recommended that: MMFs should be explicitly defined <lb/>in collective investment scheme regulations; specific limitations on the types of assets in <lb/>which MMFs could invest and the risks they may take should be applied; regulators should <lb/>closely monitor other collective investment schemes and securities similar to MMFs to avoid <lb/>confusion among investors and to limit the risk of regulatory arbitrage; they should comply <lb/>with fair valuation methods when valuing the securities; the appropriateness of the MMF <lb/>valuation practices should be reviewed by a third party; MMFs should know their investors <lb/>and their sophistication as part of risk management; they should hold a minimum amount of <lb/>liquid assets to strengthen themselves against huge redemptions and prevent forced sales; <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>67 For further information about Systemically important financial institutions (SIFIs) see: FSB, Addressing SIFIs <lb/>available at http://www.fsb.org/what-we-do/policy-development/systematically-important-financial-<lb/>institutions-sifis/ accessed 26 August 2017. <lb/>68 See, FSB, Shadow Banking: Strengthening Oversight and Regulation (2011) available at <lb/>http://www.fsb.org/wp-content/uploads/r_111027a.pdf accessed 6 June 2018. <lb/>69 The IOSCO, Policy Recommendations for Money Market Funds Final Report (2012) available at <lb/>http://www.csrc.gov.cn/pub/csrc_en/affairs/AffairsIOSCO/201210/P020121010500138903810.pdf accessed <lb/>26 August 2017. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>they should periodically conduct appropriate stress testing; they should have appropriate tools <lb/>to deal with exceptional market conditions and substantial redemption pressures; <lb/>stable/constant NAV MMFs should be converted to floating/variable NAV or, alternatively <lb/>stable NAV MMFs should be reinforced for resilience; MMFs should have in place effective <lb/>internal credit risk assessment procedures to avoid any mechanistic reliance on external <lb/>ratings agencies; the credit rating agencies&apos; current rating methodologies should be more <lb/>explicit for MMFs; MMFs&apos; investors should be informed the possibility of principal loss and <lb/>that MMFs do not guarantee capital; MMFs should disclose the funds&apos; practices in relation to <lb/>valuation and the applicable procedures in times of stress; and regulators should develop <lb/>guidelines on the framework applicable to the use of repos by MMFs. 70 The FSB endorsed <lb/>IOSCO&apos;s recommendations, and published its final report, Strengthening Oversight and <lb/>Regulation of Shadow Banking. 71 The IOSCO&apos;s recommendations, obviously, demonstrate <lb/>the role of improving MMFs legal framework in achieving the stability of the international <lb/>financial system because they aim to reinforce the safety of MMFs and reduce their potential <lb/>to create or amplify systemic risks. The importance of these recommendations comes from <lb/>the fact that they recognize that MMFs operate differently from country to country under <lb/>different market regulations, so regulators can determine the appropriate policy responses to <lb/>address the financial stability issues potentially raised by these financial institutions. <lb/>4.1 Reforms in the U.S. Regulatory Regime <lb/>In the US, MMFs are a type of mutual fund registered under the Investment Company Act <lb/>(ICA) of 1940. What makes MMFs unique relative to other mutual funds is that MMFs must <lb/>comply with the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) Rule 2a-7. 72 In 1983, the SEC <lb/>issued Rule 2a-7 that sets out portfolio requirements regarding liquidity, maturity, credit <lb/>quality and diversification which were intended to help MMFs to maintain a stable NAV. In <lb/>response to the 2008 financial crisis and breaking of the buck by the Reserve Primary Fund, <lb/>the SEC adopted reforms and amendments to Rule 2a-7 in 2010. 73 These reforms were <lb/>designed to fortify the MMFs industry and protect investors by reducing the interest rate, <lb/>liquidity and credit risks of MMF&apos;s portfolios. To illustrate, the reforms required MMFs to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>70 Ibid. <lb/>71 See, FSB, (n 68). <lb/>72 See, Matthew P Fink, The Rise of Mutual Funds: An Insider&apos;s View 178 (2 nd edn Oxford University Press, New <lb/>York 2011). <lb/>73 See, SEC, SEC Approves Money Market Fund Reforms to Better Protect Investors (2010) available at <lb/>https://www.sec.gov/news/press/2010/2010-14.htm accessed 29 August 2017. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>maintain daily at least 10 percent of an MMF&apos;s assets, and weekly, at least 30 percent of each <lb/>MMF&apos;s assets, liquidity. 74 MMFs became also under an obligation to reduce the maximum <lb/>allowable weighted average maturity (WAM) of MMF portfolios from 90 days to 60 days in <lb/>order to diminish MMFs&apos; exposure to interest rate risk. 75 Another important change was that <lb/>MMFs&apos; advisers were required to periodically stress test their funds&apos; ability to maintain a <lb/>stable NAV per share based on certain hypothetical events such as a change in short-term <lb/>interest rates. Although the 2010 MMF reforms were an effective improvement to the MFF <lb/>industry, several significant market events after the 2010 reforms, however, raised a <lb/>fundamental question about the demand for further reforms to boost the financial stability and <lb/>reduce MMFs systemic risks. Particularly, in 2011, the Eurozone sovereign debt crisis and <lb/>the US. government&apos;s debt ceiling crisis occurred, and in 2013 another US. government debt <lb/>ceiling unfolded. <lb/>In fact, after the 2010 reforms there have been no failures in the MMF industry despite the <lb/>significant turmoil in the financial markets. In 2011, during the Eurozone crisis and the <lb/>United States debt ceiling MMFs were able to meet investors&apos; heavy redemption requests. 76 <lb/>This can be attributed to the high level of liquidity that MMFs were required to hold under <lb/>the 2010 rules and the MMFs managers&apos; anticipation to investors&apos; response to the crisis, so <lb/>they responded quickly to the market conditions by increasing the fund&apos;s liquidity. However, <lb/>the investors&apos; confidence in the MMFs industry was once again faltering and consequently a <lb/>debate for further MMF reforms emerged. Importantly, when the SEC adopted the 2010 <lb/>amendments, it stated that MMFs&apos; experience during the 2008 financial crisis raised <lb/>questions of whether more substantial changes to MMFs regulations might be warranted. 77 <lb/>Further, data and analysis from the SEC&apos;s Division of Economic and Risk Analysis (DERA) <lb/>showed that additional reforms would assist in addressing potential future failures in the <lb/>MMF industry. 78 <lb/>It is significant to know that in 2010, under the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and <lb/>Consumer Protection Act of 2010 (Dodd-Frank Act) the Financial Stability Oversight <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>74 Ibid. <lb/>75 Ibid. <lb/>76 See, the Investment Company Institute, ICI Analysis of SEC&apos;s 2010 Money Market Fund Reforms: Tested, <lb/>Working, and Have Enhanced Financial Stability (2013) available at <lb/>https://www.ici.org/mmfs/sec_reforms/news/13_2010_mmf_reforms_study accessed 29 August 2017. <lb/>77 See, SEC, SEC Adopts Money Market Fund Reform Rules (2014) available at <lb/>https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2014-143 accessed 9 June 2018. <lb/>78 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Council (FSOC) was created. 79 The creation of FSOC was to identify risks to US financial <lb/>stability, respond to potential threats to the stability of the US financial system and promote <lb/>market discipline. Under Section 120 of the Dodd-Frank Act the FSOC has the authority to <lb/>issue &quot;recommendations&quot; to a primary financial regulator to apply new or strengthen existing <lb/>standards and safeguards. 80 In 2012, the FSOC used this authority and initiated a proceeding <lb/>pressing the SEC to adopt new MMF rules. 81 Even though the FSOC has the authority to <lb/>make recommendations, the SEC, a primary regulator, may reject the FSOC&apos;s <lb/>recommendation and explain its reasons. The FSOC could not force the SEC to start the <lb/>reform process; however, the SEC was under a pressure to show that it can act on its own to <lb/>address all concerns on MMFs caused by the market crisis. 82 On June 5, 2013, by a <lb/>unanimous vote, the SEC proposed amendments to the MMFs regulation. The proposed <lb/>amendments designed to address MMFs&apos; vulnerability to heavy redemptions and mitigate <lb/>potential contagion from such redemptions. On July 23, 2014, the SEC voted 3-2 to <lb/>substantially amend the regulatory framework of MMFs. The 2014 reform is one of the <lb/>biggest structural changes to MMFs in the US history, changing Rule 2a-7 radically. The new <lb/>rules came into force on October 2016. The 2014 reform rules can be grouped into four <lb/>categories: (A) rules regarding trading certain MMFs at floating NAV (FNAV); (B) a <lb/>requirement to impose liquidity fees and redemption gates; (C) rules regarding disclosure and <lb/>reporting obligations; and (D) stress testing. The following analysis will investigate the <lb/>rationale behind the new rules and their impacts on the MMFs industry and the stability of the <lb/>financial market. <lb/>A-Floating NAV <lb/>The major component of 2014 MMF reform is the FNAV. The 2014 reform requires <lb/>institutional prime and institutional municipal MMFs to value their portfolio securities using <lb/>market-based factors. 83 This means that these MMFs are no longer permitted to use the <lb/>amortized cost method to compute their NAV. Government and retail MMFs are allowed to <lb/>continue using the amortized cost method to value their securities in order to maintain a <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>79 Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act of 2010 s. 111. <lb/>80 Ibid, s. 120. <lb/>81 See, Financial Stability Oversight Council, Proposed Recommendations Regarding Money Market Mutual <lb/>Fund Reform (2012) available at https://www.treasury.gov/press-center/press-releases/Pages/tg1764.aspx <lb/>accessed 29 August 2017. <lb/>82 For further information, see, Martha Cochran, David Freeman, and Helen Clark, Money Market Fund Reform: <lb/>Sec Rulemaking in the FSOC Era 2015 Colum. Bus. L. Rev 862 (2015). <lb/>83 See, SEC, Money Market Fund Reform; Amendments to Form PF 135 (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>stable NAV. A government MMF is defined as a fund that invests 99.5% or more of their <lb/>total assets in cash, government securities, and/or repurchase agreements that are <lb/>collateralized fully (collateralized by cash or government securities). 84 A retail MMF is <lb/>defined as an MMF with policies and procedures reasonably designed to limit all beneficial <lb/>owners of the fund to natural persons. 85 The floating NAV eliminates the most unique <lb/>attribute of an MMF, the stable NAV, which makes MMFs attractive vehicles to different <lb/>types of investors. This raises a significant question: why might the SEC risk destroying an <lb/>essential part of an industry, which has performed very well in the financial markets and <lb/>served different types of investors? In order to understand the rationale behind the SEC&apos;s <lb/>decision to shift from stable NAV (SNAV) to FNAV it is essential to link the MMF 2014 <lb/>reform with the central objective of the financial regulation -financial stability-after the 2008 <lb/>financial crisis. Since the 2008 financial crisis the stability of the financial system has <lb/>become the priority of the financial regulators. Because of the social and economic costs of <lb/>financial instability, the reforms that have addressed the main financial industries such as the <lb/>banking industry (Basel III) demonstrate the emphasis on the importance of financial <lb/>stability. As discussed earlier, MMF industry is a significant industry and achieving the <lb/>financial stability objective cannot be accomplished without removing the instability <lb/>elements in this industry because any failure in the MMF sector will likely have wider impact <lb/>on other sectors. To illustrate, during the 2008 financial crisis and the subsequent events in <lb/>2011, institutional prime MMFs received huge redemption requests and were more <lb/>susceptible to runs than any other types due to the sophistication of their investors. 86 <lb/>Therefore, the SEC looks at institutional prime MMFs as a main source of vulnerability, but <lb/>can FNAVs address the susceptibility of institutional prime MMFs to run? <lb/>An FNAV is essentially the SEC&apos;s attempt to reduce the first mover advantage associated <lb/>with the structure of a SNAV because an MMF will redeem its shares at the fund&apos;s true NAV. <lb/>This means that institutional prime MMFs will operate like all other types of mutual funds <lb/>that use the mark-to-market method to price their shares. In transacting with an FNAV, <lb/>institutional prime MMFs&apos; investors should be aware when making the investment decision <lb/>that institutional prime MMFs are not anymore risk-free investments and their shares&apos; prices <lb/>might be affected by the market&apos;s conditions. Although the SEC&apos;s approach to addressing <lb/>institutional prime MMFs runs might mitigate the first mover advantage associated with the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>84 Ibid, at 202. <lb/>85 Ibid, at 223. <lb/>86 See, Fabozzi, (n 9) 653. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>motivation to run, it is unlikely to be sufficient to prevent a run during a severe liquidity crisis <lb/>because FNAVs would not prevent MMF investors from acting rationally to protect their <lb/>investments in any crisis. This can be demonstrated by the performance of FNAV MMFs in <lb/>Europe during the 2008 financial crisis where both FNAV and CNAV MMFs were equally <lb/>likely to run. 87 However, it is significant to emphasise that FNAV reform works in line with <lb/>other 2014 amendments, redemption gate and liquidity fee, which aim to address MMFs <lb/>vulnerability to run. <lb/>Importantly, the major change in the institutional prime MMF structure has adverse <lb/>consequences on this important MMF&apos;s segment. Institutional Prime MMFs&apos; transition from <lb/>stable to floating NAV might cause large shifts in assets to other investments such as <lb/>unregulated or less regulated funds, offshore MMFs or banks. Corporate cash managers, for <lb/>example, might shift their assets to other risk-free investments because their investment <lb/>policies and guidelines prevent them from investing in FNAV MMFs. According to Goldman <lb/>Sachs Asset Management, from 2014 to 2016, institutional prime MMFs&apos; assets under <lb/>management dropped from $1 trillion to $125 billion. 88 This huge shift in institutional prime <lb/>MMFs assets means that the 2014 reforms have significantly affected these MMFs, so they <lb/>have become less attractive. Nonetheless, stabilizing the financial system, from the financial <lb/>regulator&apos;s perspective, far outweighs this shift in the institutional prime MMFs&apos; assets. <lb/>B-Liquidity fees and redemption gates <lb/>Another significant change to the MMFs regulation is the introduction of liquidity fees and <lb/>redemption gates. A redemption gate is a temporary measure that may be implemented by an <lb/>MMF&apos;s board of directors that restricts redemptions in an MMF for up to 10 business days in <lb/>a 90-day period, if the fund&apos;s weekly liquid assets fall below 30% of its total assets. 89 The <lb/>board of directors can also impose liquidity fees up to 2%, if the fund&apos;s weekly liquid assets <lb/>fall below 30% of its total assets and the board determines that this measure is in the <lb/>investors&apos; best interest. 90 Nonetheless, an MMF is required to impose a liquidity fee of 1% on <lb/>all redemptions if its weekly liquid assets fall below 10% of its total assets, unless the board <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>87 See, Committee on Capital Markets Regulation, Comment letter to SEC (2013) available at <lb/>https://www.sec.gov/comments/s7-03-13/s70313-210.pdf accessed 5 September 2017. <lb/>88 See, Goldman Sachs Asset Management, US Money Market Reform by the Numbers (January 2017) available <lb/>at https://www.gsam.com/content/gsam/us/en/advisors/market-insights/gsam-insights/2017/us-money-<lb/>market-reform-by-the-numbers.html accessed 4 September 2017. <lb/>89 See, SEC, &apos;Money Market Fund Reform; Amendments to Form PF&apos; (2014) at 39. <lb/>90 Ibid, at 40. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>of directors of the fund determines that imposing such a fee would not be in the best interests <lb/>of the fund. 91 Rule 2a-7 already provided boards with the ability to suspend redemptions, <lb/>after SEC approval, provided an MMF would need to be liquidated. <lb/>The SEC rationale for imposing liquidity fees is to mitigate the first mover advantage through <lb/>increasing the cost of shares&apos; redemptions. 92 Unlike liquidity fees, redemption gates are <lb/>designed to directly stop a run in times of heavy redemptions. In other words, redemption <lb/>gates restriction aims at providing the MMF&apos;s board of directors with an immediate tool to <lb/>stop heavy redemptions in times of stress. <lb/>The shareholders&apos; right to redeem their shares at any time is a key feature that attracts <lb/>investors to invest in MMFs. By imposing liquidity fees and redemption gates, shareholders <lb/>will be prevented from accessing their funds, so these restrictions would influence the <lb/>investors&apos; investment decision to invest in MMFs. Liquidity fees and redemption gates are <lb/>discretionary tools; thus the board of directors might decide not to use them even though the <lb/>fund&apos;s assets fall below 30%. This raises an important question: why might the board of <lb/>director hesitate to impose these restrictions? Imposing a gate or fee would damage the <lb/>MMF&apos;s reputation and shareholders who have been subjected to a gate or fee are likely to <lb/>leave the fund. Prospective investors will also be careful of investing in an MMF that has <lb/>previously imposed these restrictions. Therefore, the MMFs&apos; ability to attract investors will <lb/>be limited due to the market competition conditions. These considerations would be likely to <lb/>impact the board of directors&apos; decision and determine that protecting the interest of the <lb/>investors requires them not to impose any restrictions. Even in cases of when the fund assets <lb/>fall below 10% the board still has the same power under the concept of the investors&apos; best <lb/>interest. By emphasizing on the concept of &quot;best interests&quot;, the SEC has placed a large <lb/>responsibility on the board of directors. However, the SEC did not provide meaningful <lb/>guidance on the concept &quot;best interests&quot; and how funds&apos; boards should exercise this <lb/>discretion to protect investors, and that might minimize the effectiveness of these tools. The <lb/>SEC, for example, indicated a number of factors a board might consider in determining the <lb/>fund&apos;s best interests. These may include, but are not limited to: the relevant indicators of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>91 Ibid, at 40. <lb/>92 Ibid, at 47. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>liquidity stress in the markets, the liquidity profile of the fund and expectations as to how the <lb/>profile might change in the immediate future, and the fund&apos;s experience. 93 <lb/>In addition, the question that can be raised here is: can fees and gates restrictions diminish <lb/>MMFs investors&apos; incentive to runs? When investors are aware that they should pay the cost <lb/>of their redemption requests, this could encourage them to remain invested in the funds to <lb/>avoid the exit cost. This, however, could be counterproductive. Since MMFs&apos; investors know <lb/>that MMF can impose fees and gates, any deterioration or slight stress in the financial market <lb/>might incentivise them to redeem their shares before the fund applies these tools. Further, <lb/>when other MMFs&apos; shareholders know that an MMF has imposed fees or gate they might run <lb/>to redeem their shares on concerns that their MMFs could take the same measures. In other <lb/>words, rather than diminishing MMFs&apos; incentive to run, fees and gates might increase <lb/>vulnerability of MMFs to run. As a result, the law should be clear in this regard and remove <lb/>any ambiguity that might undermine the effectiveness of these tools. <lb/>C-Disclosure and reporting <lb/>With an extensive list of additional required disclosures, the 2014 reform requires MMFs to <lb/>reflect in their disclosure the structural changes in the MMFs industry. The new disclosure <lb/>rules are designed to make MMFs&apos; levels of liquidity, redemption requests, potential <lb/>imposition of liquidity fees or redemption gates, and NAV more transparent in order to <lb/>enable investors to play an effective role in supervising and monitoring the fund activities. In <lb/>particular, MMFs are required to disclose a market-based NAV each business day. 94 As for <lb/>FNAV MMFs, the market-based NAV is the issue and redemption price; whereas in SNAV <lb/>MMFs, it is a shadow NAV. 95 <lb/>Further, in order to make FNAV MMFs investors aware of the consequences of the new <lb/>changes, MMFs must disclose that investors could lose money by investing in the fund due to <lb/>the market fluctuation and an MMF may impose redemption fees and/or temporary suspend <lb/>redemption. 96 <lb/>Under the 2010 amendments, the SEC imposed an obligation on MMFs to have websites. The <lb/>2014 amendments adopted further website disclosure requirements for MMFs. In order to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>93 Ibid, at 90. <lb/>94 Ibid, at 168. <lb/>95 Ibid, at 157 and 168. <lb/>96 Ibid, at 291. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>promote transparency and boost market discipline in the management of MMFs, funds are <lb/>required to show key information on their websites on each business day. MMFs, for <lb/>example, should show: (1) the MMF&apos;s current NAV; (2) the percentage of total assets <lb/>invested in daily and weekly liquid assets; and (3) daily net inflows or outflows. 97 <lb/>Another significant change to the disclosure requirements is the introduction of form N-CR. <lb/>MMFs must file a report with the SEC upon the occurrence of certain significant events. The <lb/>report must be sent to the SEC within one business day of the event&apos;s occurrence, and a <lb/>follow-up filing must be sent within four business days, including a clear description of the <lb/>event. 98 The SEC will make the information contained in Form N-CR publicly available upon <lb/>filing. <lb/>These disclosure amendments may provide valuable transparency to investors because they <lb/>will permit current and prospective shareholders to make informed decisions to purchase <lb/>shares of, or remain invested in, the fund. Nonetheless, extensive disclosure may overwhelm <lb/>investors by limiting their ability to determine useful information related to their investments. <lb/>Extensive disclosure may be useful for institutional investors that have competent staff who <lb/>are able to analyse the information and make informed decisions based on the disclosed <lb/>information. Nevertheless, information overload might be problematic to retail investors <lb/>because these investors do not usually have the ability to understand technical and <lb/>sophisticated information. Therefore, too much information might be confusing rather than <lb/>useful to these investors. Here, it is significant to emphasise that, as will be discussed later, <lb/>the SEC knows that the fundamental changes in the MMFs industry will make these vehicles <lb/>more attractive to institutional and sophisticated investors than retail investors. <lb/>D-Stress testing <lb/>One of the significant reforms addressed in the 2014 is the enhanced stress testing <lb/>requirement. In 2010, the SEC imposed an obligation on MMFs to periodically test their <lb/>ability to maintain a SNAV based on certain hypothetical events. 99 Nonetheless, the <lb/>disparities in the effectiveness and quality of stress testing practices among MMFs <lb/>demonstrated the need to enhance the 2010 rules. The 2014 reform requires MMF to apply <lb/>prescriptive stress testing system. Particularly, MMFs must test their ability to maintain <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>97 Ibid, at 335. <lb/>98 Ibid, at 374. <lb/>99 See, SEC, SEC Approves Money Market Fund Reforms to Better Protect Investors (2010) available at <lb/>https://www.sec.gov/news/press/2010/2010-14.htm accessed 29 March 2018. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>weekly liquid assets of at least 10% of total assets in response to several scenarios. 100 The <lb/>hypothetical stress events include: (1) increases in the level of short term interest rates; (2) a <lb/>downgrade or default of particular portfolio security positions; and (3) a widening of spreads <lb/>compared to the indexes to which portfolio securities are tied. 101 An MMF&apos;s adviser must <lb/>report the results of the stress testing to the board to evaluate the results of the stress testing. <lb/>Considering stress testing as a significant tool to achieve stability of the MMFs, the new rules <lb/>aim to minimize the possibility of a failure by requiring MMFs to test their liquidity position <lb/>in case of adverse economic developments or heavy redemption requests. It is significant to <lb/>mention that stress testing is a critical element of risk management for banks and a <lb/>fundamental tool for banking supervisors and macro-prudential authorities. Stress-testing <lb/>may be the most effective method to ensure the resilience of the financial system. Pillar 1, <lb/>minimum capital requirements, of the Basel II framework requires banks to have in place a <lb/>rigorous programme of stress testing because stress testing alerts bank management to a <lb/>variety of risks. 102 Therefore, the emphasis on this tool in the MMFs&apos; reforms can be <lb/>attributed to its effectiveness in the banking industry, and this is a clear proof of the influence <lb/>of the banking regulators on the MMFs&apos; reforms. <lb/>4.2 Reforms in the EU Regulatory Regime <lb/>The adverse impacts of the 2008 financial crisis on the European MMF industry underlined <lb/>the need to reform the MMF legal framework. Prior to the new reform, around 80% of MMF <lb/>assets were covered by the rules of Directive 2009/65/EC on Undertakings for Collective <lb/>Investment in Transferable Securities (UCITS). 103 The remaining MMFs operated under the <lb/>rules of Directive 2011/61/EU, covering &apos;Alternative Investment Fund Managers&apos; (AIFM). <lb/>The UCITS Directive regulates marketing collective investment schemes throughout <lb/>Europe. 104 This means that UCITS Directive does not target MMFS specifically. In 2010, the <lb/>Committee of European Securities Regulators (CESR), European Securities and Markets <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>100 See, SEC, &apos;Money Market Fund Reform; Amendments to Form PF&apos; (2014) at 556. <lb/>101 Ibid, at 568. <lb/>102 The Basel Committee on Banking Supervision, Principles for sound stress testing practices and supervision <lb/>(2009) available at https://www.bis.org/publ/bcbs155.pdf accessed 10 Jun 18. <lb/>103 M Szczepański, Money Market Funds: Measures to improve stability and liquidity (2017) European <lb/>Parliamentary Research Service, available at <lb/>http://www.europarl.europa.eu/RegData/etudes/BRIE/2017/608649/EPRS_BRI(2017)608649_EN.pdf accessed <lb/>3 January 2018. <lb/>104 For further information about UCITS Directive see, Mohammed Khair Alshaleel, Undertakings for the <lb/>Collective Investment in Transferable Securities Directive V: Increased Protection for Investors 13 ECL 14-22 <lb/>(2016). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Authority&apos;s predecessor, published guidelines on the common definition of European <lb/>MMFs. 105 The Guidelines codified particular management and operational rules deemed <lb/>suitable for European MMFs. <lb/>For the purpose of preserving the integrity and stability of the European financial markets, a <lb/>proposal for a regulation on MMFs was published by the European Commission in <lb/>September 2013. 106 After much delay and long debate and consultations, the new European <lb/>MMFs regulation was published in the EU Official Journal on 30 June 2017. The Regulation <lb/>came into force on 21 July 2017. Existing MMFs will have to comply with the new <lb/>regulation by 21 January 2019. <lb/>The length of time it took to reach the final agreement, around four years, suggests that the <lb/>new MMFs&apos; regulation is one of the most contentious and complex pieces of legislation that <lb/>the EU regulators have dealt with. The apparent consequences of the 2014 reform in the US <lb/>on the MMF industry, especially the shift in MMFs assets, might be a major reason for this <lb/>delay. To illustrate, the EU regulators aimed at achieving a balanced agreement between <lb/>addressing the vulnerabilities of money market funds and their potential systemic risk, and <lb/>maintaining the intrinsic value of these short-term financial instruments to businesses in the <lb/>European financial markets. <lb/>Generally, the new EU reform appears to follow the US reform in terms of the mechanisms <lb/>adopted to address MMFs&apos; vulnerability to run, namely liquidity fees and redemption gates, <lb/>transparency and stress testing. Nonetheless, the major difference between the two reforms is <lb/>the EU reform provides investors with a high degree of optionality for investing their short-<lb/>term cash. To maintain MMFs as a viable product, the new regulation offers two types of <lb/>MMF and three structural options. According to the new regulation, MMFs must be classified <lb/>as either a short-term MMF or a standard MMF. 107 On the one hand, short-term MMFs aim to <lb/>offer money market rate returns with a maximum weighted average maturity (WAM) of 60 <lb/>days and maximum weighted average life (WAL) of 120 days. With short WAM and WAL, <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>105 Available at: https://www.esma.europa.eu/sites/default/files/library/2015/11/10-<lb/>049_cesr_guidelines_mmfs_with_disclaimer.pdf accessed 30 March 2018. <lb/>106 The European Commission&apos;s proposal available at: <lb/>http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/investment/docs/money-market-funds/130904_mmfs-regulation_en.pdf <lb/>accessed 3 January 2018. <lb/>107 Regulation (EU) 2017/1131 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 14 June 2017 on money <lb/>market funds [2017] OJ L 169/8, Article 24. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>short-term MMFs seek to provide investors with the highest possible level of safety. 108 On <lb/>the other hand, standard MMFs are created with the objective of offering returns slightly <lb/>higher than short-term money market returns. 109 Therefore, standard MMFs are required to <lb/>have a maximum WAM of six months and maximum WAL of one year. <lb/>MMFs, under the new reform, may be structured as Public Debt CNAV MMFs, Low <lb/>Volatility NAV (LVNAV) MMFs or VNAV MMFs. 110 The reform has introduced LVNAV <lb/>MMF as an innovative product to attract more investors and avoid shifting MMFs assets. The <lb/>LVNAV MMF will effectively operate as a CNAV fund by applying amortized costs to <lb/>money market instruments with a remaining maturity below 75 days, as long as the difference <lb/>between such amortized cost and the market price of the instrument remain below 10 points <lb/>and as long as the market NAV of the fund does not deviate from the dealing NAV by more <lb/>than 20 basis points. 111 This means that money market instruments with a remaining maturity <lb/>of more than 75 days must be valued using mark-to-market (or mark-to-model) valuations. <lb/>To fulfil potential redemption requests, LVNAV MMFs must comply with strict daily and <lb/>weekly liquidity requirements. They must hold at least 10% in daily liquid assets and at least <lb/>30% in weekly liquid assets. 112 In contrast to LVNAV MMF, VNAV MMFs are required to <lb/>hold at least 7.5% of their assets in daily liquid assets and to hold at least 15% of their assets <lb/>in weekly liquid assets. <lb/>In addition, similar to the 2014 reform in the US, the EU reform has introduced a stringent <lb/>regime of fees and gates in the case of shortfalls in the MMF liquidity in order to diminish <lb/>MMFs investors&apos; incentive to runs. Nevertheless, the liquidity fee and redemption gate <lb/>structure under the EU regulation will not be the same as for the US reform. To illustrate, <lb/>under the EU regulation, liquidity gates and redemption fees apply to public debt CNAVs <lb/>MMFs and LVNAV MMFs only; they do not apply to VNAVs MMFs. 113 In contrast, in the <lb/>US, the redemption fees and liquidity gates apply only to institutional prime VNAV MMFs <lb/>and retail MMFs. The restrictions do not apply to government CNAV MMFs, but they may <lb/>opt into them if properly disclosed. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>108 While WAM is used to measure the sensitivity of an MMF to changing money market interest rates, WAL is <lb/>used to measure the credit risk of an MMF&apos;s portfolio. <lb/>109 Regulation (EU) 2017/1131 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 14 June 2017 on money <lb/>market funds [2017] OJ L 169/8, Article 25. <lb/>110 Ibid, Article 3. <lb/>111 Ibid, Article 29. <lb/>112 Ibid, Article 24. <lb/>113 Ibid, Article 34. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>The EU regulation distinguishes between mandatory and discretionary application of liquidity <lb/>fees and redemption gates. The discretionary application occurs when the level of weekly <lb/>liquid assets falls below 30% and net redemptions from the MMF exceed 10% in one day. In <lb/>this case, an MMF may apply a liquidity fee to redeeming investors, equal to the cost of <lb/>liquidity or impose redemptions gate up to 10% per day for up to 15 days. The MMF may <lb/>also suspend shares redemptions for up to 15 days. If the level of weekly liquid assets falls <lb/>below 10%, an MMF has two options: either apply a liquidity fee to redeeming investors, <lb/>equal to the cost of liquidity, or suspend redemptions for up to 15 days. <lb/>As explained above, in the US, the board of directors could avoid applying the mandatory <lb/>liquidity fee (1%) in case of determining that imposing such a fee will not be in the best <lb/>interests of the fund. Unlike the US, the EU regulation does not grant MMFs this power. The <lb/>strictness of the EU regime clearly appears in the consequences of applying the suspension of <lb/>redemption tool. When the total duration of the suspensions exceeds 15 days within a period <lb/>of 90 days, public debt CNAV MMF or a LVNAV MMF shall automatically cease to be a <lb/>public debt CNAV MMF or a LVNAV MMF. This implies that MMFs may prefer to apply <lb/>the liquidity fee to avoid the rigid consequences of the suspension of redemption. By <lb/>imposing strict rules, the EU regulators attempted to avoid the criticisms of the US reform <lb/>regarding the discretionary power of the board of directors to impose liquidity fees and <lb/>redemption gates. However, the mandatory application of the fees and gate could affect the <lb/>attractiveness of MMFs as bank equivalents, where shareholders can access their funds <lb/>anytime. <lb/>Similar to the US 2014 reform, the EU regulation requires MMFs to have in place sound <lb/>stress testing processes based on hypothetical scenarios. Under the new rules, stress tests <lb/>should be conducted regularly, at least bi-annually, and include factors such as credit risk, <lb/>movements in the interest rate, hypothetical redemption requests and changes in liquidity. 114 <lb/>The purpose of the stress test is to detect any potential vulnerability. In case any vulnerability <lb/>is revealed, the manager of an MMF should submit an extensive report with the results of the <lb/>stress testing and a proposed action plan to the board of directors. 115 The board of directors <lb/>has the authority to amend the proposed plan. The board of directors shall send the extensive <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>114 Ibid, Article 28. <lb/>115 Ibid, Article 28 (4). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>report to the national competent authority which in turn shall send it to the European <lb/>Securities and Markets Authority (ESMA). 116 <lb/>Prohibition of External support <lb/>A significant component that distinguishes the EU reform from the US 2014 reform is the <lb/>prohibition of the external (sponsor) support. Article 35 of the MMF regulation prohibits all <lb/>forms of external support to MMFs. 117 The debate over the external support has been pivotal <lb/>in the MMF industry whether in the EU or the US. 118 Sponsor support refers to the financial <lb/>support provided by an affiliated or parent company of the MMF&apos;s manager. The debate is <lb/>based on the significant role played by sponsors for MMFs that faced substantial redemptions <lb/>requests, especially during the financial crisis. According to Moody&apos;s, at least 146 MMFs <lb/>received sponsor support prior to 2007. 119 Further, between 2007 and 2009, 62 MMFs, <lb/>including at least 36 funds in the US and an estimated 26 funds in Europe, received financial <lb/>from their sponsors. 120 These figures demonstrate the vital role historically played by MMFs&apos; <lb/>sponsors. <lb/>The figures raise an important question about the motivations of the MMFs&apos; sponsors to <lb/>provide financial support to MMFs. It is significant to know that sponsor support is <lb/>completely discretionary. To illustrate, a sponsor is not legally or contractually under an <lb/>obligation to support its MMF in times of financial stress. As noted above, a sponsor is <lb/>usually an affiliated or parent company of the MMF&apos;s manager. This implies that sponsors <lb/>have an interest in providing support to MMFs such as an economic interest in the MMF&apos;s <lb/>management company. Sponsors could also provide support to MMFs to avoid any <lb/>reputational damage to the management company that could be caused by the failure of an <lb/>MMF. The support provided to MMFs could take various forms such as cash injections, fee <lb/>waivers, purchase of MMF&apos;s assets at an inflated price, purchase of MMF&apos;s shares to provide <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>116 Ibid, Article 28 (6). <lb/>117 Ibid, Article 35. <lb/>118 See, for example, Investment Company Institute, Is SEC Data Misleading the Public on Sponsor Support of <lb/>Money Market Funds? (2012) available at https://www.ici.org/viewpoints/view_12_mmfs_fund_support <lb/>accessed 10 Jun 18, and Moody&apos;s, Sponsor Support Key to Money Market Funds (August 2009) <lb/>https://files.alston.com/files/docs/Moody&apos;s_Report.pdf, accessed 10 June 2018, and Parlatore, (n 122). <lb/>119 Moody&apos;s, Sponsor Support Key to Money Market Funds (August 2009) <lb/>https://files.alston.com/files/docs/Moody&apos;s_Report.pdf, accessed 30 March 2018. <lb/>120 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>liquidity and the issuance of any kind of explicit or implicit guarantee for the benefit of the <lb/>MMF. 121 <lb/>Despite the importance of the sponsor support, the EU financial regulators have decided to <lb/>prohibit it completely. This prohibition could mainly be attributed to the discretionary nature <lb/>of sponsor support. Discretionary sponsor support is often described as a weakness of MMFs <lb/>because the failure of the sponsor to provide support in time of crisis to its MMF would result <lb/>in the failure of the fund itself. 122 That uncertainty associated with sponsor support is likely to <lb/>make MMFs more vulnerable to runs during periods of financial instability. <lb/>In the US, the 2014 reform has not modified the ability of an MMF sponsor to support the <lb/>MMF&apos;s operations. Nonetheless, it requires additional disclosure with respect to such support. <lb/>An MMF must provide disclosure in its statement of additional information (SAI) regarding <lb/>any occasion during the last 10 years on which the MMF received financial support from a <lb/>sponsor. 123 Further, an MMF must report instances of financial support by sponsors on Part C <lb/>of Form N-CR, including amount, nature, terms of the support, and the relationship between <lb/>the person providing the support and the MMF. 124 The SEC also requires an MMF to disclose <lb/>on its website any support received by its sponsor. Clearly, the US financial regulators took a <lb/>different approach from the EU regulators. Considering the significant role of sponsor <lb/>support in the history of MMF industry especially during the financial crisis, the SEC <lb/>preserved the sponsor support as a potential instrument that MMFs might use, but with <lb/>extensive disclosure requirements to ensure transparency to shareholders. By imposing these <lb/>disclosure requirements, the SEC attempts to achieve two objectives; (1) to make investors <lb/>aware that sponsor support is entirely discretionary; and (2) to keep the SEC informed of all <lb/>instances of sponsor support, and that will help the SEC to analyse the economic effects of <lb/>such sponsor financial support. <lb/>The disparity in the EU and the US approaches to sponsor support accentuates the necessity <lb/>of harmonization of the international legal framework of the MMF industry because this <lb/>disparity carries a threat to the stability of the global financial system, and the 2008 financial <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>121 See, Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas, Understanding the Risks Inherent in Shadow Banking: A Primer and <lb/>Practical Lessons Learned (November 2012) <lb/>https://www.dallasfed.org/~/media/documents/research/staff/staff1203.pdf accessed 30 March 2018. <lb/>122 See, Cecilia Parlatore, Fragility in Money Market Funds: Sponsor Support and Regulation 121 JEF 596 <lb/>(2016). <lb/>123 See, SEC, &apos;Money Market Fund Reform; Amendments to Form PF&apos; (2014) at 317. <lb/>124 Ibid, at 358. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>crisis is a clear proof of the impact of instability of a financial market on other financial <lb/>markets. <lb/>5. Analysing MMF&apos;s Reforms from financial stability perspective <lb/>In order to understand the rationale for the major changes to MMF regulations in the EU and <lb/>the US and their implications, it is necessary to understand the changes to the financial <lb/>regulations objectives and structure post the 2008 financial crisis. The main failures in the <lb/>financial regulation and supervision were intrinsic causes of the crisis. 125 In particular, the <lb/>financial crisis of 2008 showed many deficiencies in the pre-crisis approach to financial <lb/>stability regulation. The social and economic costs of the crisis demonstrated that the theory <lb/>of the self-correcting nature of the capital markets is not anymore adequate. 126 To illustrate, <lb/>in the self-correction process, the market price either increases or decreases in response to a <lb/>deficiency or an excess to restore the balance between quantity demanded and quantity <lb/>supplied. 127 This process works automatically to adjust from disequilibrium to equilibrium <lb/>without the need for government intervention to regulate the market. However, the collapse <lb/>of the financial system in 2008 proved that this assumption is false. As a result, the <lb/>enhancement of financial regulation was placed as a core position to strengthen financial <lb/>markets and regulatory regimes and to avoid future crises. Considerably, since the financial <lb/>crisis, the goal of financial stability has become the dominant idea of any financial reform <lb/>nationally or internationally. In the US, as discussed above, the Dodd-Frank Wall Street <lb/>Reform and Consumer Protection Act (&quot;Dodd-Frank&quot;) was passed in 2010 as a response to <lb/>the 2008 financial crisis. The preamble to Dodd-Frank defines it as an Act designed &quot;to <lb/>promote the financial stability of the United States&quot;. 128 <lb/>Prior to the 2008 financial crisis, the assumption that the resilience of individual financial <lb/>institutions is both an essential and sufficient condition to secure the resilience of the whole <lb/>financial system was erroneous because events during the crisis have demonstrated that the <lb/>resilience of individual institutions is an inadequate way of avoiding instability in the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>125 Mohamed Ariff, John Farrar and Ahmed Khalid, Regulatory Failure and the Global Financial Crisis: An <lb/>Australian Perspective 127 (Edward Elgar Publishing, Cheltenham 2012). <lb/>126 Jeffrey Friedman and Wladimir Kraus, Engineering the Financial Crisis: Systemic Risk and the Failure of <lb/>Regulation 119 (University of Pennsylvania Press, Pennsylvania 2011). <lb/>127 Ismael zadeh, Beyond Mainstream Explanations of the Financial Crisis: Parasitic Finance Capital 12 <lb/>(Routledge, New York 2014). <lb/>128 Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act 2010. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>financial system. 129 Micro-prudential rules failed to consider the impacts of individual <lb/>financial institutions&apos; risk-taking on the broader financial system and economy, 130 and how <lb/>the interconnectedness of financial institutions could increase systemic risks across the <lb/>financial system. 131 Therefore, to achieve the financial stability objective, it was necessary to <lb/>focus on the resilience and robustness of the financial system as a whole. To illustrate, due to <lb/>complexity of the financial system, actions that might be suitable for individual financial <lb/>institutions can cause destabilization to the financial system as a whole. Consequently, any <lb/>reform to individual institutions needs to be complemented by a system-wide perspective. <lb/>This holistic approach adopted by many financial regulators is called macro-prudential <lb/>policy. While the most important objective of macro-prudential and micro-prudential is to <lb/>mitigate risk, macro-prudential policies aim at identifying and mitigating potential risks to <lb/>systemic stability. 132 Early and efficient diagnosis of wide systemic risks is vital for macro-<lb/>prudential policymaking because early identification of potential risks could help rapid use of <lb/>policy tools to address these risks. 133 <lb/>In addition, macro-prudential policy uses a range of tools to achieve its objectives because <lb/>applying a single tool is unlikely to be sufficient to address the various sources of systemic <lb/>risk. This can include mandatory capital buffers, stress tests, liquidity fees and suspension of <lb/>redemption. Stress tests play a significant role in assessing the vulnerability of the financial <lb/>system to adverse shocks. 134 Mandatory capital buffers are another important tool that macro-<lb/>prudential authorities can use to address specific vulnerabilities. 135 These require financial <lb/>institutions, in addition to minimum capital requirements, to maintain higher capital to asset <lb/>ratios to ensure that they continue to operate in the event of adverse shocks in the financial <lb/>markets without the need to shrink assets. 136 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>129 R Buckley, E Avgouleas and D Arner, The Financial Stability Board and the Future of International Financial <lb/>Regulation, in Reconceptualising Global Finance and its Regulation 53 (Cambridge University Press, New York <lb/>2016). <lb/>130 See, Rainer Masera, CRR/CRD IV: The Trees and the Forest 67 PSL Quarterly Review 387 (2014). <lb/>131 See, Andreas Krause, Systemic Risk, in Investment Risk Management 189 (Oxford University Press, New York <lb/>2015). <lb/>132 See, Xavier Freixas, Luc Laeven and José Peydró, Systemic Risk, Crises, and Macroprudential Regulation 251 <lb/>(MIT Press, Massachusetts 2015). <lb/>133 Damodaran Krishnamurti and Yejin Lee, Macroprudential Policy Framework: A Practice Guide 28 (World <lb/>Bank Publications, Washington 2014). <lb/>134 Ibid, 50. <lb/>135 See, Matthias Haentjens and Pierre Gioia-Carabellese, European Banking and Financial Law 102 (Routledge, <lb/>New York 2015). <lb/>136 In Europe, the European Systemic Risk Board (ESRB) was established in 2010 as a response to the global <lb/>financial crisis. The ESRB is principally responsible for the macro-prudential oversight of the EU financial <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>The process of rebuilding stability of the financial system, therefore, should be <lb/>comprehensive and attempt to improve the resilience of each individual institution to adverse <lb/>shocks. Since the risks to financial stability can originate in the banking sector and in other <lb/>parts of the financial system, the international regulatory reform agenda has focused on <lb/>making banks safer by boosting their capital and introducing specific regulatory liquidity <lb/>ratios. The regulatory reform has also concentrated on some non-bank institutions and <lb/>shadow banking activities. In the banking sector, the Basel Committee issued in December <lb/>2010 the Basel III rules text, which provides the details of global regulatory standards on <lb/>bank capital adequacy and liquidity. The new rules set out higher quality capital, the <lb/>introduction of a leverage ratio as a backstop to the risk-based requirement better risk <lb/>coverage, and measures to foster the build-up of capital that can be drawn down in times of <lb/>stress. 137 <lb/>As discussed earlier, while MMFs did not cause the financial crisis, any shocks impacting the <lb/>MMF industry can quickly have broader, systemic consequences due to their pivotal role in <lb/>short-term funding markets and their interconnectedness with banks. Hence, imposing strict <lb/>standards in terms of maturity of underlying securities and the credit quality, and higher <lb/>disclosure requirements was inevitable to avoid leaving any gap in the financial stability <lb/>policy. The major impediment that hampered the progress of MMF reforms, whether in the <lb/>US or the EU, was the careful balance that needs to be struck between preserving the viability <lb/>of MMF as a significant tool of finance in the financial market and addressing MMFs <lb/>vulnerabilities to run, which could be a main source of instability of the financial system <lb/>during the times of market stress. For this reason, the debate about the final form of the <lb/>reform in the EU and the US was intense. Nonetheless, since the stability of the financial <lb/>system is a pre-condition to any reform after the global financial crisis, the financial <lb/>regulators have chosen to impose strict rules on MMF despite the fact that they are likely to <lb/>jeopardize the viability of some types of MMFs in the long run. This raises a significant <lb/>question about the impacts of the reforms on the MMF industry. In the US, statistics revealed <lb/>by the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) show a noticeable decline in the number <lb/>of MMFs from 2014 to 2017. In July 2014 the number of MMFs was 553 and this number <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>system in order to prevent and mitigate systemic risks to financial stability in the EU. See, Miriam Goldby and <lb/>Anat Keller, The Commission&apos;s proposal for a new European Systemic Risk Board: an evaluation 4 Law &amp; Fin. <lb/>Mkt. Rev 48 (2010). <lb/>137 Basel III started in 2013 and with full implementation by 1 January 2019. See, Narissa Lyngen, Basel III: <lb/>Dynamics of State Implementation 53 Harv. Int&apos;l L.J. 527 (2012). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>decreased to 382 in November 2017. 138 The statistics also show a massive shift in prime <lb/>MMFs&apos; assets. The assets under management in prime funds dropped sharply from <lb/>$1,710,127 million in July 2014 to $679,795 million in November 2017. 139 These statistics <lb/>demonstrate the decrease in the attractiveness of MMFs. Because the drop in the MMFs&apos; <lb/>assets is an inevitable consequence of the substantial changes to this industry, the SEC has <lb/>not made any intervention to stop it. <lb/>In fact, one of the main reasons that attracts investors to invest in MMFs is the analogous <lb/>features that make MMFs equivalents to bank deposits: instantaneous access to the liquidity <lb/>and stability of the value of the capital invested. Even if the possibility of imposing <lb/>redemption gate or liquidity fees appears unlikely to occur in normal circumstances, it could <lb/>influence the investors&apos; decision to invest in MMFs or force the existing investors to exit <lb/>from MMFs because some investors will not be willing to undertake this risk no matter how <lb/>remote it may seem. These outflows could be disruptive to financial markets. It is important <lb/>to emphasise that the investors&apos; ability to access their funds on any regular business day <lb/>without disruptions is fundamental to some investors in choosing the appropriate investment. <lb/>Another important point is that investors who invest in institutional prime MMF, which are <lb/>required to float their NAV under the new reforms, may also need to re-consider their <lb/>investment decisions because -in specific circumstances-MMFs might not be classified as <lb/>cash equivalents. To illustrate, when there is a significant change in the fund NAV or the <lb/>fund imposes a liquidity fee or a redemption gate, the investment in that fund may not be cash <lb/>equivalents because the shares are not convertible to known amounts of cash. That will only <lb/>be problematic in exceptional circumstances and in normal circumstances, MMFs are still <lb/>classified as cash equivalent because the fluctuations in the NAV will be insignificant. <lb/>Further, the complexity of the new regulation, in the EU and the US, has made MMFs more <lb/>appropriate investments for institutional investors than retail investors. Understanding the <lb/>circumstances under which MMFs are able to impose liquidity fees or redemption gates <lb/>might be difficult to retail investors because they do not have financial or legal knowledge <lb/>that enables them to make informed decisions. Although the EU reform attempts to attract <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>138 See, U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission, Money Market Fund Statistics (July 2016) available at: <lb/>https://www.sec.gov/divisions/investment/mmf-statistics/mmf-statistics-2016-7.pdf accessed 14 March 2018, <lb/>and, U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission, Money Market Fund Statistics (November 2017) available at: <lb/>https://www.sec.gov/divisions/investment/mmf-statistics/mmf-statistics-2017-11.pdf accessed 14 March <lb/>2018. <lb/>139 Ibid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>more investors, retail and institutional, by introducing LVNAV MMF, the requirements under <lb/>which they can operate as CNAV MMF are complicated for retail investors to understand and <lb/>the possibility that LVNAV MMF could operate as FNAV MMF, in case of noncompliance <lb/>with strict rules, might discourage them to invest in this new type. In fact, retail investors rely <lb/>on their own analysis to make investment decisions and they usually fail to undertake proper <lb/>research before making their investment decisions. In other words, in most of the situations <lb/>their decisions are based on information received from others. On the other hand, institutional <lb/>investors rely heavily on research backed data to make their investments. 140 They usually <lb/>have investment research teams, who have extensive access to research data and they are able <lb/>to predict potential changes in the market or the fund circumstances. As a result, institutional <lb/>investors are sophisticated enough to understand the complexity of the new reforms and <lb/>choose appropriate MMFs that conform with their investment policies. Their sophistication <lb/>allows them to respond promptly to any changes in the fund circumstances, which could <lb/>result in applying liquidity fee or redemption gate. <lb/>Based on the above analysis, it is clear that the US and EU MMF regulatory reforms are <lb/>indispensable and fall within a wider financial regulatory plan that prioritise the stability of <lb/>the financial system. Although financial regulators, in both jurisdictions, realize that the <lb/>reforms would have some serious consequences on the MMFs industry, they are assured that <lb/>the reforms will substantially strengthen financial stability. <lb/>6. Conclusion <lb/>This article has examined the MMF reforms in the EU and the US and their implication on <lb/>the MMF industry and investors from the perspective of financial stability. Addressing <lb/>MMFs&apos; systemic risk and vulnerability to run is a fundamental step in achieving financial <lb/>stability, which is the dominant objective of all financial reforms after the 2008 financial <lb/>crisis. Although the new strict rules represent a major change to the MMF industry in terms <lb/>of their operation and structure, they diminish the systemic risks associated with runs on <lb/>MMFs. Nonetheless, the article has clearly demonstrated that the new rules have drastic <lb/>consequences for some types of MMFs, especially in terms of the huge shift of assets from <lb/>some types to others or to other industries. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>140 For further information about institutional investors see, K.A.D Camara, Classifying Institutional Investors 30 <lb/>J. Corp. L 219 (2005). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the US, the requirement for institutional prime and municipal money market funds to float <lb/>their NAV, along with the introduction of fees and gates, aimed at alleviating the investors&apos; <lb/>incentive to redeem their shares ahead of others. However, the article has raised two issues <lb/>regarding the US reform. The first issue is the concepts of &quot;best interests&quot; and &quot;discretion&quot; in <lb/>decision-making given to the board of directors in determining of imposition of fees and <lb/>gates. The 2014 reform or the SEC did not provide any guidance on the concept &quot;best <lb/>interests&quot; and how MMFs&apos; boards would exercise this discretion to protect investors. <lb/>Therefore, to ensure the effectiveness of these tools and provide investors with high level of <lb/>protection, the SEC should provide clear guidance on the concept of &quot;best interests&quot;. The <lb/>second issue is related to the sponsor support. The 2014 reform emphasised the importance of <lb/>sponsor support by allowing third party sponsors to financially support MMFs. However, the <lb/>discretionary nature of sponsor support represents a fragility in the new reform and makes <lb/>MMFs vulnerable to runs during periods of financial instability. Thus, it is desirable to make <lb/>the sponsor support explicit by making sponsors committed to maintain $1 or to any form of <lb/>financial support. It is also desirable to clearly specify support mechanisms, so investors can <lb/>be aware of them. <lb/>In the EU, the new reform appears to follow the US reform in applying similar mechanisms <lb/>to address MMFs vulnerabilities to run, but with variation in their application. The article <lb/>emphasised that the introduction of LVNAV MMFs aims at avoiding the consequences of the <lb/>US reforms, especially assets shifts. However, the optionality introduced by the reform has <lb/>made MMF regulation so complex not only to the investors, but also to the funds&apos; managers. <lb/>Unlike the US reform, the EU new regulation prohibits all forms of sponsor support due to its <lb/>uncertainty. This raises a significant issue about the importance of harmonization of MMFs <lb/>regulations due to interconnection of the US and EU financial markets. In fact, any gap in the <lb/>regulations will inevitably threaten the stability of the global financial system. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>The author is grateful to Onyeka Osuji, Darren Calley and Johanna Hoekstra for comments <lb/>on earlier drafts. <lb/></div>

			<page>40 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>