<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Achieving the EU Air Policy Objectives in Due Time: A Reality or a Hoax?</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Samvel</forename>
          <surname>Varvaštian</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T07:32:08.509Z">30/01/2026 08:32:08</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.54648__eelr2015001</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Kluwer Law International BV</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2015</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.54648/eelr2015001</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Samvel Varvaštian. (2015). Achieving the EU Air Policy Objectives in Due Time: A Reality or a Hoax?. European Energy and Environmental Law Review, 24(Issue 1), 2-11. DOI: 10.54648/eelr2015001</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-01-02T12:30:46.310592Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2026-01-02T12:30:46.310592Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T13:03:11.836Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Annotation completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T21:33:44.899Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith second pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T09:04:43.903Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-28T09:44:43.300Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T07:38:40.340Z" status="candidate" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>ORCA -Online Research @ <lb/>Cardiff <lb/>This is an Open Access document downloaded from ORCA, Cardiff University&apos;s institutional <lb/>repository:https://orca.cardiff.ac.uk/id/eprint/159621/ <lb/>This is the author&apos;s version of a work that was submitted to / accepted for publication. <lb/>Citation for final published version: <lb/>Varvastian, Samvel 2015. Achieving the EU air policy objectives in due time: a reality or a hoax? European <lb/>Energy and Environmental Law Review 24 (1) , pp. 2-11. 10.54648/eelr2015001 <lb/>Publishers page: https://doi.org/10.54648/eelr2015001 <lb/>Please note: <lb/>Changes made as a result of publishing processes such as copy-editing, formatting and page numbers may <lb/>not be reflected in this version. For the definitive version of this publication, please refer to the published <lb/>source. You are advised to consult the publisher&apos;s version if you wish to cite this paper. <lb/>This version is being made available in accordance with publisher policies. See <lb/>http://orca.cf.ac.uk/policies.html for usage policies. Copyright and moral rights for publications made <lb/>available in ORCA are retained by the copyright holders. <lb/></titlePage>
    
    <front>1 <lb/>S Varvastian, &apos;Achieving the EU Air Policy Objectives in Due Time: A Reality or a Hoax?&apos; (2015) 24(1) European <lb/>Energy and Environmental Law Review 2-11 <lb/>ACHIEVING THE EU AIR POLICY OBJECTIVES IN DUE TIME: A REALITY OR A <lb/>HOAX? <lb/>Samvel Varvastian <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The identification of air pollution as a global problem contributing to health disorders and <lb/>damage to the environment sparked the development of national legislation as well as international <lb/>cooperation initiatives to improve air quality. As a result, the introduction of new and tighter air <lb/>quality standards, national emission ceilings and more environmentally-friendly technologies led to <lb/>significant progress in reducing the levels of different pollutants in the ambient air. However, <lb/>notwithstanding the achieved success, the overall damage dealt by air pollution remains high, while <lb/>further attempts to tackle it are losing their momentum. With no perceptible finish line, the situation <lb/>could last for decades, claiming hundreds of thousands of lives and billions of Euros outlays <lb/>annually, thus compromising the very foundation of air policy. The article addresses this problem <lb/>from the EU perspective. <lb/>Keywords: EU air policy, air pollution, ambient air quality, emission ceilings, Clean Air <lb/>Policy Package, Gothenburg Protocol <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The last few decades marked an increase in public and governmental awareness of the air <lb/>pollution and the problems it causes, which resulted in the intensive emergence of legislation on <lb/>clean air and reduction of air pollution adopted at national, European Union (EU) and international <lb/>level 1 . Generally speaking, air pollution means the introduction of certain substances or energy into <lb/>the air deteriorating its quality, which results in harmful effect on human, animal and plant health, <lb/>ecosystems as well as material property 2 . This process is constant and it is caused both by natural <lb/>sources, such as volcanic activity or dust and by anthropogenic activities, mainly by power <lb/>generation, road and other transport, industrial processes and waste, agriculture and some domestic <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 Communication from the Commission to the Council and the European Parliament. Thematic Strategy on air pollution. <lb/>COM(2005) 446 final (TSAP), 2. <lb/>2 See: the definition of air pollution in ECE Convention on Long-Range Transboundary Air Pollution (adopted 13 <lb/>November 1979, entered into force 16 March 1983) 1302 UNTS 217 (CLRTAP) art 1(a). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>activities, for example heating, etc 3 . Particular concern is expressed on the man-made pollution, <lb/>since the majority of air pollutants originate from it 4 . Among the most notorious air pollutants are <lb/>particulate matter (PM2.5 and/or PM10), ground-level ozone (O3), sulphur dioxide (SO2), nitrogen <lb/>oxides (NOx), ammonia (NH3), volatile organic compounds (VOC), methane (CH4), carbon <lb/>monoxide (CO), arsenic (As), cadmium (Cd), lead (Pb), mercury (Hg), nickel (Ni), etc 5 . <lb/>These as well as other pollutants contribute to a range of serious health disorders in humans, <lb/>including cardiovascular diseases, lung diseases and different forms of cancer 6 . Even more, air <lb/>pollution is a factor that often leads to premature deaths 7 . Thus, according to the estimates of the <lb/>World Health Organization (WHO) the total number of premature deaths caused by air pollution <lb/>globally in 2012 was about 7 million 8 . Meanwhile, in the EU premature deaths caused by air <lb/>pollution in 2010 were estimated at more than 400,000, making air pollution the number one <lb/>environmental cause of death, far exceeding the number of deaths in road traffic accidents 9 . <lb/>Apart from its crippling effect on human health, air pollution deals significant damage to the <lb/>environment and ecosystems. For example, sulphur and nitrogen compounds cause acidification of <lb/>soils and inland water 10 and eutrophication 11 . Moreover, many primary pollutants, such as NOx, <lb/>VOC and CH4 lead to the formation of the secondary pollutant, O3, which harmfully affects the <lb/>respiratory systems of humans and animals, damages agricultural crops, forests and other vegetation 12 . <lb/>Some pollutants, including the above-mentioned O3 and CH4 produce the greenhouse effect thus <lb/>contributing to the global warming and climate change 13 . <lb/>Due to the above-mentioned reasons, air pollution has a negative impact on the economy as <lb/>well. Thus, direct economic damage from air pollution in EU in 2010 was estimated at €23 billion, <lb/>including €15 billion from lost workdays, €4 billion from healthcare costs, €3 billion from crop <lb/>yield loss and €1 billion from damage to buildings, while total external costs of the health impacts <lb/>ranged from €330 billion to €940 billion 14 , i.e. amounting for 3-9% of EU GDP 15 . <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>3 European Environment Agency, &lt;http://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/2599XXX/page010.html&gt; accessed 17 <lb/>August 2014. <lb/>4 United States (US) Environmental Protection Agency, &lt;http://www.epa.gov/air/toxicair/newtoxics.html&gt; accessed 17 <lb/>August 2014. <lb/>5 Impact Assessment, SWD(2013)531, (Impact Assessment) 90-91. <lb/>6 ibid. <lb/>7 ibid, 90. <lb/>8 &lt;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/releases/2014/air-pollution/en/&gt; accessed 17 August 2014. <lb/>9 Impact Assessment, 18. <lb/>10 ibid, 91. Acidification is a process related to the build-up of acid in soils and water, thereby causing a reduction of the <lb/>pH value. It is caused primarily through acid rain and damages plant and animal life in forests, lakes and rivers, as well <lb/>as buildings and historical sites by corrosion. <lb/>11 ibid, 92 and 14. Eutrophication is a process of pollution in rivers and lakes resulting from an excess of plant nutrients, <lb/>which leads to the overabundance of aquatic plants. The decomposition of overabundant plant life requires significant <lb/>amounts of oxygen, leaving the water lifeless. Therefore, eutrophication poses a serious threat to biodiversity. About <lb/>62% of the EU area, including 71% of Natura 2000 ecosystems, was exposed to this process in 2010. <lb/>12 ibid, 92. <lb/>13 PCC, 2013: Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth <lb/>Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [Stocker, T.F., D. Qin, G.-K. Plattner, M. Tignor, <lb/>S.K. Allen, J. Boschung, A. Nauels, Y. Xia, V. Bex and P.M. Midgley (eds.)]. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, <lb/>United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA, 1535 pp, at 127. <lb/>14 Impact Assessment, 14. <lb/>15 &lt;http://ec.europa.eu/environment/air/index_en.htm&gt; accessed 17 August 2014. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>No wonder that the reduction of ambient air pollution and the improvement of air quality <lb/>have been on the agenda of national governments for some time, including not only advanced <lb/>economies, but the emerging economies as well 16 . However, notwithstanding the growing universal <lb/>concern over this problem and the initiatives to resolve it achieved or underway, the levels of <lb/>concentration of different pollutants in the air remain high and in some cases even rising 17 . Hence, <lb/>in EU, where significant emission reductions in all major pollutants were achieved throughout the <lb/>period 1990-2009, an increase in PM, VOC, CO and some other pollutants&apos; levels was observed in <lb/>2009-10, following from the economic recovery of EU largest economies 18 . And although these <lb/>countries succeeded in stabilizing and even improving the situation in 2010-11, which led to an <lb/>overall decrease in air pollution level across EU 19 , both health and environmental impacts of air <lb/>pollution in the whole region remain dissatisfying 20 , while the EU standards are actually trailing <lb/>behind those of the world&apos;s advanced economies 21 . The next section summarises the key elements of <lb/>the EU air policy. <lb/>1. Current EU Air Policy <lb/>The main objectives of air protection in EU, as part of EU general environmental protection <lb/>policy, which developed from the early 1970s onwards 22 , are envisaged in the primary legislation 23 . <lb/>In terms of air policy itself, regardless of the early attempts to reduce atmospheric emissions in the <lb/>1970s, which on some occasions targeted the harmonization of technical standards to conform with <lb/>the common market requirements and on other were limited to exhaust emissions from certain <lb/>industrial sectors 24 , the appearance of EU air quality legislation dates back to Directive 80/779/EC, <lb/>establishing controls for SO2 and suspended particles&apos; emission 25 . <lb/>The 1970-2000 period gave rise to a number of legal and political instruments, including <lb/>five environmental action programmes, defining the overall EU environmental policy 26 . In 2002 the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>16 Communication from the Commission to the European Parliament, the Council, the European Economic and Social <lb/>Committee and the Committee of the Regions. A Clean Air Programme for Europe. COM(2013) 918 final (Clean Air <lb/>Programme), at 10. China, for example, has recently announced additional investments on air pollution control and, <lb/>being the &apos;world&apos;s biggest carbon emitter&apos;, initiated major changes in national environmental protection laws, tightening <lb/>policy with regard to polluters. See: &lt;http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-04-24/china-enacts-biggest-pollution-<lb/>curbs-in-25-years.html&gt; accessed 17 August 2014. <lb/>17 Decision No 1386/2013/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 November 2013 on a General Union <lb/>Environment Action Programme to 2020 &apos;Living well, within the limits of our planet&apos; [2013] OJ L354/171 (7 th EAP), <lb/>paras 6, 7, 19 and 26 of the Annex. <lb/>18 European Union emission inventory report 1990-2010 under the CLRTAP, at 11-13. See: <lb/>&lt;http://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/eu-emission-inventory-report-1990-2010/at_download/file&gt; <lb/>accessed <lb/>17 <lb/>August 2014. <lb/>19 <lb/>European Union emission inventory report 1990-2011 under the CLRTAP, 13-15. See: <lb/>&lt;http://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/eu-emission-inventory-report-lrtap/at_download/file&gt; accessed 17 August <lb/>2014. <lb/>20 7 th EAP, par. 44 and 45 of the Annex. See also Impact Assessment, 17-18. <lb/>21 Clean Air Programme, 10. <lb/>22 Katharina Holzinger, Christoph Knill and Ansgar Schäfer, &apos;Rhetoric or Reality? &apos;New Governance&apos; in EU <lb/>Environmental Policy&apos; (2006) 12 European Law Journal 403, 404. <lb/>23 See: Consolidated Version of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union [2012] OJ C326/47, art 191(1). <lb/>24 Mark Wilde, &apos;The new directive on ambient air quality and cleaner air for Europe&apos; (2010) 12 Environmental Law <lb/>Review 282, 283. <lb/>25 Impact Assessment, 14. <lb/>26 Katharina Holzinger, Christoph Knill and Ansgar Schäfer, 410-413. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Council and the European Parliament adopted the 6 th Environment Action Programme (6 th EAP), <lb/>which established a common EU long-term objective for air quality: to achieve, inter alia, &apos;levels of <lb/>air quality that do not give rise to significant negative impacts on and risks to human health and the <lb/>environment&apos; 27 . And although the 6 th EAP ended in July 2012, this key objective was later reiterated <lb/>in the new General Union Environment Action Programme to 2020 (7 th EAP) 28 . <lb/>Currently, the EU air policy framework comprises the following five main elements 29 : <lb/>The first is the Thematic Strategy on Air Pollution (TSAP) adopted in 2005, which sets out <lb/>the overall policy direction that emerged from the 2000-04 review of air policy, including interim <lb/>objectives for 2020 towards the EU long-term objective and cost-effective actions to achieve those <lb/>objectives while promoting overall policy coherence 30 . TSAP implies a range of mechanisms, such <lb/>as, for example, the improvement of the ambient air quality legislation by merging legal instruments <lb/>into single legislation and further cutting of certain hazardous emissions into the air 31 . <lb/>The merging of legal instruments resulted in the second element of the air policy framework <lb/>-the Ambient Air Quality Directive (AAQD) 32 which covers major primary pollutants, such as SO2, <lb/>NO2, NOx, CO and PM and secondary pollutant, O3. The scope of the AAQD is quite broad 33 , <lb/>though its primary target is to set ambient concentrations for a range of parameters to be achieved <lb/>everywhere in the EU and define the minimum standards for assessing and managing air quality in <lb/>the Member States 34 . This is achieved through the introduction of certain requirements for zones and <lb/>agglomerations 35 , expressed in a range of different values, such as limit value 36 , target value 37 , etc. <lb/>If these values are exceeded, the persons in concern have a right to require the authorities to draw up <lb/>an action plan in order to reduce the risk and to limit its duration 38 . <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>27 Decision No 1600/2002/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 July 2002 laying down the Sixth <lb/>Community Environment Action Programme [2002] OJ L242/1, art 7(1). <lb/>28 7 th EAP, Recitals 3 and 15. <lb/>29 Impact Assessment, 15. <lb/>30 ibid. <lb/>31 TSAP, 5. <lb/>32 Directive 2008/50/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 May 2008 on ambient air quality and <lb/>cleaner air for Europe [2008] OJ L152/1. The AAQD is a result of substantial revision and merging of five acts, namely <lb/>Directives 96/62/EC on ambient air quality assessment and management, 1999/30/EC relating to limit values for sulphur <lb/>dioxide, nitrogen dioxide and oxides of nitrogen, particulate matter and lead in ambient air, 2000/69/EC relating to limit <lb/>values for benzene and carbon monoxide in ambient air, 2002/3/EC relating to ozone in ambient air and Decision <lb/>97/101/EC establishing a reciprocal exchange of information and data from networks and individual stations measuring <lb/>ambient air pollution within the Member States (Recital 3). <lb/>33 AAQD, art 1. <lb/>34 Impact Assessment, 15. <lb/>35 Zones and agglomerations are parts of Member States&apos; territory, established by the Member States to carry out air <lb/>quality assessment and management pursuant to art 4 of the AAQD. <lb/>36 A scientifically based level, with the aim of avoiding, preventing or reducing harmful effects on human health and/or <lb/>the environment as a whole, to be attained within a given period and not to be exceeded once attained (art 2(5)). <lb/>37 A scientifically based level, above which direct adverse effects may occur on plants or ecosystems but not on humans <lb/>(art 2(9)). <lb/>38 AAQD, art 24(1). This rule follows from the decision of the European Court of Justice (ECJ) in the case C-237/07 <lb/>Janecek v Freistaat Bayern [2008] ECR I-6221, based on art 7(3) of the preceding Directive 96/62/EC. The case <lb/>originated from the claim of a natural person, Mr Janecek, living on Munich&apos;s central ring road. The claimant was <lb/>concerned about the level of PM10, which exceeded the limit value fixed for this pollutant for much more than 35 times. <lb/>The ECJ stated that &apos;natural or legal persons directly concerned by a risk that the limit values or alert thresholds may be <lb/>exceeded must be in a position to require the competent authorities to draw up an action plan where such a risk exists, if <lb/>necessary by bringing an action before the competent courts.&apos; (para 39) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Apart from the pollutants covered, the provisions of AAQD, however, do not extend to some <lb/>heavy metals with high carcinogenic properties, namely As, Cd, Hg and Ni as well as to other large <lb/>group of organic pollutants, the polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons 39 since the latter two cases proved <lb/>to be difficult in terms of implementation 40 . Accordingly, these pollutants are regulated by Directive <lb/>2004/107/EC 41 , though the merging of its provisions with those of the AAQD is potentially possible, <lb/>once sufficient experience has been gained in relation to the implementation of the former 42 . <lb/>The third element, the National Emission Ceilings Directive (NECD) 43 aims at limiting the <lb/>total emissions from each Member State for a set of acidifying and eutrophying pollutants and O3 <lb/>precursors 44 , namely SO2, NOx, VOC and NH3 45 . The principle requirement of the NECD for <lb/>Member States is to limit their annual national emissions of these pollutants to amounts not greater <lb/>than the emission ceilings laid down in Annex I and ensure that they are not exceeded after 2010 46 . <lb/>To achieve this, Member States are required to draw up and implement national programmes to <lb/>meet the emission ceilings, which should be revised if projections show that the ceilings are unlikely <lb/>to be met 47 . <lb/>The fourth element comprises a range of measures at EU, national and international level <lb/>controlling pollution at the source to achieve the objectives set in the above-mentioned <lb/>instruments 48 . Examples of such measures include the control of emissions to air and water from <lb/>mobile sources (road and non-road) and shipping, agriculture and manure storages as well as <lb/>households and other small combustion sources 49 . The importance of controlling air pollution at <lb/>source is, inter alia, highlighted in the AAQD as well 50 . <lb/>Finally, international action under different platforms, including the exchange of scientific <lb/>and technical information, provides an important backbone for the EU air policy framework 51 . <lb/>International initiatives are crucial due to the transboundary nature of some pollutants, for example <lb/>O3, the background concentrations of which in Europe are influenced by O3 production and transport <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>39 AAQD, Recital 4. <lb/>40 Wilde, 284. <lb/>41 Directive 2004/107/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 15 December 2004 relating to arsenic, <lb/>cadmium, mercury, nickel and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in ambient air [2005] OJ L23/3. <lb/>42 AAQD, Recital 4. The problem behind the implementation is related to the fact that due to the strong hazardous nature <lb/>of the pollutants in question, scientific evidence shows that there is no identifiable threshold below which these <lb/>substances do not pose a risk to human health. Yet, with a view to cost-effectiveness, ambient air concentrations of these <lb/>substances, which would not pose a significant risk to human health, cannot be achieved in specific areas (Directive <lb/>2004/107/EC, Recital 3). For that particular reason, the Directive limits itself on providing only target values rather than <lb/>binding limit values (Wilde, 288), though the introduction of the latter in the future is not per se impossible (Directive <lb/>2004/107/EC, art 8(2)(b)). Notably, the most difficult case proved to be mercury, which resulted in the absence of a <lb/>target value for this especially hazardous substance and the undertaking of a separate research programme that led to the <lb/>suspension of the setting of a target value in respect of this substance until the research is complete (Directive <lb/>2004/107/EC, Recitals 9 and 10, Wilde, 288). <lb/>43 Directive 2001/81/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 October 2001 on national emission <lb/>ceilings for certain atmospheric pollutants [2001] OJ L309/22. <lb/>44 ibid, art 1. <lb/>45 ibid, art 4(1). <lb/>46 NECD, art 4. <lb/>47 ibid, Recital 12, art 6. <lb/>48 Impact Assessment, 15. <lb/>49 &lt;http://ec.europa.eu/environment/air/review_air_policy.htm&gt; accessed 17 August 2014. <lb/>50 AAQD, Recital 2. <lb/>51 Impact Assessment, 15. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>in the entire northern hemisphere 52 . The key instrument in terms of international cooperation is the <lb/>CLRTAP and its protocols 53 . Among the latter is the 1999 Gothenburg Protocol to Abate <lb/>Acidification, Eutrophication and Ground-level Ozone (Gothenburg Protocol) 54 which plays a vital <lb/>role in EU air quality policy 55 . The Protocol initially targeted the reduction in emissions of four <lb/>pollutants, namely SO2, NOx, NH3 and VOC 56 and established emission ceilings for these pollutants <lb/>to be achieved by 2010 57 as well as the limit values for emissions 58 . After the Protocol was amended <lb/>in 2012 59 it introduced tighter reduction commitments for the above-mentioned substances (along <lb/>with new requirements for yet another pollutant, PM2.5 60 ), to be attained for 2020 and beyond 61 . <lb/>2. Key Problems <lb/>Although the above-mentioned elements create a comprehensive legal background for air <lb/>protection in the EU region, there are certain factors significantly undermining the policy. <lb/>The most obvious problem is the non-compliance with existing EU legislation 62 . This <lb/>problem is easily perceived from the number of Member States, facing infringement procedures for <lb/>failing to meet PM limit values, with similar situation likely to follow in case of NO2 and NOx 63 . <lb/>Regarding the PM-related infringement procedures, it should be observed that a number of such <lb/>procedures resulted in a series of cases brought before the ECJ on the initiative of the European <lb/>Commission (Commission) 64 , which based its arguments on the requirements of the AAQD and/or <lb/>the preceding legislation with respect to PM10 limit values 65 . These cases originated from very <lb/>similar circumstances -the failure of Member States to ensure that the concentrations of PM10 in <lb/>ambient air did not exceed the limit values set in the above-mentioned legislation 66 . <lb/>The reasons behind the problem of non-compliance are different in their nature, though the <lb/>two main drivers identified are the pollution sources themselves and the failure to manage air quality <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>52 ibid, 136. <lb/>53 ibid, 137. <lb/>54 Protocol to the 1979 Convention on Long-Range Transboundary Air Pollution to Abate Acidification, Eutrophication <lb/>and Ground-Level Ozone (adopted 30 November 1999, entered into force 17 May 2005) 2319 UNTS 81 (Gothenburg <lb/>Protocol). <lb/>55 Thus, the effects-orientated policy of the Gothenburg Protocol, based on scientific and technical knowledge has been <lb/>endorsed by the EU and subsequently applied in EU legislation, for example, in the NECD. Impact Assessment, 137 and <lb/>139. <lb/>56 Gothenburg Protocol, art 2. <lb/>57 ibid, Annex II. <lb/>58 ibid, Annexes IV-VI. <lb/>59 &lt;http://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/env/documents/2013/air/eb/ECE.EB.AIR.114_ENG.pdf&gt; accessed 17 August <lb/>2014. <lb/>60 ibid, art 2. <lb/>61 ibid, Annex II, etc. <lb/>62 Impact Assessment, 15 and 19. <lb/>63 Impact Assessment, 20. <lb/>64 See: C-365/10 Commission v Slovenia [2011] ECR I-0040, C-479/10 Commission v Sweden [2011] ECR I-0070, (C-<lb/>34/11) Commission v Portugal [2012] (ECJ, 15 November, 2012), C-68/11 Commission v Italy [2012] (ECJ, 19 <lb/>December, 2012). <lb/>65 (n 32). <lb/>66 Notably, in all these cases the Court did acknowledge the failure to fulfil the obligations of the Member States in <lb/>question under the preceding legislation in mid-2000s, but dismissed the actions with regard to the alleged breach of the <lb/>AAQD provisions due to ratione temporis. See: (n 64) Commission v Portugal, paras 50, 55 and 56, Commission v Italy, <lb/>paras 55, 56 and 67. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>properly 67 . Hence, despite the fact that vehicles in general have delivered substantial emission <lb/>reductions across the range of regulated pollutants, diesel engines, especially in light-duty vehicles, <lb/>still deliver significant NOx emissions, and what is even worse, many Member States continue to <lb/>promote the sale and use of such vehicles compared to gasoline and other cleaner fuel vehicles by <lb/>means of national taxation policies 68 . The problem with policy issues is further exacerbated by the <lb/>increase in traffic volumes, especially in urban areas 69 . Last but not least, the illegal practices by <lb/>some end users that defeat the anti-pollution systems to improve driving performance or save on the <lb/>replacement of costly components also contribute to the problem 70 . Consequently, while the NOx (as <lb/>well as other emissions&apos;) limit values for diesel passenger cars have been gradually tightened from <lb/>1993 to 2009 through the introduction of higher European emission standards, the estimated average <lb/>NOx emissions in real driving conditions have experienced a slight increase 71 . Meanwhile, due to <lb/>engine technology developments, the share of NO2 emissions in the NOx mixture has increased, <lb/>posing additional challenges for the attainment of the NO2 air quality standards 72 . Accordingly, all <lb/>these factors compromise the compliance with both AAQD and NECD. Other examples of poorly <lb/>controlled sectors include domestic combustion and concentrated local pollution, causing major PM <lb/>compliance problems 73 as well as agriculture, which is responsible for 90% of the remaining NH3 <lb/>emissions, the primary driver of eutrophication in Europe 74 . <lb/>As a result of the above-mentioned examples and in spite of broad compliance, reached for a <lb/>number of key pollutants, standards for some other pollutants, namely PM10, NO2 and O3, remain <lb/>widely exceeded throughout Europe with a substantial part of the EU population and environment <lb/>exposed to harmful pollution levels 75 . <lb/>On the other hand, the problem lies not only in the Member States&apos; non-compliance with the <lb/>existing legislation, but the failure of the legislation itself to meet the EU international <lb/>commitments, following the 2012 amendment of the Gothenburg Protocol 76 . Thus, the national <lb/>emission ceilings established under the NECD are no longer compatible with the requirements of the <lb/>amended Protocol, particularly in the light of updated emission reduction commitments for SO2, <lb/>NOx, NH3 and VOC as well as new commitments for PM2.5 for 2020 and beyond 77 . <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>67 Impact Assessment, 21. <lb/>68 ibid, 21 and 22. <lb/>69 Impact Assessment, 22. <lb/>70 ibid, 21. <lb/>71 ibid, 22. <lb/>72 ibid. <lb/>73 ibid, 22, 23. <lb/>74 ibid, 25. <lb/>75 ibid, 19. Thus the percentage of air quality management zones in compliance with AAQD requirements for PM10, NO2 <lb/>and O3 in 2010 was 68%, 76% and 65% respectively, while the percentage of population exposed to the levels of these <lb/>pollutants above limit values calculated at about 40% in case of PM10, from 6% to 12% in case of NO2 and 35% in case <lb/>of O3. Meantime, the percentage of 108 national ceilings complying with the NECD requirements is estimated at 90%. <lb/>76 Impact Assessment, 20. <lb/>77 See: (n 59) Annex II, Tables 2-6 and NECD, Annex I. It should be noted that according to the projections, the <lb/>obligations of the amended Protocol are expected to be met without further measures, yet formal transposition into the <lb/>NECD is deemed necessary for ratification, to confirm the EU general commitment to the Gothenburg outcome and to <lb/>encourage the participation of other parties, including Eastern European, Caucasus and Central Asian states. Impact <lb/>Assessment, 20. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>The major drawback, however, is the failure of the current policy to meet the long-term air <lb/>quality objective, that is to reach the minimum impact levels as recommended by the WHO 78 . This <lb/>issue is of substantial practical importance, because even in case of full compliance with the existing <lb/>legislation, major health and environmental impacts of air pollution will persist 79 , contrary to the <lb/>main objective of the EU air policy to prevent such impacts. For instance, the number of premature <lb/>deaths from exposure to the pollutants is expected to reduce from 406,000 in 2010 to 340,000 by <lb/>2020, while the reductions beyond 2020 are estimated to be very insignificant 80 . A similar fate is <lb/>expected for the reduction in percentage of forest areas with exceeding acidification as well as <lb/>ecosystem areas with exceeding eutrophication -in both cases a relatively significant rate of <lb/>decrease from 2010 to 2020 does not extend from then onwards 81 . <lb/>To summarise, even according to the best scenario possible, air pollution will continue to <lb/>substantially affect both human health and the environment in the long-term perspective, claiming <lb/>hundreds of thousands of lives and billions of Euros annually; therefore a revision of policy is <lb/>deemed essential 82 . <lb/>3. The Revision of the Policy and the Clean Air Policy Package <lb/>Following the earlier initiatives undertaken prior to the TSAP or under it 83 and drawing upon <lb/>the experience gained throughout the implementation of the 6 th EAP 84 the Commission carried out a <lb/>comprehensive review of EU air policy in the run of 2011-13. The review resulted in some <lb/>immediate measures, for example, the successfully negotiated revision of the amended Gothenburg <lb/>Protocol as well as the adoption of the revised Directive on the Sulphur Content of Liquid Fuels 85 . <lb/>Furthermore, a range of other measures, orientated to address the current air policy in broader terms <lb/>was developed. This set of measures, adopted by the end of 2013 was named the Clean Air Policy <lb/>Package (CAPP) 86 . <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>78 Thus, current EU standards for PM10, PM2.5 and O3 as provided in the AAQD are as follows: 40 μg/m 3 and 25 μg/m 3 <lb/>averaged over a calendar year limit values for PM10 and PM2.5 respectively to be attained by 2010 (Annex XI and Annex <lb/>XIV respectively) with the decrease in limit value for PM2.5 to 20 μg/m 3 to be attained by 2020 (Annex XIV), and the <lb/>long-term objective for O3 averaged in a daily eight-hour mean within a calendar year set at 120 μg/m 3 (Annex VII). <lb/>Meanwhile, the updated WHO 2005 guidelines set the concentrations for these pollutants at 20 μg/m 3 , 10 μg/m 3 and 100 <lb/>μg/m 3 respectively. See: WHO Air quality guidelines for particulate matter, ozone, nitrogen dioxide and sulfur dioxide, <lb/>2005, <lb/>summary <lb/>of <lb/>risk <lb/>assessment, <lb/>p. <lb/>9 <lb/>and <lb/>14. <lb/>See: <lb/>&lt;http://whqlibdoc.who.int/hq/2006/WHO_SDE_PHE_OEH_06.02_eng.pdf?ua=1&gt; accessed 17 August 2014. <lb/>79 Impact Assessment, 24. <lb/>80 Impact Assessment, 27. <lb/>81 ibid. <lb/>82 TSAP, 3. <lb/>83 For example, the merging of different legislation into single AAQD. <lb/>84 7 th EAP, Recitals 3-5. <lb/>85 (n 49). <lb/>86 &lt;http://ec.europa.eu/environment/air/index_en.htm&gt; accessed 17 August 2014. Basically, the CAPP comprises four <lb/>documents: the Clean Air Programme, Proposal for a Directive on the limitation of emissions of certain pollutants into <lb/>the air from MCPs (MCPs Proposal), Proposal for a revised NECD (NECD Proposal) and Proposal for a Council <lb/>Decision on the acceptance of the amended Gothenburg Protocol. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the light of the outstanding problems, the review concentrated on two major challenges -<lb/>ensuring the compliance with existing legislation (the short-term objective) and the successful <lb/>implementation of the EU long-term air policy objective 87 . <lb/>The short-term objective stipulates a set of specific measures to be undertaken within the <lb/>2020 timeframe. The latter includes ensuring full implementation of current legislation and ensuring <lb/>that the emissions of light duty diesel vehicles in real driving conditions are brought in line with <lb/>regulatory requirements, facilitating action on residual local compliance problems, promoting <lb/>enhanced policy coordination at Member State and regional/local level, and finally, ratifying the <lb/>Gothenburg Protocol and incorporating the obligations of the protocol into EU legislation 88 . <lb/>Particular attention is drawn to reducing NOx emissions from light duty diesel engines in real <lb/>driving conditions, since the latter proved to be an especially notorious case of non-compliance 89 . <lb/>Therefore, in its CARS 2020 Communication, the Commission committed to actively support the <lb/>development and implementation of a new driving test cycle and test procedure to assess NOx <lb/>emissions of light duty vehicles under real driving conditions 90,91 . Measures taken on the basis of <lb/>these new procedures should ultimately ensure the substantial reduction of real world NOx <lb/>emissions, required to achieve the latest European emission standard&apos;s (Euro 6) NOx emission limits <lb/>under real driving conditions 92 . <lb/>Throughout the review, five options were considered to reach the short-term objective <lb/>(comparing with the baseline scenario of no new EU regulatory action), namely the adoption of new <lb/>EU source control legislation, the tightening of national emission ceilings beyond the levels agreed <lb/>as part of the Gothenburg Protocol, the strengthening of EU support for national and local action at <lb/>the Member States level, the further promotion of tighter international air pollution controls and <lb/>even the weakening of the limit values or relaxing the attainment dates 93 . The latter option, however, <lb/>was almost immediately identified as counterproductive, while the first two options were <lb/>acknowledged to be of low effectiveness 94 . At the same time, although the promotion of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>87 Impact Assessment, 34 and 35. Notably, these objectives are aligned with the general priority objectives of the 7 th <lb/>EAP (art 2). Furthermore, &apos;strengthening efforts to reach full compliance with Union air quality legislation and defining <lb/>strategic targets and actions beyond 2020&apos; is required as a particular tool in achieving the programme&apos;s key <lb/>environmental goals (para 28(v)). <lb/>88 Impact Assessment, 35. <lb/>89 Clean Air Programme, 3. <lb/>90 Communication from the Commission to the European Parliament, the Council, the European Economic and Social <lb/>Committee and the Committee of the Regions. Cars 2020: Action Plan for a Competitive and Sustainable Automotive <lb/>Industry in Europe. COM(2012) 636 final, 11-12. <lb/>91 This commitment follows from Regulation (EC) No 715/2007 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 20 <lb/>June 2007 on type approval of motor vehicles with respect to emissions from light passenger and commercial vehicles <lb/>(Euro 5 and Euro 6) and on access to vehicle repair and maintenance information [2007] OJ L171/1, art 14(3), which <lb/>requires from the Commission to &apos;keep under review the procedures, tests and requirements referred to in Article 5(3) <lb/>[such as requirements for tailpipe emissions, evaporative emissions, durability of pollution control devices, measurement <lb/>of greenhouse gas emissions, hybrid and alternative fuel vehicles, measurement of engine power, etc.] as well as the test <lb/>cycles used to measure emissions. If the review finds that these are no longer adequate or no longer reflect real world <lb/>emissions, they shall be adapted so as to adequately reflect the emissions generated by real driving on the road&apos;. <lb/>92 Clean Air Programme, 3. <lb/>93 Impact Assessment, 37-45. <lb/>94 ibid, 41-46. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>international action was deemed potentially necessary, the measurable impacts of such option were <lb/>expected to materialise only after 2020 95 . <lb/>On the other hand, targeted EU support measures were considered to be the best way to <lb/>achieve the short-term objective 96 . Such measures would principally comprise the enhanced capacity <lb/>building for local air quality assessment and management to enable better-targeted and more cost-<lb/>effective air pollution reduction strategies, promoting enhanced synergies between local and/or <lb/>national air quality management, broadening the toolbox available to national and local authorities <lb/>for assessing and managing air pollution, etc. and, of course, fostering enhanced public awareness, <lb/>participation and support for national and local action, including the marketing and sale of eco-<lb/>friendly products 97 . An example of such policy enhancement would be the promotion of advanced <lb/>technologies, building on the &apos;Super Ultra Low Emission Vehicle&apos; concept, originally developed in <lb/>the US 98 . The sum for the implementation of the above-mentioned measures, estimated around €100 <lb/>million, would cover at least 30% of the non-compliance zones and is expected to be leveraged by <lb/>information exchange and additional finance to provide comprehensive support for the remaining <lb/>non-compliant areas 99 . <lb/>Meanwhile, the long-term objective implies not only no exceedence of the WHO guideline <lb/>levels for human health (though the latter may also develop over time), but no exceedence of the <lb/>maximum levels that the ecosystems can tolerate without degrading as well 100 . Thus the scope of the <lb/>long-term objective includes proportionally tapping the pollution reduction potential of contributing <lb/>sectors, addressing background pollution and improving the information base for assessing policy <lb/>implementation and effectiveness 101 . In principle, the scope covers the tasks of drawing trajectories <lb/>for emission reductions in key pollutants beyond 2020 towards the potential achievement of the <lb/>WHO standards and setting the &apos;gap closure&apos; percentage 102 as well as the development of measures <lb/>for combating emissions at source, particularly from medium combustion plants (MCPs) 103 . <lb/>The first two tasks proved to be rather complicated due to both the variety of options under <lb/>consideration and certain difficulties in analysing the potential impact of these options in the given <lb/>timeframe as well as their cost-effectiveness. Eventually, it was decided to focus primarily on PM2.5 <lb/>health impacts, since the latter were most damaging and could be monetized, thus cost-effectiveness <lb/>of options would be easily compared 104 . Moreover, the gap closure for this pollutant would also <lb/>deliver a certain reduction for O3, eutrophication and acidification 105 . Comparing all contributing <lb/>factors, the 75% gap closure for PM2.5 health impacts was identified as most beneficial with <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>95 ibid, 42-46. <lb/>96 ibid. <lb/>97 ibid, 39 and 40. <lb/>98 Clean Air Programme, 4. <lb/>99 Impact Assessment, 44. <lb/>100 Clean Air Programme, 6. <lb/>101 Impact Assessment, 35. <lb/>102 ibid, 48. The percentage by which the new objectives would close the gap between the baseline scenario (0%) on one <lb/>hand, and the result of applying all (maximum) technically feasible reduction measures (100%), on the other. <lb/>103 Combustion plants with a rated thermal input equal to or greater than 1 MW and less than 50 MW, irrespective of the <lb/>type of fuel used. Proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on the limitation of emissions <lb/>of certain pollutants into the air from medium combustion plants. COM(2013) 919 final, art 2(1). <lb/>104 Impact Assessment, 48. <lb/>105 ibid, 61. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>additional 80% and 46% gap closure for eutrophication and O3 respectively as a potential <lb/>improvement to this option 106 . Accordingly, this option comprises a range of measures, such as <lb/>using low sulphur coal and fuel oil, improved stoves and boilers, stricter NOx and SO2 controls <lb/>throughout industries as well as improvements in feed, manure storages and fertilizers in <lb/>agriculture 107 . All these steps are expected to entail significant and positive shifts in combating the <lb/>negative effects of air pollution beyond 2020, retaining the improvement rates close to those in the <lb/>short-term 108 . <lb/>One of the main legislative pillars to achieve these strategic pollution reductions in the long-<lb/>term would be the revised NECD 109 . It would align the EU reduction commitments beyond 2020 for <lb/>the currently regulated pollutants (SO2, NOx, VOC and NH3) to the tighter requirements of the <lb/>amended Gothenburg Protocol and accordingly introduce new commitments (comparing to the <lb/>existing NECD) for the reduction of PM2.5 as well as new reduction commitments for the pollutant <lb/>not covered by the Protocol, namely CH4 110 . The trajectories for emission reductions in SO2, NOx, <lb/>NH3 and VOC for 2025 and 2030 (in comparison to 2005), drawn from the above-mentioned option <lb/>of 75% gap closure for PM2.5 111 and the emission reduction commitments set in the proposal for a <lb/>revised NECD 112 , however, reflect a more stringent approach than the amended Protocol 113 . <lb/>Moreover, the revised NECD would also be expected to play a part in tackling air pollution <lb/>at source from agriculture and international shipping. In case of agriculture, the applicable <lb/>mechanism would be the national air pollution control programme, adopted, implemented and <lb/>regularly updated by Member States, describing how their reduction commitments shall be met 114 . <lb/>Where necessary, such programmes should include specific measures, aimed at curbing emissions <lb/>from the agricultural sector 115 . With regard to international shipping, the proposal for a revised <lb/>NECD provides a more flexible regulatory approach than the existing. It still does not account for <lb/>emissions from international maritime traffic (art 4(3)) (similar to art 2 of the existing NECD), but <lb/>with one exception: that in order to comply with the interim emission levels determined for 2025 <lb/>and the national emission reduction commitments applicable from 2030 onwards, the Member States <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>106 ibid, 70. <lb/>107 Impact Assessment, 49. <lb/>108 ibid, 71. For example, as mentioned above, the number of premature deaths is estimated to drop by 60,000 by 2020, <lb/>but this trend fails to keep its pace in the following years. The chosen option, however, entails a further 60,000 <lb/>premature deaths&apos; decrease by 2025 and yet another 60,000 by 2030, thus keeping the current trend intact. <lb/>109 Proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on the reduction of national emissions of <lb/>certain atmospheric pollutants and amending Directive 2003/35/EC. COM(2013) 920 final, 1. <lb/>110 NECD Proposal, Recitals 5 and 6, art 4(1) and Annex II. <lb/>111 Impact Assessment, 50. These trajectories stand as follows: -79% (-82%) for SO2, -64% (-69%) for NOx, -49% (-<lb/>51%) for PM2.5, -30% for NH3 and -50% (-51%) for VOC. <lb/>112 NECD Proposal, Annex II. The proposal uses a slightly different emission reduction scheme than the trajectories: for <lb/>the 2020 -2029 interim period and beyond 2030. Accordingly, the reduction rates are: -59% (-81%) for SO2, -42% (-<lb/>69%) for NOx, -22% (-51%) for PM2.5, -6% (-27%) for NH3 and -28% (-50%) for VOC. Also, the Proposal introduces a <lb/>-33% reduction for CH4 beyond 2030. <lb/>113 The amended Gothenburg Protocol (Annex II, Tables 2-6) sets the reduction rates for 2020 onwards, which <lb/>correspond to the 2020-29 interim period reduction rates, presented in the proposal for a revised NECD above. <lb/>114 NECD Proposal, 3. <lb/>115 ibid, Recital 13, art 6(2) and Annex III Part 1. The measures in question include prohibition of certain fertilizers, <lb/>strategic reduction of emissions from manure storages and animal housing, banning of open field burning of agricultural <lb/>harvest residue, waste and forest residue, etc. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>may offset NOx, SO2 and PM2.5 emission reductions achieved by international maritime traffic <lb/>against these emissions, released by other sources in the same year 116 . <lb/>A quite different case though is the problem of abating emissions from MCPs. The key <lb/>driver here is a clearly perceived gap in EU source legislation, specifically addressing air emissions <lb/>of polluting substances from MCPs, although the combustion of fuel in both small and large <lb/>combustion plants is covered by existing legislation 117 . Yet, the MCPs are used in a wide variety of <lb/>applications (including electricity generation, domestic/residential heating and cooling and <lb/>providing heat/steam for industrial processes, etc.) and are an important source of emissions of SO2, <lb/>NOx and PM, while the number of such plants in the EU exceeds 140,000 118 . The main requirements <lb/>of the proposed legislation include the mandatory registration for all MCPs 119 , setting the emission <lb/>limit values 120 as well as establishing a system of emissions&apos; monitoring and environmental <lb/>inspection imposed on operators and Member States respectively 121 . <lb/>Overall, the above-mentioned measures should substantially improve the situation across <lb/>Europe. In total, the new policy is expected to reduce the rate of premature mortality by 52% and the <lb/>ecosystem area with exceeding eutrophication by 35% by 2030 (relative to 2005) comparing to 40% <lb/>and 22% decrease respectively, resulting from the full implementation of current legislation 122 , with <lb/>overall economic benefits ranging from €40 billion to €150 billion per annum 123 . This, however, <lb/>does not signify that the long-term objective of complying with the WHO guidelines could be <lb/>reached in the nearest future (at least by 2030), since the latter possibility is acknowledged to be <lb/>technically unfeasible in that timescale 124 . Yet, the ultimate goal of the EU air policy is to reach such <lb/>compliance, thus the question on both the potential role of the CAPP in the long run and some <lb/>further actions beyond 2030 remains open. <lb/>4. Reflections on the Future <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>116 ibid, art 5(1). The application of this mechanism though, is contingent on several conditions: a) that the emission <lb/>reductions occur in the sea areas that fall within the Member States&apos; territorial seas, exclusive economic zones or in <lb/>pollution control zones if such zones have been established; b) that the Member States have adopted and implemented <lb/>effective monitoring and inspection measures to ensure a proper operation of this flexibility; c) that the Member States <lb/>have implemented measures to achieve lower NOx, SO2 and PM2.5 emissions from international maritime traffic than the <lb/>emissions levels that would be achieved by compliance with the Union standards applicable to emissions of NOx, SO2 <lb/>and PM2.5 and have demonstrated an adequate quantification of the additional emission reductions resulting from these <lb/>measures; d) that the Member States have not offset more than 20% of the NOx, SO2 and PM2.5 emission reductions <lb/>calculated in accordance with point (c), provided that the offset does not result in non-compliance with the national <lb/>emission reduction commitments for 2020 set out in Annex II. <lb/>117 MCP Proposal, 2. <lb/>118 ibid. <lb/>119 ibid, art 4(1). The registration procedure includes a notification by the operator (art 4(2 and 3)), containing <lb/>information on the rated thermal input and the type of the MCP, type and share of fuels used, expected number of <lb/>operating hours, etc. (Annex I). The existing MCPs are exempted from this procedure, provided that the above-<lb/>mentioned information has been made available to the competent authorities (art 4(5)). <lb/>120 ibid, art 5. It should be emphasized that the proposed Directive&apos;s limit values for the pollutants covered (namely SO2, <lb/>NOx and PM) are in line with those set in legislation for large combustion plants and derived from the amended <lb/>Gothenburg Protocol (at 4), opting for strategic emissions&apos; reduction beyond 2020 (art 5(2) and Annex II). <lb/>121 ibid, arts 6 and 7. <lb/>122 Clean Air Programme, 5 and 6. <lb/>123 Impact Assessment, 71. <lb/>124 ibid, 70. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>The recent review of EU air policy coincided with the end of the 6 th EAP and the beginning <lb/>of the 7 th EAP, which basically faces the same challenges as its predecessor 125 . Still, with the short-<lb/>term objective of complying with the existing legislation relatively within reach, the main attention <lb/>shifts towards the long-term air improvement perspectives, which look less promising. Thus, <lb/>notwithstanding substantial benefit to air quality, it is clearly acknowledged that the new policy <lb/>alone would be insufficient to achieve the long-term objective by 2030, while the compliance with <lb/>WHO guidelines by 2050 at the latest is also put under much doubt 126 . This extended timescale has <lb/>not been chosen at random: it reflects the long-term vision of the EU priority objectives for 2050 <lb/>required by the 7 th EAP 127 and, accordingly, the 2030-50 prolonged scenario of Maximum Control <lb/>Effort (MCE) developed throughout the review, combining the effect of further phasing out of the <lb/>most polluting sources (including the solid fuels, such as coal), increased electrification, energy <lb/>efficiency gains and the application of all technically available pollution control measures 128 . The <lb/>outcomes of this scenario demonstrate that in the case of background concentration of PM2.5, at <lb/>least, the level will be below the currently established WHO guideline value virtually everywhere in <lb/>the EU 129 . Furthermore, the MCE scenario stipulates quite significant further reductions in SO2, <lb/>NOx, NH3 and VOC 130 . Nevertheless, while all these reductions would be feasible under the MCE <lb/>assumptions, they could not be cost-effectively achieved by technical measures alone; therefore their <lb/>practical implementation would depend on structural and other changes which at the moment cannot <lb/>be assumed 131 . Currently, it can only be concluded that such changes would eventually require a <lb/>complex approach of promoting sustainable development, additional research, enhanced innovation <lb/>policy and business conditions, etc., as repeated on numerous occasions in EU strategic <lb/>documents 132 . <lb/>Considering this, yet another issue should be mentioned, namely the potential revision of the <lb/>AAQD. This Directive, enshrining the key requirements, so much needed for the bringing down of <lb/>the air pollution concentrations below the WHO guidelines in the future, was excluded from the <lb/>revision, since the review assumed that such revision would not be appropriate at this point, at least <lb/>until the update of the NECD 133 . <lb/>The above-mentioned points signify that the successful implementation of the WHO <lb/>guidelines, hence the long-term objective, is postponed to a rather remote future. Accordingly, the <lb/>importance of the undertaken review may seem to diminish, while the policy itself seems to <lb/>acknowledge the inability to reach any breakthrough. Still, the situation, however pessimistic it may <lb/>sound, is far more complex than could be described here and the issues playing part in both the <lb/>pollution and its tackling by far outnumber the ones presented above. Undoubtedly, neither the <lb/>current review and its proposed policy update nor the potential revision of the AAQD, per se, could <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>125 7 th EAP, Recitals 4 and 5. <lb/>126 Impact Assessment, 70. <lb/>127 7 th EAP, Recital 8. <lb/>128 Impact Assessment, at 49, 70. <lb/>129 ibid, 70. <lb/>130 ibid. <lb/>131 ibid, 70 and 200. <lb/>132 See: Communication from the Commission. Europe 2020: A strategy for smart, sustainable and inclusive growth. <lb/>COM(2010) 2020, at 9-15. See also 7 th EAP, Recital 8. <lb/>133 Clean Air Programme, 4. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>guarantee the immediate results, not only due to limited technical capabilities, but due to major role <lb/>of a whole range of factors, such as global climate, weather and air quality variations, the interaction <lb/>between natural and anthropogenic pollution, inefficiency of some of the adopted abatement <lb/>schemes and last, but certainly not least, social and economic trends 134 . These factors may <lb/>potentially play a decisive role in combating air pollution, forcing the governments to mitigate or <lb/>even forgo the carried out abatement measures 135 . <lb/>Moreover, these factors are often coupled with a degree of scientific uncertainty. An <lb/>example of such uncertainty was presented above with regard to setting of a target value for Hg in <lb/>Directive 2004/107/EC. As a result, in this case, the long-term objective, drawing upon 2000 WHO <lb/>air quality guidelines was simply overshadowed by the general lack of scientific information, <lb/>reflected in their vague statements 136 . At the same time, the preference for target values over limit <lb/>values in case of other pollutants covered by this very Directive, resulting from a successful <lb/>lobbying campaign by the industry 137 clearly reflected an economic consideration. Consequently, the <lb/>adopted piece of legislation was bound to both these factors, hence the long term-objective resulted <lb/>to be an underdog. <lb/>The evolution of scientific knowledge is a constant process, as demonstrated throughout the <lb/>update of the WHO guidelines 138 , thus the introduction of tighter standards for at least some air <lb/>pollutants in the perceptible future is possible. The EU air policy, however, chasing after these <lb/>standards is not very likely to catch up with them in due time, though in doing so it inevitably <lb/>benefits from both saved lives&apos; and outlays&apos; yield. After all, the new policy itself admits that <lb/>achieving the long-term objective is feasible only on a step-by-step basis 139 . Therefore, it foresees <lb/>the review of the progress on achievement of the objectives and implementation of the instruments <lb/>on a five-yearly basis, with the first review by 2020 140 . Evidently, this review will have to consider <lb/>many things, including not only the direct measures discussed above, but the tightening of the <lb/>AAQD standards, the problem of pollutants covered by Directive 2004/107/EC, further <lb/>developments in source controls and structural improvements so much needed for a gradual <lb/>implementation of the long-term objective 141 . <lb/>Conclusion <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>134 See: 7 th EAP, Recital 7, WHO air quality guidelines for Europe, 2 nd edition, 2000 (WHO 2000 guidelines) <lb/>&lt;http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0005/74732/E71922.pdf&gt; accessed 17 August 2014, 41. <lb/>135 Notably, a similar situation occurred in Commission v Italy (n 64), where the latter claimed that its failure to fulfil the <lb/>obligations with regard to PM10 emission reduction was forced by the mentioned factors (paras 36, 40 and 41). <lb/>Furthermore, Italy stated that &apos;ensuring compliance with those limit values would have involved the adoption of drastic <lb/>economic and social measures and the infringement of fundamental rights and freedoms such as the free movement of <lb/>goods and persons, private economic initiative and the right of citizens to public utility services&apos; (para 59). <lb/>The Court, however, deeming the force majeure situation possible (para 64), decided that in the present case, the <lb/>arguments put forward were too general and vague to constitute a case of it (para 65). <lb/>136 WHO 2000 guidelines, 160. With regard to Hg, the guidelines simply stated that &apos;to prevent possible health effects in <lb/>the near future […], ambient air levels of mercury should be kept as low as possible&apos;. <lb/>137 Wilde, 288. <lb/>138 WHO air quality guidelines. Global update 2005. Particulate matter, ozone, nitrogen dioxide and sulfur dioxide. See: <lb/>&lt;http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0005/78638/E90038.pdf&gt; accessed 17 August 2014, 1. <lb/>139 Clean Air Programme, 11. <lb/>140 ibid, 10. <lb/>141 7 th EAP, paras 47 and 48 of the Annex. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Currently, the EU air policy is challenged by two major problems: the failure to comply with <lb/>the existing legislation and the failure of the legislation itself to achieve the EU long-term air policy <lb/>objective of bringing down the values of key air pollutants below the WHO recommended <lb/>guidelines. The first problem is expected to be resolved primarily by targeted EU support measures, <lb/>enhancing the local capabilities of the Member States. Meanwhile, achieving the levels of air quality <lb/>that do not cause significant negative impacts on human health and environment requires much <lb/>more effort, including the update of existing legislation and the adoption of specific new <lb/>mechanisms. However, due to the complexity of the air pollution phenomenon, its current state and <lb/>future trajectories, relying on these measures alone would be unwise. That is why the undertaken <lb/>revision of the air policy and the set of mechanisms developed in its course cannot be considered a <lb/>decisive factor in achieving the long-term objective, rather only one of many steps towards it. Only <lb/>a combined effort of legislative means, structural improvements and new scientific information <lb/>coupled with further comprehensive revision of air policy could lead to successful achievement of <lb/>the ultimate goal of EU air policy. </body>


	</text>

</TEI>