<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Collective Redress: Broadening EU Enforcement through State Liability?</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>James</forename>
          <surname>Marson</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-25T14:38:54.484Z">1/25/2026 3:38:54 PM</date>
        <title>review</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.54648__eulr2016015</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Kluwer Law International BV</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2016</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.54648/eulr2016015</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>James Marson. (2016). Collective Redress: Broadening EU Enforcement through State Liability?. European Business Law Review, 27(Issue 3), 325-351. DOI: 10.54648/eulr2016015</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-01-02T12:19:23.904245Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2026-01-02T12:19:23.904245Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T14:10:42.841Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Annotation completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T21:42:38.267Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith second pass completed </desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T09:07:50.889Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-25T15:08:41.188Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>University of Huddersfield Repository <lb/>Marson, James and Ferris, Katy <lb/>Collective Redress: Broadening EU Enforcement Through State Liability? <lb/>Original Citation <lb/>Marson, James and Ferris, Katy (2016) Collective Redress: Broadening EU Enforcement Through <lb/>State Liability? European Business Law Review, 27 (3). pp. 325-351. ISSN 0959-6941 <lb/>This version is available at http://eprints.hud.ac.uk/id/eprint/24667/ <lb/>The University Repository is a digital collection of the research output of the <lb/>University, available on Open Access. Copyright and Moral Rights for the items <lb/>on this site are retained by the individual author and/or other copyright owners. <lb/>Users may access full items free of charge; copies of full text items generally <lb/>can be reproduced, displayed or performed and given to third parties in any <lb/>format or medium for personal research or study, educational or not-for-profit <lb/>purposes without prior permission or charge, provided: <lb/>• The authors, title and full bibliographic details is credited in any copy; <lb/>• A hyperlink and/or URL is included for the original metadata page; and <lb/>• The content is not changed in any way. <lb/>For more information, including our policy and submission procedure, please <lb/>contact the Repository Team at: E.mailbox@hud.ac.uk. <lb/>http://eprints.hud.ac.uk/ <lb/></front>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>COLLECTIVE REDRESS: BROADENING EU ENFORCEMENT <lb/>THROUGH STATE LIABILITY? <lb/>James Marson * and Katy Ferris ** <lb/>ABSTRACT. This article advances an argument that private enforcement of <lb/>European Union (EU) rights has largely been stunted due to a series of blocking <lb/>tactics by Member States, enabled through a form of tacitic subservience of the <lb/>Court of Justice of the European Union. Currently, State Liability is neither an <lb/>effective system of redress under tortious liability, nor a genuine enforcement <lb/>mechanism in domestic law. By enabling collective redress in State Liability, we <lb/>present an argument, missing explicitly in current literature, that both as a viable <lb/>remedy through the (UK&apos;s modified) tort of breach of statutory duty, and through <lb/>granting effective redress through action by the EU Commission, State Liability will <lb/>become the mechanism for corrective justice the Court of Justice envisaged in 1991. <lb/>In 2011, the EU Commission issued a non-binding Recommendation establishing <lb/>collective redress for breach of competition law. Could this be seen as positive <lb/>positioning by the EU to seize the initiative for greater access to individuals of justice <lb/>and justiciable solutions? <lb/>Keywords: State liability, collective redress, enforcement mechanisms, statutory <lb/>duty, EU Commission, damages. <lb/></front>
	  
	  <body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>The purpose of this article is to critique the remedy of State Liability for individuals <lb/>suffering loss as a result of a Member States&apos; non-implementation or incorrect <lb/>transposition of EU law. &apos;Enforcement mechanisms&apos; is a topic which has been <lb/>considered through a vast literature and from varying perspectives. Even a novice to <lb/>the subject will be aware that as a consequence of membership of the EU, <lb/>obligations have been imposed on individuals (and not confined to the signatory <lb/>Member State) to follow laws derived from the EU. A corollary to this has been to <lb/>ensure individuals have the full access to protective rights established at an EU <lb/>level. Typically, the EU creates a directive (the most common source of EU <lb/>legislation) which establishes harmonisation of the law through the 28 Member <lb/>States. Directives are an oft used legislative instrument as they do not impose the <lb/>rigidity and uniformity of EU Regulations, and whilst binding as to the result to be <lb/>achieved, they grant to Member States discretion as to the choice of form and <lb/>methods through which to give effect to (or, in the parlance, to transpose) the law. 1 <lb/>The intention has always been that in using directives as a legislative source, the EU <lb/>articulates the main aims and objectives of the necessary law, it provides the <lb/>Member States a period of time within which to transpose the law into their legal <lb/>systems, and thereafter, individuals access the law through the domestic transposing <lb/>provision. Where access to the EU law in this manner is not possible (due to, for <lb/></body>

			<front>* Principal Lecturer in Law, Sheffield Hallam University. <lb/>** Senior Lecturer in Law, The University of Huddersfield. <lb/></front>
	  
	  <listBibl>1 Article 288 Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>example, the Member State&apos;s non-implementation or incorrect transposition of the <lb/>law), the EU Commission has the authority to compel a Member State&apos;s compliance. <lb/>The Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (TFEU) provides for <lb/>enforcement through, first, a (pre-litigation) notification and secondly, a judicial <lb/>procedure, 2 -the Commission fulfilling the role of &apos;guardian of the treaties.&apos; The <lb/>Commission has a substantial role of ensuring Member States conform to obligations <lb/>and it possesses unlimited discretion 3 as to which cases are brought before the <lb/>Court of Justice. Beyond investigations undertaken under its volition, other Member <lb/>States, 4 individuals and organisations are also empowered to complain to the <lb/>Commission regarding alleged infringements. The Commission has the power to fine <lb/>Member States for late transposition of directives through a special penalty regime. 5 <lb/>However, despite this power, late transposition notices are not uncommon -for <lb/>instance they have previously been applied against more than two-thirds of Member <lb/>States, 6 and even against 23 7 Member States in a further example. <lb/>Where the notification procedure of ensuring compliance fails, the <lb/>Commission may launch infringement proceedings at the Court of Justice. In 2012, <lb/>there were 1343 infringement cases open, 8 and although this number has fallen <lb/>consistently since 2009, 9 and the explicit intentions of the Commission produce <lb/>demonstrable improvements in the levels of Member State compliance, 10 there <lb/>remain complaints from both academics 11 and the EU Parliament 12 regarding the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>2 Articles 258-260 TFEU. <lb/>3 The discretionary investigatory power is sometimes negatively viewed as enabling selective <lb/>enforcement. See Richard Rawlings, Engaged Elites Citizen Action and Institutional Attitudes in <lb/>Commission Enforcement, 6 European Law Journal 4, 10 (2000). <lb/>4 Available in Article 259 TFEU, although, given the political ramifications for undertaking such an <lb/>action, its use (and success) has been very limited (the following cases are where this mechanism <lb/>has been used -Case 141/78 France v United Kingdom [1979] E.C.R. 2923; Case C-388/95 Belgium <lb/>v Spain [2000] E.C.R. I-3123; Case C-145/05 Spain v United Kingdom [2006] E.C.R. I-7917; Case C-<lb/>364/10 Hungary v Slovakia). <lb/>5 Article 260(3) TFEU. <lb/>6 Regarding Directive 2010/78/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November <lb/>2010 amending Directives 98/26/EC, 2002/87/EC, 2003/6/EC, 2003/41/EC, 2003/71/EC, 2004/39/EC, <lb/>2004/109/EC, 2005/60/EC, 2006/48/EC, 2006/49/EC and 2009/65/EC in respect of the powers of the <lb/>European Supervisory Authority (European Banking Authority), the European Supervisory Authority <lb/>(European Insurance and Occupational Pensions Authority) and the European Supervisory Authority <lb/>(European Securities and Markets Authority) (L 331/120). <lb/>7 In respect of Directive 2010/78/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November <lb/>2010 amending several Directives in respect of the powers of the European Supervisory Authority <lb/>(European Banking Authority), the European Supervisory Authority (European Insurance and <lb/>Occupational Pensions Authority) and the European Supervisory Authority (European Securities and <lb/>Markets Authority). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">8 Of these, 1062 were closed following compliance by the Member State, but 128 cases were still <lb/>open as it could not be confirmed that the Member State had complied with the judgment of the Court <lb/>of Justice. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>9 http://ec.europa.eu/eu_law/docs/docs_infringements/annual_report_30/com_2013_726_en.pdf. p. 8 <lb/>10 See Robert Thompson, Opposition Through the Back Door in the Transposition of EU Directives, <lb/>11 European Union Politics, 577, 592 (2010) &apos;The… states&apos;… deviat[ion] is effectively reduced to zero <lb/>when the Commission explicitly supports a Directive&apos;s provision. Such support signals the <lb/>Commission&apos;s intention to monitor compliance stringently in Member States that express incentives to <lb/>deviate.&apos; <lb/>11 Melanie Smith, Enforcement, Monitoring, Verification, Outsourcing: The Decline and Decline of the <lb/>Infringement Process, 14 European Law Review 777 (2008) and Carol Harlow &amp; Richard Rawlings, <lb/>Accountability and Law Enforcement: The Centralised EU Infringement Procedure, 12 European Law <lb/>Review 447 (2006). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>efficacy and transparency of the system of infringement proceedings. Enforcement <lb/>actions by the Commission remain an important 13 and significant aspect of effective <lb/>governance, 14 yet all too frequently, it has been reported that this system is not fit for <lb/>purpose, 15 does not provide accessible justice for those individuals affected, does <lb/>not deter Member States sufficiently from flagrant breaches of EU law, and has been <lb/>restricted in its success 16 due to the expanding membership and competence of the <lb/>EU. It is clear, even by the admission of the Commission itself, that EU law is <lb/>frequently not being implemented and enforced in a satisfactory manner. 17 <lb/>The focus of enforcement by the Commission is to ensure Member States <lb/>fulfil their obligations, and whilst a breach often results in individuals being denied <lb/>access to rights conferred by the EU, the sanctions imposed on the recalcitrant State <lb/>do not take into account the effects of such a breach or associated losses incurred <lb/>by individuals. No private remedy is provided through enforcement at an EU level. <lb/>This is the remit of the domestic level of enforcement. <lb/>Beginning with the direct effect of treaty articles (and later directives), affected <lb/>individuals who were denied access to EU rights due to, for example, the non-<lb/>transposition of a directive, could argue that the national court had to give effect to <lb/>the directive directly in that court. This was a remedy only available against a State <lb/>body or (latterly) an emanation of the State, and hence could not be used between <lb/>private parties (such as an employee with a claim against an employer unless it <lb/>involved an &apos;advance effect&apos; or &apos;negative effect&apos; of directives through a Mangold 18 -<lb/>type application). Due to this constraint in the law, the Court of Justice developed the <lb/>remedy of indirect effect and its requirement of a purposive method of statutory <lb/>interpretation 19 (but which was of very limited use in the case of non-transposition of <lb/>the directive and where no domestic law, capable of a purposive interpretation, <lb/>existed). Finally, through Francovich 20 and the establishment of the State&apos;s non-<lb/>contractual liability for losses, the Court created a system of compensatory redress <lb/>for individuals to be provided through the national law, and enforceable through the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>12 The lack of transparency in proceedings was raised by the European Parliament in &apos;Report on the <lb/>25th Annual Report from the Commission on Monitoring the Application of Community Law (2007)&apos; <lb/>A6-0245/2009, para 13. <lb/>13 See Jonas Tallberg, Paths to Compliance: Enforcement, Management, and the European Union, 56 <lb/>International Organization 609 (2002). <lb/>14 And an increasingly important aspect of respect for the rule of law and the Commission&apos;s interests <lb/>in strengthening its enforcement in this area -see European Commission &apos;Communication from the <lb/>Commission to the European Parliament and the Council: A New EU Framework to Strengthen the <lb/>Rule of Law&apos; Brussels, 11.3.2014 COM(2014) 158 final. <lb/>15 See Christian B. Jensen, Implementing Europe: A Question of Oversight, 8 European Union Politics <lb/>451, 453 (2007). <lb/>16 See Tobias Lock Is Private Enforcement of EU Law Through State Liability a Myth? An Assessment <lb/>20 Years After Francovich, 49 Common Market Law Review 1675 (2012). <lb/>17 Communication from the Commission on Implementing European Community Environmental Law, <lb/>COM/2008/0773 final -http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52008DC0773:EN:NOT <lb/>18 Case C-144/04 Werner Mangold v Rüdiger Helm [2005] E.C.R. I-10013. <lb/>19 Although see Lisa Schultz Bressman &amp; Abbe R. Gluck, Statutory Interpretation from the Inside -An <lb/>Empirical Study of Congressional Drafting, Delegation, and the Canons: Part II, 66 Stanford Law <lb/>Review 725 (2014) for an analysis and critique of the theories underpinning the textualist and <lb/>purposivist approaches to statutory interpretation. The authors conclude that an alternative paradigm <lb/>is required, adopting a pragmatic approach to interpretation. <lb/>20 Joined Cases C-6/90 and C-9/90 Francovich and Bonifaci and others v Italy [1991] E.C.R. I-5357. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>domestic courts, which, whilst being a damages action for losses, is frequently <lb/>referred to in the body of law known as &apos;enforcement mechanisms&apos;. 21 <lb/>Enforcement mechanisms has been a subject of importance since the <lb/>inception of the Community, as a lack of enforcement (and a failure to secure access <lb/>to rights) may be considered democratised theft. 22 Member States that do not <lb/>adhere to EU obligations, particularly in relation to social policy and employment <lb/>rights, may gain a political, economic, and financial benefit. Losses sustained by <lb/>individuals for such transgressions may, financially at least, be relatively small <lb/>although the impact on their lives and the relationship they have with (for example) <lb/>their employer and the State is substantial. Member States that do adhere to EU <lb/>obligations will incur costs either directly or through the competitiveness of the <lb/>organisations that operate within the Member State, and a competitive disadvantage <lb/>is evidently the consequence. The history of the Court of Justice&apos;s case law on this <lb/>subject has been to ensure compliance amongst Member States, thereby creating <lb/>fairness to all the individuals who work within the remit of that State&apos;s authority, and <lb/>ensuring that Member States do not obtain an advantage from their breach of EU <lb/>law. The time has come for the full effects of Francovich to be realised 23 and for a <lb/>substantial mechanism to be established which compels adherence to the law. <lb/>II. THE DEBILITATING EFFECT OF COSTS <lb/>A Member State&apos;s breach of EU law does not affect an individual in isolation, but <lb/>rather there are multiple affected individuals all suffering an inability to avail <lb/>themselves of (often) protective rights which are designed with the aim of, for <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>21 For a discussion of the EU utilizing rights, enforceable by individuals, to establish policy without the <lb/>associated costs, see R. Daniel Kelemen, Suing for Europe: Adversarial Legalism and European <lb/>Governance, Comparative Political Studies 39, 101 (2006). <lb/>22 See David Vogel, The Hare and the Tortoise Revisited: The New Politics of Consumer and <lb/>Environmental Regulation in Europe, 33 British Journal of Political Science 557 (2003). <lb/>23 In the UK, for example, in the first 20 years of the availability of redress through State Liability, a <lb/>mere 22 cases were heard before English courts -R v Secretary of State for the Home Department ex <lb/>p. Gallagher [1996] 2 CMLR. 951; Bowden v South West Water Services Ltd [1998] 3 CMLR. 330; R v <lb/>Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food ex p. Lay and Gage [1998] COD 387; Boyd Line <lb/>Management Services Ltd v Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food (No.1) [1999] Eu. L.R. 44; R <lb/>v Department of Social Security Ex p. Scullion [1999] 3 CMLR. 798; R v Secretary of State for <lb/>Transport ex p. Factortame Ltd (No.5) [2000] 1 AC 524; Evans v Secretary of State for the <lb/>Environment, Transport and the Regions [2001] EWCA Civ 32; R v Secretary of State for Transport <lb/>ex p. Factortame Ltd (No.6) [2001] 1 WLR 942; Three Rivers DC v Bank of England (No.3) [2003] 2 <lb/>AC 1; Phonographic Performance Ltd v Department of Trade and Industry [2004] EWHC 1795 (Ch); <lb/>Sayers v Cambridgeshire CC [2006] EWHC 2029 (QB); Sempra Metals Ltd (formerly <lb/>Metallgesellschaft Ltd) v Inland Revenue Commissioners [2007] UKHL 34; Byrne v Motor Insurers&apos; <lb/>Bureau [2008] EWCA Civ 574; Moore v Secretary of State for Work and Transport [2008] EWCA Civ <lb/>750; Spencer v Secretary of State for Work and Pensions [2008] EWCA Civ 750; FJ Chalke Ltd v <lb/>Revenue and Customs Commissioners [2009] EWHC 952 (Ch); Cooper v Attorney General [2010] <lb/>EWCA Civ 464; R (on the application of MK (Iran)) v Secretary of State for the Home Department <lb/>[2010] EWCA Civ 115; Test Claimants in the FII Group Litigation v Revenue and Customs <lb/>Commissioners [2010] EWCA Civ 103; R (on the application of Negassi) v Secretary of State for the <lb/>Home Department [2011] EWHC 386 (Admin); Test Claimants in Thin Cap Group Litigation v <lb/>Revenue and Customs Commissioners [2011] EWCA Civ 127; Harmon CFEM Facades (UK) Ltd v <lb/>Corporate Officer of the House of Commons 67 Con. L.R. 1. Of these, in 12 cases was the claimant <lb/>an individual, and in total, 9 of the 22 cases were successful in obtaining a remedy. The more recent <lb/>case of Delaney v Secretary of State [2014] EWHC 1785 (QB) and the judgment regarding the <lb/>element of discretion (or lack thereof) for the State and its subsequent liability gives hope for future <lb/>cases. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>example, the betterment of their working lives. However, the existing system of <lb/>liability redress is for each individual to claim against the State to obtain damages. 24 <lb/>Issues of costs, 25 procedural difficulties, 26 quantum of damages, and the cost/benefit <lb/>of the resources required to obtain redress through litigation compared with the <lb/>monetary gains awarded, present problems to the current system which has resulted <lb/>in its limited effectiveness in the 24 years since the Francovich ruling. <lb/>In realising the effects of the Francovich judgment, consideration of how a system <lb/>of collective redress can help to remove a substantial barrier to the functionality of <lb/>the enforcement of EU law and also help to deter non-and incorrect transposition of <lb/>directives is paramount. The premise of this argument is from the Commission&apos;s <lb/>recent non-binding Recommendation regarding collective redress for alleged <lb/>breaches of EU antitrust / competition law. As part of the Commission&apos;s consultation <lb/>process prior to enactment of the Recommendation, the European Coalition for <lb/>Corporate Justice 27 commented: <lb/>Compensatory collective redress should have to cover all sectors where the <lb/>mass damage due to the breaches of EU law is possible and not be limited to the <lb/>areas of consumer law or competition. This would allow for example cases of loss <lb/>of personal data or breaches of data protection, negligent financial advice to <lb/>financial service users, environmental damage or breaches of employment rights <lb/>to be tackled via collective claims. 28 <lb/>Parallels may be drawn between the Commission&apos;s non-binding Recommendation <lb/>regarding collective redress for instances of anti-competitive behaviour by bodies <lb/>within Member States, and an extension of the principle to State Liability. Here the <lb/>Commission is primarily granting rights to individuals to access justice where, in <lb/>many cases at least, it would be financially unviable to pursue such action through <lb/>the courts. The expense of litigation, coupled with the very low remedy awarded <lb/>under quantum, restricts the ability of individuals in such a situation to obtain <lb/>redress. Similarly, social policy directives establishing protections from discrimination <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>24 The reality is that most do not enforce their rights. Specifically in relation to tortious liability, <lb/>research presented by Richard E. Miller &amp; Austin Sarat, Grievances, Claims and Disputes: Assessing <lb/>the Adversary Culture, 15 Law &amp; Society Review 525, 544-45 (1981) demonstrated that, in the US, <lb/>merely 3.8% of those individuals with a tort grievance actually enforce their rights in court. That figure <lb/>could be even lower in the UK. <lb/>25 See, for way as an example of the Danish Consumer Ombudsman scheme -&apos;Report Paves the <lb/>Way for Class Action Lawsuits on Behalf of Danish Consumers&apos; http://www.forbrug.dk. Also, a system <lb/>whereby claimants engaged in the same Member State, experiencing the same legal issue and, often, <lb/>experiencing the same level of financial loss would be likely to benefit from a more efficient use of <lb/>legal resources and would result in &apos;judicial economy&apos; for the legal system in a reduction in the <lb/>numbers of individual claims necessary to achieve the same result. In the UK, costs associated with <lb/>access to courts and justice were proportioned accordingly -Court Fees: 3-5%; Bailiffs&apos; Fees: 3-5 %; <lb/>Lawyers&apos; Fees: 70-90%; Experts&apos; Fees: 5-10%; Witness Compensation: 2-5%; and <lb/>Translation/Interpretation Fees: 5-7% (Jean Albert &quot;Study on the Transparency of Costs of Civil <lb/>Justice Proceedings in the European Union&quot; (EC Commission, DG for Justice, Freedom and Security <lb/>2007), 9). <lb/>26 Hans-W, Micklitz &amp; Astrid Stadler, The Development of Collective Legal Actions in Europe, <lb/>Especially in German Civil Procedure, 17 European Business Law Review 1481 (2006). <lb/>27 <lb/>&apos;Towards a Coherent European Approach to Collective Redress.&apos; Available at <lb/>http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/health_consumer/dgs_consultations/ca/replies_collective_redress_consultatio <lb/>n_en.htm. <lb/>28 ibid. Answer to Q33 in the Commission consultation document. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>experienced on the basis of (for example) sexual orientation, 29 beliefs and non-<lb/>beliefs, 30 because the individual works under a fixed term contract 31 or is a part-time <lb/>worker, 32 have been incorporated into domestic law on the basis of a parent EU <lb/>Directive. Further, fundamental protections on the requirements to preserve the <lb/>rights and conditions of work attributed to employees following the transfer of a <lb/>business from one owner to the next, 33 and requirements to consult with employees <lb/>and/or their representatives in the event of redundancies and/or transfers of an <lb/>undertaking 34 are also subject to a parent EU law. In the instances identified above, <lb/>the UK has been found (or an argument has been presented alleging it to be) in <lb/>breach of its obligations, with the result that individuals have been denied protection <lb/>to which they were entitled. The level of compensation available often makes it <lb/>uneconomic to bring an individual claim, but the worker wishes to assert his or her <lb/>rights or gain protection which is currently unavailable through domestic law. Direct <lb/>effect is unavailable in cases where the individual is employed in the private sector <lb/>(due to the horizontal / vertical distinction and application of directives), and indirect <lb/>effect is a possible, albeit opaque remedy, where there exists domestic legislation <lb/>capable of interpretation (although this is by no means a given state of affairs and <lb/>frequently falls to the reference procedure 35 and consequent delay in accessing a <lb/>remedy). State Liability is therefore not merely (or indeed nor should it be seen <lb/>principally as) a mechanism to provide compensation for breach. Rather, we argue, <lb/>its significance is in enabling an individual to force a Member State to take remedial <lb/>action 36 and comply with EU law in order, albeit indirectly, to access a right which <lb/>has been denied him or her and to act as the watchdog the Court of Justice had <lb/>envisaged when developing the suite of enforcement mechanisms. <lb/>III. STATE LIABILITY AND THE AWARD OF DAMAGES <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>29 Council Directive 2000/78/EC of 27 November 2000 establishing a general framework for equal <lb/>treatment in employment and occupation, OJ L 303, Art 1, and transposed in the UK through the <lb/>Disability Discrimination Act 1995 and the Equality Act 2010. <lb/>30 Council Directive 2000/78/EC of 27 November 2000 establishing a general framework for equal <lb/>treatment in employment and occupation, OJ L 303, Art 1. <lb/>31 Council Directive 1999/70/EC of 28 June 1999 concerning the framework agreement on fixed-term <lb/>work concluded by ETUC, UNICE and CEEP OJ L 175/43, and transposed in the UK through The <lb/>Fixed-term Employees (Prevention of Less Favourable Treatment) Regulations 2002. <lb/>32 Council Directive 97/81/EC of 15 December 1997 concerning the Framework Agreement on part-<lb/>time work concluded by UNICE, CEEP and the ETUC OJ L 14 and transposed in the UK through The <lb/>Part-time Workers (Prevention of Less Favourable Treatment) Regulations 2000. <lb/>33 Council Directive 77/187/EEC of 14 February 1977 on the approximation of the laws of the Member <lb/>States relating to the safeguarding of employees&apos; rights in the event of transfers of undertakings, <lb/>businesses or parts of businesses, OJ L 061, and Council Directive 2001/23/EC of 12 March 2001 on <lb/>the approximation of the laws of the Member States relating to the safeguarding of employees&apos; rights <lb/>in the event of transfers of undertakings, businesses or parts of undertakings or businesses, OJ L 82. <lb/>34 Council Directive 98/59/EC of 20 July 1998 on the approximation of the laws of the Member States <lb/>relating to collective redundancies, and transposed in the UK through The Trade Union and Labour <lb/>Relations (Consolidation) Act 1992, amended by the Collective Redundancies and Transfer of <lb/>Undertakings (Protection of Employment) (Amendment) Regulations 1995 and The Transfer of <lb/>Undertakings (Protection of Employment) Regulations 1981, amended by the Collective <lb/>Redundancies and Transfer of Undertakings (Protection of Employment) (Amendment) Regulations <lb/>1995 and 1999. <lb/>35 Article 267 TFEU. <lb/>36 Although others have already discussed the concept of extending Francovich-type damages <lb/>actions beyond the mere award of monetary compensation -see in particular Michael Dougan, The <lb/>Francovich Right to Reparation: Reshaping the Contours of Community Remedial Competence, 6(1) <lb/>European Public Law 103 (2000). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>A little over twenty years ago, the Court of Justice famously held: 37 <lb/>… the effectiveness of [EU] rules would be impaired and the protection of the <lb/>rights which they grant would be weakened if individuals were unable to obtain <lb/>compensation when their rights are infringed by a breach of law for which a <lb/>Member State can be held responsible. 38 <lb/>The ruling provided for the effectiveness of EU law to be reaffirmed, 39 and a new <lb/>(hybrid) form of liability in public law 40 (despite the fact that many disputes arising <lb/>from the breach of EU law affect private parties), to be established and made <lb/>enforceable before national courts. English law did not provide a neat form 41 of <lb/>tortious liability into which the principles established through State Liability would fit. <lb/>It did not align neatly with the rules to establish misfeasance in public office (as the <lb/>test of bad faith and deliberate 42 abuse of power is more onerous than the tests for <lb/>State Liability), nor negligence, as liability here is usually linked with fault 43 leading to <lb/>some form of injury or harm connected with the award of damages. Liability for pure <lb/>economic loss is particularly difficult to establish and from which to gain redress, and <lb/>whilst State Liability provides damages for economic losses incurred by the claimant, <lb/>it does not give the claimant direct access to the EU rights conferred through the <lb/>law, 44 nor does it require the claimant to link the damages claimed with actual proof <lb/>of harm. State Liability in the UK adopts a bastardised 45 form of breach of statutory <lb/>duty, 46 albeit with fundamental distinctions. Whereas the basis of a State Liability <lb/>action is to recover damages from the State (by its nature a public body and <lb/>therefore involving a public tort), 47 the tort of breach of statutory duty avoids the <lb/>imposition of liability and &quot;distinguishes clearly between private and public law <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>37 The Court of Justice, had, in Case 6/60 Humblet v Belgium [1960] E.C.R. 559, 569 established the <lb/>duty on Member States to make good damage incurred due to national laws conflicting with EU law. <lb/>38 Fn 20 at [33]. <lb/>39 Despite arguments as to its success (see e.g. Roberto Caranta, Judicial Protection Against Member <lb/>States: A New Jus Commune Takes Shape, 32 Common Market Law Review 703, 725 (1995); <lb/>Fernand Schockweiler, La responsabilité de l&apos;autorité nationale en cas de violation du droit <lb/>communautaire, 28 Revue trimestrielle de droit européen 27, 42 (1992), it is arguable that such <lb/>effectiveness has never been realised. <lb/>40 Although a second set of legal proceedings outside of the normal &apos;private&apos; sphere may &apos;hardly be <lb/>compatible with the requirement of an effective legal remedy&apos; Case C-316/93 Vaneetveld v SA Le <lb/>Foyer [1994] E.C.R. I-763, at [775], per Jacobs AG. <lb/>41 In Application des Gaz SA v Falks Veritas Ltd [1974] 1 Ch 381, Lord Denning had suggested (obiter <lb/>[395-6]) the creation of a new form of tort law to provide an effective remedy for such breaches. <lb/>42 Three Rivers District Council v Bank of England (No.3) [2000] UKHL 33; [2003] 2 AC 1. <lb/>43 The requirement of a finding of fault was rejected by the Court of Justice in Brasserie du Pêcheur v <lb/>Germany [1996] at [56]. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">44 It does grant such access indirectly as the Member State, having been found in breach of its EU <lb/>law obligations and ordered to compensate the affected claimant, will change / amend / &apos;clarify&apos; the <lb/>law to avoid any further claims (and exposure to damages actions). Hence, following the finding of <lb/>State Liability, the State invariably grants access to individuals through remedial action. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>45 See comments by Judge Toulmin QC, R v The Secretary of State for Transport ex parte <lb/>Factortame Ltd. (No.7) [2000] EWHC (Tech) 179 at [176]. <lb/>46 Breach of statutory duty was used by Lord Diplock in Garden Cottage Foods Ltd v Milk Marketing <lb/>Board [1984] AC 130 [141] when identifying potential liability for breach of Art. 86 EEC Treaty (now <lb/>Art. 102 TFEU) as applicable to individuals who suffered loss. <lb/>47 X v Bedfordshire CC [1995] 2 AC 633. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>actions such as judicial review.&quot; 48 Breach of statutory duty includes a remoteness <lb/>element whereby the statute must include an objective requirement that the breach <lb/>and damage suffered is actionable in private law, and thereby the statute intended <lb/>for the conferment of a remedy for the claimant. Statutes often do not expressly <lb/>identify such an intention and the courts are left in the position of &apos;hunting&apos; for <lb/>intention, incorporating presumptions and weightings, through textual and purposive <lb/>examination. This led to the creation 49 of a State Liability remedy model based on <lb/>non-contractual / tortious liability. 50 For English law, a new hybrid fusion of English <lb/>and EU law was created and to be applied by the domestic courts. <lb/>Despite Francovich and the resultant necessity for the domestic judicial <lb/>activism and creation leading to a suitable tortious liability remedy, Member States <lb/>continued to be required to fulfil their obligations for the correct and timely <lb/>implementation of directives. Failure in this regard may lead to the award of <lb/>damages as the Member State was obliged to make good any loss / damage 51 <lb/>sustained by the claimant, and justified on the principles of equivalence 52 and <lb/>effectiveness. 53 <lb/>Victims of infringement / transgression of EU law thus have routes by which to <lb/>claim damages where they have suffered loss or harm. This was established in <lb/>relation to competition law generally in Courage and Crehan 54 and Manfredi, 55 <lb/>having already been established in Francovich in relation to State Liability. Beyond <lb/>the general principles of law which allow redress as identified in these cases, <lb/>however, various practical limitations apply to affect the reality of the ability for the <lb/>individual victims to successfully recover damages. In the UK, for example, the <lb/>prospect of an individual personally funding a public law action or, without retaining <lb/>legal representation, presenting such a case is a practical impossibility. Trades <lb/>unions and some public bodies do fund State Liability claims, but these are relatively <lb/>rare and, in 2012, in the UK, only 2.6 million workers were union members engaged <lb/>in the private sector. Such private sector workers lack the protection of availing <lb/>themselves of a (vertical) direct effect claim against their employer, they may face <lb/>the problems of enforcing the law through indirect effect, and whilst these workers <lb/>may have the financial and legal support of their union to pursue a remedy of State <lb/>Liability, clearly the overwhelming majority of workers in both public and private <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>48 Paula Giliker, English Tort Law and the Challenge of Francovich Liability: 20 Years On, 128 The <lb/>Law Quarterly Review 541, 546 (2012). <lb/>49 A national system establishing and facilitating the award of a remedy was required, however, given <lb/>the unique nature of the effects of Francovich, and its adoption by Member States to be lukewarm at <lb/>best, by 1997, no Member State had introduced any legislative measures to give effect to this <lb/>development in EU law (SOU &apos;Det Allmannas Skadestandsansvar vid Overtradelse av EG-regler&apos; <lb/>1997, 194). <lb/>50 Although not every breach / infringement of EU law by a Member State constitutes a tort -Borgouin <lb/>S. A. and Others v Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food [1986] QB 716. <lb/>51 Francovich Fn 20 at [36]. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">52 In relation to anti-trust / competition law, the principle requires Member States to sanction breaches <lb/>of the EU law in the same way, and thereby equivalent to, the application of domestic law. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>53 A national court must not make it impossible of excessively difficult for a party to exercise his or her <lb/>EU rights -see Francovich [1991] Fn 2 at [33] and [39]. Further, In Autologic Holdings Plc v Inland <lb/>Revenue Commissioners [2004] EWCA Civ 690 [2004] 2 All ER 957 Gibson LJ stated: &apos;The <lb/>importance of the principle of effectiveness in Community law cannot be overstated. Any provision of <lb/>national law which makes the exercise of a right conferred by Community law practically impossible or <lb/>extremely difficult cannot prevail.&apos; 25. <lb/>54 Case 453-99 Courage Ltd. v Crehan [2001] E.C.R. I-6297. <lb/>55 Joined Cases C-295-298/04 Vincenzo Manfredi v Lloyd Adriatico Assicurazioni SpA [2006] E.C.R. <lb/>I-6619. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>sectors are not trade union members. Further, 27% of permanent employees were <lb/>trade union members compared with 15% of temporary employees. 56 The statistics <lb/>demonstrate greater vulnerability for workers who are not in trades unions and who <lb/>are less likely to possess the funds to bring their own, individual action for State <lb/>Liability. <lb/>IV. CLASS ACTIONS / COLLECTIVE REDRESS <lb/>There exists a catalogue of complexity and barriers which an individual must <lb/>overcome to avail him/herself of, first, compensation through State Liability and <lb/>secondly, a means of enforcing EU rights. Beyond the domestic procedural rules <lb/>regarding tortious liability of a public body, one of the most debilitating factors of any <lb/>public law action is the financial cost involved. This has been recognised at an EU <lb/>level, and the response of the Commission has seen it institute mechanisms, first by <lb/>encouraging Member States through its non-binding Recommendation to establish a <lb/>system of collective redress, and secondly (albeit a separate measure) by <lb/>compelling them through a (proposed) directive relating to compensation, connected <lb/>to breaches of EU anti-competition laws. 57 This has initially been established on the <lb/>basis of, and restricted to, anti-trust / competition law, but the principle of enabling <lb/>collective redress to access/enforce EU rights is a compelling move. 58 The EU <lb/>evidently recognised a major barrier to justiciable problems and action needed to be <lb/>taken at an EU level to ensure individuals can access justice, along with the broader <lb/>positive effects that derive therefrom. <lb/>It is important to recognise from the outset that incentivising private <lb/>individuals 59 to enforce their rights and to act as a watchdog in assisting the <lb/>Commission in its role as guardian of the treaties has not simply been the exclusive <lb/>want or remit of the EU. Increasingly, Member States 60 in the EU have been <lb/>establishing systems whereby individuals are in a position, through private claims, to <lb/>seek damages on the basis of corporate wrongdoing and malfeasance 61 (although <lb/>this does not mean that such systems are particularly widespread or have universal <lb/>agreement). 62 The positive positioning of some Member States has been mirrored by <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>56 Department of Business Innovation &amp; Skills (2012) &apos;Trade Union Membership 2012 Statistical <lb/>Bulletin May 2013, p. 6. <lb/>57 Proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on certain rules governing <lb/>actions for damages under national law for infringements of the competition law provisions of the <lb/>Member States and of the European Union. COM(2013) 404, 11.6.2013. <lb/>58 For a comparative study of the effectiveness of collective redress in competition law see Clifford A. <lb/>Jones, Private Enforcement of Antitrust Law in the EU, UK and USA (Oxford University Press 1999). <lb/>59 See Judith Resnik, Money Matters: Judicial Market Interventions Creating Subsidies and Awarding <lb/>Fees and Costs in Individual and Aggregate Litigation, 148 University of Pennsylvania Law Review <lb/>2119, 2144-6 (2000) where &apos;By the 1960s, lawyers, judges, academics and legislators began to <lb/>conceive of civil justice as having characteristics readily associated with criminal justice and <lb/>administrative systems:.. Creating incentives for entrepreneurial private actors to use the civil justice <lb/>system to partake in the work of public norm enforcement offered an alternative to centralizing power <lb/>exclusively within the government.&apos; <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">60 France, for example, has recently established a system of collective redress into its Consumer <lb/>Code -albeit restricted to State authorised consumer associations. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>61 Hans-W. Micklitz &amp; Astrid Stadler, The Development of Collective Legal Actions in Europe, <lb/>Especially in German Civil Procedure, 17 European Business Law Review 1473 (2006). <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">62 For example, the German (conservative / social democrat) coalition government elected in 2013 <lb/>have opposite views on the issue of collective redress in competition laws, with the negative position <lb/>being such a development would be unnecessary, be subject to abuse and require substantial <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>the EU, albeit the extent of, and the best mechanism by which to facilitate, such <lb/>access has been in consideration for some time. Approximately 19 Member States <lb/>including the UK have existing, or are proposing, collective redress mechanisms, <lb/>using opt-in and opt-out models, which in many ways follow the collective redress <lb/>procedures in the US. The existing use of collective redress has largely been limited <lb/>to consumer rights, securities litigation and anti-competition law violations. This <lb/>sectoral approach is instructive in that any further expansion of collective redress <lb/>would need to adopt a similar pattern. Employment protection / social policy appears <lb/>to be an area of EU competence that would benefit from the application of a system <lb/>of collective redress. <lb/>A. COLLECTIVE REDRESS -TO OPT-IN OR OPT-OUT? <lb/>Under a system of collective redress, two mechanisms are available as viable <lb/>options. The first is a system whereby the affected individual has to make an <lb/>informed decision to pursue an action against the defendant and be part of the <lb/>&apos;class&apos; of litigants in a particular case. This is the &apos;opt-in&apos; procedure which ensures <lb/>that a definable, genuine group of affected individuals who have been impacted by <lb/>the breach and have sustained some form of monetary loss can be identified, and <lb/>associated remedies through compensation can be distributed. Individuals declare <lb/>that they intend to participate in the legal action which assists the court in <lb/>establishing with certainty a group of claimants. As this group exists in advance, <lb/>distribution of any award is easier, as is the calculation of risk by the defendant of the <lb/>potential damages, 63 and it aligns itself with the legal systems of many Member <lb/>States. The opt-in system is often championed as enabling a legal freedom not <lb/>offered through opt-out. With opt-in, each individual has the option to form part of the <lb/>collective group seeking redress, whilst enabling those who wish to pursue an <lb/>individual claim to proceed without any restraints. However, as demonstrated in case <lb/>studies presented in 2007, the BEUC (the European Consumers&apos; Bureau) found: <lb/>the freedom not to have one&apos;s claim is often overstated in opt-in regimes. <lb/>Commencing proceedings without the explicit consent of those affected is not <lb/>necessarily a limitation on the claimant&apos;s freedom of choice, since people are <lb/>able to withdraw from the group and pursue individual actions or decline to <lb/>litigate altogether. 64 <lb/>Further, the opt-in system has been criticised as not removing the problem of <lb/>potential-claimant inertia 65 and where lawyers are not motivated (presumably <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">amendment to the Code of Civil Procedure; and the UK coalition government has stated its misgivings <lb/>regarding the extent of the reach to establishing a system of collective redress. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>63 Many defendants value collective redress due to the finality of the action with no fear of subsequent <lb/>claims from affected individuals or a requirement to maintain a damages fund beyond the life of the <lb/>collective claim and appeals -see Francis E. McGovern, Distribution of Funds in Class Actions--<lb/>Claims Administration, 35 Journal of Corporation Law 123 (2009). <lb/>64 BEUC (2007) Private Group Actions -Taking Europe Forward. BEUC Reflections on a Future <lb/>European Collective Redress Scheme for Individual Damage Claims p. 15. Available at <lb/>http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/health_consumer/dgs_consultations/ca/replies_collective_redress_consultatio <lb/>n_en.htm. <lb/>65 See Albert A. Foer &amp; Jonathan W. Cuneo, Toward an Effective System of Private Enforcement in <lb/>Albert A. Foer &amp; Jonathan W. Cuneo (eds) The International Handbook on Private Enforcement of <lb/>Competition Law 605 (Edward Elgar Publishing 2010). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>financially rather than through other altruistic and value-based factors), litigation will <lb/>simply be an ineffective means of accessing rights. 66 As way of an example, the <lb/>Enterprise Act 2002 s.19 inserted into the Competition Act 1998 a new section <lb/>(s.47B) which provided for representative actions to be brought on behalf of <lb/>consumers. Under this legislation, the Consumer Association, on behalf of a few <lb/>hundred named individuals, brought proceedings against the retailer JJB Sports in a <lb/>follow-on 67 action by the Office for Fair Trading regarding price-fixing on the supply <lb/>of replica football shirts. The defendant settled, but the proportion of consumers who <lb/>joined the case compared to the number of consumers affected was very small, and <lb/>the value of the claim, compared to the costs of pursuing it, led to the Consumer <lb/>Association remarking that it would not bring a similar opt-in action again. 68 <lb/>The alternative mechanism available is where the affected individuals will <lb/>automatically form part of the collective action unless they declare and thereby affirm <lb/>that they wish to be excluded. This is the &apos;opt-out&apos; procedure. Each mechanism has <lb/>its benefits and drawbacks, and in the consultation process undertaken by the <lb/>Commission, and the feedback provided, the majority of respondents identified that <lb/>the opt-in mechanism was their preferred choice. The opt-out mechanism is widely <lb/>considered to be the more aggressive form of collective redress and may not be <lb/>particularly apt for situations of consumer protection / antitrust violations. Hence, the <lb/>overwhelming response in this respect by the respondents to the Commission&apos;s <lb/>consultation exercise, and the resultant Recommendation, selected the &apos;opt-in&apos; <lb/>model. Of course, State Liability is a different proposition and given that individuals <lb/>denied access to rights provided by the EU affects a clearly identifiable class (who <lb/>by their nature share a commonality) -such as workers when the situation involves <lb/>certain social policy laws -and the damages sustained will in many situations be <lb/>similar / identical to all the members of that class, the opt-out model should be <lb/>adopted (similar to that used in Denmark). It is ultimately more suitable for low value <lb/>claims and where individuals are unlikely to be aware that their rights have been <lb/>infringed or breached. This mechanism provides the most inclusive and appropriate <lb/>approach to enable access to justice and promoting accountability, transparency and <lb/>to incentivize compliance with EU obligations. Many citizens in the EU affected by <lb/>the breach of the Member State are poorly placed to opt-in to a class action claim, <lb/>they may have limited access to information, be socially isolated, or suffer health <lb/>problems that can be exacerbated by the stress of individually pursuing a claim <lb/>through the courts. Collective redress through a system of opt-out can reduce these <lb/>problems. <lb/>B. COLLECTIVE REDRESS -WHY NOT? <lb/>Criticisms of a system of collective redress, despite the existence of advantages to <lb/>both individuals and the Commission in ensuring access to EU rights and holding to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>66 ibid at 607-8. <lb/>67 A follow-on action occurs where an infringement of competition law has been found by a <lb/>competition authority (for example the European Commission and/or an industry-sector regulator). <lb/>The claimant must, however, demonstrate how the claim relates to his/her own case. For further <lb/>developments on this, and the boundaries for such claims, see Case C 557/12 Kone AG and others <lb/>v ÖBB-Infrastruktur AG 5 th June 2014. <lb/>68 As reported in The Law Society response to the EU Commission consultation document Towards a <lb/>Coherent European Approach to Collective Redress (2011), 9-10. Available at <lb/>http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/health_consumer/dgs_consultations/ca/replies_collective_redress_consultatio <lb/>n_en.htm. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>account those responsible for breaches, are numerous. The main criticisms to its <lb/>adoption in the EU, and particularly articulated in relation to anti-competition laws -<lb/>but in some instances could be applied to State Liability generally, include the <lb/>following. <lb/>(I) THE US MODEL WILL BE MIRRORED IN THE EU <lb/>The US is frequently presented as embodying the worst effects of a litigation <lb/>culture 69 where lawyers provoke abusive claims 70 (unlikely to be successful at trial) <lb/>and are the only &apos;beneficiaries&apos; of class actions. 71 Lazy generalisations critiquing <lb/>alternative methods of enforcement of rights are quite unhelpful when formulating a <lb/>new paradigm of access to justice and it would be unwise to consider that claims that <lb/>are unsuccessful or their outcome is uncertain are by their nature abusive. It is even <lb/>more so when individuals affected by the current system are those often least able to <lb/>protect themselves or to fund representation. It is without doubt that, in using the <lb/>model of the US as a comparator, some cases will have been heard in the US courts <lb/>which are without merit, which are abusive, and will be brought with the intent of a <lb/>settlement to be reached to avoid the litigation costs/judgment and costs of <lb/>discovery 72 and award of damages or due to the exposure to risk through multiple <lb/>claimants / treble damages awards and associated legal fees. 73 <lb/>However, in reality there are few if any meaningful, empirical bases on which <lb/>these arguments have been sustained. It is possible that meritless claims might be <lb/>initiated by the inexperienced (lawyer or claimants) or those who wish for a public <lb/>&apos;day in court&apos;. But this, along with abusive claims, can be effectively controlled <lb/>through judicial examination of the case and subsequent management. Damages <lb/>awards, in cases involving State Liability in the UK, based as they are on the hybrid <lb/>tort of breach of statutory duty, are hence not subject to the award of punitive <lb/>damages. The defendant in the case of State Liability actions will, naturally, be the <lb/>State and therefore will not suffer the damage of adverse competition or cases being <lb/>brought by a competitor seeking advantage through pursuing &apos;nuisance&apos; claims. <lb/>Fears that lawyers will merely take cases, which for individuals would be <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>69 See Deborah R. Hensler, Nicholas M. Pace, Bonnie Dombey-Moore, Elizabeth Giddens, Jennifer <lb/>Gross &amp; Erik Moller, Class Action Dilemmas: Pursuing Public Goals for Private Gains (RAND Institute <lb/>for <lb/>Civil <lb/>Justice <lb/>2000) <lb/>at <lb/>15-18, <lb/>available <lb/>at <lb/>http://www.rand.org/pubs/monograph_reports/MR969/index.html. <lb/>70 For example, in the US, Rule 11 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure was established to ensure <lb/>that claims presented in federal courts have merit (are not frivolous) and are not brought for an <lb/>improper purpose -although see Julia K. Cowles, Rule 11 of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure and <lb/>the Duty to Withdraw a Baseless Pleading, 56 Fordham Law Review 697, 700 (1988) for a <lb/>demonstration of the general lack of effectiveness of the Rule in deterring such claims and how US <lb/>class action claims fails to lead to benefits to the claimants (consumers and citizens). <lb/>71 Whilst it is frequently noted that private individuals to class action claims rarely obtain a meaningful <lb/>remedy whilst lawyers representing the group obtain very large payments for their services, see Brian <lb/>T. Fitzpatrick, An Empirical Study of Class Action Settlements and their Fee Awards, 7 Journal of <lb/>Empirical Legal Studies 811 (2010) and Theodore Eisenberg &amp; Geoffrey P. Miller, Attorney Fees and <lb/>Expenses in Class Action Settlements: 1993-2008, 7 Journal of Empirical Legal Studies 248, 262, 265 <lb/>(2010) which demonstrated that lawyers&apos; fees were 12% for cases where recovery of damages <lb/>exceeded $175.5 million (and 23% for claims involving significant smaller awards). <lb/>72 Referred to &apos;nuisance settlements theory&apos;, see Brief of the American Bar Association as Amicus <lb/>Curiae in Support of Neither Petitioners Nor Respondents at 10-11, Bell Atl. Corp. v Twombly, 550 US <lb/>544 (2007) (No. 05-1126). <lb/>73 Referred to as &apos;hydraulic pressure theory&apos;, see Charles B. Casper, The Class Action Fairness Act&apos;s <lb/>Impact on Settlements, 20 Antitrust 26 (2005). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>uneconomic to pursue, and will lead to an opening of the floodgates, have not <lb/>materialised in jurisdictions where collective redress is available. Further, to prevent <lb/>some form of unjust enrichment or unethical practice being pursued, the UK could <lb/>adopt a &apos;cy pres&apos; system where residual money from the award of damages can be <lb/>used in specified mechanisms to assist in achieving the aims of the claim (i.e. the <lb/>basis of the action), as opposed to being returned to the defendant or being retained <lb/>by the lawyers. <lb/>The legal systems of the US compared with those within the EU are different <lb/>and the procedural rules in which they operate are sufficiently distinct to prevent any <lb/>potential for reflected negative consequences. Juries do not assess the quantum of <lb/>damages, members of the judiciary are not elected, contingency fee arrangements <lb/>limit the fees recoverable by lawyers and damages are based on losses incurred in <lb/>prescribed areas. As such, concerns that the Member States in the EU will find their <lb/>legal systems inundated with spurious and speculative claims appear unfounded. <lb/>The Commission recognised the potential problem of directly following the US <lb/>model (or attracting unfavourable comparisons) and as such suggested use of an <lb/>opt-in model in its Recommendation which necessitates a deliberate action to <lb/>become a party to the class of litigants in the case. The UK&apos;s Consumer Rights Act <lb/>2015, 74 however, despite the arguments presented above, enables collective redress <lb/>in anti-competitive / anti-trust cases 75 following a more &apos;radical&apos; opt-out model. 76 Not <lb/>only does the UK appear to be leading the way in this regard, fears of developing a <lb/>US-style litigation culture seem to be ill-founded. <lb/>(II) THE AGGREGATION AND AMPLIFICATION EFFECT <lb/>Opponents to the use of collective redress often point to the existence of the <lb/>aggregation effect 77 and the resultant possibility of abuse. Collective redress enables <lb/>individuals who would otherwise be unable to seek access to their rights due to the <lb/>limitations of high costs and low financial &apos;rewards&apos; to challenge wrongdoing. <lb/>However, it is argued, this aggregation (including possibly tens / hundreds of <lb/>thousands of weak claims) may in effect change substantive rights due to <lb/>defendants settling claims where the mere possibility of an adverse ruling could <lb/>result in potentially significant compensation payments (regardless of the merits of <lb/>the claim); and, it is argued from a consumer / antitrust perspective, that such <lb/>aggregation may result in a disincentive for firms to operate businesses in a Member <lb/>State where they could be exposed to collective redress claims and be subject to <lb/>expensive litigation. This would be to the detriment of the citizens of the Member <lb/>State who benefit from the legitimate activities of businesses but which may choose <lb/>not to operate in the Member State due to this fear. <lb/>However, collective redress, despite the aggregation effect, does have the <lb/>ability to persuade the defendant to seek the use of alternative forms of dispute <lb/>resolution and/or the settlement of the claims prior to court action on the basis of the <lb/>improved bargaining position achieved by the claimants. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">74 Which gives effect to the provisions of the Recommendation regarding collective redress in relation <lb/>to breach of anti-trust / competition laws. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>75 See Schedule 8, Part 1. <lb/>76 A limited right for representative groups / trade associations to take action on behalf of consumers, <lb/>on an opt-out basis, through an amended Competition Act 1998 (s.47B). <lb/>77 See Richard A. Epstein, Class Actions: Aggregation, Amplification and Distortion, University of <lb/>Chicago Legal Forum, 475 (2003). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Through the aggregation of claimants&apos; loss, individuals may have suffered <lb/>greater or lesser loss but are still part of the same collective action. This is true in <lb/>relation to anti-competitive laws, but the disparity in redress through damages <lb/>becomes more apparent when considered in the wider context of EU law generally, <lb/>and particularly in social policy laws where, for example, protective awards are made <lb/>in relation to the lack of effective consultation prior to redundancies, 78 potential <lb/>breaches of an individual&apos;s right to enforce a maximum working week, 79 and, of <lb/>much greater significance in this regard, an individual who may have suffered some <lb/>form of discrimination at work. 80 Where these breaches are effective due to inaction <lb/>or incorrect transposition of EU law by a Member State, aggregating losses <lb/>sustained through adherence to strict quantification criteria could prove to be <lb/>problematic, and further, where there are potentially many thousands of individuals <lb/>affected, the prospective claim for damages against the State could be so <lb/>prohibitively expensive, that a court would not feel capable of imposing such a <lb/>judgment. Indeed, potential losses sustained through the breach of EU law and <lb/>where the Member State is considered liable under torts law, could dwarf any fine or <lb/>imposition of sanctions available to the EU. A safeguard, which would by necessity <lb/>have to be incorporated into any such enforcement mechanism, would be the <lb/>discretion of the courts to reject legal actions or to limit the maximum compensation <lb/>awarded. That of course leads to the unenviable situation whereby the greater the <lb/>damage sustained by individuals and the more flagrant abuse by a recalcitrant <lb/>Member State, the less likely that full damages would be available. <lb/>Under the existing system of individual actions, such claims will, by necessity, <lb/>be heard in different courts with the possible and likely result that different <lb/>conclusions (judgments) will be drawn between the various court cases. This leads <lb/>to a reduction in any (rolled-up) awards being made against the defendant. With <lb/>collective redress, the individual claims are collated into a single action with the <lb/>&apos;gamble&apos; for the defendant that an adverse ruling could have financially devastating <lb/>results (the amplification effect). The UK Competition Law Association cite the US <lb/>case Rhone-Poulenc where Judge Posner remarked on the situation where perhaps <lb/>as few as 8% of the claimants in this class action would likely satisfy the tests to <lb/>establish the liability of the defendant and there was &apos;great likelihood that the <lb/>plaintiffs&apos; claims… lack(ed) legal merit.&apos; 81 However, the US Supreme Court <lb/>acknowledged the significance of class actions as a mechanism to facilitate <lb/>claimants to pool resources, they are &apos;peculiarly appropriate&apos; where the &apos;issues <lb/>involved are common to the class as a whole&apos; 82 and they enable an &apos;opportunity to <lb/>save the enormous transaction costs of piecemeal litigation.&apos; 83 <lb/>(III) DETERRENCE DOES NOT WORK <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>78 USDAW v Ethel Austin Ltd (In Administration) [2013] UKEAT/0547/12/KN, and USDAW and Wilson v <lb/>Unite the Union, WW Realisation 1 Ltd and Secretary of State for Business, Innovation &amp; Skills [2013] <lb/>UKEAT/0548/12/KN. <lb/>79 Case C-484/04 Commission v United Kingdom [2006] IRLR 888. <lb/>80 Compare the approaches taken in Rowstock Ltd v Jessemey [2013] ICR 807 and Onu v Akwiwu &amp; <lb/>Anor [2013] ICR 1039 and the necessity of judicial acrobatics to comply with EU law. <lb/>81 UK Competition Law Association (2011) Response to European Commission&apos;s Consultation on <lb/>Collective Redress www.competitionlawassociation.com (ukmatters: 18238974.3) April, 2.3(b). <lb/>82 Califano v Yamasaki, 442 US 682, 701 (1979). <lb/>83 Ortiz v Fibreboard Corp., 527 US 815, 860 (1999). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>One of the main arguments for collective redress being applied to cases of State <lb/>Liability is the ability of individuals to access their rights, and to deter Member States <lb/>from breaching their EU obligations. A cautionary note regarding the efficacy of the <lb/>deterrence effect of collective redress can be seen when considered from the <lb/>perspective of the developments in consumer protection and anti-trust actions. <lb/>Hodges remarks that: <lb/>most of the UK cases have involved industries that are already heavily <lb/>regulated. 84 There is no evidence in those cases that regulation was <lb/>inappropriate or ineffective or that the corporations would have acted any <lb/>differently at the relevant times. If that is so, the argument for indirect <lb/>regulation by threat of litigation, as a complementary mechanism to direct <lb/>regulation… looks weak, unnecessarily duplicative, and wasteful of resources. <lb/>If litigation does produce change, it seems to be a very costly way of doing <lb/>so. 85 <lb/>This argument has been challenged in the US courts, 86 but it is also true that <lb/>deterrence may &apos;remain far from optimal due to three remaining problems: the <lb/>rational apathy on the side of individual victims (in particular, those who suffered trifle <lb/>damage), problems to finance the claim and the risk of free-riding, which may equally <lb/>reduce the number of claims brought below the efficient level.&apos; 87 Further, whilst <lb/>industries may be regulated, transposition of directives remains the duty of the State <lb/>and inaction or misapplication in this area negatively impacts on an individual who is <lb/>dependent on an accessible legal system through which to seek redress. The distinct <lb/>nature of State Liability in this respect negates the arguments relating to the <lb/>ineffectiveness of deterrence in collective actions. <lb/>C. COLLECTIVE REDRESS AND DETERRENCE <lb/>A significant argument for the adoption of a form of collective redress against <lb/>Member States, and not simply limited to cases of anti-trust / competition laws, is <lb/>that Member States are charged with the responsibility of transposing correctly and <lb/>on time EU laws in the form of directives. There are mechanisms in place to protect <lb/>a Member State that innocently fails in the correct transposition, and the EU provides <lb/>Member States with sufficient time in order to comply with the judicious transposition <lb/>of the law. Given the safeguards, Member States that fail in their duty should be <lb/>subject to sanctions and these have traditionally been through complaints <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>84 This is true, but it is also quite evident that public methods of fining companies for breaches of the <lb/>law have, often, been largely ineffective in controlling bad behavior, have not led to a deterrence to <lb/>many large companies, and there is certainly not an over-deterrence that some commentators have <lb/>suggested could be the ultimate result of regulation through collective redress. See Centre for <lb/>European Policy Studies et al., Making Antitrust Damages Actions More Effective in the EU: Welfare <lb/>Impact and Potential Scenarios, at 28, Contract DG Comp/2006/A3/012 final (Dec. 21, 2007). <lb/>85 Christopher Hodges, Multi-Party Actions: A European Approach, Duke Journal of Comparative and <lb/>International Law 321, 341 (2001). <lb/>86 To counteract the potential problems of the deterrence effect of collective redress, the US Supreme <lb/>Court identified that &apos;the purpose of giving private parties treble-damage and injunctive remedies was <lb/>not merely to provide private relief, but was to serve as well the high purpose of enforcing the antitrust <lb/>laws&apos; Zenith Radio Corp. v Hazeltine Research, Inc. 395 US 100, 130-31 (1969). <lb/>87 Centre for European Policy Studies et al., Making Antitrust Damages Actions More Effective in the <lb/>EU: Welfare Impact and Potential Scenarios, at 28, Contract DG Comp/2006/A3/012 final (Dec. 21, <lb/>2007), 301. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>procedures initiated by or through the Commission. Member States will be aware <lb/>that sanctions for breach of EU law have traditionally been limited, the Commission <lb/>lacks in many cases the ability and resources to effectively monitor 28 Member <lb/>States and the plethora of laws and legal areas in which the EU has competence, <lb/>and enforcement by individuals through State Liability has been established since <lb/>1991, but relatively few cases have been brought before the courts and even fewer <lb/>have been successful. 88 Indeed it is well remembered that Mr Francovich failed in his <lb/>own seminal case of establishing State Liability. 89 Given these few examples <lb/>provided to illustrate the limitations of the effectiveness of State Liability as a means <lb/>of ensuring compliance with EU law, is it any wonder that Member States may take a <lb/>rational view that where compliance with EU law may be ideologically, politically or <lb/>financially repugnant, the sanctions for breach (if and when such a breach is <lb/>discovered and actioned) would not dissuade them from such activity? Collective <lb/>redress enables a mechanism of cost-internalisation for the wrong-doer to exist <lb/>which is necessary as currently, there is little in the way of practical deterrence 90 that <lb/>would compel a Member State to comply with its EU obligations against its will or <lb/>judgement. This follows the optimal deterrence model established by Gary Becker <lb/>who identified the cost that deterrence requires from both public and private <lb/>resources, but such costs have to be addressed in relation to the seriousness of the <lb/>breach and its effects on society. 91 This is by the very nature of the model, the <lb/>optimal aspect. 100% compliance with the law by a Member State is unlikely, if at all <lb/>possible (or indeed desirable -it may prove to be inefficient to devote the necessary <lb/>resources to provide compliance at this level). What is required is enforcement that <lb/>provides an equilibrium between the costs and benefits to the individuals, society, <lb/>the Member States and the EU as a collective body. The consensus 92 appears to be, <lb/>however, that whilst deterrence is an important aspect of collective redress, 93 this <lb/>should not extend to the award of punitive damages. 94 It has been remarked that <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>88 See fn. 23. <lb/></listBibl><note place="footnote">89 Here, Francovich used a domestic industrial relations, rather than a more appropriate civil claims, <lb/>procedure -although the Italian legal system appeared not to know which was the designated <lb/>procedure to use in such a case. <lb/></note><listBibl>90 Deterrence can be exhibited in many ways, including negative publicity and the effects on <lb/>reputation, whilst also encompassing financial penalties which may have a broader effect on private <lb/>organisations involved in wrongdoing. As a way of an example of the effectiveness of this second <lb/>example of the deterrent effect of collective interests, Lande and Davis, citing results of an empirical <lb/>research project involving 40 private anti-trust class-action claims in the US, found that the amounts <lb/>recovered in damages by private individuals exceeded the aggregate amount of fines imposed by <lb/>public bodies in the same period of time. Robert H. Lande &amp; Joshua P. Davis, Benefits from Private <lb/>Antitrust Enforcement: An Analysis of Forty Cases, 42 University of San Francisco Law Review 879, <lb/>906 (2008). <lb/>91 See Catherine M. Sharkey, Punitive Damages as Societal Damages, 113 Yale Law Journal 347 <lb/>(2003). <lb/>92 However -see Francis E. McGovern, Punitive Damages and Class Actions, 70 Louisiana Law <lb/>Review 435, 462 (2010) for an opposite view &apos;Whether called &quot;economic,&quot; &quot;extra compensatory,&quot; <lb/>&quot;exemplary,&quot; or &quot;punitive,&quot; these global damages would result in tortious defendants being held <lb/>responsible for all the harm they cause rather than only the subset of harm calculated from the <lb/>damages won by opportunistic plaintiffs.&apos; <lb/>93 It is seen as a mechanism not so concerned with the compensation of claimants&apos; losses but <lb/>principally aimed at retribution and deterring wrongful / harmful conduct -Exxon Shipping Co. v <lb/>Baker, 128 Ct. 2605, 2621 (2008). <lb/>94 Punitive damages should only be awarded in cases where the defendant&apos;s actions have been so <lb/>reprehensible as to warrant &apos;advanced&apos; sanction and punishment -State Farm Mut. Auto Ins. Co. v <lb/>Campbell, 538 U.S. 408, 427 (2003). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>punitive damages is analogous with the fines imposed following conviction of a <lb/>criminal offence. 95 <lb/>It is also feasible that without appropriate redress and sanctioning of the <lb/>wrong-doer, the wrong-doing activities are continued and a state of underdeterrence <lb/>is established. Examples of continued incorrect transposition of directives by the UK <lb/>are numerous and the inability of redress through State Liability has perpetuated this <lb/>state of affairs. McGovern 96 provides an overview of this problem and demonstrates <lb/>the various difficulties that belie the availability of State Liability in its use and effect: <lb/>A problem of underdeterrence can arise in the context of mass tortious activity… <lb/>From the perspective of society as a whole, if a defendant faces litigation from <lb/>only ten to twenty percent of the plaintiffs who are tortiously harmed-a normal <lb/>range of lawsuit filings-then that defendant will underinvest… because it is not <lb/>fully benefitting from the avoidance of liability resulting from an optimal <lb/>investment. If only twenty percent of injured plaintiffs sue, then the defendants <lb/>will be responsible for only twenty percent of the damages and will, therefore, <lb/>invest less… to correspond with the lower benefit of the avoided [incident]. 97 <lb/>There have been relatively few cases of State Liability actions in the UK since 1991, <lb/>and even where cases have been successfully argued, awards of damages are <lb/>applied to the individual claimant. If one takes social policy law as an example, EU <lb/>social policy directives often affect many millions of workers in the UK, the UK <lb/>government may not be particularly concerned over potential legal action for its <lb/>breach of the law under the current structure of procedural limitations, court fees and <lb/>requirement that each claimant brings his or her claim individually. Collective <lb/>redress, particularly one adopting an opt-out model, may redress this imbalance by <lb/>facilitating cases more readily through the courts and any subsequent award of <lb/>damages against the defaulting State could be multiplied many thousands of times to <lb/>the class of claimants to the action. Collective redress could prove to be a <lb/>substantial weapon in defending individual workers&apos; rights. <lb/>V. GIVING EFFECT TO COLLECTIVE REDRESS IN STATE LIABILITY <lb/>To begin, a significant issue to overcome in adopting a system of collective redress <lb/>in State Liability is of ensuring adherence to the principles of primacy and national <lb/>procedural autonomy. EU law is supreme over inconsistent domestic law (EU law <lb/>has primacy) although the application of EU law has been decentralised to the <lb/>Member States. Individuals enjoy the right to claim compensation for breaches of EU <lb/>law but the details of facilitating such claims are subject to national procedural law. <lb/>The concern occurs where there is friction between the requirement to adhere to EU <lb/>law and any existing national procedure which may prevent its effective application. <lb/>In an attempt to avoid obvious tensions that may exist, the Court of Justice has <lb/>conditioned the use of national procedural rules to comply with EU law on the basis <lb/>of the principles of equivalence and effectiveness. Equivalence requires that national <lb/>procedural rules governing a dispute with an EU law dimension may not be less <lb/>favourable than those governing domestic disputes. As effectiveness necessitates <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>95 Browning-Ferris Indus. of Vt., Inc. v Kelco Disposal, 492 U.S. 257, 275 (1989). <lb/>96 Fn 92. <lb/>97 ibid at 452-453. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>the right to effective judicial protection, 98 individuals must have access to the <lb/>application of EU law, and appropriate systems of judicial review and supervision. <lb/>The principle of effectiveness has led to issues relating to access to courts and <lb/>judicial proceedings, 99 legal aid, 100 national rules on standing, 101 and the use of <lb/>mandatory out-of-court dispute resolution procedures 102 (to name but a few). It is <lb/>clear that effectiveness enjoys a broad approach in interpretation by the Court of <lb/>Justice, and this may extend to effective access where individual litigation may prove <lb/>practically inaccessible. <lb/>Therefore, it is reasonable to conclude that the current system of access to <lb/>EU law and to domestic remedies exists. Primacy of EU law in this regard is not in <lb/>question, it is the application of national rules, along with national procedural <lb/>autonomy, that is being examined. There is no denying that an individual with <lb/>sufficient resources, be that personal or through association with a supporting body, <lb/>has the ability to seek damages against a Member State for breach of EU law. What <lb/>has been presented so far is a brief overview of the potential problems that exist for <lb/>individuals seeking access to courts and access to awards of damages. This is not <lb/>the same as what has been termed a direct collision between EU law and national <lb/>procedural rules. Rather, this exemplifies the indirect collision whereby national <lb/>procedural rules can essentially hinder the effect of access to EU law. Primacy 103 <lb/>does not provide an adequate solution as there is no incompatibility of national law <lb/>which can be set aside to give greater access and effectiveness to the EU law <lb/>sought. Therefore the argument being presented requires the assistance and <lb/>cooperation of Member States to give greater effectiveness to EU law through <lb/>national courts. This has been achieved through the Commission Recommendation <lb/>in relation to collective redress for anti-competitive behaviour, and it is possible that <lb/>Member States, in good faith, could realise the effectiveness of damages for <lb/>individuals affected by the breach of EU law through its own action or inaction, and <lb/>given the strict and literal approach to future transposition to be taken, as promised <lb/>by the government, it would by necessity only be the most flagrant breaches of EU <lb/>law which would satisfy the &apos;sufficiently serious breach&apos; to establish the culpability of <lb/>the State and the award of damages. <lb/>If a system of collective redress can overcome a major barrier to the accessibility of <lb/>State Liability, with its power to compel action on the part of Member States whilst <lb/>deterring malpractice or intransigence, what form should it take? Three bodies that <lb/>could take the necessary action are the Commission, the Member States <lb/>themselves, or the Court of Justice. Using a legislative or case law approach, each <lb/>would have benefits and drawbacks, and whilst it is beyond the scope of this article <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>98 Sacha Prechal &amp; Rob J.G.M. Widdershoven, Effectiveness or Effective Judicial Protection: A Poorly <lb/>Articulated Relationship, in: Tristan Baumé et al. (eds.), Today&apos;s Multi-layered Legal Order: Current <lb/>Issues and Perspectives, 283 (Zutphen: Paris 2011). <lb/>99 Case C-268/06 Impact v Minister for Agriculture and Food and others [2008] E.C.R. I-2483. <lb/>100 Case C-279/09 DEB v Germany [2010] E.C.R. I-13849. <lb/>101 Case C-12/08 Mono Car Styling SA (in liquidation) v Odemis and others [2009] E.C.R. I-6653. <lb/>102 Joined Cases C-317/08 to C-320/08 Alassini and Others v Telecom Italia [2010] E.C.R. I-2213, <lb/>and Case C-418/11 Texdata Software GmbH [2013] ECR I-0000. <lb/>103 For a broader discussion of primacy and procedural autonomy see René Barents, The Precedence <lb/>of EU Law from the Perspective of Constitutional Pluralism, 5 European Constitutional Law Review, 5, <lb/>421 (2009), and Koen Lenaerts &amp; Tim Corthaut, Of Birds and Hedges: the Role of Primacy in Invoking <lb/>Norms of EU Law, 31 European Law Review, 287 (2006). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>to critique each in the depth necessary to do justice to such discussion, 104 it is <lb/>sufficient at this point to outline the most significant aspects. <lb/>The most likely form collective redress would take is through legislative action <lb/>from the Commission (supported by subsequent judicial action through the Court of <lb/>Justice and national courts). As has been seen, in respect of competition law and the <lb/>protection of consumers, the Commission had identified problems in the availability <lb/>of damages and enforcement generally: <lb/>despite the requirement to establish an effective legal framework turning <lb/>exercising the right to damages into a realistic possibility, and although there <lb/>have recently been some signs of improvement in certain Member States, to date <lb/>in practice victims of EC anti-trust infringements only rarely obtain reparation for <lb/>the harm suffered. 105 <lb/>The Commission called 106 for Member States to introduce a system of injunctive and <lb/>compensatory collective redress mechanisms in domestic law with a deadline of July <lb/>26, 2015. Being a Recommendation, and requesting implementation, did not <lb/>establish any compulsion on Member States to transpose this initiative into domestic <lb/>law. However, the Commission stated that it would evaluate the status of collective <lb/>redress laws in the Member States after a four-year period. Even at this stage, given <lb/>the details provided by the Commission and the request for Member States to adopt <lb/>this Recommendation, it is considered to be a mere intermediate step 107 and that <lb/>certainly within the four-year period, the Commission will be establishing a directive <lb/>to ensure collective redress is part of the legal systems of Member States when <lb/>protecting consumers generally and anti-trust / competition laws in particular. Many <lb/>Member States already had collective redress mechanisms in place in their legal <lb/>systems prior to the Recommendation and, unsurprisingly, there has been a quiet <lb/>acceptance to the aims of the Commission in this regard. On 12 June 2013, following <lb/>the Recommendation, the UK began consultation on its draft Consumer Rights Bill <lb/>which, among others, sought to establish a system of enforcement of consumer and <lb/>competition laws utilising, in part, collective redress (and collective settlement) as a <lb/>vehicle for access to justice. <lb/>This form of collective redress was realised in England and Wales in 2015 <lb/>through the Consumer Rights Act. This is a very positive first step, and through <lb/>utilising an opt-out model, it demonstrates a movement towards seeing the value of <lb/>collective redress in combating wrong-doing, providing access to justice, and <lb/>deterring actions which seek to provide a competitive advantage deriving from <lb/>malfeasance or abuse. The government was not obliged to follow the <lb/>Recommendation, and the fact that both the EU and the UK have voluntarily entered <lb/>into the spirit of access to rights and access to justice through a mechanism of <lb/>collective redress, albeit in relation to competition laws, must be viewed as a <lb/>potential willingness to progress this to other areas. The opt-out model chosen by <lb/>the UK in Schedule 8 of the Consumer Rights Act to transpose the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">104 Such detailed discussion will be provided in the second part to this article. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>105 White Paper on Damages Actions for Breach of the EC Antitrust Rules COM (2008) 165 final (2 <lb/>April 2008) 1.1, at [2]. <lb/>106 Draft Commission Recommendation on common principles for injunction and compensatory <lb/>collective redress mechanisms in the Member States concerning violations of rights granted under <lb/>Union Law, C (2013) 3539/3, 11 June 2013. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">107 As the Recommendation procedure is not binding, but is of politically persuasive force. <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>Recommendation, offers potentially greater benefits for individuals (and competitors) <lb/>than may have been achieved through an opt-in model. Deterrence will likely be <lb/>greater, as will facilitating the functioning of the internal market. <lb/>A. ESTABLISHING THE RULES OF COLLECTIVE ACTIONS IN STATE LIABILITY <lb/>Extending the argument for collective redress to State Liability will necessitate <lb/>legislative action by the EU rather than relying on the Member States or indeed the <lb/>Court of Justice to take up such an initiative. Member States would and have <lb/>demonstrated differing approaches to such access, and whilst they may be willing to <lb/>accede to the necessity for collective redress when preventing the worst examples of <lb/>anti-competitive behavior, whether Member States would willingly establish a system <lb/>which makes it easier for claims against them due to their own transgression of EU <lb/>law is unlikely at best. A Regulation or directive would be required to compel <lb/>adherence and &apos;acceptance&apos; of a system of collective redress in this area. <lb/>Further, collective redress would likely be subject to limitations and <lb/>restrictions on the bodies empowered to bring such claims; be subject to strict <lb/>deadlines; 108 rules of quantification and limitations to the awards of damages would <lb/>be essential for the efficacy of a system of collective redress in areas of competence <lb/>such as social policy; and it would have to require Member States to provide access <lb/>to documents and evidence regarding consultations and discussion 109 culminating in <lb/>the transposition of a directive -subject to a balancing of the rights and legitimate <lb/>interests of the State and the claimants (possibly exercised by the Court of <lb/>Justice). 110 Despite the discovery rules in England and Wales which are broad, <lb/>especially when compared to the requirements established by the Commission in <lb/>relation to anti-competition enforcement, it may also necessitate the adoption of an <lb/>exception to the general rules on burden of proof by adopting legal presumption. <lb/>This situation would benefit the claimants who may not have access to materials and <lb/>evidence 111 through which to substantiate a prima facie assertion -although the <lb/>presumption is defeated through (even weak) evidence. Finally, collective redress <lb/>would be governed through the application of strict procedural rules to ensure control <lb/>of the activities of claimants and their representatives. 112 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">108 Such as an EU-based, not less than five-year, limitation period in which claims may be lodged, <lb/>given the disparity in limitation periods for damages actions between the Member States. <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>109 Although, given the often long periods between enactment of a national implementing law and a <lb/>subsequent analysis of judicial enquiry in a related claim, gathering sufficient information to <lb/>demonstrate the State&apos;s deliberate non-compliance can be problematic -see Delaney v Secretary of <lb/>State [2014] EWHC 1785 (QB) paras 94-101. <lb/>110 Per Case C-536-11 Bundeswettbewerbsbehorde v Donau Chemie AG and others (2013) E.C.R. I-<lb/>0000, paras 46 and 47. <lb/>111 In an opinion delivered on 7 February 2013 in Donau Chemie (n 89) A-G Jääskinen stated: &apos;… the <lb/>principle of effective judicial protection laid down in Article 47 of the Charter comprises various <lb/>elements; in particular, the rights of the defence, the principle of equality of arms, the right of access <lb/>to a tribunal and the right to be advised, defended and represented… Hence, limiting availability of <lb/>critical evidential material undermines the right of litigants to a judicial determination of their dispute. It <lb/>also impacts on their rights to bring cases effectively.&apos; (paras 52 and 53). <lb/>112 As in the US, for example, with the US Federal Rules of Civil Procedure which at Rule 23(a) <lb/>provides for the satisfaction of four criteria applicable to all class action claims (see Amchem Prods. v <lb/>Windsor, 521 US 591, 613 (1997): 1) the numerosity of the class; a commonality of the class in <lb/>relation to questions of law or fact; 3) a typicality of the class members&apos; claim; and 4) adequacy of the <lb/>legal representation afforded the members of the class in relation to their interests. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>In relation to those rules necessary to substantiate claims, it is likely that rules <lb/>similar to those established for anti-competition law, 113 based as they are on a <lb/>breach of statutory duty, would be followed. This has been particularly successful in <lb/>areas such as enforcement and obtaining damages in workplace health and <lb/>safety. 114 Having breached the statutory duty (due to non-or (sufficiently serious) <lb/>incorrect transposition) which has caused the claimants damage/loss (through denial <lb/>of protective employment rights for example), the first two tests are satisfied. The <lb/>remaining tests require the claimant to establish that the legislator intended to create <lb/>a private right of action and fourthly, that the statute sought to protect the victim <lb/>against the damage suffered. <lb/>Despite the objection of using breach of statutory duty to facilitate the award <lb/>of a civil remedy for a failing on the part of a legislator, which may for example cause <lb/>&apos;an undesirable potential for conflict between governmental discretion and the private <lb/>right of enforcement&apos;, 115 a Member State has the capacity to safeguard its position <lb/>and limit exposure to unreasonable and unsustainable damages actions by multiple <lb/>claimants. It may choose to explicitly avoid the award of damages (unless <lb/>unequivocally provided for in the relevant EU parent law) by placing into the <lb/>transposing legislation, and making available, a system of compensation or other <lb/>remedies which are &apos;no less accessible&apos;. This would thus avoid the requirement for <lb/>State Liability claims from the outset by making an alternative form of remedy <lb/>available to all (multiple) claimants. Protection in this area has also been provided to <lb/>Member States where, for example, broad discretion as to the requirements of <lb/>transposition of EU law is present. 116 In Dillenkofer v Federal Republic of <lb/>Germany, 117 as there was little doubt what the directive required, the fact that <lb/>Germany failed in its transposition duties resulted in a finding of liability on the part of <lb/>the State due to the lack of discretion. Further, where the State has made a genuine, <lb/>albeit mistaken attempt at transposition, liability will not be established unless the <lb/>misunderstanding was cynical or egregious. 118 <lb/>A successful claim of breach of statutory duty requires satisfaction of the test <lb/>that the relevant statute intended to protect victims against the kind of damage <lb/>suffered. Claimants seeking redress under laws established through the EU&apos;s social <lb/>policy competence, for example, are likely to be well placed to demonstrate they fall <lb/>under the specific class of persons to whom legislation sought to protect. Further, <lb/>establishing that claimants possessed the standing for the purposes of satisfying the <lb/>requirement of being in a class who are protected from the kind of damage suffered <lb/>is not subject to a maximum, hence multiple claimants seeking collective redress in <lb/>one legal action would not be a bar to a claim, 119 insofar as they are an ascertainable <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>113 J. S. Davidson &apos;Actions for Damages in the English Courts for Breach of EEC Competition Law&apos; <lb/>(1985) 34(1) International and Comparative Law Quarterly 183. <lb/>114 Margaret Fordham, Breach of Statutory Duty: A Diminishing Tort, Singapore Journal of Legal <lb/>Studies 370 (1996). <lb/>115 Barry J. Rodger &amp; Angus MacCulloch, Community Competition Law Enforcement, Deregulation <lb/>and Re-regulation: The Commission, National Authorities and Private Enforcement, 4(3) Columbia <lb/>Journal of European Law 610 (1998). <lb/>116 See Case C-392/93 R v HM Treasury, ex parte BT [1996] QB 615) and the commentary of the <lb/>Court of Justice in Brasserie du Pêcheur (see paras 43 and 44). <lb/>117 Joined Cases C-178, 179 and 188-190/94 Dillenkofer v Federal Republic of Germany [1996] <lb/>E.C.R. I-4845. <lb/>118 See R (on the application of Negassi) v Secretary of State for the Home Department [2013] EWCA <lb/>Civ 15. <lb/>119 Roe v Sheffield City Council [2004] QB 653. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>class. The final issue, and most problematic, is of the specific head of damages. This <lb/>will likely prove to be the most significant issue for collective redress through breach <lb/>of statutory duty. Awards of damages as compensation for physical injury are not <lb/>uncommon, whereas awards for economic losses have generally been much more <lb/>restrictive, 120 and will likely be the only remedy sought for the State&apos;s Liability in <lb/>transposing EU law. Foreseeability and remoteness have effectively limited the <lb/>extension of economic losses as being recoverable in isolation of physical loss <lb/>(which is deemed foreseeable) for many reasons, the floodgates argument being <lb/>central to limiting the number of claimants and the defendant&apos;s exposure to risk <lb/>(which would be significant in cases involving social policy laws and workers) and <lb/>that economic loss involves an unreasonable level of speculation. To remove any <lb/>uncertainty, and the associated &apos;speculative&apos; dimension to economic loss, legislative <lb/>action would remove doubt and establish clear rules regarding its application <lb/>throughout the Member States. Crehan 121 established the English courts approach to <lb/>bending the rules regarding the requirement of foreseeability to facilitate a successful <lb/>claim for economic loss. Similarly, the Commission could also legislate to enable <lb/>discretion for national courts to find recovery for economic loss and to enable their <lb/>calculation of any subsequent awards to be based on factual circumstances. <lb/>As has been demonstrated in this article, there are several examples of the <lb/>limited effectiveness of State Liability in its current form. This is despite the judicial <lb/>activism of the Court of Justice. The Commission, by assessing the impact of the <lb/>Recommendation, and in subsequently developing the expected directive on <lb/>collective redress for breaches of competition law, has demonstrated a willingness to <lb/>legislate. This is despite the potential constitutional problems this may present. More <lb/>broadly than the UK, there are potential problems for some Member States 122 in the <lb/>nature of a general system of collective redress which binds individuals to a legal <lb/>action and subsequent judgment to which they did not take part, make any outward <lb/>step in which to be involved, and in which the individual did not have the possibility to <lb/>intervene. The opt-out model is certainly a welcome movement by the UK and would <lb/>be a necessity when introducing collective redress for State Liability. The traditional <lb/>inter partes method of litigation needs to be reassessed when considering an <lb/>effective means of holding the State to account for breaches of EU law and whilst <lb/>constitutional rights may be impinged, and associated complexity would be <lb/>introduced through opt-out claims, the benefits for individuals, largely denied any <lb/>meaningful access to State Liability and reliant as they currently are on action <lb/>through the Commission to hold a Member State to account, outweigh these <lb/>potential problems. This point is not made flippantly, but a new paradigm for effective <lb/>rights management and enforcement is required if the new legal order of the EU, 123 <lb/>first enshrined in 1963, is to be effected across the Member States. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>120 In torts if not contract, as famously seen in Spartan Steel &amp; Alloys Ltd v Martin &amp; Co (Contractors) <lb/>Ltd [1973] 1 QB 27 which demonstrates the requirement for economic losses as recoverable when <lb/>associated with physical loss. However, Hedley Byrne &amp; Co Ltd v Heller &amp; Partners Ltd [1964] AC 465 <lb/>stands as the exception here. <lb/>121 Crehan v Inntreprenneur Pub Co [2004] EWCA Civ 637. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="footnote">122 For example the German Constitution where no general collective redress mechanism exists. The <lb/>German Code of Civil Procedure is focused on two party claims although an opt-out settlement <lb/>system was inserted into the Capital Market Model Claims Act (Kapitalanleger -<lb/>Musterverfahrensgesetz (KapMuG)). <lb/></note>
	  
	  <listBibl>123 Case 26/62 Van Gend en Loos v Nederlandse Administratie der Belastingen [1963] E.C.R. 1, <lb/>[1963] CMLR 105. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>With the Commission&apos;s Recommendation, and the subsequent UK response <lb/>through the Consumer Rights Act 2015, it appears a definite move towards collective <lb/>protection and enabling greater access to justice is taking place. The UK has gone <lb/>further than necessary to hold wrong-doers in the field of competition law to account <lb/>and facilitate a class of affected individuals&apos; access to their rights. It can only be <lb/>hoped that in applying these strict standards of behaviour to such entities operating <lb/>in the UK, and establishing an ease of access to available enforcement mechanisms, <lb/>the government is equally willing to accede to future calls for collective redress in <lb/>State Liability, potentially against itself. <lb/>VI. CONCLUSIONS <lb/>This article has sought to identify a path to justice for individuals affected by a breach <lb/>of EU obligations of a Member State. To facilitate State Liability&apos;s use and evolution <lb/>from a damages-only action through tortious liability, to becoming a viable <lb/>enforcement mechanism, the need for a system of collective redress to be made <lb/>available is crucial. Using the collective redress model established in the <lb/>Commission&apos;s Recommendation in 2011 as the basis for extending the argument <lb/>that political will may be present from the actions of the Commission and the <lb/>Member States to facilitate access to justice through collective redress, it has been <lb/>argued that extending this principle to State Liability as a genus, but on a sectoral <lb/>basis, would provide both benefits of redress and access, whilst fulfilling the EU&apos;s <lb/>requirement that Member States adhere to their obligations. There are no legal or <lb/>political bars to prevent the extension of collective redress to State Liability, the fears <lb/>that collective redress will lead to the establishing of a litigation culture and abusive <lb/>legal system across the EU are ill-founded, and Member States appear to be <lb/>amenable to the concept and exercise of collective redress as a system of facilitating <lb/>private enforcement of EU law. <lb/>Individuals who are denied rights granted through the membership of the EU <lb/>must have an appropriately accessible and transparent system of redress available. <lb/>Many individuals lack the social and economic power to secure their EU rights, and <lb/>were this not the case, the system of EU law reporting and education, in the UK at <lb/>least, makes awareness of laws and existing sources of help limited, disjointed and <lb/>prohibitory. Individuals are also affected in their daily lives by EU rights (perhaps <lb/>most visible to them through social policy initiatives) which, when denied through <lb/>inadequate action on behalf of the State, profoundly and adversely affect their lives, <lb/>but may be difficult to quantify financially. This makes the system of redress through <lb/>State Liability as a mere damages action restrictive, largely inappropriate, but <lb/>presently necessary. The consequential deterrence effect of many, albeit individually <lb/>financially insignificant joined cases, may be witnessed when awards are provided to <lb/>a class of claimants such as workers. The collective effect of such damages <lb/>payments may serve as the necessary incentive for a State to correctly, and on-time, <lb/>transpose EU directives. <lb/>The cost/benefit ratio of the necessary changes to the Member States&apos; legal <lb/>systems requires close examination, but it appears, prima facie, to be worth the <lb/>resource investment by the Commission to remedy the current limited effectiveness <lb/>of State Liability. Data is needed as relatively little research has been conducted that <lb/>conclusively substantiates the economic benefit for the introduction of collective <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>actions in State Liability. 124 However, the advantages of making EU rights <lb/>accessible, creating a transparent system of redress and limiting the opportunities for <lb/>a wrong-doing State from benefiting therefrom, certainly provides substantial <lb/>advantages in ensuring EU law is followed and made available to those who are <lb/>often the most vulnerable in society. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>124 Although such a methodology has been established and applied to collective redress in consumer <lb/>protection -see European Commission -DG SANCO &apos;Evaluation of the effectiveness and efficiency <lb/>of collective redress mechanisms in the European Union&apos; Final Report. Part I: Main Report Submitted <lb/>by: <lb/>Civic <lb/>Consulting <lb/>(Lead) <lb/>and <lb/>Oxford <lb/>Economics <lb/>(available <lb/>at <lb/>http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/redress_cons/finalreportevaluationstudypart1-final2008-11-26.pdf) at <lb/>[136]. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>