<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Still Searching for a Reliable Script: Access to Scientific Knowledge in Environmental Litigation in Italy</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Roberto</forename>
          <surname>Caranta</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-25T09:29:16.766Z">1/25/2026 10:29:16 AM</date>
        <title>review</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.54648__eelr2018019</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Kluwer Law International BV</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2018</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.54648/eelr2018019</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Roberto Caranta. (2018). Still Searching for a Reliable Script: Access to Scientific Knowledge in Environmental Litigation in Italy. European Energy and Environmental Law Review, 27(Issue 4), 158-168. DOI: 10.54648/eelr2018019</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2026-01-02T12:29:04.163679Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2026-01-02T12:29:04.163679Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T14:45:10.816Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Annotation completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-07T21:52:04.204Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith second pass completed </desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T09:05:12.886Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-25T10:06:19.568Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
			19 December 2025 <lb/>
    
    <front>AperTO -Archivio Istituzionale Open Access dell&apos;Università di Torino <lb/>Original Citation: <lb/>Still Searching for a Reliable Script: Access to Scientific Knowledge in Environmental Litigation in <lb/>Italy <lb/>Terms of use: <lb/>Open Access <lb/>(Article begins on next page) <lb/>Anyone can freely access the full text of works made available as &quot;Open Access&quot;. Works made available <lb/>under a Creative Commons license can be used according to the terms and conditions of said license. Use <lb/>of all other works requires consent of the right holder (author or publisher) if not exempted from copyright <lb/>protection by the applicable law. <lb/>Availability: <lb/>This is the author&apos;s manuscript <lb/>This version is available http://hdl.handle.net/2318/1693455 <lb/>since 2019-02-19T14:08:07Z <lb/>Still Searching for a Reliable Script: Access to Scientific Knowledge in Environmental Litigation in <lb/>Italy <lb/>Roberto Caranta <lb/></front>

			<body>1. INTRODUCTION <lb/>The rules on evidence and the approach to access to scientific knowledge by administrative courts <lb/>have changed greatly in Italy during the past 20 years. The changes impact environmental litigation, <lb/>but their scope is wider and quite general. The UE general principle of effective judicial protection <lb/>contributed to the evolution of Italian law towards a somewhat closer look to the factual findings on <lb/>which administrative decisions are based. 1 The practice of judicial review, including in environmental <lb/>matters, however, is often rather deferent to the findings of the public decision makers. The aim of <lb/>this paper is to critically analyse the Italian rules and judicial practice concerning access to scientific <lb/>knowledge in environmental litigation. <lb/>In line with the approach taken in this special issue, this contribution will focus exclusively <lb/>on access to scientific knowledge in the &apos;general&apos; administrative courts. 2 This covers both first <lb/>instance (Tribunali amministrativi regionali -TAR, one in each of the 20 Regions in the country) and <lb/>appeal (Consiglio di Stato) courts. 3 Different rules, which will not be analysed here, apply in front of <lb/>the &apos;ordinary courts&apos; having jurisdictions over &apos;environmental damage&apos; claims, 4 and before the Court <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1 For the division of roles between EU and national courts based on a number of principles, including effective judicial <lb/>protection, and for further references see M. Eliantonio and T. Palonnitty &apos;The EU requirements for the standards of <lb/>review and for the duty of national courts to access scientific knowledge in environmental litigation: a story of moving <lb/>targets and vague guidance&apos; in this same issue, p. 1 f. <lb/>2 See generally M. Protto, &apos;Giurisdizione in generale&apos; R. Caranta (dir.), Il nuovo processo amministrativo (Zanichelli, <lb/>2011) pp. 113-172. <lb/>3 Full text of all the judgments is available at www.giustizia-amministrativa.it (in Italian); the search engine is not very <lb/>good and a number of pay-for-access websites where judgments are indexed are normally used. It is to be noted that in <lb/>Italy cases are not referred to by the names of the parties; more bureaucratically, the sequence &apos;court, date, number&apos; is <lb/>used; references in this contribution will conform to the national pattern. <lb/>4 Further, if not fully updated, information may be found in the Italian report on the experience gained in the application <lb/>of <lb/>Directive <lb/>2004/35/EC <lb/>Ares(2013)2770018 <lb/>-<lb/>29.07.2013, <lb/>available <lb/>at: <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>of auditors which is competent to entertain actions aimed at recovering costs for the State budget <lb/>flowing from environmental breaches (for instance, due to remedial action taken following <lb/>pollution). 5 <lb/>Changes in the doctrines concerning both the bounds of judicial review by administrative <lb/>courts and access to scientific knowledge in cases brought before the administrative courts competent <lb/>to review administrative decisions or inaction, as well as changes in the legislation, will be presented <lb/>first (2). The actual practice of the administrative courts will then be analysed with reference to a <lb/>number of cases thought to be emblematic regarding the judicial review of decisions taken by the <lb/>administration in environmental matters (3). Conclusions assessing the practice of the administrative <lb/>courts against EU law and EU case law, including those implementing the Aarhus Convention, will <lb/>conclude the paper (4). It is stressed from the outset that this author fully share the conclusion that <lb/>&quot;the requirements imposed by EU law only provide a vague guidance and minimum denominators&quot; <lb/>and that it is questionable if this is sufficient to meet the requirement of &apos;substantive review&apos; as <lb/>imposed under Article 9 of the Aarhus Convention. 6 <lb/>2. FACTS AND THE ADMINISTRATIVE COURTS <lb/>In the first half of the XIX century the Consiglio di Stato was fashioned following the French Conseil <lb/>d&apos;Etat model. The Consiglio di Stato was to advise the King on appeals brought against decisions <lb/>that had been confirmed all through the administrative hierarchy. 7 <lb/></body>
    
    <listBibl>http://ec.europa.eu/environment/legal/liability/pdf/eld_ms_reports/IT.pdf , p. 45 ff; see also the EFFACE report on <lb/>Fighting <lb/>Environmental <lb/>Crime <lb/>in <lb/>Italy: <lb/>A <lb/>Country <lb/>Report <lb/>available <lb/>at <lb/>http://efface.eu/sites/default/files/EFFACE_Fighting%20Environmental%20Crime%20in%20Italy.pdf . <lb/>5 Cass. civ., Sez. Unite, 21 May 2014, n° 11229, Foro ital., 2015, I, 2481. <lb/>6 See the detailed analysis by M. Eliantonio and T. Palonnitty &apos;The EU requirements for the standards of review and for <lb/>the duty of national courts to access scientific knowledge in environmental litigation: a story of moving targets and vague <lb/>guidance&apos; above fn 1. <lb/>7 For further analysis please refer to R. Caranta, &apos;Administrative Appeals in Italy&apos;, in J-B. Auby and T. Perroud (eds.), <lb/>Droit comparé de la procédure administrative. Comparative Law of Administrative Procedure (Bruylant, 2016) pp. 806 <lb/>ff. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>In this framework, the advice was based on the file established by the public administration <lb/>that had taken the decision challenged. This was to a large extent a paper-based inquisitorial rather <lb/>than adversarial procedure. Those challenging an administrative decision were seen as mere <lb/>instruments to allow the State to amend its own mistakes in the higher interest of the rule of law (so-<lb/>called contentieux objectif). 8 Facts were not much of an issue, and in any case they were material only <lb/>insofar as they had been ascertained by the decision maker and as such established in some of the <lb/>documents in the file. 9 <lb/>With a number of legislative instruments adopted between 1889 and 1905, the Consiglio di <lb/>Stato was granted a judicial capacity in addition to its traditional advisory capacity. As a rule, however, <lb/>judicial review was confined to legality. Only very exceptionally were the administrative courts given <lb/>the power to look into the merits of the decision. <lb/>The distinction between legality and merits is of course fraught with difficulties, in Italy as <lb/>elsewhere. Basically, Italian courts embraced a wide notion of discretion that extended to cover both <lb/>policy decisions about conflicting public and private interests and complex factual assessments. 10 <lb/>Moreover, Italian courts are most ready to read complex decisions as involving both policy choices <lb/>and complex factual assessments. These decisions and assessments were reviewable only in so far as <lb/>they were close to irrational. Judicial review focused on matter of procedures and on the reasons given <lb/>by the decision maker. Otherwise administrative courts tended to defer to the choices made by the <lb/>administration. 11 Full review has instead always been performed concerning simple facts, such as <lb/>measuring noise emissions. 12 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>8 This was again consistent with the French model: M. Fromont, Droit administrative des Etats européens (PUF, 2006) <lb/>9 See, also for references to the Italian legal literature M. Eliantonio, Europeanisation of Administrative Justice? (Europa <lb/>Law Publishing, 2008) p. 184. <lb/>10 R. Caranta, &apos;On Discretion&apos; in S. Prechal -B. van Roermund (eds), The Coherence of EU Law (Cambridge University <lb/>Press, 2008) pp. 191 ff. <lb/>11 M. Eliantonio, Europeanisation of Administrative Justice? above fn 9, at p. 185; see also A. Comino &apos;The Application <lb/>of the Aarhus Convention in Italy&apos; in R. Caranta, A. Gerbrandy, B. Müller (eds), The Making of a New Legal Culture: <lb/>the Aarhus Convention (Europa Law Publishing, 2018) p. 176 f. <lb/>12 E.g. T.A.R. Sicilia, Palermo Sec. I, 12 December 2011, n° 2333. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Procedural rules laid down in R.D. 17 August 1907 n° 642 indicated the evidence allowed, <lb/>and they were fully in line with the paper-based procedure which was briefly described above. <lb/>Basically, the administrative courts had full access to the facts of the case, including through recourse <lb/>to outside expertise, only in those exceptional situations in which their jurisdiction extended to the <lb/>merits of the decision. When their jurisdiction was limited to legality review, the administrative courts <lb/>had to rely on the documents in the administrative file. At most they could ask the decision maker for <lb/>clarifications (schiarimenti) or additional factual investigations (verificazioni). 13 Recourse to expert <lb/>witnesses was not an option. As Mariolina Eliantonio has remarked, &apos;since the choices of the <lb/>administration involving technical aspects could not be reviewed by the courts, there was no point in <lb/>giving the courts themselves the power to entrust an independent expert with the task of analysing <lb/>and reporting on these choices&apos;. 14 <lb/>In the past twenty years or so, the traditional deference to the decision maker has been <lb/>reconsidered and the procedural rules have been changed. 15 <lb/>2.1. A Harder Look? <lb/>Late in the last century and early in this millennium, under pressure from scholars and taking stock <lb/>from the evolving case law on effective judicial protection as then developed by the European courts <lb/>(both the CJEU and the ECHR), the administrative courts reconsidered their approach to judicial <lb/>review specifically concerning complex factual assessments. 16 As Eliantonio has made clear, this was <lb/>based on the understanding administrative courts had of the European general principle of effective <lb/>judicial protection rather than on specific precedents by either the CJEU or the ECHR. 17 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>13 See also M. Eliantonio, Europeanisation of Administrative Justice? above fn 9, pp. 183 f. <lb/>14 Ibid, p. 186. <lb/>15 Ibid, pp. 181 ff. <lb/>16 This influence is analysed by M. Eliantonio, Europeanisation of Administrative Justice? above fn 9, pp. 190 ff. <lb/>17 Ibid., p 190. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>The leading case concerned a work disability claim brought by a public servant and as such <lb/>falling under the full jurisdiction of the administrative courts. 18 This was soon followed by an <lb/>important competition case belonging to the general legality review jurisdiction of the same courts. 19 <lb/>In both cases, the Consiglio di Stato expressly disavowed marginal or peripheral or extrinsic <lb/>(estrinseco) judicial review to embrace a direct appraisal of the decision-making process (so called <lb/>controllo intrinseco). 20 Courts still considered themselves forbidden from taking the decision in the <lb/>place of the administration (substitutive review), but were ready to fully and directly review whether <lb/>the right factual investigation process had been chosen and whether the relevant scientific and <lb/>technical rules had been respected. 21 <lb/>The Consiglio di Stato tries to strike the uneasy balance between the effectiveness of judicial <lb/>protection on the one hand, and what it perceives as the impossibility of a court to decide on the merits <lb/>of an administrative case on the other hand. In a case concerning sanctions for abuse of a dominant <lb/>position, the highest administrative court held that judicial review covers both the rationality and <lb/>proportionality of the decision taken and the reasons given for it. It also extends to checking whether <lb/>accepted scientific procedures were adhered to. However, given what is assumed to be the relativity <lb/>of scientific knowledge (relatività delle valutazioni scientitiche), judicial review must stop short of <lb/>second-guessing the substance of the administrative decision. 22 <lb/>Reference to the &apos;relativity of scientific knowledge&apos; is found frequently in the case law 23 and <lb/>as such is repeated in scholarly writings, including textbooks. 24 It is to be kept in mind, and it is <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>18 Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 9 April 1999, n° 601 <lb/>19 The leading case is Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 23 April 2002, n° 2199, Foro amm. CdS, 2002, 1007, note N. Rangone &apos;Intese <lb/>nel mercato assicurativo e sindacabilità dei provvedimenti antitrust&apos;, and Giur. comm. 2003, II, 170, note R. Caranta &apos;I <lb/>limiti del sindacato del giudice amministrativo sui provvedimenti dell&apos;Autorità garante della concorrenza e del mercato&apos;. <lb/>20 M. Eliantonio, Europeanisation of Administrative Justice? above fn 9, pp. 190 f. <lb/>21 For further discussion see M. Eliantonio, Europeanisation of Administrative Justice? above fn 9, pp. 190 ff.; R. Caranta <lb/>and B. Marchetti, &apos;Judicial Review of Regulatory Decisions in Italy; Changing the Formula and Keeping the Substance?&apos; <lb/>in O. Essens, A. Gerbrandy and S. Lavrijssen (eds.) National Courts and the Standard of Review in Competition Law and <lb/>Economic Regulation (Europa Law Publishing, 2009), 145-171, at 150 ff. <lb/>22 Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 13 September 2012, n° 4873; Cons. Stato, Sez. VI, 7 November 2005, n° 6152. <lb/>23 E.g. Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 24 November 2015, n° 5327; Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 14 October 2015, n° 4747; Cons. Stato, <lb/>Sec. V, 13 September 2012, n. 4873; Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 12 October 2011, n. 5519. <lb/>24 V. Cerulli Irelli, Lineamenti di diritto amministrativo 5th (Giappichelli, 2016) 298 f. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>perhaps regrettable, that the change in the doctrines concerning the proper bounds of judicial scrutiny <lb/>originated from competition law cases. Economics is the &apos;scientific&apos; knowledge relevant in these <lb/>cases. Economics, however, is hardly a science under the understanding of science as based on the <lb/>validation/falsification of hypotheses through experiment, developed during the Enlightenment with <lb/>reference to the natural sciences. Economic assessments, and especially prospective economic <lb/>assessments, are often &apos;arguable&apos; or &apos;debatable&apos; rather than true/false. 25 <lb/>Uncertainty in the evaluation is of course not limited to economics. Another area where the <lb/>administrative courts have shown much restraint is in reviewing the classification of heritage <lb/>buildings which is decided base on vague standards such historical relevance, cultural significance <lb/>and aesthetic merit. 26 <lb/>This approach, and the limits to judicial review coming with it, might be justified with <lb/>references to the circumstances of some categories of cases. It is however worth noticing that in the <lb/>well-known Tetra Laval case the uncertainty inherent in prospective economic analysis has led the <lb/>Court of Justice to both acknowledge &quot;the margin of discretion implicit in the provisions of an <lb/>economic nature which form part of the rules on concentrations to require&quot; 27 and -somewhat <lb/>contradictorily -to allow the EU courts to probe deeply the reasoning in the challenged decision, and <lb/>this even more so &quot;in the case of a prospective analysis required when examining a planned merger <lb/>with conglomerate effect&quot;. 28 While the exact reading of the Tetra Laval judgment is not without <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>25 Economics was brilliantly analysed with reference to philosophy of science by D.M. Hausmann, The inexact and <lb/>separate science of economics (Cambridge, 1992) spec. 152 ff. <lb/>26 E.g. Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 14 October 2015, n° 4747. <lb/>27 Case C-12/03, Commission v. Tetra Laval ECLI:EU:C:2005:87, paragraph 38. <lb/>28 Paragraph 39. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>challenges, scholars agree in that the case marked a step towards a closer look into administrative <lb/>decisions even when they involve complex analysis, 29 which extends beyond the economic field. 30 <lb/>Given to the rather casual approach of Italian courts to precedents which will be discussed <lb/>later, reference to the relativity of scientific knowledge has instead become the standard in judicial <lb/>review and has been extended to every complex factual assessment, including those performed with <lb/>the methodologies of the natural sciences that are relevant in environmental cases. These cases do not <lb/>necessarily always imply &apos;uncertain science&apos; even if complex environmental impact assessments <lb/>might well involve uncertain prospective evaluations. 31 <lb/>Reviewing the procedure and the reasons given is still a process-oriented rather than <lb/>substance-oriented review. 32 While no longer marginal, judicial review in Italy is still somewhat weak <lb/>and does not amount to strong or full -or to use US administrative law terminology -de novo <lb/>review. 33 <lb/>Whether the change in the doctrines -the law in the books -has really impacted how judicial <lb/>review is actually performed -the law in action -is open to debate. <lb/>Food for thought was provided by a series of judgments concerning challenges to a decision <lb/>by the anti-trust authority to fine a number of companies providing jet fuel to Italian airports for price <lb/>fixing. As is often the case with competition cases, the decision involved complex economic analysis, <lb/>such as the proper delimitation of the relevant market and the quantification of the effects of the <lb/>agreement that restrained competition in the said market. Since each of them was engaged in an <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>29 See for instance J. Mendes, &apos;Discretion, care and public interests in the EU administration: Probing the limits of law&apos; <lb/>[2016] 53 Common Market Law Review, 427 ff; A. Fritzsche, &apos;Discretion, Scope of Judicial Review and Institutional <lb/>Balance in European Law&apos; [2010] 47 Common Market Law Review, 380; M.F. Bay and J. Ruiz Calzado, &apos;Tetra Laval II: <lb/>the Coming of Age of the Judicial Review of Merger Decisions&apos; [2005] 28 World Competition 437 ff; for a well articulated <lb/>analysis of the different evaluation/assessment steps involved in a merger decision see A. Gerbrandy, Prospective <lb/>Analysis and Establishing Substantive truth in Review of Merger Decisions in Court&apos; [2014] Netherlands Administrative <lb/>Law Library 8 ff and 13 (also available at http://www.nall.nl/tijdschrift/nall/2014/02/NALL-D-14-00001 ). <lb/>30 See the analysis by M. Eliantonio and T. Palonnitty &apos;The EU requirements for the standards of review and for the duty <lb/>of national courts to access scientific knowledge in environmental litigation: a story of moving targets and vague guidance&apos; <lb/>above fn 10 f. <lb/>31 A. Gerbrandy, Prospective Analysis and Establishing Substantive truth in Review of Merger Decisions in Court&apos; above <lb/>fn, p. 3. <lb/>32 See also A. Lamorgese, La giurisdizione contesa. Cittadini e pubblica amministrazione (Giappichelli, 2014) 18. <lb/>33 See also A. Sandulli, &apos;The Use of Comparative Law before the Italian Public Law Courts&apos;, in M. Andenas -D. <lb/>Fairgrieve (eds.), Courts and Comparative law (Oxford University Press, 2015) 266-278, at 274 f. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>egregious blame-shifting game, the companies involved sought judicial review individually. One and <lb/>the same factual situation thus gave rise to different judgments. They then separately appealed the <lb/>first instance judgment, leaving the fines to stand. The Consiglio di Stato itself disposed of the appeals <lb/>with separate judgments penned by different judges. The striking feature is that the different <lb/>judgments expounded very different theories as to the proper bounds of judicial review. Some came <lb/>very close to marginal review and were content with finding the overall reasons given by the antitrust <lb/>authority globally persuasive. Other judgments, while still finding no ground to strike out the <lb/>challenged decision in the end, almost embarked on de novo reviews by closely scrutinising each step <lb/>in the authority&apos;s reasoning and looking into the facts relied upon by the authority, including proven <lb/>information exchanges among the companies involved. 34 <lb/>The jet fuel litigation easily supports different readings. Stressing that all judgments came to <lb/>the same conclusion and left the antitrust authority&apos;s decision standing, one could be excused for <lb/>thinking that doctrines on judicial review do not matter. At the least, the judgments show that Italian <lb/>administrative judges are divided as to their proper role. This however might entail that different <lb/>panels might approach -and review -similar cases differently. It is also worth stressing that the <lb/>administrative court did not think it necessary to have recourse to expert witnesses, rather preferring <lb/>to look directly into the facts of the case. <lb/>Generally speaking, it is difficult to make a solid link between the doctrines expounded in a <lb/>judgment and the type of review actually performed. Hard(er) look doctrines are often expounded <lb/>with reference to the review of decisions that would most probably not have anyway withstood <lb/>judicial scrutiny even under a hands-off approach. This was the case with a decision ordering <lb/>immediate remedial action to avoid groundwater contamination. The court found that the public <lb/>administration had not considered at all whether the measures imposed were actually needed and <lb/>whether alternatives less detrimental not just for the addressee of the decision but for the environment <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>34 See R. Caranta and B. Marchetti, &apos;Judicial Review of Regulatory Decisions in Italy; Changing the Formula and Keeping <lb/>the Substance?&apos; in O. Essens, A. Gerbrandy and S. Lavrijssen (eds.) National Courts and the Standard of Review in <lb/>Competition Law and Economic Regulation above fn 18, 145-171, spec. at 159 ff, where the cases are analysed. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>itself existed. Whatever the power of factual evaluation given to the decision maker, its actual use <lb/>was labelled &quot;arbitrary&quot;. Of course, it did not help the respondent authority that it had failed to provide <lb/>any evidence that the addressee of the decision was responsible for the contamination. Also damning <lb/>was the fact that, on the same day it issued the order, challenged and later annulled by the court, the <lb/>public administration wrote to all the industries located in the area proposing an agreement to plan an <lb/>overall clean-up. 35 <lb/>In other easy cases, reference to a doctrine expounding marginal review may instead hide the <lb/>fact that the judges had peered into the file and were satisfied with the substantive outcome achieved <lb/>by the decision maker. This is believed to have been the case when a first instance court upheld the <lb/>decision not to forgo the breaches of rules for the protection of the cultural heritage by a landowner <lb/>who had built some shacks using disparate materials on an area along the shores of the Garda Lake <lb/>characterised by olive grooves. After having recalled the precedents calling for restraint in reviewing <lb/>discretion, the courts basically concluded that the pictures in the file showed that the local authority <lb/>was justified in coming to the conclusion that the huts were eyesores that could only be remedied by <lb/>levelling them. 36 <lb/>Further analysing environmental cases will shed some light on this grey area of the law. Before, <lb/>the evolution of the legislation has to be briefly described. <lb/>2.2. Changes to the Means of Proof. <lb/>Whatever its limits, the shift to &apos;intrinsic review&apos; brought with it the need for expert advice to help <lb/>judges to assess whether the right technical or scientific procedures were duly followed or not. 37 <lb/>Evolution in the case law was later consolidated into legislation which also answered the need for <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>35 T.A.R. Toscana, Sec. II, 19 May 2010, n° 1524. <lb/>36 T.A.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sec. II, 18 March 2011, n° 440; see also T.A.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sec. II, 2 February <lb/>2011, n° 224, where the court held that the municipality was justified in considering unacceptable from an aesthetic point <lb/>of view a plastic fence in a wooded area; pictures are however not referred to in this latter case. <lb/>37 M. Eliantonio, Europeanisation of Administrative Justice? above fn 9, p. 191 <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>expert advice. A series of changes in the law culminated in the 2010 Code of judicial administrative <lb/>procedure widening the means of proof available in legality review proceedings. 38 <lb/>The starting point is to be found in Articles 63 and 64 of the Code, which has reaffirmed the <lb/>traditional approach to the burden of proof. Because the public administration conducted the <lb/>investigation, Italian administrative law adheres to a (weak) inquisitorial system. 39 The parties are <lb/>asked to provide what evidence they have. The court, however, has wide powers as to how to find <lb/>evidence, including by asking of its own volition the administration, the parties or third parties for <lb/>documents and information. 40 <lb/>Concerning the means of proofs specifically, the Code juxtaposes old and new but also <lb/>significantly changes the rules of the game. The powers of administrative courts to order factual <lb/>investigations (verificazioni) have been strengthened and widened under Article 66. Today the court <lb/>can entrust factual investigations to any expert, including those from outside the public sector. Under <lb/>Article 63(4), administrative courts have also been given the power to have recourse to expert <lb/>witnesses if this is strictly necessary. It is to be noted that in writing about &apos;expert witnesses&apos; we are <lb/>using a term that is widely understood in the English-speaking world. In Italy, experts are asked to <lb/>produce a written report, which is circulated to the parties who may have been named ex parte experts, <lb/>in turn reacting with written report(s). There is in principle no cross-examination of the expert witness <lb/>named by the court in what is still an eminently paper-based procedure. <lb/>This does not however bring Italian law in conflict with either the Aarhus convention or EU <lb/>law. The requirement of (some measure of) &apos;substantive control in no way needs to be translated into <lb/>a US style adversarial procedure. The problem rather lies -as will be clarified in the next sections -<lb/>in the little use Italian administrative courts make of the new means of proof available to them. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>38 Legislation later consolidated in the Code now in force is analysed by M. Eliantonio, Europeanisation of Administrative <lb/>Justice? above fn 7, pp. 194 f; see also See the analysis by M. Eliantonio and T. Palonnitty &apos;The EU requirements for the <lb/>standards of review and for the duty of national courts to access scientific knowledge in environmental litigation: a story <lb/>of moving targets and vague guidance&apos; above fn 1, p. 20 ff. <lb/>39 Ibid, pp. 186. <lb/>40 See generally P. Chirulli, &apos;Istruttoria&apos; in R. Caranta (dir.), Il nuovo processo amministrativo above fn 1, 521-572. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>The difference between verificazioni and expert witnesses no longer depends, as was the case <lb/>in the past, on the fact that the former are committed to the same office that made the decision or to <lb/>another public administration (or official working with an administration). Also, it is not unusual to <lb/>entrust the role of expert witness to some official working with a different administration. The <lb/>difference between verificazioni and expert witnesses has been clarified in some judgments in the <lb/>sense that the former provide additional factual information as compared to what is already clear from <lb/>the administrative file. On the other hand, expert witnesses provide a factual evaluation based on <lb/>some specific technical knowledge supplementing what judges, who in Italy are all trained in law, <lb/>may know. 41 In practice, the distinction may not be that clear-cut. However, the two means of proof <lb/>are differently regulated in terms of the role that the parties -or experts named by them -have to <lb/>play. Specific due-process rules are expressly provided for, with reference to the activities committed <lb/>to expert witnesses only. 42 <lb/>Whatever the difference, because of the restraint they often display when reviewing <lb/>discretionary administrative decisions, Italian administrative courts seem more confident in having <lb/>recourse to outside help in order to collect information on facts that are not too complex, and are <lb/>definitely not interlinked with policy considerations. One good instance of this is provided by a recent <lb/>decision by the first instance court in Piedmont. Some farmers were refused an ex post authorisation <lb/>to build a small shelter near their blueberry orchard because the Cuneo municipality considered it to <lb/>be too close to a canal. Applicable rules on no-building areas along canals specified different <lb/>minimum distances from canals with or without concrete shoulders. The documents in the <lb/>administrative file mentioned two canal names, and it was unsure whether this was two discrete canals <lb/>or just one, and also whether the relevant one had concrete shoulders or not. Probably distrusting very <lb/>much the services of the municipality, the court commissioned an expert to investigate what were <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>41 Cons. Stato, Sec. V, 7 June 2016, n° 2433; Cons. Stato Sez. VI, 12 November 2014, n° 5552. <lb/>42 See e.g. Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 17 January 2017, n° 175; breach of those safeguards will lead to the judgment being <lb/>quashed in appeal: Cons. Stato, Sec. V, 26 November 2013, n° 5610. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>clear facts (one or two canals? with or without concrete shoulders?) whose verification left no margin <lb/>to uncertainty. 43 <lb/>3. ON THE LAW IN ACTION <lb/>In principle, the analysis of the Italian case law in this area might be structured in different ways. One <lb/>possibility would be to classify judgments based on the doctrines on judicial review they adhere to. <lb/>Only, as shown above, one might well doubt that the review actually performed truly and plainly <lb/>follows from the accepted theoretical framework. Another possibility would be trying to establish <lb/>some kind of continuum based on how intense the review was in each case. This would, however, <lb/>obliterate the very different breadth of the discretion or margin of choices left to the decision maker <lb/>by the legislation applicable in different areas. <lb/>The preferred course of action is therefore to classify the case law according to the relevant <lb/>environmental measure and the degree of discretion or power of factual or scientific assessment given <lb/>to the decision maker. The analysis will start with those instances in which factual assessments and <lb/>policy decision are inextricably interwoven, such as in the case of EIA procedures. Because of the <lb/>broad margins of discretion enjoyed by the decision maker in such cases, a more peripheral approach <lb/>to review is to be expected. This should not be the case in those situations in which the public authority <lb/>is given more or even very limited powers of factual assessment. 44 <lb/>Before going into the case analysis, a few cautionary remarks need to be made. Italian courts, <lb/>including administrative courts, are very casual concerning precedents. Often, the facts of the case <lb/>are only sketched in the judgment. As is well known, precedents are instead taken very seriously in <lb/>common law jurisdictions. &apos;The peculiar feature of the English doctrine of precedent is its strongly <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>43 T.A.R. Piemonte, Sec. II, 17 April 2017, n° 611; see also, concerning the measurement of noise levels, T.A.R. Sicilia, <lb/>Palermo Sec. I, 12 December 2011, n° 2333. <lb/>44 The difference between types of discretion is highlighted in M. Eliantonio and T. Palonnitty &apos;The EU requirements for <lb/>the standards of review and for the duty of national courts to access scientific knowledge in environmental litigation: a <lb/>story of moving targets and vague guidance&apos; above fn 1, p. 3 f: see also above, § 2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>coercive nature&apos;. 45 However, only rationes decidendi are binding. 46 The &apos;ratio of a case relates the <lb/>proposition of law discussed in the judgment or judgments to the facts of the case and to the claims <lb/>of the parties&apos;. 47 This means that &apos;the facts of the case form very much more than just a context: they <lb/>play a crucial role in determining its future force&apos;. 48 Propositions that are not part of the ratio are <lb/>simply obiter. They retain (some) persuasive authority, but do not bind following judgments. 49 <lb/>Precedents are seen as establishing very specific rules attuned to the special factual situation of the <lb/>case at hand rather than declaring broad principles. Different rules may be devised and applied in <lb/>certain following cases if the facts or specific circumstances are different. In sum, &apos;students of the <lb/>common law study discrete cases and the facts, reasons, and distinctions courts rely on to resolve <lb/>them&apos;. 50 <lb/>Apparently less concerned about the facts, Italian courts tend to discuss at some length the <lb/>legal principles and rules applicable and their interpretation. The jet fuel cases discussed above are a <lb/>good instance for this. The discussion of the relevant doctrines is often concluded with a short phrase <lb/>summing up the law as it is understood by the court (the so called massima). When deciding a case, <lb/>the Corte di Cassazione must and the plenary section of the Consiglio di Stato may lay down one or <lb/>more massime to bind the lower or the referring court if the case is sent back to them. 51 Moreover, <lb/>under Article 74 of d.lgs. 2 July 2010, n° 104 (the Code of judicial administrative procedure), <lb/>administrative courts may declare an action clearly inadmissible or unfounded by simply referring to <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>45 R. Cross and J.W. Harris, &apos;Precedent in English Law (4 th edn., Clarendon Pres, 1991) p. 3. <lb/>46 Ibid, p. 6; the authors discuss at length the distinction in Ch. 2. <lb/>47 Simon Whittaker, &apos;Precedent in English Law: A View from the Citadel&apos; [2006] Eur. Rev. Priv. Law 705, p. 718. <lb/>48 Ibid.; see also R. Cross and J.W. Harris, &apos;Precedent in English Law above fn, p. 43 f. <lb/>49 Simon Whittaker, &apos;Precedent in English Law: A View from the Citadel&apos; above fn 39, p. 720. <lb/>50 Michael L. Wells, &apos;A Common Lawyer&apos;s Perspective on the European Perspective on Punitive Damages&apos; [2010] 70 <lb/>Louisiana Law Rev. 557, 560; see also Simon Whittaker, &apos; Precedent in English Law: A View from the Citadel&apos; [2006] <lb/>Eur. Rev. Priv. Law 705, 711 f; for a more qualified approach see however Rupert Cross and J.W. Harris, Precedent in <lb/>English Law (4 th edn., Clarendon Pres, 1991) p. 14 f. <lb/>51 Concerning the Consiglio di Stato see Art. 99 of d.lgs. of 2 July 2010, n° 104 (the Code of judicial administrative <lb/>procedure); see G. Corso, &apos;L&apos;Adunanza plenaria e la funzione nomofilattica&apos; (2014) Rassegna forense, 633-640. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>a previous judgment expressly called precedente. 52 In practice this often means referring to the <lb/>massima of a previous judicial decision, possibly cutting and pasting it into the new judgment. 53 <lb/>The law in Italy cannot be explained by referring to one or few leading cases or even by going <lb/>deeper into a discussion about the facts and rationes decidendi of different cases in search of <lb/>meaningful distinctions. What can be provided is an impressionist picture of what are believed to be <lb/>the different trends discernible in the case law. More often than not, some judgments could be find <lb/>being at odds with the picture. <lb/>3.1. EIA Procedures <lb/>In Italy the Environmental Impact Assessment -EIA is treated as semi-binding on the final decision. <lb/>The decision maker responsible for taking the final decision might well come to a different conclusion, <lb/>but he or she will not just have to give reasons for departing from the EIA conclusion but should <lb/>collect additional data or evidence. 54 Unsurprisingly decision makers tend to stick to the outcome of <lb/>EIA and to give reasons by referring to it. Those wanting to challenge the final decision will mainly <lb/>focus their pleas on the procedure followed for the EIA and its substantive outcomes. In the case law <lb/>EIA is treated as a topical instance of a procedure and a decision in which factual assessments and <lb/>policy decisions are inextricably interwoven. 55 <lb/>In what is often referred to as the leading case in this specific area, one company had asked <lb/>the Region for authorisation to open a landfill to be used to collect non-hazardous waste. 56 Following <lb/>what the Consiglio di Stato characterised as a thorough investigation, the EIA on the requested <lb/>authorisation was negative for a number of reasons. These included the fact that the municipality in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>52 See M. Sinisi, Il giusto processo amministrativo tra esigenze di celerità e garanzie di effettività della tutela <lb/>(Giappichelli, 2017) spec. pp. 288 ff. <lb/>53 Which of course should not be the case: M. Ramajoli, &apos;La tipologia delle sentenze del giudice amministrativo&apos; in R. <lb/>Caranta (dir.), Il nuovo processo amministrativo, above fn 1, 595-629, at p. 627. <lb/>54 Cons. Stato Sec. V, 17 October 2012, n° 5294. <lb/>55 Eg Cons. Stato Sec. VI, 22 February 2007, n° 933; see A. Comino &apos;The Application of the Aarhus Convention in Italy&apos; <lb/>above fn, 177. <lb/>56 Cons. Stato, Sec. V, 2 October 2014, n° 4928. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>whose territory the landfill was to be opened had in the meantime decided to rebrand itself as a tourist <lb/>destination by developing bio-and traditional agriculture; that the Region had adopted policy <lb/>guidelines favouring the development of existing landfills rather than the opening of new ones; that <lb/>the need for new landfills had been inflated by the applicant, who had not taken into due account the <lb/>principle of proximity; 57 that the proposed installation was closer to an urban area than allowed in the <lb/>applicable zoning regulation; and that the opening of the proposed landfill would have adversely <lb/>affected traffic in the area. In the end, a number of policy reasons militated against the landfill, and <lb/>these were not overweighed by any need in the public interest. 58 <lb/>The first instance administrative court had dismissed an application for judicial review and <lb/>this was appealed by the developer. Referring to earlier cases, the Consiglio di Stato illustrated its <lb/>doctrinal approach by stressing that EIA decisions are not just based on technical assessments, rather <lb/>presupposing policy choices about conflicting public and private interests, including those calling for <lb/>the so-called zero-option. This translates into a reinforced duty to give reasons for a positive decision <lb/>once public interests militating against the proposed project have been invoked during the procedure, <lb/>including by stakeholders. 59 Somewhat contradictorily, the court acknowledged a wide discretion to <lb/>the decision maker, thus implying limited judicial review on the decision taken, while at the same <lb/>time placing a high burden on the decision maker in terms of reasons to be given. 60 <lb/>Most of the pleas of the company were rejected on appeal. The higher administrative court <lb/>held that, far from giving preponderant weight to the opinion of the local municipalities, the Regional <lb/>authority had considered all the relevant elements, including that the proposed landfill was not <lb/>necessary to meet the needs of the population. 61 Moreover, the decision had been taken after the <lb/>applicant had been given ample opportunity to reply to the objections raised against the project. In <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>57 Which is codified in Art. 16 of Directive 2008/98/EC on waste and repealing certain Directives (the so-called Waste <lb/>Framework Directive). <lb/>58 See sect. 1 of the judgment. <lb/>59 Ibid, sect. 7.1. <lb/>60 Ibid.; see also sect. 7.2.3. <lb/>61 Ibid, sect. 7.2.1.1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>line with the generally accepted view in Italian case law, the court also held that it was not necessary <lb/>for the decision maker to rebut individually and analytically each and every argument raised by the <lb/>applicant to defeat the counter-objections. 62 Finally, the court dismissed the detailed factual <lb/>arguments developed by the applicant to criticize as either obsolete or wrong the data concerning the <lb/>amount of waste generated in the region and the capacity of the landfills already in use that were <lb/>relied upon by the decisions maker. According to the court, these arguments amounted to a dissenting <lb/>opinion that could not put into question the legality of the decision taken; possible different <lb/>understandings of the factual situation do not allow the courts to override a well motivated decision <lb/>adopted following a thorough investigation. 63 <lb/>This judgment deserved a somewhat lengthy description because it is thought to represent <lb/>well the attitude of Italian administrative courts when faced with challenges to complex factual <lb/>assessments and policy choices made by the decision maker. The courts tend to be satisfied when told <lb/>a plausible story that gives consistent reasons as to the procedure followed and the decision taken. <lb/>Provided that the right to be heard has been sufficiently safeguarded during the administrative <lb/>procedure, the courts will not be drawn into adversarial arguments about the relevant facts. Even an <lb/>articulate alternative presentation of those facts by the applicant for judicial review will not be enough <lb/>for the courts to consider asking expert advice. Such attitude seems inconsistent with even a very <lb/>modest reading of the requirement for &apos;substantive legality&apos; review spelt out in Article 9(2) of the <lb/>Convention. 64 It is also doubtful whether it does meet -or not -&apos;minimum standard&apos; to be applied <lb/>&apos;to the examination of the facts&apos; required in the Commission Notice on Access to Justice in <lb/>Environmental Matters. 65 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>62 Ibid, sect. 7.2.2. <lb/>63 Sect. 7.2.3. <lb/>64 See, also for a comparison of the standards laid down in Art. 9(29 and 9(3) of the Aarhus Convention, M. Eliantonio <lb/>and T. Palonnitty &apos;The EU requirements for the standards of review and for the duty of national courts to access scientific <lb/>knowledge in environmental litigation: a story of moving targets and vague guidance&apos; above fn 10 ff, <lb/>65 C(2017) 2016 final, paragraph 139. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>This somewhat hands-off approach applies beyond environmental cases to include factual <lb/>evaluation concerning measures to safeguard the landscape and cultural heritage, whose protection <lb/>predates environmental concerns in Italy. 66 <lb/>4.2. Wildlife Management and Hunting Plans <lb/>Measures concerning wildlife management also normally entail policy decisions based on complex <lb/>factual situations requiring scientific assessments. This is specifically true concerning hunting plans. <lb/>Regions and sub-regional (provincial) entities are competent to draw hunting plans, set the dates for <lb/>the hunting season, decide the species that can be hunted and delimit the areas set aside for <lb/>reproduction and protection. Hunter lobbies are politically very strong in a number of Italian regions, <lb/>leading decisions makers to stretch, and often to breach, EU and national rules. 67 <lb/>One of the most interesting cases concerning access to scientific knowledge on environmental <lb/>matters involved a series of provincial hunting plans of the Bergamo province in the Lombardy <lb/>Region. The judgment is significant for highlighting both the possibilities open under the current <lb/>legislation, including having recourse to expert witnesses, and for the limits that administrative courts <lb/>place on their review. 68 <lb/>In 2006 WWF Italy challenged the provincial hunting plan. The latter was amended in 2008 <lb/>to remedy the fact that the EIA had followed instead of preceding the adoption of the plan and that <lb/>the EIA document was largely cut and pasted from the one drafted by another province. The WWF <lb/>challenged the new plan in the course of the initial first instance judicial proceeding, which was still <lb/>ongoing and ended up lasting four years. All in all, the claimant raised 32 pleas, making the judgment <lb/>fairly long by recent Italian administrative court standards. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>66 See again T.A.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sec. II, 18 March 2011, n° 440, which was briefly discussed above. <lb/>67 E.g. Case C-164/09, Commission v. Italy, ECLI:EU:C:2010:672. <lb/>68 TA.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sec. II, 9 April 2010, n° 1532. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>The analysis by the first instance court started by recalling the bounds on its review power. <lb/>The court held that the case fell under legality review, meaning that it could not go into the merits of <lb/>the case, substituting its own decision to the one taken by the administration. 69 In this framework, the <lb/>report established by the expert witness might only be used to assess whether the choices made by <lb/>the decision maker were logically coherent, taking as the standard the scientific knowledge relevant <lb/>to those choices. 70 <lb/>Two of the main pleas raised by the WWF were held to be well founded. The first concerned <lb/>the proper delimitation of the &apos;alpine region&apos;. This is relevant because the national legislation provides <lb/>a different rate of set aside for sanctuary and reproduction for the alpine region compared with the <lb/>rest of the province. The expert witness named by the court clarified that two conflicting theories may <lb/>be used to delimit the alpine region. The first is &apos;natural&apos; in that it only relies on the presence of <lb/>specific fauna found exclusively in mountain areas. The second is &apos;cultural&apos; and also takes into <lb/>consideration the traditions of the local populations and how they interact with the environment. All <lb/>the experts, including those named by the parties, agreed that both approaches are acceptable, <lb/>meaning that there is no consensus in the science. This is indeed a good instance of &apos;uncertainty&apos; <lb/>affecting the natural sciences. However, the Bergamo province did not adhere to either of the two <lb/>theories. According to the expert witness named by the court, the province simply copied the <lb/>cartography already used twenty years before (if not earlier). This made the plan adopted by the <lb/>province illegal for both breach of the duty to give reasons and irrationality. The plan did not explain <lb/>the methodology chosen and in any case, given the changes in the environment which may be <lb/>expected after twenty years, the 1997 cartography could not but be considered obsolete. 71 <lb/>The first instance court also held as illegal the methodology applied to define set aside areas. <lb/>The province, acting on a literal interpretation of the regional legislation, included all areas in which <lb/>hunting is forbidden to make up the tally of areas set aside for sanctuary. Therefore, areas along roads <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>69 Ibid, sect. 3. <lb/>70 Ibid, sect. 4. <lb/>71 TA.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sec. II, 9 Apr 2010, n° 1532, sect 12 f. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>or railways and close to houses were so considered. Interpreting the legislation in the light of the aim <lb/>to allow enough areas for the fauna to find shelter and reproduce, the court found that such areas are <lb/>unfit for purpose. Therefore, they should have not been factored among the areas set aside for <lb/>conservation. Here the court was mainly concerned with law rather than with facts. The expert witness <lb/>was however relied upon to find that indeed a sizeable part of the areas ostensibly set aside as <lb/>sanctuary could not answer the needs of the fauna. 72 Similarly, the expert&apos;s opinion was relied upon <lb/>when finding that sanctuary areas around alpine passes were not correctly designed, since the <lb/>cartography showed overlaps between what ostensibly were sanctuaries and badly defined areas <lb/>where hunting lodges were situated. This was all the worse since the province could have easily <lb/>plotted the exact site of the hunting lodges based on documentation it held in its archives. 73 <lb/>Other pleas raised by the WWF were rejected. For instance, relying on the expert&apos;s opinion, <lb/>the first instance court upheld the provisions in the plan concerning the areas and times in which <lb/>hunting dogs could be trained because they were considered to be in line with the criteria used in <lb/>&apos;animal management sciences&apos; (scienze faunistiche). 74 Also the court stuck to the traditional approach <lb/>to participation and the duty to give reasons, holding that the claimant could not expect the decision <lb/>maker to discuss analytically each and every point raised by those taking part in the administrative <lb/>procedure. 75 <lb/>This judgment shows that (some) administrative courts are at least ready to have recourse to <lb/>expert witnesses to check the accuracy of some benignly complex facts forming the base for policy <lb/>decisions. When it is so, a court goes further in the judicial review than in the EIA case discussed in <lb/>the previous section. This shows the law in the books can indeed be interpreted and applied fully in <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>72 Ibid, sect. 14 ff, and specifically sect. 20 concerning the information derived from the report established by the expert <lb/>witness. It is to be noted that the experts named by the province had not challenged the findings by the expert named by <lb/>the court on this point. <lb/>73 Ibid, sect. 22 ff. <lb/>74 T.A.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sec. II, 9 Apr 2010, n° 1532, sect. 26. <lb/>75 Ibid, sect. 5 and 6. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>line with the requirements in Article 9 of the Aarhus Convention and in the EU implementing <lb/>legislation. <lb/>This judgement also provides some interesting information about the practice concerning the <lb/>role and treatment of expert witnesses, albeit predating the 2010 Code of judicial administrative <lb/>procedure. Firstly, the expert chosen was a public servant working for the wild animal management <lb/>department of another region. Secondly, but possibly not unrelated to the first aspect, the costs for <lb/>the expert were limited, amounting to something more than EUR 7000 for two reports, one each for <lb/>the 2006 and 2008 plans, the latter exceeding 2000 pages. Finally, since not all the pleas were <lb/>considered well-founded, the court ordered each party to bear its own costs, and to share the costs for <lb/>the expert witness. The latter judgement seems somewhat unfair, since the WWF was successful on <lb/>most of the issues it raised. Still, given the limited costs involved, it is doubted this infringes the <lb/>requirement of &apos;non prohibitively expensive&apos; set out in Article 9(4) of the Aarhus Convention. 76 <lb/>3.3. Remedial Measures <lb/>In Italy, public authorities often issue orders against those responsible for water pollution and/or <lb/>ground contamination. These orders normally require the polluter to remedy the harm done to the <lb/>environment through decontamination work and/or the building of catchment walls and basins to <lb/>prevent further environmental damage. There is (almost) no policy involved here, and all the <lb/>questions revolve around the most technically appropriate way(s) and means to remedy the <lb/>situation. 77 These measures, which entail a relevant when not heavy financial burden on the polluter, <lb/>are generally challenged in court. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>76 A.D. Nagy &apos;The Aarhus-Acquis in the EU. Developments in the Dynamics of Implementing the Three Pillars Structure&apos; <lb/>in R. Caranta, A. Gerbrandy, B. Müller (eds), The Making of a New Legal Culture: the Aarhus Convention above fn, p. <lb/>47 ff, <lb/>77 T.A.R. Toscana, Sec. II, 6 July 2010, n° 2316. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Administrative courts do not hesitate to strike down insufficiently reasoned orders as it was <lb/>already shown by the judgement annulling the decision ordering immediate remedial action to avoid <lb/>groundwater contamination because of lack of reasons. 78 They have also proven to be ready to <lb/>challenge decisions based on fact-finding activities performed in breach of due process legal <lb/>requirements and/or for which insufficient reasons were given, including concerning the absence of <lb/>less burdensome measures for the addressee of the administrative order. 79 <lb/>In other cases, the courts have trodden more carefully. One such case involved a remedial and <lb/>prevention order against a company responsible for polluting ground water, including affecting a <lb/>natural protection area. The company was required to build containment works. The first instance <lb/>court started by quoting a long section of a judgement of the Consiglio di Stato rendered in an abuse <lb/>of dominant position case and which was already recalled, excluding direct review of the substance <lb/>of the decision because of &apos;scientific relativism&apos;. 80 On this basis, the court was very quick to point <lb/>out that the containment works were fully adequate to prevent further harm to the environment and <lb/>also fully proportional (&quot;del tutto proporzionata&quot;) to the specific factual situation. 81 <lb/>This is an instance of an administrative court referring to a massima from a judgment <lb/>concerning a completely different factual situation to dispose quickly of the case at hand. Some <lb/>elements of proportionality analysis are present in the judgment, but they seem to have been used just <lb/>to provide a touch of modernity or to make shallow reasons appear fashionable. Of course the <lb/>applicant was probably not very deserving, since it neither denied responsibility, nor seemed to have <lb/>advanced any alternative remedy to what was a non-contested case of pollution. Still, one might <lb/>wonder why it took the first instance court of Apulia seven years to pass judgment on a very simple <lb/>case. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>78 T.A.R. Toscana, Sec. II, 19 May 2010, n° 1524. <lb/>79 T.A.R. Toscana, Sec. II, 6 July 2010, n° 2316; here (again) the order included remedial measures for pollution which <lb/>was not attributable to its addressee. <lb/>80 T.A.R. Puglia, Lecce Sec. I, 5 September 2014, n° 2304, sect. 3.1; see also, between the same parties, T.A.R. Puglia, <lb/>Lecce Sec. I, 5 September 2014, n° 2305. <lb/>81 T.A.R. Puglia, Lecce Sec. I, 5 September 2014, n° 2304, sect. 3.2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>What is remarkable is that none of the above judgments was based on the court performing -<lb/>or committing to an expert -a detailed factual investigation. Clearly insufficient reasons were at time <lb/>sufficient to lead to the annulment of the administrative decision challenged. When it was not so, like <lb/>in the last case referred to, the administrative court seemed to back off from any additional fact finding <lb/>initiative. Again this might seem inconsistent with even a minimal reading of the requirement of <lb/>&apos;substantive review&apos; as laid down in Article 9 of the Aarhus Convention, but it is also true that the <lb/>applicant for judicial review did nothing in this case to prod the court to take a more inquisitive <lb/>approach. <lb/>Finally, in one case, a first instance administrative court annulled an urgent order to remedy <lb/>pollution from household wastewater in the Circeo natural reserve. From the expertise acquired in a <lb/>parallel case opposing the addressee of the order and his neighbours before the civil courts, it was <lb/>clear that the problem originated from a series of breaches of building rules committed in the past <lb/>when the original small houses were significantly enlarged. According to the court, an urgent order <lb/>was not the kind of decision provided by the law to answer such past breaches. 82 <lb/>This solution might be considered somewhat formalistic, but the judgment is still significant <lb/>because it shows some readiness to act on expertise acquired in front of other courts. <lb/>3.4. Other Authorisations/ Concessions not Requiring EIA <lb/>Granting authorisations or concessions for works or infrastructure not requiring EIA normally <lb/>presupposes very limited factual assessment powers. The impact is more limited and the technical <lb/>challenges faced by the decision maker are limited. Still, the administrative courts generally claim <lb/>that they may only review the procedure and the reasons given. 83 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>82 T.AR. Lazio, Sec. III Quater, 26 January 2016, n° 7528. <lb/>83 Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 4 November 2013, n° 5293, sect. 2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Notwithstanding this doctrinal stance, at times the courts can be seen reviewing -and <lb/>upholding -the substance of the decision taken by the public authority. This is so especially when <lb/>the decision corresponds to common sense, as in the case with the shacks and huts built close to the <lb/>shores of the Garda Lake. 84 This was also the case with a request to allow non-permanent leisure <lb/>beach facilities throughout the year on some sandy dunes on the coasts of Apulia. The Consiglio di <lb/>Stato upheld the negative decision based on advice from the authority competent for cultural heritage <lb/>and the environment that had required the facilities to be fully removed at the end of each summer <lb/>season. The court reasoned that the facilities had a negative visual impact on the surrounding <lb/>environment and the provision to remove them was expressly considered to be &apos;intrinsically <lb/>congruous&apos;. The decision challenged was also held to strike a justified balance between <lb/>environmental considerations and the financial interests of the beneficiary of the authorisation (who <lb/>of course wanted to avoid the extra costs ensuing from periodical removal and reinstallation). 85 <lb/>When confronted with cases characterised by limited assessment powers, Italian <lb/>administrative courts seems ready to look into the substance of the administrative decision challenge, <lb/>and this whatever the doctrinal approach they decide to adhere to. Generally speaking therefore, the <lb/>case law analysed in this sections are in line with requirement of &apos;substantive review&apos; as laid down <lb/>in Article 9 of the Aarhus Convention. 86 <lb/>3.5. Sanctions <lb/>Widespread illegality does not (always) mean impunity. Sanctions happen and are often challenged. <lb/>One case concerned illegal quarrying activity in Campania, with an ensuing fine of EUR 3.479,36 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>84 T.A.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sec. II, 18 March 2011, n° 440; see also T.A.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sec. II, 2 February <lb/>2011, n° 224, where the court held that the municipality was justified in considering unacceptable from an aesthetic point <lb/>of view a plastic fence in a wooded area; pictures are however not referred to in this latter case. <lb/>85 Cons. Stato, Sec. VI, 4 November 2013, n° 5293, sect. 2. <lb/>86 See A.D. Nagy &apos;The Aarhus-Acquis in the EU. Developments in the Dynamics of Implementing the Three Pillars <lb/>Structure&apos; above fn, p. 47 ff. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>and an order to stop the activity and restore the area to what it was before. The owner of the land <lb/>denied all responsibility, claiming that the alteration of the area had either happened before he bought <lb/>the land or was the result of naturally occurring erosion. He asked for an expert to report on the factual <lb/>situation. Based on the expert&apos;s report, which had contrasted a number of past and present images of <lb/>the area taken from the air, the court found that quarrying had indeed recently taken place and upheld <lb/>the decision taken by the public administration. Beside the fine, the claimant had to pay EUR 4.000,00 <lb/>for the legal costs of the opponent Region and EUR 2.542,23 for the expert. 87 <lb/>Here again, as in the cases analysed in the previous section, the margin of discretion is not an <lb/>issue, and courts are ready to look into the facts, including by referring to expert witnesses. <lb/>4. Conclusions <lb/>Changes in the legislation in the past twenty years have given the Italian administrative courts the <lb/>tools they need to conduct factual investigations and to have access to scientific knowledge through <lb/>both verificazioni and expert witnesses. The administrative courts themselves have reconsidered the <lb/>doctrine concerning judicial review, allowing themselves somewhat wider margins of scrutiny on the <lb/>decisions taken by the public authority. This, however, stops short of going into the substance of the <lb/>decision and even shorter of substituting a judicial decision to the one taken by the competent <lb/>administrative authority. The administrative courts are very ready to concede wide discretion, <lb/>including room for policy decision, to the public administration. Also they tend to approach science <lb/>with a heavy dose of scepticism and label scientific knowledge as characterised by much uncertainty. <lb/>When in doubt, the courts bow to the choices made by the decision maker. <lb/>As already remarked, the fact that changes in the doctrines of judicial review first took place <lb/>with reference to competition cases did not help much. The Italian administrative courts have simply <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>87 T.A.R. Campania, Sec. IV, 7 December 2016, n° 5708, sect. 8.5. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>and plainly extended the doctrines on the bounds of judicial review to the analysis of environmental <lb/>cases. 88 At times this is even done by recalling massime that were drafted with reference to cases <lb/>miles away from environmental law, such as for instance -and again -competition law. 89 <lb/>It might also be the case that the administrative courts were and are most probably not ready <lb/>to go much further in judicial review anyway. Scholars too are deeply divided in Italy, with a number <lb/>of them expounding the virtues of limited review and justifying it on different arguments ranging <lb/>from separation of power to the lack of specialised knowledge of administrative courts. 90 <lb/>In practice, judicial review in environmental cases is therefore still very much focused on the <lb/>reasons given, looking at their logical consistency more than at their soundness, and even less so at <lb/>the soundness of the decision taken (unless of course the decision plainly conforms to or instead flies <lb/>in the face of common sense). Italian administrative courts seldom avail themselves of expert <lb/>witnesses, and this in turn keep their review to the surface of the administrative decision. Individual <lb/>judges cannot indeed be expected to be endowed with specialised scientific knowledge. <lb/>The situation is at times different when the facts are clear or the factual investigation required <lb/>is reasonably straightforward. If so, as shown by the case concerning the Bergamo hunting plans, at <lb/>least some administrative courts are ready to have recourse to experts to obtain a fuller knowledge of <lb/>the factual situation on which policy decision have been made and to rely on experts&apos; findings. 91 <lb/>It is difficult to say in general whether the Italian practice of judicial review is in line with the <lb/>EU general principle of effective judicial protection. The case law of the Court of Justice has shown <lb/>signs of restraint in the past few years. Moreover, this case law is less than straightforward on the <lb/>specific topic standard of review and means of proof. Finally, and in any case, it certainly stops short <lb/>of requiring a full review of factual assessments, including complex ones. 92 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>88 This seems to be a quite general pattern in Europe: see D.C. Dragos and B. Neamtu &apos;Access to justice under the <lb/>Aarhus Convention: the Comparative View&apos; in R. Caranta, A. Gerbrandy, B. Müller (eds), The Making of a New Legal <lb/>Culture: the Aarhus Convention above fn, p. 390. <lb/>89 Eg T.A.R. Puglia, Lecce Sez. I, 5 September 2014, n° 2304, discussed above. <lb/>90 See, also for further references, B. Marchetti, &apos;Il giudice amministrativo tra tutela soggettiva e oggettiva: riflessioni di <lb/>diritto comparato&apos; in Diritto processuale amministrativo 2014, 2014, p. 74 <lb/>91 TA.R. Lombardia, Brescia Sez. II, 9 April 2010, n° 1532. <lb/>92 E.g. Case C-71/14, East Sussex County Council, ECLI:EU:C:2015:656; Case C-120/97, Upjohn, EU:C:1999:14 <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Also it is difficult to say generally whether Italian case law is in line with the obligations <lb/>flowing from the Aarhus Convention and from the EU measures implementing it. The Commission <lb/>Notice on Access to Justice in Environmental Matters is not very specific on this topic. It refers to a <lb/>&apos;minimum standard&apos; to be applied &apos;to the examination of the facts&apos; 93 without further elaborating on <lb/>what these &apos;minimum standards are. 94 This notwithstanding, the more hands-off judgments are indeed <lb/>hard to reconcile with the requirement of &apos;substantive legality&apos; review predicated in Article 9 of the <lb/>Aarhus Convention. 95 <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>93 C(2017) 2016 final, paragraph 139. <lb/>94 See the analysis by M. Eliantonio and T. Palonnitty &apos;The EU requirements for the standards of review and for the duty <lb/>of national courts to access scientific knowledge in environmental litigation: a story of moving targets and vague guidance&apos; <lb/>above fn, 18 f. <lb/>95 See, also for a comparison between the standards laid down respectively in Art. 9(2) and 9(3) of the Aarhus Convention, <lb/>M. Eliantonio and T. Palonnitty &apos;The EU requirements for the standards of review and for the duty of national courts to <lb/>access scientific knowledge in environmental litigation: a story of moving targets and vague guidance&apos; above fn, 10 ff, </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>