<?xml-model href="https://mpilhlt.github.io/grobid-footnote-flavour/schema/grobid.training.segmentation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>J. D.</forename>
          <surname>Morton</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="li">Mengjiao Li</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="schulze">Judith Schulze</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T08:57:19.406Z">30/01/2026 09:57:19</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.60082_2817-5069.2531</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Osgoode Hall Law School, York University</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">1959</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.60082/2817-5069.2531</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>J. D. Morton. (1959). Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession. Osgoode Hall Law Journal, 1(2), 72-81. DOI: 10.60082/2817-5069.2531</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-12T15:44:48.942758Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-12T15:44:48.942758Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-16T18:21:37.599Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections_completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-18T09:30:03.602Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Cross_validtaion_Schulze</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-23T09:39:07.286Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2025-12-28T08:50:02.049Z" status="draft" who="#li">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-11T21:05:13.726Z" status="draft" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Judith 3 pass completed</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-14T08:42:23.284Z" status="checked" who="#schulze">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-19T15:10:32.283Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T08:57:29.851Z" status="candidate" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
  
        
	<front>Osgoode Hall Law Journal <lb/>Osgoode Hall Law Journal <lb/>Volume 1, Number 2 (April 1959) <lb/>Article 6 <lb/>4-1-1959 <lb/>Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession <lb/>J. D. Morton <lb/>Osgoode Hall Law School of York University <lb/>Follow this and additional works at: https://digitalcommons.osgoode.yorku.ca/ohlj <lb/>Article <lb/>Citation Information <lb/>Morton, J. D.. &quot;Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession.&quot; Osgoode Hall Law Journal 1.2 <lb/>(1959) : 72-81. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.60082/2817-5069.2531 <lb/>https://digitalcommons.osgoode.yorku.ca/ohlj/vol1/iss2/6 <lb/>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Journals at Osgoode Digital Commons. It has been <lb/>accepted for inclusion in Osgoode Hall Law Journal by an authorized editor of Osgoode Digital Commons. <lb/>Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession <lb/>.osgoode.yorku.ca/ohlj/vol1/iss2/6 <lb/>Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine <lb/>of Recent Possession <lb/>J. D. MORTON <lb/></front>

			<body>The possession of recently stolen goods will, in the absence of an in-<lb/>nocent explanation, support an inference that the possessor knew that <lb/>they were stolen. The facts on which the inference depends are (1) <lb/>the possession and (2) the absence of an innocent explanation, and if a <lb/>person be charged with possession of stolen goods, he is entitled to an <lb/>acquittal if the court is left with a reasonable doubt as to either or <lb/>both of these facts. Such is the result if no legal notions such as <lb/>doctrines or presumptions are involved and such appears to be the <lb/>position adopted in the decisions in Rex v. Schama and Abramovitc).A <lb/>Regina v. Morin 2 Regina v. Hogg 3 and Regina v. O&apos;Keefe 4 . <lb/>Yet all these cases deal extensively with what appears to be an <lb/>important factor in the result-the so-called doctrine of recent pos-<lb/>session. What is this so-called doctrine? Certainly it is not a pre-<lb/>sumption, 5 nor does it deal with recent possession as it is not the <lb/>recentness of the possession but the recentness of the theft which is <lb/>significant. There appears to be little doubt as to the words in which <lb/>the so-called doctrine may be-stated. e.g. <lb/>&quot;If the prosecution establishes the fact of theft and the fact of recent <lb/>possession by the accused of the stolen goods, then, in the absence of any <lb/>evidence to explain how the accused obtained possession of them, the <lb/>jury may convict the accused.&quot; 6 <lb/>I suggest, however, that there is doubt about the legal function <lb/>of the doctrine. The conventional view appears to be that it functions <lb/>by way of the judge&apos;s direction to the jury. <lb/>&quot;It is essential in cases of this kind that there be a careful and proper <lb/>direction.&quot; <lb/>7 <lb/>As to such proper direction there is confusion and this confusion <lb/>stems from a failure to distinguish between the two notions passing <lb/>under the name of &quot;burden of proof&quot;. I have set out my views on <lb/></body>

			<front>* Professor Morton, M.A., LL.B. (Trinity College, Dublin), The King&apos;s Inns, <lb/>Dublin, and of Osgoode Hall, Barrister-at-law is a full-time member of the <lb/>Teaching Staff at Osgoode Hall Law School. <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>1 (1914), 11 Cr. App. R. 45. <lb/>2 [1957] O.R. 337 (C.A.). <lb/>3 [1958] O.R. 723 (C.A.). <lb/>4 [1958] O.R. 499 (C.A.). <lb/>5R . v. Morin at p. 3 41 per Laidlaw J.A. <lb/>6 Ibid., at p. 341. <lb/>7 Ibid., at p. 341. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1959] Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession <lb/></note>

			<page>73 <lb/></page>

			<body>this distinction elsewhere S and it is sufficient to say here that I accept <lb/>the term &quot;Primary Burden&quot; as indicating the risk of non-persuasion, <lb/>and &quot;Secondary Burden&quot; as indicating the risk of non-production of <lb/>evidence. <lb/>The primary burden will assist the trier when, in a criminal case, <lb/>he has a reasonable doubt as to the facts. In such circumstances, the <lb/>concept of primary burden directs him to find against him who is <lb/>under the primary burden, generally the prosecution. It can only <lb/>function when the trier is in possession of all the evidence; that is, <lb/>at the end of the case. The secondary burden on the other hand is <lb/>an entirely different and unrelated notion which assists the trier in <lb/>arriving at a conclusion by an entirely different route. The secondary <lb/>burden is not concerned with the persuasion of the trier in the par-<lb/>ticular case, it is concerned with the preliminary testing of the <lb/>evidence and operates by way of the non-suit or directed verdict. <lb/>The difference between these two concepts is obvious when one <lb/>considers the course of a criminal trial before a judge and jury. Not <lb/>infrequently at the close of the case for the prosecution, defence <lb/>counsel will move for a directed verdict of acquittal on the ground <lb/>that there is no case to answer. The trial judge must then rule on <lb/>whether or not the prosecution has introduced evidence upon which <lb/>a reasonable jury could convict, or, in other words, whether the <lb/>prosecution has made out a prima facie case. It is this burden of <lb/>producing evidence which could support a verdict, the burden of <lb/>satisfying the judge in his capacity of preliminary tester, which is <lb/>distinguished as the secondary burden of proof. Should the trial <lb/>judge refuse to direct a verdict and permit the case to go to the jury, <lb/>then the prosecution is properly said to have discharged the secondary <lb/>burden which was, up till that moment, resting upon it. This <lb/>secondary burden is properly qualified as a legal notion in that it <lb/>depends for its operation on the legal device of a directed verdict. <lb/>Further, in the absence of a true presumption, no secondary burden <lb/>will be thrust on to the defence. The secondary burden is the risk <lb/>of a directed verdict; generally there is no directed verdict of guilt <lb/>in a criminal case. This is not to say that an accused who introduces <lb/>no evidence does not run any risk. He will of course run the risk of <lb/>the jury accepting the evidence of the prosecution and convicting. <lb/>This is not, however, a legal risk, i.e. it does not depend on a legal <lb/>device. <lb/>What then of the primary burden in our hypothetical case? <lb/>This again is a legal notion depending on the legal device of the <lb/>judge&apos;s direction to the jury. Having refused the application for a <lb/>directed verdict of acquittal, the judge must, in his direction at the <lb/>end of the case, explain that the risk of non-persuasion rests on the <lb/>prosecution. He will inform the jury that if they positively accept <lb/>the evidence offered and the inferences suggested by the prosecution, <lb/>they must then convict; or if, on the whole evidence, they are left with <lb/>a reasonable doubt as to the guilt of the accused, they must then <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>8 Special Lectures: Evidence, Law Society of Upper Canada (1955). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>
    

			<body>acquit. It is the risk of this particular jury being left with a reason-<lb/>able doubt that is properly referred to as the primary burden. <lb/>The tendency has been to lump both these notions under the <lb/>one term &quot;burden of proof&quot;. The confusion which inevitably results <lb/>is well exemplified in the following passage from a recent Ontario <lb/>judgment. <lb/>&quot;It is possession by an accused person of recently stolen goods that <lb/>constitutes the foundation of a prima facie case against him and creates <lb/>a presumption of guilt. It is a persuasive presumption which imposes <lb/>on the accused person a burden of giving an explanation of his possession <lb/>that might reasonably be true. When such an explanation has been <lb/>given the burden then continues to rest, as always, on the Crown to <lb/>prove the guilt of the accused beyond reasonable doubt.&quot; 9 <lb/>Nothing can &quot;then continue to rest, as always&quot;,-the phrase does <lb/>not make sense, nor does the much quoted direction from Sclhama <lb/>and Abramovitch make legal sense: <lb/>&apos;Where the prisoner is charged with receiving recently stolen property, <lb/>when the prosecution has proved the possession by the prisoner, and <lb/>that the goods had been recently stolen, the jury should be told that <lb/>they may, not that they must, in the absence of any reasonable <lb/>explanation, find the prisoner quilty.&quot;1o <lb/>The purpose of a judge&apos;s direction to a jury is (1) to control the <lb/>jury, (2) to assist the jury. In what way does the above direction <lb/>fulfill these functions? The jury are told that they may convict. <lb/>Now &quot;may&quot; imports &quot;may not&quot; so the direction can be paraphrased <lb/>in part to read, <lb/>&quot;The jury must be told that they may or may not... in the absence of <lb/>any reasonable explanation find the prisoner guilty.&quot; <lb/>I hope that the absurdity of such direction is obvious. It neither <lb/>controls nor assists the jury in any way and if it conveys to the jury <lb/>anything at all, it is that they are free to act capriciously in the <lb/>matter. Further, as pointed out in argument in Morin, if the trial <lb/>judge uses the word &quot;presumption&quot; in such context, the jury in an <lb/>attempt to take some meaning from the direction, are likely to take <lb/>it at the least as meaning that they are expected to convict. <lb/>Before attempting a solution to the mystery of the proper function <lb/>of the so-called doctrine, it is proposed to examine two recent Ontario <lb/>cases. <lb/>Regina v. O&apos;Keefe <lb/>This was an appeal from a conviction on a charge of breaking <lb/>and entering. Stolen goods, the subject matter of the charge, were <lb/>proved to bear the finger prints of the accused. The trial judge based <lb/>the conviction on a finding that; <lb/>(i) the fingerprints established that the accused had had <lb/>possession of the goods, and <lb/></body>
    
                <listBibl>9 1. v. O&apos;Keefe, ante footnote 4 at p. 502, per Laidlaw, J.A. <lb/>10 Ante footnote I at p. 49, per Reading, L.C.J. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">(VOL. I <lb/>1959] Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession <lb/></note>

			<page>75 <lb/></page>

			<body>(ii) the explanation offered by the accused was not one that he <lb/>could accept as one that might reasonably be true. <lb/>The Court of Appeal allowed the appeal, quashed the conviction <lb/>and ordered a judgment of acquittal entered. It is proposed to <lb/>examine each of the judgments. <lb/>Laidlaw J.A. <lb/>Laidlaw J.A. apparently based his decision on a finding that the <lb/>Crown had &quot;failed to establish a prima facie case against the accused <lb/>because there was no sufficient proof that any of the stolen articles <lb/>were in the possession of the accused at any time.&quot;&apos;-&apos; The decision <lb/>to quash the conviction did not then depend on the so-called doctrine <lb/>of recent possession, since in this instance there was no basis estab-<lb/>lished on which to found the so-&apos;called doctrine. Admittedly, there is <lb/>some ambiguity as to the meaning intended to be conveyed by the <lb/>term &quot;&apos;prima facie&quot; by reason of the reference to &quot;conclusive proof&quot; <lb/>in the preceding paragraph. <lb/>&quot;The mere fact that a person has handled stolen goods and left his <lb/>finger prints on them is not conclusive proof that he had possession in <lb/>law of them.&quot; 12 <lb/>Now, in order to get its case to the jury, the prosecution is not <lb/>required to produce any more than evidence on which a reasonable <lb/>jury, properly directed, could find possession. It is not required to <lb/>demonstrate possession. True, the finger prints are not conclusive <lb/>but it is submitted that this is immaterial. <lb/>The paragraph continues: <lb/>&quot;That fact alone does not raise any presumption that they came into his <lb/>possession in a dishonest or unlawful manner.&quot; 13 <lb/>If the fingerprints would not support a finding of possession in <lb/>law, then it is hard to see how they could establish something which <lb/>depends upon a finding of possession in law. <lb/>The paragraph continues: <lb/>&quot;The inference cannot be drawn from that fact alone, that he had any <lb/>control whatsoever in respect of the stolen goods: Indeed, the mere <lb/>fact of handling stolen goods and leaving fingerprints upon them is <lb/>equally consistent with innocence as with any wrongful act in respect of <lb/>them.&quot; 14 <lb/>The first sentence of this concluding portion clearly refers to <lb/>possession in law. The final sentence however refers to &quot;a wrongful <lb/>act in respect of them&quot;. It must be pointed out that &quot;possession in <lb/>law of stolen goods&quot; is not of itself wrongful in the absence of guilty <lb/>knowledge on the part of the possessor. <lb/>Taken as a whole, however, the paragraph does support the <lb/>suggestion that Laidlaw J.A. allowed the appeal on the basis that <lb/>there was no evidence on which a reasonable jury could have found <lb/></body>
    
            <listBibl>11 R. v. O&apos;Keefe, [19581 O.R. 499, at p. 505 (C.A.). <lb/>12 Ibid., at p. 505. <lb/>13 Ibid., at p. 505. <lb/>14 Ibid., at p. 505. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>possession. This suggestion is further supported by the references to <lb/>prima facie proof of possession in the judgments of Lebel and Morden <lb/>JJ.A. in the same case. By this view, the remarks of Laidlaw J.A. <lb/>on the so-called doctrine of recent possession must be read as obiter <lb/>dicta. <lb/>In any event, the learned judge defined the so-called doctrine of <lb/>recent possession (in the passage quoted above&apos; 5 ) and considered the <lb/>finding of the trial judge that the explanation advanced by the <lb/>accused was not one he could accept as &quot;one which might reasonably <lb/>be true&quot;. <lb/>&quot;In a case in which the doctrine of recent possession is properly <lb/>applicable, the accused may be found guilty in the absence of an explana-<lb/>tion of his possession of stolen goods that may reasonably be true. In <lb/>my opinion, the accused gave an explanation of that kind and character <lb/>and the burden then continued to rest on the Crown to prove beyond <lb/>reasonable doubt that the accused was guilty of the offence with which <lb/>he was charged.&quot;16 <lb/>The explanation actually advanced by the accused was that he <lb/>had happened to meet a man named George who told him that he <lb/>was &quot;in the selling field&quot;; that George asked if -he could sell the <lb/>accused anything and that out of curiosity, he had examined some <lb/>of the goods, leaving his finger prints upon them. It must be pointed <lb/>out that this is not an explanation of his possession of the goods. It <lb/>is a denial of possession in law. His Lordship concluded: <lb/>&quot;The explanation given by the accused in this case creates in my mind <lb/>a reasonable doubt as to his guilt, and the Crown offered no evidence <lb/>in reply to remove that doubt. Therefore, in my opinion, the case for the <lb/>prosecution fails for want of proof.&quot;17 <lb/>In view of the well settled rule that in general a court of appeal <lb/>will not substitute its finding of fact for that of the trial judge, it <lb/>must be taken that the decision was that no reasonable jury could <lb/>have been left without a reasonable doubt as to guilt, i.e. the verdict <lb/>could not be supported by the evidence. <lb/>LeBel J.A. <lb/>LeBel J.A., while he did not agree with Laidlaw J.A. that proof of <lb/>the fingerprints would not constitute a Prima facie case, apparently <lb/>allowed the appeal on the ground that the verdict could not be <lb/>supported by the evidence. <lb/>&quot;The explanation might reasonably be true on the state of the record <lb/>in my opinion, and he was entitled, therefore, to the benefit of the doubt. <lb/>I agree with Morden J.A., as to the cogency, from the Crown&apos;s stand-<lb/>point, of the evidence of the fingerprints. They were found upon <lb/>recently stolen goods to which the appellant had had no lawful right of <lb/>access, and I should be reluctant, indeed, to hold that the law is such <lb/>that no explanation was required of him in the circumstances. I think <lb/>there was. He had prima facie possession, at least . .. The appellant <lb/>was called upon at the end of the Crown&apos;s case to show, if he could, <lb/>that his account of an innocent handling of the goods was one that <lb/>might reasonably be true. This is what... the appellant showed here.&quot; 18 <lb/></body>
    
            <listBibl>15 !id., at p. 505. <lb/>16 Ibid., at p. 505. <lb/>17bid., at p. 506. <lb/>18 Ibid., at p. 507. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">(VOL. I <lb/>1959] Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession <lb/></note>

			<page>77 <lb/></page>

			<body>Only two things suggest that the learned judge was influenced <lb/>by the so-called doctrine of recent possession. Firstly, the proposition <lb/>that with the establishment of a prima facie case a burden of some <lb/>sort is imposed on the accused, and secondly, the references to &quot;an <lb/>explanation which might reasonably be true&quot;. It should be noted <lb/>thatin Rex v. WoolmingtonP 9 the House of Lords held that the <lb/>establishment of a prima facie case by the prosecution did not, of <lb/>itself, impose any burden on the defence. <lb/>Morden J.A. <lb/>Morden J.A. differed with Laidlaw J.A. as to the legal significance <lb/>of the fingerprint evidence. <lb/>&quot;In my opinion, the Crown had made out a prima facie case of <lb/>possession in law against the appellant. If this trial had been before a <lb/>Jury, the Judge could not have directed them to bring in a verdict of <lb/>acquittal.&quot; 20 <lb/>&quot;.. . At this stage of the case, no question of proof beyond a reasonable <lb/>doubt arises. From the proof of the appellant&apos;s fingerprints upon the <lb/>stolen articles, an inference could have been drawn that he had possession <lb/>in law. Whether or not such an inference should be drawn in any <lb/>particular case is a question for the jury, and in this case for the trial <lb/>Judge only, after all the evidence had been adduced. <lb/>In my opinion, in the instant case the trial Judge correctly rejected <lb/>the motion of the appellant&apos;s counsel to dismiss the charge at the <lb/>conclusion of the Crown&apos;s case. <lb/>The secondary onus, that of adducing evidence, passed to the appellant. <lb/>If he had called no evidence explaining the presence of his fingerprints, <lb/>then he would have run the risk of the Judge drawing the inference <lb/>that he had had possession in law and finding him guilty. However, he <lb/>did give evidence on his own behalf and I agree with the careful analysis <lb/>of this evidence by Laidlaw J.A. and his opinion of its affect. The <lb/>appellant&apos;s explanation of the presence of his finger prints, in all the <lb/>circumstances of this case, might reasonably be true. The Crown had <lb/>thus failed to discharge the primary onus, which continued throughout <lb/>the trial, of proving that the appellant had had possession in law of the <lb/>goods. The essential foundation for the doctrine of recent possession <lb/>was not established and the appellant was, therefore, entitled to have <lb/>been acquitted. ... &quot;21 <lb/>It would appear from this that Morden J.A. acknowledges the <lb/>existence of three different kinds of burdens of proof. He agrees <lb/>with the proposition, set out earlier in this article, that one may be <lb/>described as &quot;Primary&quot;, continuing throughout the trial and con-<lb/>cerned with persuading the trier after all the evidence has been <lb/>adduced. He agrees further that there is a different onus on the <lb/>prosecution of establishing a prima facie case, with the penalty of a <lb/>directed verdict of acquittal in the event of failure. This is referred <lb/>to by His Lordship, by implication, as the secondary burden In the <lb/>above quoted sentence, &quot;The secondary onus, that of adducing <lb/>evidence, passed to the appellant&quot;. However, this burden, which <lb/>&quot;passed&quot; to the appellant, was not the same ,burden as had rested <lb/>on the prosecution up till the moment the trial judge rejected the <lb/>motion for a directed verdict. The secondary burden on the prosecu-<lb/>tion was a burden with Zegal effect-it was the risk of a directed <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>19 [1935] A.C. 462 <lb/>2 0 . v. O&apos;Keefe, ante at p. 509. <lb/>21 Ibid., at pp. 509, 510. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>verdict; the so-called secondary onus on the appellant had no legaZ <lb/>effect-if he had not adduced evidence there would have been no legal <lb/>consequence, no directed verdict of conviction. His was not the legal <lb/>risk, but the factual risk of the trier saying &quot;Well, he has not given <lb/>an explanation, and unexplained possession convinces me of his guilt&quot;. <lb/>Suppose he advanced an explanation that in the mind of a trial judge <lb/>sitting with a jury, might reasonably be true, would the trial judge <lb/>thereupon direct the jury to acquit? Surely not!2 2 In the words of <lb/>Morden J.A. himself, &quot;whether or not an inference should be drawn <lb/>in any particular case is a question for the jury&quot;. 2 3 It is this factual <lb/>risk of losing the case which has caused great confusion in the <lb/>classification of burdens of proof. It has been variously referred to <lb/>as the &quot;provisional&quot; burden, the &quot;tactical&quot; burden, both of which are <lb/>devoid of legal effect. It is presumably what Laidlaw J.A. referred <lb/>to as &quot;a persuasive presumption&quot;. 24 That such persuasive presump-<lb/>tion is devoid of legal effect is obvious from the already quoted words <lb/>of Laidlaw J.A. <lb/>... imposes . . . a burden of giving an explanation .. . that might <lb/>reasonably be true. When such an explanation has been given the burden <lb/>then continues to rest, as always, on the Crown to prove the guilt of the <lb/>accused beyond reasonable bounds.&quot; 25 <lb/>In other words, whether or not the accused gives an explanation <lb/>that might reasonably be true, the burden of proving the guilt of the <lb/>accused beyond a reasonable doubt rests upon the Crown. If the so-<lb/>called burden resting on an accused has no legal effect, why mention <lb/>it? Why give it a legal name? It Is hoped to attempt to answer this <lb/>question after an examination of another recent Ontario case. <lb/>Regina v. Hogg <lb/>This was an appeal from a conviction on two counts, the first of <lb/>breaking and entering and theft, the second of receiving goods know-<lb/>ing them to have been stolen. The defence was an alibi for the time <lb/>when the goods were proved to have been stolen and an explanation <lb/>that the accused was merely keeping the goods for another person <lb/>and &quot;did not know the stuff was stolen&quot;. There was no direct evidence <lb/>as to the breaking and entering and theft charge. One of the grounds <lb/>of appeal was that the trial Judge had failed to properly direct the <lb/>jury on the doctrine of recent possession. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>2 2 Glanville Williams in his Criminal Law, The General Part (1953), at <lb/>p. 698, advances the converse proposition that the trial judge may test the <lb/>efendant&apos;s evidence in rebuttal in order to see whether it is fit to be left to <lb/>the jury. In this view, the trial judge, at the end of the course, would <lb/>consider the reasonableness of an explanation advanced by accused before <lb/>permitting that explanation to go to the jury. It would appear that there Is <lb/>no authority for such proposition if one appreciates that the remarks, e.g. In <lb/>Eichler v. The King, [19391 S.C.R. 101, as to the trial judge applying his mind <lb/>to the reasonableness of the explanation, refer to a trial judge sitting alone. <lb/>He is then to apply his mind to such a question just as the jury must do. <lb/>Mancini v. D.P.P., [1942] A.C. 1, is authority for an unrelated proposition that <lb/>a trial judge need not put evidence to a jury, which even if believed by the <lb/>jury would not amount to a defence in law. <lb/>23 R. v. O&apos;Keefe, ante at p. 509. <lb/>24 Ibid., at p. 502. <lb/>25 Ibid., at p. 502. <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="headnote">[VOL.. I <lb/>1959] Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession <lb/></note>

			<page>79 <lb/></page>

			<body>Schroeder J.A. <lb/>In allowing the appeal and directing a new trial, Schroeder, J.A. <lb/>said, <lb/>... A careful perusal of the charge does not disclose that any instruc-<lb/>tion was given to the jury in accordance with the rule stated in Pichler <lb/>v. The King, [19391 S.C.R. 101.... The learned trial Judge instructed <lb/>the jury that in considering the alibi defence presented by the two <lb/>accused, they should determine whether it &quot;might reasonably be true&quot; <lb/>but no similar instruction was given to the jury with respect to the <lb/>appellant&apos;s explanation of his possession of the stolen property.. . &quot; <lb/>&quot; . In my respectful opinion the objection taken to the learned trial <lb/>Judge&apos;s charge is fatal, and the non-direction complained of amounts to <lb/>misdirection. Recent possession of goods proved to have been stolen is <lb/>at most prima facie evidence that they have been illegally obtained, and <lb/>is circumstantial evidence from which an adverse inference may be drawn <lb/>in the absence of an explanation which might reasonably be true. Recent <lb/>possession standing by itself could not support a finding of guilt, because <lb/>it is not inconsistent with innocence. It is the absence of an explanation <lb/>which might reasonably be true that gives probative force to the circum-<lb/>stances of such recent possession: R. v. Scarle (1929), 51 C.C.C. 128. In <lb/>defining the doctrine of recent possession the learned trial Judge did not <lb/>direct the jury&apos;s attention to the importance to be attached to the <lb/>prisoner&apos;s explanation of his possession of the goods when applying that <lb/>doctrine ... &quot;,26 <lb/>Schroeder J.A. then referred to the &quot;true rule&quot; as found in <lb/>Richler, 2 Schama, 28 and Ungaro. 29 <lb/>Porter C.J.O. (MacKay J.A. concurring) <lb/>Porter C.J.O. concurred with the result arrived at by Schroeder <lb/>J.A. but disagreed in part with his statement of the law as to recent <lb/>possession and its force and effect as prima facie evidence. <lb/>&quot;. .. Recent possession of goods proved to have been stolen is prima facie <lb/>evidence that they have been illegally obtained. Recent possession <lb/>standing by itself could support a finding of guilt... .&quot;30 <lb/>If this passage and the statements of Schroeder J.A. (set in italics <lb/>in the judgment quoted above) be compared, there appears to be a <lb/>disagreement as to the meaning of &quot;prima facie.&quot; When Schroeder <lb/>J.A. says &quot;Recent possession is at most prima facie evidence&quot; and <lb/>then &quot;Recent possession standing by itself could not support a finding <lb/>of guilt&quot;, he might be understood as drawing a distinction between <lb/>&quot;prima facie evidence&quot; and &quot;evidence which could support a finding <lb/>of guilt&quot;. This, indeed, would appear to be the meaning that Porter <lb/>C.J.O. took from his words. However, when one tries to attach <lb/>meaning to the words &quot;standing by itself&quot;, it becomes apparent that <lb/>the disagreement is merely verbal. Recent possession cannot &quot;stand <lb/>by itself&quot; at the end of the case (a finding of guilt can only be made <lb/>at the end of a case). If there is no explanation of the possession, <lb/>then it stands with the fact of no explanation (an explanation which <lb/>might not reasonably be true is, in legal effect, no explanation). As <lb/></body>
    
                <listBibl>2 6 R . v. Hogg, [1958) O.R. 723 at pp. 727, 728 (italics added). <lb/>27 [19391 S.C.R. 101. <lb/>28 (1914), 11 Cr. App. R. 45. <lb/>29 [1950) S.C.R. 430. <lb/>3 0 R . v. Hogg at 729. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>suggested at the beginning of this article, the absence of an explana-<lb/>tion is just as much a fact as the presence of an explanation. <lb/>Is not the Crown under the secondary burden of introducing <lb/>evidence as to this fact of no explanation in order to avoid a directed <lb/>verdict of acquittal? It is submitted that the Crown is under no <lb/>such &apos;burden and that it is the so-called doctrine of recent possession <lb/>which frees the Crown from this risk of a directed verdict. It is <lb/>further submitted that the doctrine of recent possession does no more <lb/>than &apos;discharge this burden. <lb/>To re-state the author&apos;s proposition: a jury could logically infer <lb/>the fact of stealing or guilty knowledge on the basis of (1) possession <lb/>in law, (2) no (reasonable) explanation of such possession. Generally <lb/>the prosecution must introduce evidence upon the basis of which an <lb/>inference of guilt could be drawn by a reasonable jury. If the general <lb/>rule is applied, the Crown would therefore be required to establish <lb/>the two basic facts of (1) possession in law and (2) no (reasonable) <lb/>explanation, or suffer a directed verdict. In these cases of theft and <lb/>receiving where the doctrine applies, the Crown is, however, freed <lb/>from the risk of a verdict being directed on the ground that they have <lb/>introduced no evidence which could support a finding of no (reason-<lb/>able) explanation. They must be allowed to go to the jury on evidence <lb/>which could establish possession in law. <lb/>If this proposition be accepted, then the apparent conflict between <lb/>the views of Schroeder J.A. and Porter C.J.O. disappears and they <lb/>may both be taken as supporting the following proposition: <lb/>(i) Possession of goods proved to have been recently stolen is <lb/>prima facie evidence that they have been illegally obtained, <lb/>i.e. the Crown will escape a directed verdict by introduding <lb/>evidence on which a reasonable jury could find possession <lb/>in law. <lb/>(ii) A reasonable jury could infer guilt upon the basis of posses-<lb/>sion in law and the absence of an explanation which might <lb/>reasonably be true. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>It is this writer&apos;s contention that the doctrine of recent possession <lb/>has no other function than to discharge the secondary burden which <lb/>would otherwise rest on the prosecution. In this view, therefore, <lb/>the doctrine of recent possession is a matter for the judge and sould <lb/>never be mentioned to the jury. <lb/>What then of the direction apparently required by the Schama <lb/>judgment? If one examines the charge of the learned trial Judge <lb/>in that case, it is apparent that he had, in effect, directed the jury <lb/>that unless they found an explanation to satisfy themselves, they <lb/>must find the accused guilty. It is submitted that the oft-quoted <lb/>words of the Court of Criminal Appeal amount to no more than &quot;the <lb/>learned trial Judge should not have told them that they must convict&quot;. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="headnote">(VOL. I <lb/>1959] Burdens of Proof and the Doctrine of Recent Possession <lb/></note>

			<page>81 <lb/></page>

			<body>In any case of theft or receiving in which the prosecution <lb/>establishes possession of the goods there are two possibilities: <lb/>(i) the accused may offer no explanation of such possession, or <lb/>(Ii) the accused may offer an explanation. <lb/>Admittedly, according to Schama, where there is no explanation <lb/>the jury should be directed that they may find the accused guilty. <lb/>It has earlier been submitted that such direction is meaningless. <lb/>What would amount to a helpful direction in such a case? It is <lb/>submitted that, where the prosecution has introduced prima facie <lb/>evidence of possession in law and the accused has offered no explana-<lb/>tion at all, the trial Judge might usefully direct the jury in the <lb/>following way. <lb/>If you are not satisfied beyond a reasonable doubt that the accused had <lb/>possession in law of the goods, you must acquit. If you are satisfied <lb/>eyond a reasonable doubt as to his possession in law of these goods then <lb/>you wil take into account the absence of any explanation of such <lb/>possession. If, however, you are left with a reasonable doubt on the <lb/>whole evidence as to the guilt or innocence of the accused, then you must <lb/>acquit. <lb/>The objection may be made that such a direction, in the absence of <lb/>any explanation, might amount to misdirection in that it would be <lb/>&quot;comment on the failure of the person charged to testify&quot;, contrary <lb/>to the Canada Evidence Act s. 5(5). BurdeZZ 31 is, however, authority <lb/>that such a comment is not prohibited. <lb/>What direction is suggested in a case where the accused, either <lb/>himself or through other witnesses, has put forward an explanation <lb/>of his possession? Here the writer can call on distinguished authority <lb/>for the following: <lb/>&quot;It is not necessary to use on all occasions the formula which was used <lb/>in Rex v. Schama and Abramovitch... if the explanation given by the <lb/>accused persons which, when they have given it becomes part of the <lb/>sum of evidence in the case, leaves the jury in doubt whether the <lb/>accused honestly or dishonestly received the goods, they are entitled to <lb/>be acquitted because the case has not been proved.&quot; 32 <lb/>In other words the jury should be told that if they are left with <lb/>a reasonable doubt on the whole evidence, they must acquit. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>31 (1906), 11 O.L.R. 440, at p. 448, per Osler J.A. <lb/>32 B. v. Hepwortk and Fearnley, [19551 2 Q.B. 600, at pp. 602, 603, per <lb/>Goddard, L.C.J. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>