<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Gary Murray</forename>
          <surname>Keyes</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="sperber">Marcia Sperber</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo Okamura</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="lfoppiano">Luca Foppiano</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2026-01-30T09:00:27.508Z">30/01/2026 10:00:27</date>
        <title>final</title>
        <idno type="fileref">10.60082_2817-5069.2528</idno>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Osgoode Hall Law School, York University</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">1959</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.60082/2817-5069.2528</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Gary Murray Keyes. (1959). Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution. Osgoode Hall Law Journal, 1(2), 20-48. DOI: 10.60082/2817-5069.2528</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-12T15:44:35.756155Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">536e79c</label>
        <label type="flavor">article/dh-law-footnotes</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-12-12T15:44:35.756155Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-15T15:17:39.203Z" status="checked" who="#sperber">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-16T16:11:36.486Z" status="approved" who="#kazuyo">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
    <change when="2026-01-30T09:00:41.025Z" status="candidate" who="#lfoppiano">
      <desc>Corrections</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Osgoode Hall Law Journal <lb/>Osgoode Hall Law Journal <lb/>Volume 1, Number 2 (April 1959) <lb/>Article 3 <lb/>April 1959 <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/>Gary Murray Keyes <lb/>Follow this and additional works at: https://digitalcommons.osgoode.yorku.ca/ohlj <lb/>Article <lb/>Citation Information <lb/>Citation Information <lb/>Keyes, Gary Murray. &quot;Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution.&quot; Osgoode Hall Law Journal 1.2 (1959) : <lb/>20-48. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.60082/2817-5069.2528 <lb/>https://digitalcommons.osgoode.yorku.ca/ohlj/vol1/iss2/3 <lb/>This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the Journals at Osgoode Digital Commons. It has been <lb/>accepted for inclusion in Osgoode Hall Law Journal by an authorized editor of Osgoode Digital Commons. <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/>This article is available in Osgoode Hall Law Journal: https://digitalcommons.osgoode.yorku.ca/ohlj/vol1/iss2/3 <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/>GARY MURRAY KEYES *<lb/></front>
	  
	  <body>For the most part, fundamental freedoms have been adequately <lb/>safeguarded in Canada, but there have been a number of disturbing <lb/>incidents in recent years. The Quebec Padlock Law of 1937, aimed at <lb/>preventing the propogation of Communism, also struck at freedom of <lb/>speech and religion;1 the Alberta &quot;Press Bill&quot; of the same year, was <lb/>an attempt on the part of the state to restrict freedom of the press; 2 <lb/>the threatened deportation of Canadian citizens of Japanese origin in <lb/>1945, 3 and arbitrary arrest and interrogation in the espionage in-<lb/>vestigation of 1946, all illustrate that the question of adequate pro-<lb/>tection of civil liberties is not an imaginary problem. Since the <lb/>adoption by the United Nations of the Universal Declaration of Human <lb/>Rights, 4 there has been a growing conviction that certain civil <lb/>liberties would be better safeguarded by means of a constitutional <lb/>amendment to the British North America Act or by a solemn <lb/>statutory declaration of the federal Parliament. This conviction was <lb/>early exemplified in a speech by John Diefenbaker in the 1947 House <lb/>of Commons Debates in support of a Canadian Charter of Human <lb/>Rights, when he said that: <lb/>&quot;a Bill of Rights ... <lb/>would be a declaration delineating the field of <lb/>liberty that must be reserved to the individual against continuing invasion <lb/>on the part of the state.&quot;5 <lb/>Now we are contemplating a manifestation of the views expressed <lb/>by Mr. Diefenbaker and many others, namely the federal Bill for the <lb/>Recognition and Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Free-<lb/>doms. 6 We are asking ourselves just what rights we possess as <lb/>citizens? What do freedom of religion, of the press, of speech, and <lb/>association mean in Canadian law? Have we any guarantee of <lb/>equality before the law? Above all is there any value in trying to <lb/>draw up a Bill of Rights setting out the freedoms and rights we feel <lb/>the constitution should protect? Or is it wiser to let the judiciary <lb/></body>

			<front>* Mr. Keyes is presently enrolled in the Third Year of the Osgoode Hall Law <lb/>School. </front>
	  
	  <listBibl>1 See Communistic Propaganda Act, R.S.Q. 1941, c. 52, ss. 3, 12; Switzman <lb/>v. Elbling and A.G. of Quebec, [1957] S.C.R. 265. <lb/>2 See Reference re Alberta Statutes, [1938] S.C.R. 100; [1939] A.C. 117: <lb/>3 See Co-Operative Committee on Japanese Candians v. A.G. for Canada, <lb/>[1947] A.C. 87 (P.C.). <lb/>4 For preliminary drafts and final text see (1948), 26 Can. Bar Rev. 548, <lb/>1106 and (1949), 27 Can. Bar Rev. 203. <lb/>5 Canada, House of Commons Debates: 1947, vol. 4, at p. 3155. <lb/>6 Bill C-60, first reading September 5, 1958; See Appendix &quot;A&quot; for full text. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

	  <page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>guard our civil liberties as has been the tradition in England for so <lb/>long? 7 To answer these questions, it will be the burden of the first <lb/>part of this article to define the term &quot;civil liberties&quot;, and determine <lb/>what protection they have been afforded by our written and unwritten <lb/>constitution and concomitant case law. The second part of this paper <lb/>shall deal with the jurisdiction of the proposed Bill of Rights as a <lb/>federal enactment, the meaning in law of some of its salient terms such <lb/>as &quot;due process of law&quot;, and the comparative value of a statutory <lb/>enactment on civil liberties in the light of American and British <lb/>experience. <lb/>Part I-Traditional Safeguards of Our Rights and Liberties <lb/>A. The Meaning of The Term &quot;Civil Liberties&quot; <lb/>A leading writer on Constitutional Law, Professor F. R. Scott, <lb/>has put forth the view that the distinction between freedom and right <lb/>is without any real difference in law. 8 In his view, there is no <lb/>freedom where there is no right. Freedom of speech involves the <lb/>absence of restraint upon the person enjoying the freedom, but it <lb/>must also involve a legal restraint upon all persons who would interfere <lb/>with that freedom, and these legal restraints come either from the <lb/>common law or from legislation. <lb/>It is suggested that these statements by Professor Scott are too <lb/>sweeping and only add to the confusion surrounding the interpretation <lb/>of the term &quot;property and civil rights&quot; in head 13 of section 92 of the <lb/>B.N.A. Act. Most writers in the field of jurisprudence distinguish <lb/>between a right and freedom. Indeed, a careful analysis indicates <lb/>that a right exists where there is positive law on the subject, a liberty <lb/>where there is no law against it. 9 <lb/>A right is a correlative to a duty in another person, while a <lb/>liberty is not. The argument that rights and freedoms are the same <lb/>is usually based on the proposition that every one has a right not to <lb/>be interfered with in the exercise of his liberties. But, in fact, there <lb/>are two essentially different premises involved in this proposition: <lb/>the first means that he does not commit a legal wrong by doing <lb/>so-and-so, and the second means that you commit a legal wrong by <lb/>interfering with my doing so-and-so. 1 0 <lb/>Circumstances arise where there is a liberty to do something <lb/>without a right not to be interfered with in doing it <lb/>One of the best <lb/>examples of a liberty or freedom unprotected by a corresponding <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>7See McD. Clokie, The Preservation of Civil Liberties (1947), 13, Can. <lb/>J. Eco. Pol. Sci. at 394. <lb/>s Scott, Dominion Jurisdiction over Human Rights and Fundamental <lb/>Freedoms (1949), 27 Can. Bar Rev. 497. <lb/>9 See generally, Storey v. Graham, [18991 1 Q.B. at p. 411 per Channel <lb/>L.J.; Allen v. Flood, [1898] A.C. at p. 29 per Cave L.J.; Hohfeld, Fundamental <lb/>Legal Conceptions (1934), pp. 38-50; Pound, Fifty Years of Jurisprudence <lb/>(1937), 50 Harv. L. Rev. 557; Salmond on Jurisprudence, 10th ed. by G. L. <lb/>Williams (1947), 328. <lb/>10 Williams, The Concept of Legal Liberty (1956), 56 Col. L. Rev. 1129. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/>[VOL.1 <lb/></note>

	  <page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>duty is freedom of speech. No one has a duty to listen to me. The <lb/>only duty might be the duty to gag me but this is part of the law <lb/>of torts. I have no right to be heard. Thus freedom of speech can <lb/>be regarded as the residium after subtracting all the particular duties <lb/>to refrain from sedition and slander, etc. <lb/>There is a dual significance in the jurisprudential distinction <lb/>between a right and freedom. On the one hand, it provides a natural <lb/>law basis for the judicial creation of certain absolute freedoms,11 <lb/>&quot;inherent rights of the Canadian citizen&quot;,12 which are immune from <lb/>abridgment by the provinces of Canada, 13 and which include &quot;freedom <lb/>of speech, religion and the inviolability of the person.&quot;14 Indeed, <lb/>certain dicta exhorting an untrammelled publication of news and <lb/>political opinion 15 might indicate that civil liberties are forbidden <lb/>powers implicit in the B.N.A. Act and incapable of abridgment by <lb/>either the provinces or the Dominion. On the other hand, the word <lb/>&quot;rights&quot; in civil rights has acquired a very special meaning in Canada <lb/>through its use to describe a particular area of provincial legislative <lb/>power in section 92(13) of the B.N.A. Act. As used there, the term <lb/>is primarily concerned with private law, the legal relationship <lb/>between persons in private life. The rights and liberties under dis-<lb/>cussion here are exclusively in the field of public law, defining <lb/>relationships between government and private persons. <lb/>The distinction between &quot;civil liberties&quot; and &quot;rights&quot; in head 13 <lb/>of section 92 is crucial to the discussion in this paper. Too often it <lb/>has been assumed that the hereto usual characterizations of &quot;civil <lb/>liberties&quot; as &quot;Property and Civil Rights&quot; are not open to question, <lb/>and that, therefore, provincial legislation constitutionally can relate <lb/>directly to the individual&apos;s basic freedoms. The reasons for judgment <lb/>given by Rand and Kellock JJ. in the Saumur 16 case, however, provide <lb/>solid support for a different, public law, basis of civil liberties. <lb/>Kellock J. in an excellent historical analysis of the origin of the <lb/>term &quot;Property and Civil Rights&quot; concludes that the Quebec Act of <lb/>1774, the Constitutional Act of 1791, the Act of Union of 1840 and <lb/>the Freedom of Worship Act of 1852 were not meant to fall within <lb/>the meaning of the phrase. In his opinion, the British North <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>11 Saumur v. The City of Quebec, [1953] 2 S.C.R. 299 at p. 329, per Rand <lb/>J.; and see generally Price, Mr. Justice Rand and The Privileges and Im-<lb/>munities of Canadian Citizens (1958), 16 Fac. of L.R. pp. 25-27. <lb/>12 Reference re Exemption of U.S. Forces from Canadian Criminal Law <lb/>(1943), 80 Can. C.C. at pp. 214-5. <lb/>13 Winner v. S.M.T. (Eastern Ltd.) and A.G. for New Brunswick, (1951) <lb/>4 D.L.R. 529, where Rand J. affirmed &quot;A right or capacity to remain and to <lb/>engage in work in the Province.&quot;&quot; <lb/>14Saumur v. City of Quebec and A.G. of Quebec, [1953] 2 S.C.R. 299 at <lb/>p. 329 where Rand J., said: &quot;Strictly speaking, civil rights arise from positive <lb/>law; but freedom of speech, religion and the inviolability of the person are <lb/>original freedoms which are at once the necessary attributes and modes of <lb/>self-expression of human beings and the primary conditions of their com-<lb/>munity life within a legal order&quot;; and see ex judicie writing, I.C. Rand, <lb/>The Right to Knowledge and Its Free Use (1954), Col. L Rev., 67. <lb/>15 Reference re Alberta Statutes, [1938] S.C.R. 100 at pp. 132-134 per <lb/>Cannon J.; and Brewin: (1957), 35 Can. Bar Rev., 234. <lb/>1 6 Saumur v. City of Quebec, ante at pp. 325-356. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

	  <page>23 <lb/></page>
				
				<body>America Act itself indicates &apos;that the subject matter of religious <lb/>profession is not a matter of provincial legislative jurisdiction within <lb/>any of the heads of section 92.17 Rand J. in the same case recognizes <lb/>that the statutory history of the expression &quot;Property and Civil <lb/>Rights&quot; demonstrates that such matters as &quot;religious belief, duty and <lb/>observances were never intended to be included within the collocation <lb/>of powers.&quot;18 The recent dedision in Switzman v. ffbing19 provided <lb/>an opportunity for Kellock J. to reaffim this distinction between <lb/>&quot;civil liberties&quot; and &quot;rights&quot; of section 92(13).20 Rand J. in the <lb/>same case declares that the Quebec Padlock Law was &quot;directed <lb/>against the freedom or civil liberty of the actor; no civil right... <lb/>is affected.... There is nothing of civil rights in this...21 <lb/>The importance, then, of this distinction between rights and <lb/>liberties throws into relief the true nature of the term civil rights <lb/>or civil liberties. Civil liberties in this connotation are distinguished <lb/>from all the other rights that individuals may enjoy under law <lb/>because they are specially buttressed in one way or another against <lb/>violation by governments. Civil liberties are also distinguishable from <lb/>political rights.22 Political rights are those which give adult citizens <lb/>the right to the franchise or qualify them to hold public office, and <lb/>so forth; civil liberties, on the other hand, are those which protect <lb/>individuals against political interference, and are not restricted to <lb/>citizens but are public rights. There are really two kinds of civil <lb/>liberties. First, there are the essential freedoms that men want for <lb/>their own sake. Secondly, there are procedural civil liberties. Both <lb/>kinds may be termed, civil liberties.23 <lb/>B. The Constitutional Basis of Civil Liberties. <lb/>The function of the Supreme Court in Canada parallels in part <lb/>that of the Supreme Court in the United States in that both courts <lb/>interpret written constitutions and can declare ultra vires statutes <lb/>which are repugnant to their provisions. In Great Britain, no such <lb/>powers exist, as there are no legal limitations on the supremacy of <lb/>the British Parliament. Civil liberties in Great Britain legally are <lb/>quite vulnerable, yet it is generally felt that the rights and liberties <lb/>of the individual are better protected there than in the United States. <lb/>The cardinal reason perhaps is that the people of Great Britain have <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>17Ibid., at p. 347; and for further comments on the distinction see: <lb/>Citizens Insurance v. Parsons (1881), App. Cas. 96 (P.C.); Union Colliery v. <lb/>Bryden, [1899] A.C. 580 (P.C.); A.G. Ont. &apos;v. H.S.R., [1903] S.C.R. 101. <lb/>28Ibid., at p. 329. <lb/>39 [1957] SC.R. 285. <lb/>20 bid., at p. 308. <lb/>21 Ibid., at p. 305. <lb/>22 Ibid., at p. 306 where Kellock J. refers to his own judgment in Saumur <lb/>v. The City of Quebec, ante, and particularly to the statement therein pro-<lb/>duced from Mr. Justice Mignault&apos;s work, as follows: &quot;Les droits sont les <lb/>facultes on avantages que les lois accordent aux personnes. Ils sont civils, <lb/>politiquies ou publics...&quot; <lb/>23 See generally, Corry, Democratic Government and Politics (1952), <lb/>Chapters 15 and 19. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/>[VOL.1 <lb/></note>

	  <page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>acquired a veneration for their statutory and common law rights <lb/>which is founded on a tradition of freedom under law and which <lb/>makes them jealous of threatened encroachments.24 <lb/>As indicated above, there has been a growing conviction in Canada <lb/>that traditional sodial and political safeguards are not sufficient and <lb/>that certain fundamental liberties should be specially protected, so <lb/>that they will not be at the mercy of any intolerant group in a <lb/>legislature or a cabinet. Aside from actual and threatened infractions <lb/>of civil liberties in recent years, one of the main reasons for the <lb/>inadequate protections referred to earlier is the uncertainty as to <lb/>which authority is responsible for their protection. Unlike the U.S. <lb/>Constitution, there are few legislative powers denied to both federal <lb/>and provincial governments. It is generally argued that each is <lb/>supreme within the limits of power conferred and that there is <lb/>nothing which is beyond the reach of either federal or provindial <lb/>law-making authority.25 It should be noted, however, that certain <lb/>observations of Rand J. in the Switzman case, do not support this <lb/>generally accepted proposition. In his opinion neither the provincial <lb/>nor the federal authorities can destroy the &quot;constitutional structure&quot;, <lb/>itself. If this is so, power to do so therefore is forbidden and beyond <lb/>the federal and provincial law-making authorities.26 <lb/>Nevertheless, the main question for determination here is whether <lb/>civil liberties are in the exclusive domain of the federal government <lb/>or of the provinces or whether they are in a common field of legis-<lb/>lation? <lb/>A convenient grouping of civil liberties for subsequent analysis <lb/>is as follows: <lb/>(1) freedom of the press and speech <lb/>(2) freedom of religion <lb/>(3) freedom of the person from interference, or security of the <lb/>person and freedom of association. <lb/>This list is by no means exhaustive. It will be used as a basis for <lb/>examining the protection presently afforded civil liberties by the <lb/>Canadian constitution. <lb/>(1) Freedom of the Press and Speech <lb/>After the &quot;Glorious Revolution&quot; of 1688-9, the infamous Licensing <lb/>Acts27 fell into disuse. Thus legislature and administrative inaction <lb/>laid the basis for freedom of the press. But it should be observed <lb/>that this does not mean that anyone can say or write whatever he <lb/>wishes with impunity. If his statements are seditious, libellous or <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>24 See generally, Mad. Dawson, The Government of Canada (1952), <lb/>Chapter 10. <lb/>25Per Lord Loreburn in A.G. Ont. v. A.G. Canada, [19121 A.C. 571 (P.C.) <lb/>at p. 581: &quot;there can be no doubt that under this organic instrument the <lb/>powers distributed between the Dominion . . . and the provinces . . . cover <lb/>the whole area of self-government within... Canada.<lb/> 6 Switzman v. ElbZing, ante at p. 307, and see Murphy v. C.P.R., [1958] <lb/>S.C.R. 626 at p. 643 per Rand J. <lb/>27 25 Henry VIII, c. 15 (1533); 14 Charles II, c. 33 (1662). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">[VOL. I <lb/>1959] <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

	  <page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>slanderous, he is liable to be punished under the criminal code or <lb/>provincial statutes.28 It is, thus only in the residium after subtract-<lb/>ig the particular duties imposed by the state, that freedom of the <lb/>press exists. <lb/>The right to receive and disseminate information is of paramount <lb/>importance in a democratic state. Of exceptional interest in this <lb/>regard is the decision of the Supreme Court of Canada in Boucher v. <lb/>The King, 29 where sedition was defined so as to remove the danger <lb/>of the Criminal Code, at the hands of the state in times of crisis, <lb/>being used to repress freedom of expression in political and religious <lb/>affairs. In this case, Aimd Boucher, a Quebec farmer, distributed <lb/>leaflets, published by the Witnesses of Jehovah, containing a vigor-<lb/>ously worded protest against what was described as the hateful <lb/>persecutions of Christians caused by &quot;priest domination.&quot; On the <lb/>first hearing of the appeal, five judges of the Supreme Court ordered <lb/>a new trial. Application was then made, and granted, to have the <lb/>appeal reargued before a full Court of nine judges. It was held <lb/>(Rinfret C.J.C., Taschereau, Cartwright and Fauteux JJ. dissenting), <lb/>that Boucher be acquitted as there was no evidence either in the <lb/>pamphlet or otherwise upon which a jury, properly instructed, could <lb/>find him guilty of the offence charged. <lb/>The main interest of this case lies in the conflict of views as <lb/>to the proper definition of sedition. A seditious libel was stated in <lb/>section 133(2) of the Criminal Code (1927) to be a libel expressive <lb/>of seditious intent. The Court had to resort to the common law of <lb/>England as the Code contained no definition of &quot;seditious intent.&quot; <lb/>The Court rejected the definition in Stephen&apos;s Digest of Criminal <lb/>Law in respect to two clauses: a seditious intention is an inten-<lb/>tion (i) &quot;to bring into hatred or contempt or to incite disaffection <lb/>against . . . the administration of justice&quot;, and (ii) &quot;to promote <lb/>feelings of ill-will and hostility between different classes of His <lb/>Majesty&apos;s subjects.&quot;30 It was finally held that neither language <lb/>calculated to promote feelings of ll-will and hostility between different <lb/>classes of His Majesty&apos;s subjects nor criticizing the courts is seditious <lb/>unless there is the intention to incite to violence or resistance to or <lb/>defiance of constituted authority. <lb/>This decision is highly significant. There can be no more power-<lb/>ful weapon for the suppression of freedom than vague definitions of <lb/>sedition and like offences. Locke J. points out that after 1689 the <lb/>press was exploited in the party warfare when the party (in power <lb/>tried to crush its opponents by prosecuting as seditious libels all <lb/>publications which supported the opposition. Giving a further state-<lb/>ment of the right of free public discussion, Mr. Justice Locke said: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>28 See The Canadian Criminal Code, 1953-54, 2-3 Elizabeth II, (Can.), c. 51; <lb/>publication of material in aid of offences against the Code: s. 123, s. 177(1) (f), <lb/>s. 179(1) (a), s. 403(1) (a); false advertising: s. 306; material declared offen-<lb/>sive: s. 150, s. 151, s. 246, ss. 247-267; An Act respecting Publications and <lb/>Public Morals, 1950, (Que.) c. 12, amen. 1950-51 (Que.) c. 13, and The Libel <lb/>and Slander Act, (1958) c. 51 (Ont.). <lb/>29 [1951] S.C.R. 265, varying on re-hearing, [1950] 1 D.L.R. 657; Brewin: <lb/>(1951), 29 Can. Bar Rev. 193. <lb/>30 Stephen&apos;s Digest of Criminal Law, 8th ed., at p. 94. <lb/>1959] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/>[VOL.1 <lb/></note>

	  <page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;The right of free public discussion upon all matters affecting the state <lb/>and its government, subject only to the restraint imposed by the laws <lb/>both civil and criminal as to defamation, and in the case of the adminis-<lb/>tration of justice to the law as to contempt of court, has long since become <lb/>firmly established.&quot;31 <lb/>It is the right, he concludes, of His Majesty&apos;s subjects to criticize <lb/>freely the manner in which the government of the country is carried <lb/>on, the conduct of those administering the government, and the justice <lb/>that is carried out. <lb/>In discussing the liberties which vest in the people, and, the free <lb/>play of ideas, Mr. Justice Rand stated, in the spirit of the great free <lb/>speech opinions of Holmes and Brandeis, that: <lb/>&quot;Freedom of thought and speech and disagreement in ideas and beliefs, <lb/>on every conceivable subject, are of the essence of our life. The clash of <lb/>critical discussion on political, social and religious subjects has too deeply <lb/>become the stuff of daily experience to suggest that mere ill-will as a <lb/>product of controversy can strike down the latter with illegality.&quot;32 <lb/>The same basic constitutional problem arose in the Reference re <lb/>Alberta Statutes.33 The Supreme Court of Canada there invalidated <lb/>the Alberta Press Bill which had been enacted by the newly-elected <lb/>Social Credit government as a measure to curtail adverse criticism <lb/>in the press of its unorthodox financial programme. It should be <lb/>stated at the outset that the decision :n that reference taken in its <lb/>strict ratio was simply that the Bill in question, being part of, and <lb/>dependent upon, a general scheme of social credit legislation already <lb/>invalidated on other constitutional grounds, fell with the other <lb/>legislation. <lb/>The decision in the Alberta Press case, is germane here, however, <lb/>because of the illuminating analysis, by three members of the Court, <lb/>of the relationship between our constitution (&quot;similar in principle <lb/>to that of the United Kingdom&quot;) our parliamentary institutions and <lb/>freedom of expression. Sir Lyman P. Duff, then Chief Justice of <lb/>Canada, was of the opinion that in addition to the federal power of <lb/>disallowance, the Dominion alone had power to legislate for the <lb/>protection of the right of free public discussion, and that it was beyond <lb/>the powers of the Provinces to abrogate the right of public debate or <lb/>suppress Its exercise in public meetings or through the medium of the <lb/>press.34 The terms in which the Chief Justice (with whom Mr. <lb/>Justice Davis concurred), spoke were sufficiently broad to embrace <lb/>federal protection of civil liberties connected with the operation of <lb/>provindial parliamentary institutions. <lb/>A similar view is expressed by Cannon J.: <lb/>&quot; .. no political party can elect a prohibitory barrier to prevent the <lb/>electors from getting information concerning the policy of the Govern. <lb/>ment .... There must be an untrammelled publication of the news and <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>31 Boucher v. The King, ante p. 330. <lb/>32 Ibid., at p. 288. <lb/>33 [1938] S.C.R. 100; [1939] A.C. 117; and see Laskin: (1941), 19 Can. <lb/>Bar Rev. 49; Nichols: (1948), 26 Can. Bar Rev. 1001; Brewin: (1957), 35 <lb/>Can. Bar Rev. 554. <lb/>34 Ibid., at pp. 132-134. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

	  <page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>political parties contending for ascendancy ... the federal parliament is <lb/>the sole authority to curtail, if deemed expedient and in the public <lb/>interest, the freedom of the press in discussing public affairs and the <lb/>equal rights in that respect of all citizens throughout the Dominion.&quot;35 <lb/>Cannon J. also made another highly significant observation. He <lb/>threw out the idea that Canadian citizens enjoy freedom of expression <lb/>as an incident or piivilege of their citizenship status.36 This idea was <lb/>later picked up, though without acknowledgment, by Rand J. in his <lb/>remarks on the freedom to move from place to place in the Winner <lb/>case: <lb/>cc. <lb/>a province cannot prevent a Canadian from entering it except, <lb/>conceivably.., for some local reason.&quot;37 <lb/>In view of the fact that other reasons were given to strike down <lb/>the impugned Alberta Statutes, the remarks of the Court on civil <lb/>liberties were obiter and do not conclusively settle their general con-<lb/>stitutional basis. One half of the Court dealt with freedom of the <lb/>press and speech and each gave different reasons. According to Duff <lb/>C.J.C., the provinces cannot abridge freedom of speech because the <lb/>B.N.A. Act contemplates &quot;a Constitution similar in principle to that <lb/>of the United Kingdom&quot;, the basis of which are Parliamentary institu-<lb/>tions, to which free discussion is vital. Now an important constitu-<lb/>tional rule of the British Constitution is parliamentary supremacy. <lb/>The British Parliament can validly abrogate any civil liberty. Does <lb/>this mean that the federal Parliament can validly abrogate freedom <lb/>of discussion? According to Abbott J. in Switzman v. Elbling, <lb/>Parliament itself cannot (except by a process of constitutional <lb/>amendment) destroy freedom of discussion in peace-time. The B.N.A. <lb/>Act is, in the opinion of Abbott J., based on: <lb/>&quot;the right of candidates for Parliament or for a legislature, and of <lb/>citizens generally, to explain, criticize, debate and discuss in the freest <lb/>possible manner such matters as the qualifications, the policies and the <lb/>political and economic and social principles advocated by such candidates <lb/>or by the political parties or groups of which they can be members.&quot; <lb/>In this interpretation of the B.N.A. Act, the learned judge finds <lb/>certain constitutional guarantees of freedom implicit and incapable <lb/>of abridgment by either the provincial or federal government. This <lb/>conclusion, if well founded, has merit. It, would mean that civil <lb/>liberties could validly be regarded as forbidden powers, at least in <lb/>normal times, giving the courts a sound basis for invalidating pro-<lb/>vincial or federal legislation directly relating to such liberties. It <lb/>would assist the judiciary in discharging its function as guardian of <lb/>the individual&apos;s rights and freedoms. The initial question of which <lb/>authority has the constitutional right to legislate on civil liberties <lb/>would have been settled, and the courts could proceed as invited to <lb/>define the boundaries of these freedoms. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>35 Ibid., at pp. 146-147. <lb/>36 Ibid., at p. 149. <lb/>37 Winner v. S.M.T. (Eastern Ltd.), [19511 S.C.R. 887 at p. 920. <lb/>38 [19571 S.C.R. 285; Brewin: (1957), 35 Can. Bar Rev. 554; Cooper: (1954), <lb/>1 McGill L.J. 281. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/>[VOL.1 <lb/></note>

	  <page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>Abbott J.&apos;s conclusion, however, is open to question on two main <lb/>grounds. In the first place, the dedisions of the majority of several <lb/>members of the Court were severely limited. Kerwin C.J.C., Locke, <lb/>Cartwright, Fauteux and Nolan JJ., found as the sole ground for <lb/>striking down the infamous Padlock Act of Quebec4O that its effect <lb/>was to make criminal the propagation of communism. It was not <lb/>legislation in relation to &quot;property and civil rights in the Province or <lb/>in relation to matter of a merely private or local nature in the <lb/>province&quot; (notwithstanding the dissent of Taschereau J.). It was <lb/>criminal legislation under the exclusive control of the federal Parlia-<lb/>ment. Therefore, the observations of Rand J. (with whom Kellock J. <lb/>concurred), and Abbott J. go far beyond what was necessary for the <lb/>dedisior. In this regard, it should be noted that Rand J. did not go <lb/>as far as Abbott J.: he nowhere says there is a forbidden power <lb/>except when it comes to tampering with what he calls the &quot;consti-<lb/>tutional structure.&quot; Secondly, the learned judge bases his observa-<lb/>tion that freedom -of expression is a forbidden power on the judgment <lb/>of Duff C.J.C. in the Alberta Reference. It has already been suggested <lb/>that since only one half of the Court in that case expressed an opinion <lb/>on its civil liberties aspects, no binding conclusions should be based <lb/>on it; this is especially so as other reasons were given by all the <lb/>judges to stike down the questioned legislation. <lb/>Taken together or singly, it is submitted that the foregoing <lb/>decisions do not conclusively settle the constitutional basis for freedom <lb/>of expression, although they may work in favour of the parliament <lb/>of Canada. Because of this unsettled state of the law, it would be <lb/>rash to conclude that there as a bill of rights safeguarding freedom <lb/>of expression embodied in the B.N.A. Act. There is, therefore, a <lb/>need for judicial clarification of the status of this civil liberty; such <lb/>a clarification, moreover, may be facilitated, rather than Impaired, by <lb/>the introduction of the proposed Bill of Rights. <lb/>(2) Freedom of Religion <lb/>Aside from Sunday legislation and the separate schools question, <lb/>the issue of freedom of religion was, prior to 1953, never clearly <lb/>defined in our Court of last resort. In that year, the case of Saumur <lb/>v. The City of Quebec and the A.-G. of Quebec 41 finally reached the <lb/>Supreme Court -of Canada. This case concerned the constitutional <lb/>validity of a by-law of Quebec City under which a Jehovah&apos;s Witness <lb/>had been convicted of distributing pamphlets without the prior per-<lb/>mission of the police chief as required by the by-law. The Supreme <lb/>Court, by a five-to-four vote, held that the by-law did not apply to <lb/>prevent the defendant, as a member of the Jehovah&apos;s witnesses, from <lb/>distributing tracts in Quebec City streets. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>39 Ibid., at p. 327. <lb/>40 R.S.Q., 1941, c. 52. <lb/>41 [1953] 2 S.C.R. 299; Laskin, Our Civil Liberties (1954), 61 Queen&apos;s <lb/>Quarterly, 455; Chalmers: (1954), 12 U. of T. School of L.R. 12; Howe: <lb/>(1948), 27 Can. Bar Rev. 1248. <lb/>[VOL. I <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

	  <page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>As a result of the division of opinion, the position of the civil <lb/>liberty of freedom of religion is unsettled and unsatisfactory. A <lb/>majority of the Court, Kerwin, Rand, Kellock, Estey and Locke, JJ., <lb/>held that the legislation authorizing the by-law was beyond the <lb/>competence of the provincial legislature as an interference with <lb/>religious freedom and not a matter of property and civil rights.42 <lb/>They relied on the dicta of Duff C.J.C. and Cannon J. in the Reference <lb/>re Alberta Statutes. In essence, four judges of the majority viewed <lb/>the legislation as pertaining to censorship of religion, and, by anology <lb/>to censorship of press, they felt this to be a strictly federal matter. <lb/>Although the Court was not called upon to decide whether religion <lb/>itself was a subject matter under the legislative competence of the <lb/>Parliament of Canada, it can be inferred from the reasons given that <lb/>such is the case. <lb/>Kerwin J. as he then was, seems to support the majority, but <lb/>in fact his explicit disapproval of Duff C.J.C.&apos;s dicta in the Alberta <lb/>Reference case indicates that he considered freedom of religion (and <lb/>presumably of the press) as controlled by provincial legislature under <lb/>head 13 of section 92 of the B.N.A. Act. The by-law in question <lb/>did not apply, in his view, to the action of the accused in distributing <lb/>religious literature because of the Freedom of Worship Act which <lb/>granted religious freedom in the provinces. To all intents and <lb/>purposes, Kerwin J. decided with Rinfret C.J.C., Taschereau and <lb/>Fauteux JJ., that freedom of worship was not a subject of legislation <lb/>within the jurisdiction of Parliament but instead was a civil right in <lb/>the province and subject to the control of provincial legislatures. <lb/>The reasons given by Cartwright J. In agreeing with the minority <lb/>are significant. He finds the true nature of the legislation to be <lb/>related to the use of streets; though it might affect freedom of religion, <lb/>it was not in relation to freedom of religion. In future tests of how <lb/>far freedom of religion is beyond the competence of the provinces, <lb/>the use of this aspect theory by Cartwright J. (with whom Fauteux <lb/>concurred) would not deprive either judge from holding that legisla-<lb/>tion aimed at restricting religious freedom is beyond the power of the <lb/>Province. This characterization of the legislation by Cartwright J. <lb/>may reflect his view of the constitutional basis of civil liberties, or it <lb/>may mean that he simply has not made up his mind, or that, having <lb/>regard to the explosive nature of the case and the obvious split <lb/>between the Roman Catholic-Protestant judges, he adopted a more <lb/>compromising position. In an important constitutional case like this, <lb/>Cartwright J.&apos;s position may illustrate a rough analogy between court <lb/>solidarity and the cabinet solidarity of the federal government. <lb/>Perhaps Cartwright J., as an English-speaking Protestant, purposely <lb/>sided with the minority to prevent showing a split in the Supreme <lb/>Court to the world at large on racial and religious grounds! <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>42 But see the judgment of Kerwin 5. who based his reasons on a differ-<lb/>ent ground. <lb/>43 [1955] S.C.R. 799. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/>[VOL.1 <lb/></note>

	  <page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>If civil liberties have no independent constitutional ground, it <lb/>would be easy to find its aspect to be in relation to highways or <lb/>matters of local interest. If, however, civil liberties have an inde-<lb/>pendent constitutional basis, as indicated by the views expressed by <lb/>Duff C.J.C. and Cannon J. in the ATherta Reference and by Rand, <lb/>Kellock, Estey, Locke JJ. in the Birk&apos;s case, freedom of religion has <lb/>some measure of protection.43 In the writer&apos;s opinion, these basic <lb/>liberties would recdive more assured protection under federal author-<lb/>ity in the light of previous provincial abridgments. As it is now, <lb/>protection varies unevenly from province to province. Therefore just <lb/>as criminal law was placed under federal authority to ensure uni-<lb/>formity of justice to all the citizens of Canada, similarly, jurisdiction <lb/>over fundamental liberties should repose in the federal law-making <lb/>authority. <lb/>In Henry Birk&apos;s &amp; Sons Ltd., v. Montreal and A.-G. of Quebec, 44 <lb/>the Supreme Court of Canada unanimously held to be ultra vires an <lb/>amendment passed in 1949 by the Quebec legislature to the Early <lb/>Closing Act of that province and the subsequent Montreal by-law <lb/>which required the closing on specified Catholic Feast-days, of all <lb/>retail stores in the city. The real purpose of the legislation, the <lb/>Court held, was not to provide additional holidays for retail employees <lb/>under section 92 (13), (15) or (16), but to enforce observance of <lb/>days because of their religious significance. The legislation, being <lb/>analogous to Sunday observance laws, was competent only to the <lb/>Parliament of Canada under section 91(27), &quot;Criminal Law&quot;, in the <lb/>opinions of Kerwin, C.J.C., Fauteux, Taschereau, Estey, Cartwright, <lb/>and Abbott JJ. <lb/>The case is a reminder of the unsettled state of the law as to the <lb/>seat of legislative power relating to aspects of religion other than <lb/>Sunday observance. Rand J., referring to his reasons in Saumur, <lb/>expressed the opinion that the legislation related to religion and there-<lb/>fore was beyond provincial competence. Kellock and Locke JJ. agreed <lb/>that the legislation was analogous to Sunday observance legislation, <lb/>which had always been part of the criminal law, but also saw the <lb/>by-law as legislation respecting freedom of religion as dealt with by <lb/>earlier statutes. This case then goes some way towards making <lb/>religious freedom a separate head immune to provincial interference; <lb/>further inferences are less compelling. <lb/>(3) Freedom of the Person and Freedom of Association <lb/>A person cannot be detained or penalized for what he has said <lb/>on some vague ground that it is unwise in the public interest or <lb/>unfair generally. A charge must be laid alleging violation of a <lb/>specific law. Freedom of the person is secured in the same way. <lb/>The common law, supplemented by statute, defines the offences for <lb/>which a man may be convicted and &apos;imprisoned. The individual who <lb/>infringes none of these laws, enjoys freedom of person. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <listBibl>44 Ibid., and see Brewin: (1956), 34 Can. Bar Rev. 81; Castor: (1956), 14 <lb/>Fac. of L.R. 105. <lb/></listBibl>

	  <note place="headnote">[VOL. I <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>Anyone, however, may find himself arrested on suspicion of a <lb/>crime. But here the law provides limitations. The Petition of Right <lb/>in 1628 protects the person agalnst arbitrary arrest. In 1763 a series <lb/>of civil actions established the illegality of general warrants of <lb/>arrest. 4 5 The Criminal Code forbids a blank warrant and attempts to <lb/>avoid the abuse of the power of arrest and seizure. 46 If an arrested <lb/>person is not formally charged and tried speedily for some specific <lb/>offence, he can secure his release on habeas corpus. 47 <lb/>Another safeguard of personal freedom is the right to sue for <lb/>damages for assault, malicious prosecution and false imprisonment <lb/>when public officials exceed their lawful powers of arrest and deten-<lb/>tion The recent decision by the Supreme Court of Canada in Lamb <lb/>v. Benoit 48 affords an instance of judicial vigilance in protecting <lb/>freedom of the person. In this case, a Jehovah&apos;s Witness recovered <lb/>damages against the local police for false arrest, false imprisonment <lb/>and malicious prosecution. The appellant was charged with the <lb/>distribution of a publication alleged at the time to be seditious libel. <lb/>In the words of Rand J.: <lb/>The arrest and prosecution were quite without justification or excuse and <lb/>the detention. .. carried out in a manner and in conditions little short of <lb/>disgraceful...&quot; <lb/>The shocking aspect of this case was the attempt by the police <lb/>to force the appellant to sign a waiver of all claims for false arrest by <lb/>threatening to charge her with promulgation of a seditious libel. The <lb/>case exemplifies our dependence on the judiciary in protecting the <lb/>security of persons especially against the abuse of authority by public <lb/>officials. 4 9 Of special note was the court&apos;s obvious vigilance in <lb/>delineating the bounds of a police officer&apos;s authority to lay a criminal <lb/>information. The court was unable to agree that certain statutes <lb/>relied on by Benoit, a special constable of the Quebec Provincial <lb/>Police, could give umbrage where there is lack of &quot;good faith&quot; in <lb/>prosecuting. In the words of Locke J.: <lb/>&quot;The mere bona fide belief that he has power to do the act complained <lb/>of is not enough; he must believe in facts which give him the power if <lb/>they existed.... As to Benoit, without any lawful justification, he caused <lb/>the arrest and imprisonment of the appellant and was responsible for the <lb/>laying of the information and prosecution which followed. The appellant <lb/>was subjected to the ignominy of arrest and prosecution for the offence <lb/>of distributing a seditious libel, of which offence Benoit knew from the <lb/>outset she was innocent...&quot; <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>4 5 Leach v. Money (1765), 19 St. Tr. 1002; Wilkes v. Wood (1763), 19 St. <lb/>Tr. 1154. <lb/>46 1953-54, 2-3 Eliz. II, (Can.) ss. 429-445. <lb/>4 7 Habeas Corpus Acts: 1640, 16 Can. 1 c. 10; R.S.O., 1950, c. 163; R.S.N.B., <lb/>1952, c. 101; R.S.N.S., 1954, c. 1M7; R.S.P.E.I., 1951, c. 70; and Can. Cr. Code, <lb/>s. 680. <lb/>48 [1959] S.C.R. (this case is unreported at the time of writing, but <lb/>reasons for judgment were delivered in January 1959) and see also Kennedy <lb/>v. Tomlinson, an appeal concerning malicious prosecution of an alleged <lb/>vagrant, heard by the Ontario Court of Appeal on the 30th of March, 1959, <lb/>and as yet unreported). <lb/>4 9 See dicta of Boyd C. in Toothe v. Frederick, 14 P.R. 287. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">19591 <lb/></note>
	  
	  <page>32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/>[VOL. I <lb/></note>

			<body>Freedom of association lis a public right within the competence <lb/>of the federal parliament. By defining seditious conspiracies and <lb/>unlawful assemblies, the Criminal Code permits all other&apos; kinds of <lb/>associations which do not come within these restrictions. 50 Though <lb/>the provinces may validly enact legislation to regulate the use of <lb/>parks and public places under section 92(13) and (16) of the B.N.A. <lb/>Act, the extent of this power seems limited by the Criminal Code. <lb/>The power to declare an assembly unlawful could be abused but <lb/>there appear to be no cases on the relevant section -of the Code. 5 1 <lb/>Part If-The Proposed Bill of Rights <lb/>A. Federal Jurisdiction <lb/>The B.N.A. Acts do not contain a Bill of Rights as does the U.S. <lb/>constitution. To a large extent, the civil liberties outlined in Part I <lb/>above remain at the mercy of the appropiate legislature. Never-<lb/>theless some matters which have important implications for civil <lb/>liberties are guaranteed in the B.N.A. Act and are put beyond the <lb/>reach of either Dominion or provincial legislatures. The use of <lb/>English and French languages is guaranteed by section 133; the right <lb/>to separate schools by section 93; the right to a new parliament <lb/>every five years by section 50; the right to an annual session of <lb/>parliament by section 20; section 99 ensures security of tenure of <lb/>office for the judges of the Superior Courts in the province and thus <lb/>protects the right to an independent judiciary. <lb/>Since the proposed Bill of Rights was announced in September, <lb/>1958, many commentators have decried its utility as a mere statutory <lb/>enactment and have called for its incorporation into the B.N.A. Act. <lb/>Such an amendment would have the effect of making the prescribed <lb/>rights more secure against legislative repeal. Civil liberties so <lb/>entrenched would restrict the jurisdiction of legislatures and enable <lb/>the Courts to set aside subsequent statutes impinging thereon. How-<lb/>ever, we are confronted with a Bill of Rights which is a federal <lb/>statute settng out, like the English Bill of Rights of 1689, cardinal <lb/>rights and liberties of Canadian citizens. Instead of extolling the <lb/>value of a Bill of Rights as an amendment to the B.N.A. Act, it is <lb/>suggested that it is more useful if we recognize the proposed federal <lb/>enactment as a &quot;fait accompli&quot; and attempt to assess its constitutional <lb/>basis and the legal implications of some of its terms. This approach, <lb/>it is submitted, is more realistic in the light of the large majority <lb/>supporting the government proposing the Bill. <lb/>A Bill of Rights such as that proposed will not bind future parlia-<lb/>ments, although it will bind subsequent governments. It can be <lb/>amended or abrogated by a mere majority vote. Whether future <lb/>enactments could impliedly abridge or infringe any of the rights or <lb/>freedoms recognized dn Part 1 of the Bill is an open question. Section <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>50 Ss. 60 and 64. <lb/>51 See Ryan, More About a Bill of Rights (1958), 1 Can. Bar J. 74; and <lb/>Chaput v. Romain, [1955] S.C.R. 834. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>3 of the Bill directs that all future acts and regulations shall not be <lb/>so construed. In England, the power of a &apos;sovereign&apos; legislature to <lb/>repeal by implication any previously existing legislation has been <lb/>strongly relied upon as establishing the proposition that the courts <lb/>there could never inquire into the validity of an Act of Parliament <lb/>since the power of Parliament to amend both the substance of the <lb/>law and the manner of its working are uncircumscribed. The <lb/>significance of the power of implicit repeal may be illustrated by two <lb/>cases: Vauxhall Estates v. Liverpool Corporation 52 and Ellen Street <lb/>Estates v. Minister of Healt. 53 In the latter, Maugham L.J. refers <lb/>to the constitutional position that Parliament can alter an Act <lb/>previously passed, and dt can do so by repealing in express terms the <lb/>previous Act, and it can do so in another way, &quot;namely by enacting <lb/>a provision which is clearly inconsistent wvith the previous Act.&quot; <lb/>Maughan L.J. concluded: <lb/>&quot;The legislature cannot, according to our constitution, bind itself as to <lb/>the form of subsequent legislation, and it is impossible for Parliament to <lb/>enact that in a subsequent statute dealing with the same subject matter <lb/>there can be no implied repeal. If in a subsequent Act, Parliament <lb/>chooses to make plain that the earlier statute is being to some extent <lb/>repealed, effect must be given to that intention just because it is the <lb/>will of the legislature.&quot; <lb/>The language of Maugham L.J. is emphatic but how far do these <lb/>propositions extend? If the federal Bill of Rights is based on a valid <lb/>constitutional basis, according to the propositions laid down by <lb/>Maugham L.J., valid subsequent federal legislation could impliedly <lb/>repeal the rights protected by the Bill of Rights.M <lb/>The real strength of the Bill aside from a valid constitutional <lb/>basis, resides in the solemnity of the occasion on which it is adopted <lb/>and the symbolic nature of its provisions. This is the touchstone <lb/>which will guide judicial interpretation and give effect to section 3. <lb/>In the Nova Scotia Delegation 55 case, Rand J. observed that the <lb/>delegation of power over federal subject matters to provincial legis-<lb/>lators, though not an absolute transfer of power, might prove <lb/>impossible to revoke if people get used to having it exercised by <lb/>provincial legislators, as the power may vest in the form of a consti-<lb/>tutional convention. This vesting argument of Mr. Justice Rand&apos;s <lb/>might work in favour of the Bill of Rights, so that future Parliaments <lb/>would hesitate to expressly repeal any of its provisions and the courts <lb/>would be reluctant to construe subsequent legislation as impliedly <lb/>repealing any of the terms of the Bill of Rights. <lb/>In Part I of this article an attempt was made to trace the protec-<lb/>tions afforded civil liberties and to locate their constitutional basis. <lb/>By analysis of the cases on freedom of speech, press and religion, it <lb/>was seen that the Courts tend to reject provincial infringements of <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>52 [1932J 1 K.B. 733. <lb/>53 [1934] 1 K.B. 590. <lb/>54See Marshall, Parliamentary Sovereignty And The Commonwealth <lb/>(1957), p. 35. <lb/>55A.G. Nova Scotia v. A.G. of Canada, [1950] 4 D.L.R. 369 at p. 387. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>basic liberties but only impliedly place their constitutional basis in the <lb/>Dominion. Dicta of the Supreme Court have been interpreted in <lb/>some quarters as establishing that an implied bill of rights has been <lb/>written into the B.N.A. Act in such a way as to be beyond the reach <lb/>of both the Dominion and provinces. <lb/>What should concern us here is the area of federal jurisdiction <lb/>over the proposed Bill. To put the question another way, are the <lb/>liberties enumerated in Part I of the Bill within the exclusive domain <lb/>of Parliament or of the provinces? The B.N.A. Act distributes <lb/>legislative authority between the federal and provincial governments; <lb/>it allocates all powers of government to one or other of the authorities. <lb/>As Lord Loreburn has said: <lb/>&quot;there can be no doubt that under this organic instrument the power <lb/>distributed between the Dominion on the one hand, and the provinces on <lb/>the other covers the whole area of self-government within ... Canada. <lb/>It should be subversive of the entire scheme and policy of the Act to <lb/>assume that any point of internal self-government was withheld from <lb/>Canada.&quot;56 <lb/>Therefore, since there are no legislative powers denied to the <lb/>Dominion and provincial governments, there can be no forbidden <lb/>powers such as civil liberties and no implied bill of rights beyond <lb/>the competence of both the Dominion and provinces. <lb/>The usual method of locating the constitutional basis of challenged <lb/>legislation is to inquire whether it falls within any of the heads of <lb/>section 92 of the B.N.A. Act. If it does not, it is exclusively federal <lb/>under the general and residuary powers in section 91. If the impugned <lb/>law also falls within section 92, we must apply certain canons of <lb/>interpretation. We may be able to apply the rule of mutual modifica-<lb/>tion; 57 or seek the leading feature of the challenged law. 58 If we <lb/>cannot find a leading feature, and the Dominion and provinces <lb/>legislate on the same matter under different aspects, there being an <lb/>inconsistency, the Dominion&apos;s power prevails under the general power <lb/>to make laws &quot;for the peace, order and good government of Canada.&quot; 59 <lb/>It should be noted that in this dual aspect situation the mere fact <lb/>the Dominion does not legislate, the provincial legislation is not ipso <lb/>facto, intra vires as it can be overriden by the Dominion. 60 With <lb/>these rules of interpretation in mind, we can now consider whether <lb/>the federal Parliament has jurisdiction to enact a statute dealing <lb/>with fundamental freedoms and human rights under the peace order <lb/>and good government clause of section 91 of the B.N.A. Act. <lb/>The civil liberties of Part I of the proposed bill are, it is submitted, <lb/>the public rights of all Canadian citizens. They should not be <lb/>characterized under the private law concepts of property and civil <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>56A.G. Ont. v. A.G. Canada, [19121 A.C. 571 (P.C.) at p. 581. <lb/>57 Citizen&apos;s Insurance v. Parsons (1881), App. Cas. 96 (P.C.). <lb/>58 Union Colliery v. Bryden, [18991 A.C. 580 (P.C.). <lb/>59 A. G. Ont. v. A.G. Can., [18941 A.C. 189. <lb/>6 OSee especially, Kennedy, The Interpretation of the British North <lb/>America Act (1943), 8 Camb. L.J. 146; MacDonald, The Canadian Constitution <lb/>Seventy Years After (1937), 15 Can. Bar Rev. 401. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">[VOL. I <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>rights or as matters of merely local or private importance to the <lb/>province. Taken in their broad sense, as public rights, they are not <lb/>obviously related directly to any single specific head of section 91. <lb/>They, therefore, belong to the Parliament of Canada, to which is <lb/>assigned the general and residuary power to make laws for the peace, <lb/>order and good government of Canada on all subjects not exclusively <lb/>assigned to the provinces. 61 <lb/>Even if this submission were entirely acceptable, we would still <lb/>be faced with the somewhat empty facade of the residuary power. 6 2 <lb/>Judicial interpretations from 1896 to 1946 have reduced the residuary <lb/>clause significantly. From 1867 to 1896 the Privy Council construed <lb/>parliament&apos;s powers broadly, giving full value to the general power. 63 <lb/>From 1896 judicial interpretation worked a contraction of these <lb/>powers in defence to the provincial powers in section 92.64 Under <lb/>the &quot;emergency&quot; doctrine propounded by Lord Chancellor Haldane, <lb/>the Dominion&apos;s general power could be used only in periods of national <lb/>emergency such as war. 6 5 <lb/>Recent cases, however, indicate that the federal general power <lb/>may be expanding. In A.-G. Ont. vu. Canada Temperance Federation, <lb/>Lord Simon found the test of the scope of the general power: <lb/>&quot;to be in the real subject matter of the legislation: if it is such that it <lb/>goes beyond local or provincial concern or interests and must from its <lb/>inherent nature be the concern of the Dominion as a whole.., then it <lb/>will fall within the competence of the Dominion Parliament as a matter <lb/>affecting the peace, order and good government of Canada, though it <lb/>may in another aspect touch upon matters specially reserved to the <lb/>Provincial Legislatures.&quot;66 <lb/>This, of course, is a return to the Russell test. It should be remem-<lb/>bered, nevertheless, that Lord Simon&apos;s &quot;inherent nature&quot; test was <lb/>partially curtailed by the Margarine Case. 67 In that case, Lord <lb/>Morton held that Lord Simon&apos;s test must be considered in the light <lb/>of Lord Atkin&apos;s observations in the Labour Conventions case, so that <lb/>abnormal circumstances are required for the federal general power <lb/>to justify overriding head 13 of section 92. Lord Morton&apos;s remarks <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>61 See Laskin, Peace, Order and Good Government Re-examined (1947), <lb/>25 Can. Bar Rev. 1054; Laskin (1957), 35 Can. Bar Rev. 101. <lb/>62 MacDonald, The Privy Council and the Canadian Constitution (1951), <lb/>29 Can. Bar Rev. 1021; Laskin, The Supreme Court of Canada: A Final Court <lb/>of and for Canadians (1951), 29 Can. Bar Rev. 1038. <lb/>63 Russell v. The Queen (1882), 7 App. Cas. 829 at p. 839, per Sir Montague <lb/>E. Smith: &quot;Few, if any, laws could be made by parliament for the peace, <lb/>order and good government of Canada which did not in some incidental way <lb/>affect property and civil rights; and it could not have been intended, when <lb/>assuring to the provinces exclusive legislative authority on the subjects of <lb/>property and civil rights, to exclude the parliament from the exercise of this <lb/>general power whenever any such incidental interference would result from it. <lb/>64 See A.G. Ont. v. A.G. Can., [18963 A.C. 348, 359-61 (P.C.); In Re Board <lb/>of Commerce Act, [1922] 1 A.C. 191 (P.C.); Toronto Electric Commissioners V. <lb/>Snider, [19253 A.C. 396 (P.C.); Co-operative Committee on Japanese Canadians <lb/>v. Canada, [1947] A.C. 87 (P.C.). <lb/>65 In Re Board of Commerce Act, [1922] 1 A.C. 191 (P.C.); Toronto Elec-<lb/>trio Commission v. Snider, [1925] A.C. 396 (P.C.). <lb/>66 [1946] A.C. 193 (P.C.). <lb/>67 Reference re Validity of Section 5(a) of the Dairy Industry Act, [19513 <lb/>A.C. 179. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">19591 <lb/>OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>may be taken, then, as a caveat against too liberal an approach to <lb/>what is of national concern. <lb/>It is noteworthy that the Supreme Court of Canada, in the first <lb/>major decision on this problem after the abolition of appeals to the <lb/>Privy Council, followed Lord Simon&apos;s &quot;inherent nature&quot; test in the <lb/>Johannesson case, 68 instead of the Watson-Haldane-Duff approach <lb/>developed in the Local Prohibition case, the Snider case, the Natural <lb/>Products case, and the Margarine case. And even more recently a <lb/>judge of the Ontario High Court of Justice in Pronto Uranium Mines <lb/>v. O.L.R.B., expliditly chose to rely on the Canada Temperance test <lb/>which might indicate that the &quot;peace, order and good government&quot; <lb/>clause of section 91 is only a &quot;sleeping giant.&quot; These recent cases <lb/>provide ample justification for what easily could (and should) be <lb/>an expansion of the federal power to include the proposed Bill of <lb/>Rights. What could be, by its very nature, of greater concern to <lb/>the Dominion as a whole than the protection of those liberties which <lb/>are the primary condition of social life, thought and communication? <lb/>B. An Interpretation of Some of the Terms of the Bill of Rights <lb/>In Part I of this article, cases pertaining to freedom of speech, <lb/>press, association, religion and person were analyzed to locate their <lb/>constitutional basis. Despite varying opinions, one conclusion can <lb/>reasonably be deduced: all leading dicta place jurisdiction over civil <lb/>liberties beyond the competence of the provinces. These cases will <lb/>be highly persuasive in future judicial interpretations of civil liberties <lb/>as modified in section 2 of -the Bill of Rights. <lb/>Future difficulties, however, Will be met in the interpretation of <lb/>other sections and terms of the Bill. This is especially true of section <lb/>2(a) and (b): <lb/>&quot;2. It is hereby recognized and declared that in Canada there have <lb/>always existed, and shall continue to exist, the following human rights <lb/>and fundamental freedoms; namely, <lb/>(a) The right of the individual to life, liberty, security of the person and <lb/>enjoyment of property, and the right not to be deprived thereof <lb/>except by due process of law. <lb/>(b) The right of the individual to the protection of the law without <lb/>discrimination by reason of race, national origin, colour, religion or <lb/>sex;&quot; <lb/>Fortunately, many of these terms are similar to those used in the <lb/>U.S. Bill of Rights. Assistance, therefore, may be derived for future <lb/>Canadian interpretation from the U.S. case law, especially with regard <lb/>to the phrases &quot;due process of law&quot; and &quot;protection of the law... <lb/>without discrimination.&quot; <lb/>(1) Due Process of Law <lb/>(a) Historical Origins. <lb/>The phrase &quot;due process of law&quot; comes from an early Edward <lb/>II statute, reading as follows: <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>68 Johannesson v. West St. PauW, [19521 S.C.R. 292. <lb/>69 [1956) 5 D.L.R. (2nd) 342. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">(VOL. I <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>&quot;No man of what state or condition he be, shall be put out of his lands <lb/>or tenements, nor taken, nor imprisoned, nor disinherited, nor put to <lb/>death, without he brought to answer by due process of law.&quot; 70 <lb/>This statute in turn relates back to the famous chapter 39 of the <lb/>Magna Carta: <lb/>&quot;No freedman shall be captured or imprisoned or disseised or outlawed <lb/>or exiled or in any way destroyed, nor will we go against him or send <lb/>against him, except by lawful judgment of his peers or by the law of <lb/>the land.&quot; 71 <lb/>The important phrase in chapter 39 ds &quot;by the law of the land&quot;, <lb/>which is made by Coke synonymous with the latin phrase, &quot;by due <lb/>process of law&quot;; and that in turn Coke equates to &quot;due process of the <lb/>Common law&quot;, that is, &quot;the indictment or presentment of good and <lb/>lawful men . . . or writ original of the common law.&quot; Historical <lb/>evidence, however, shows that Coke did not regard &quot;the law of the <lb/>land&quot;, as he defined it, as beyond the power of parliamentary altera-<lb/>tion. 7 2 Nor did the early colonial constitutions after 1776, in which <lb/>the phrase &quot;law of the land&quot; applies, import any limitation on legis-<lb/>lative power. 73 <lb/>&quot;Law of the Land&quot; and &quot;Due Process of Law&quot;, however, derive <lb/>their contemporary importance from their character as restrictions <lb/>upon legislation in general. This function is significant in U.S. con-<lb/>stitutional law because of the sweeping powers of judicial review <lb/>exercised by the Supreme Court. <lb/>(b) U.S. JudiciaZ Interpretation. <lb/>The phrase &quot;due process of law&quot; has had a chequered history in <lb/>U.S. judicial interpretation. It appears in the federal Constitution in <lb/>two separate amendments. The first ten amendments embodying the <lb/>Bill of Rights were intended to curb all branches of the federal <lb/>Government in the fields touched by the amendments-Legislative, <lb/>Executive, and Judicial. The Fifth, Sixth, and Eighth Amendments <lb/>were pointedly aimed at confining the exerdise of power by courts <lb/>and judges within precise boundaries, particularly in the procedure <lb/>used for trial of criminal cases. The Fifth amendment required <lb/>indictment by Grand Jury in many criminal trials, prohibits double <lb/>jeopardy, self-incrimination, deprivation of life, liberty or property <lb/>without due process of law or the taking of property for public use <lb/>without just compensation. Fears of arbitrary court action sprang <lb/>largely from the past use of courts in the imposition of criminal <lb/>punishments to suppress speech, press, and religion. Hence the con-<lb/>stitutional limitations of court powers were essential supplements to <lb/>the First Amendment which was itself designed to ensure the widest <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>70 28 Edw. IT, c. 3. <lb/>71 See McKechnie, Magna Carta (2nd rev. ed. 1914) at p. 28. <lb/>7 2 Inst. II, 50-1; and see generally Jenks, The Myth of Magna Carta <lb/>(1904), Indep. Rev. 206; Selected Essays on Constitutional Law (1938), at p. <lb/>174. <lb/>7 3 Thorpe, American Charters. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>scope for all people to believe and to express the most divergent <lb/>political, religious and other views. 74 <lb/>But these limitations were not expressly imposed upon state court <lb/>action. In 1833, Barron v. Baltimore,7 5 held that the first eight <lb/>amendments did not apply to the states. This was the controlling <lb/>constitutional rule when the Fourteenth Amendment was proposed <lb/>in 1866. The avowed purpose of that amendment was to make <lb/>negroes citizens with full and equal rights as citizens despite the <lb/>prior decision in Scott v. Sandford. 7 6 Some, however, feel that one <lb/>of the chief objects of the provisions of the Amendment&apos;s first section, <lb/>separately or as a whole, was to make the Bill of Rights applicable <lb/>to the states. 7 7 <lb/>On the whole, interpretations of the phrases &quot;due process of Law&quot; <lb/>or &quot;the law of the land&quot; prior to 1870 placed few restrictions on the <lb/>legislatures which were not merely procedural in character. The <lb/>federal courts were seldom called on to protect either personal <lb/>privileges or property rights under the Fifth Amendment. And when <lb/>such an attempt was made it usually resulted in failure for the <lb/>litigant. <lb/>78 <lb/>When the Fourteenth Amendment was adopted in 1868, with <lb/>the proviso that no one shall &quot;deprive any persons of life, liberty <lb/>or property without due process of law; nor deny to any person within <lb/>its jurisdiction the equal protection of the laws&quot;, a problem of con-<lb/>stitutional interpretation arose. The states feared this amendment <lb/>would subordinate them increasingly to federal authority. When the <lb/>Slaughter-House 7 9 cases came before the Supreme Court, it being <lb/>decided that the amendment was designed primarily to protect the <lb/>negro, a strong dissent by Field J. avowed that the Amendment was <lb/>to &quot;protect the citizens of the United States against the deprivation <lb/>of their common rights by state legislation.&quot; This dissent prompted <lb/>counsel in later cases to urge that the new Amendments were intended <lb/>to place the whole jurisprudence of the country under the protection <lb/>of the Supreme Court. 8 0 Due process, applied in England as a guard <lb/>against executive usurpation, became in the U.S., a defense against <lb/>arbitrary legislation.81 Soon the prohibition against arbitrary acts <lb/>as a part of Due Process, was applied to many types of state legis-<lb/>lative and administrative acts. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>74See generally Selected Essays on Constitutional Law (1938), vol. I at <lb/>pp. 174-206. <lb/>75 (1883), 7 Pet. 243. <lb/>76 (1957), 19 How. 393. <lb/>7 7 See Black J. (dissenting) in Adamson v. California (1947), 332 U.S. <lb/>46; . . . stating that the historical purpose of the Fourteenth Amendment <lb/>never received full consideration and he proceeds to make applicable fully <lb/>the Fifth Amendment and all the privileges of the Bill of Rights under the <lb/>aegis of the due process of law clause of the Fourteenth Amendment. <lb/>78 See Murray&apos;s Lessee v. Haboker Land &amp; Improvement (1855), 18 How. <lb/>272, but see also Hurtado v. California (1884), 110 U.S. 516. <lb/>79 (1873), 16 Wall 36 at p. 39; and see also Corwin (1909), 7 Mich. L. Rev. <lb/>643. <lb/>80 Murdock v. Memphis (1899), 20 Wall 590. <lb/>s1 Hurtado v. California, ante. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">(VOL.. I <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>This marked a complete departure from the Slaughter-House <lb/>philosophy of judicial tolerance of State regulation of business activity <lb/>by the use of an expanded meaning of &quot;due process&quot; in the Fourteenth <lb/>Amendment as a protection from state infringement of individual <lb/>liberties of the Bill of Rights. 8 2 The Twining v. New Jersey 8 3 <lb/>decision, rejecting the compelled testimony clause of the Fifth <lb/>Amendment, was the end result of this new interpretation. This <lb/>case went so far as to declare that the &quot;privileges or immunities&quot; <lb/>clause of the Fourteenth Amendment did not forbid the states to <lb/>abridge the rights enumerated in the first Eight Amendments. 8 4 <lb/>Later decisions have undermined this interpretation which broadly <lb/>precluded reliance on the Bill of Rights to determine what is and <lb/>what is not a &quot;fundamental&quot; right. For, despite Hurtado and <lb/>Twining, the Supreme Court has held that the Fourteenth Amend-<lb/>ment operates to protect from state invasion certain fundamental <lb/>rights safeguarded by the Bill of Rights. <lb/>(c) Recent Trends in the Interpretation of Due Process and <lb/>Their Applicability to Canada. <lb/>Turning now to the further developments under the Fourteenth <lb/>Amendment, attention is drawn to the unsuccessful effort on the <lb/>part of a minority of the Court in 1947 to reconsider the fundamental <lb/>rights interpretation of the Due Process Clause and to equate the <lb/>Fourteenth Amendment with the specific limitations of the Bill of <lb/>Rights. In Adamson v. California, 5 the majority affirmed Twining <lb/>v. New Jersey S6 to the extent that privilege against self-incrimination <lb/>was not included among the basic freedoms protected by the due <lb/>process clause. Mr. Justice Black (with whom Douglas J. concurred <lb/>completely, and Murphy and Rutledge JJ. concurred partly), <lb/>vehemently attacked the use of the natural law formula as the basis <lb/>of Due Process of Law. He characterized the natural law approach <lb/>as an &quot;incongruous excrescence&quot; upon the Constitution, and invoked <lb/>historical sources to support his proposition that the original intention <lb/>of the Fourteenth Amendment was to make the Bill of Rights appli-<lb/>cable to the states. He objects to the fundamental rights approach on <lb/>the basis that it emphasises &quot;judicial subjectivity&quot; in creating rights <lb/>not explicit in the Constitution and often permits the disregard of <lb/>limitations which should be emphasized. <lb/>Mr. Justice Frankfurter, of the majority, interprets the Due <lb/>Process clause of the Fifth Amendment independently of the Four-<lb/>teenth in relation to the federal government. By invoking the <lb/>Fourteenth Amendment, the court must ascertain whether the pro-<lb/>ceedings offend those canons of decency and fairness which express <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>82 See Kauper, Frontiers of Constitutional Liberty, (University of Michi-<lb/>gan Thomas Cooley Lectures 1956) at p. 171; and Mendolsohn (1955), 41 <lb/>Va. L. Rev. 493. <lb/>83 (1908), 211 U.S. 78. <lb/>84 Ibid., at p. 83. <lb/>85 Ante footnote 77. <lb/>86 Ante footnote 83. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>the notions of justice of English speaking peoples. The importance <lb/>of this case for our purposes is that it represents an attempt to escape <lb/>from the static historical interpretation of Due Process in the <lb/>interests of broadening the bounds of personal security at the expense <lb/>of the state&apos;s power to define the procedure employed in its adminis-<lb/>tration of criminal justice. 8 7 <lb/>Looking at the cases and these didactic excerpts from the legal <lb/>history of the term &quot;due process of law&quot;, one might well ask just <lb/>what the term does mean, and how far its American meaning may <lb/>be applicable to the Canadian scene. Aside from the problem of <lb/>whether Due Process of Law meant the same thing for state and <lb/>federal actions, it is submitted that the term implies the individual&apos;s <lb/>protection from the state&apos;s coercive power unless the latter is exercised <lb/>in accordance with established usages and procedure. That process <lb/>was due process which conformed to procedures established by law. <lb/>Standing in the context of the limitations in the first ten Amendments, <lb/>the Due Process clause of the Fifth Amendment might fairly be <lb/>expressed as meaning that all proceedings which threaten vital <lb/>interests, whether criminal or civil in character, shall conform to <lb/>procedures established by law, whether by constitution, statute or <lb/>decision, as distinguished from arbitrary assertions of power by <lb/>governmental offidials. The freezing of the due process concept of <lb/>the Fourteenth Amendment has to some extent stultified its growth <lb/>and oriented its meaning towards the broadly conceived &quot;fair trial&quot; <lb/>standard. Due Process of Law requires a proceeding under authority <lb/>of a general law, &quot;a law which hears before it condemns, which <lb/>proceeds upon inquiry, and renders judgment only after trial.&quot; <lb/>From this brief summary, it should be clear that there are at <lb/>least two dangers inherent in the due process concept. One is that <lb/>Canadian courts should be careful not to equate political rights and <lb/>interests of corporate enterprise in being free from government <lb/>control of any kind, in the same way the U.S. Supreme Court did <lb/>under the so-called &quot;substantive due process.&quot; The second danger lies <lb/>in the fundamental rights approach of Mr. Justice Frankfurther in <lb/>the Adamson case with its emphasis on &quot;due process&quot; as a formula <lb/>concept which is both nebulous and subjective and disregards the <lb/>other important limitations explicitly set out in the proposed Bill of <lb/>Rights and in the Criminal Code. Of paramount importance, of <lb/>course, will be the use of this concept as a basis of review of decisions <lb/>of administrative tribunals in conjunction with section 3 (c) (d) and <lb/>(e) calling for a fair hearing in accordance with the principles of <lb/>fundamental justice. <lb/>(d) Due Process of Law and Parliamentary Privilege. <lb/>There have not been for many years problems concerning the <lb/>exercise of parliamentary privileges in this country. 8 8 It may be <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>87 See generally, Kauper, ante footnote 82. <lb/>88 See Ward, Called to the Bar of the House of Commons (1957), 35 Can. <lb/>Bar Rev. 529. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">[VOL. I <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>stated with substantial accuracy that, like the Imperial Parliament, <lb/>each House of the Parliament of Canada can now define its own <lb/>privileges, determine when they have been violated, and within <lb/>certain limits, what punishments shall be inflicted. With the <lb/>exercise of these powers the courts will not directly interfere. So, <lb/>while the writ of habeas corpus is always available to a person <lb/>imprisoned by either House, the courts uniformly remand the prisoner <lb/>to custody if the return shows he is held on the order of the House. <lb/>The ground of the committment will not be inquired into, and it was <lb/>held that the return need not state in what the contempt of the <lb/>House consisted. 8 9 <lb/>Each House claims to be the sole judge of its own privileges and <lb/>the courts recognize this as far as undoubted privileges are con-<lb/>cerned. 90 But there has been controversey between the courts and <lb/>parliament as to their respective functions in dealing with alleged <lb/>privileges. The courts have taken the view that parliament can judge <lb/>the breach, only if the privileges claimed have been found to exist <lb/>by the courts. Parliament has taken the view that the only function <lb/>of the courts is to help as occasion arises in carrying out the wishes of <lb/>Parliament. <lb/>During the Pipeline Debate in the House of Commons in 1956, the <lb/>Speaker entertained a motion that the writers of two letters to an <lb/>Ottawa newspaper, Eugene Forsey and Marjorie LeLacheur, had made <lb/>statements which were &quot;derogatory of the dignity of parliament and <lb/>deserve the censure of this House.&quot; 91 Although the Speaker sub-<lb/>sequently ruled that the statements were &quot;fair and reasonable com-<lb/>ment&quot;, a ruling today that the writers were in contempt of Parliament <lb/>and the issue of a Speaker&apos;s warrant for their committal until they <lb/>appeared before the Bar of the House of Commons would have raised <lb/>a nice constitutional question. If the Speaker&apos;s warrant showed cause, <lb/>the possibility of judicial review would exist. But if no cause were <lb/>shown, on the basis of the present law it is doubtful whether the <lb/>courts would be prepared to accept the warrant on an application for <lb/>habeas corpus. The nice question arises in the light of the &quot;due pro-<lb/>cess&quot; clause of section 2 of the new Bill of Rights: if it is held that <lb/>this phrase means determination by &quot;superior courts&quot; whenever an <lb/>individual is detained, the issue is settled. The writers would not have <lb/>to appear before the Bar of the House of Commons until the courts <lb/>had determined whether there had in fact been a breach of parliament-<lb/>ary privilege. <lb/>Of importance, however, is the U.S. experience in interpreting <lb/>&quot;due process of law.&quot; This experience may be highly persuasive for <lb/>Canadian judicial interpretation. Therefore, U.S. decisions that &quot;due <lb/>process of law&quot; does not necessarily mean, determination by a <lb/>&quot;superior&quot; court may prompt reliance on the historical origins of the <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>89 See (1925-26), 74 Penn. L. Rev. 691. <lb/>90 S toccda7e v. Hansard (1839), 9 A. &amp; E. 1; Sheriff of Middlesex&apos;s Case <lb/>(1840), 11 A. &amp; E. 273. <lb/>91 Canada, House of Commons Debates, 1956, pp. 4528-90. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">19591 <lb/>OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>phrase. Thus, according to the modes of procedure current in Eng-<lb/>land before the colonization of America, Parliament alone was judge <lb/>and jury. It should be remembered that, although the question of <lb/>parliamentary privilege has not arisen for several years, the frequent <lb/>use of parliamentary investigating committees such as the Accounts <lb/>Committee of 1958 will render the problem more important. Thus, if <lb/>the engineers or the Queen&apos;s Printer, Edmond Cloutier had failed to <lb/>appear when summoned before the Parliamentary Committee, or <lb/>having appeared proved unco-operative in answering questions, could <lb/>they be committed for contempt, without recourse to the courts first? <lb/>0. Section 2 (b) &quot; ... protection of the law without discrimination...&quot; <lb/>There is a striking similarity between section 2 (b) of the Bill of <lb/>Rights and the first section of the U.S. Fourteenth Amendment. The <lb/>phrase &quot;equal protection of the law&quot;, though not in the Fifth Amend-<lb/>ment, had early been interpreted as a requirement for legislative and <lb/>executive acts by certain state and federal courts prior to 1879.92 <lb/>But it was used without any clear purpose in the Fourteenth Amend-<lb/>ment so that there was little effort to apply its vague content to con-<lb/>crete cases. 93 Later, the equal protection clause was found to be a <lb/>supplement to what would otherwise have been construed together to <lb/>prevent all arbitrary legislative and administrative acts, and like <lb/>certain other implied limits on legislatures, the equal protection <lb/>principle was made and essential part of the concept of due process. 94 <lb/>It is suggested, however, that the phrase &quot;the right... to the <lb/>protection of the law without discrimination...&quot; -will provide a separ-<lb/>ate head of legislative authority embodying the protection of the <lb/>general rules governing Canadian citizens procedurally in court with-<lb/>out discrimination. In addition, it may be the means of prohibiting <lb/>discrimination on racial and religious grounds in employment prac-<lb/>tices, and in access to housing and places of public accommodation <lb/>just as the Fourteenth Amendment was used by the U.S. Supreme <lb/>Court to invalidate the segregation laws in the Southern states of the <lb/>U.S., requiring separate accommodation for negroes and the like. 9 5 <lb/>Although the federal Parliament has passed a Statute forbidding dis-<lb/>crimination against any person on the grounds of race, creed, colour, <lb/>nationality, ancestry, place of origin and sex, it is limited in its ap-<lb/>plication to employees under its jurisdiction. Therefore the practical <lb/>value of section 2 (b) of the proposed Bill of Rights will depend on the <lb/>constitutional basis of the statute in toto or in part. <lb/>In most fields, the subject of discrimination ostensibly comes <lb/>within the power of the provinces. Some provinces have passed acts <lb/>similar to the federal Fair Employment Practices Act. 96 The only <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>92 Holden v. James, 11 Mass. 396. <lb/>93 The Slaughter House Cases, ante at p 89. <lb/>94 Connolly &apos;v. Union Sewer Pipe do. 184 U.S. 540; Truax v. Corrigan, 257 <lb/>U.S. 312 at p. 322, per Taft C.J. <lb/>95See Brown v. Board of Education (1954), 347 U.S. 483; Bolling v. <lb/>Sharpe (1954), 347 U.S. 447. <lb/>96 (1952-53), 2-3 Eliz. II, (Can.) c. 19. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">[VOL. I <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>comprehensive statute is the Saskatchewan Bill of Rights At 97 <lb/>which prohibits discrimination &quot;because of race, creed, religion, colour <lb/>or ethnic or national origin&quot; in six areas-employment, carrying on <lb/>business, owning land, accommodations in public places, membership <lb/>in professional and trade organizations, and education. The Ontario <lb/>Fair Accommodations Practices Act forbids the denial &quot;to any person <lb/>of the accommodation services or facilities available in any place <lb/>to which the public is customarily admitted.&quot; 9 8 <lb/>Aside from the general consideration referred to earlier providing <lb/>for the constitutional basis of the Bill of Rights under the residuary <lb/>power of the federal parliament, section 2(b) may be specially pro-<lb/>tected by the heretofore undeveloped legislative head of &quot;rights of <lb/>citizenship.&quot; A separate status of citizenship was considered by Rand <lb/>J. in Winner v. S.M.T. (Eastern Ltd.), when he observed as obiter: <lb/>&quot;The first and fundamental characteristic of the constitutional act was <lb/>the creation of a single political organization of subjects of His Majesty <lb/>within the geographical area of the Dominion, the basic postulate of which <lb/>was the initiation of a Canadian citizenship. Citizenship is membership <lb/>in a state; and in the citizens inhere those rights and duties, the correla-<lb/>tives of allegiance and protection, which are basic to that status. <lb/>The British North America Act makes no express allocation of citizen-<lb/>ship as the subject-matter of legislation to either the Dominion or the <lb/>provinces; but as it lies at the foundations of the political organization <lb/>as its character is national, and by implication of head 25, section 91, <lb/>&quot;Naturalization and Aliens, it is to be found within the residual powers <lb/>of the Dominion:&quot; Canada Temperance case at p. 205. Whatever else <lb/>might have been said prior to 1913, the Statute of Westminister, coupled <lb/>with the declarations of constitutional relations of 1926, out of which it <lb/>issued, creating in substance a sovereignty, concludes the question.&quot; 9 9 <lb/>Then Rand J. expressed the opinion that &quot;a province cannot prevent a <lb/>Canadian from entering it except, conceivably, in temporary circum-<lb/>stances, for some local reason, as, for example, health.&apos; &apos;1 00 <lb/>In an excellent commentary 101 on the substantive implications of <lb/>Rand J.&apos;s Winner opinion, it is suggested that the reason for creating <lb/>a separate &quot;citizenship status&quot; was the desire to secure to civil <lb/>liberties &quot;an independent constitutional value&quot; &apos;1 02 in order to give an <lb/>&quot;appropriate constitutional form to matters which because of their <lb/>unique character have a unity of interest and significance, extending <lb/>equally to all parts of the Dominion. &apos; 10 3 Surely the right of the In-<lb/>dividual to the protection of the law without discrimination &quot;is a <lb/>matter which from its inherent nature&quot; is of concern to the Dominion <lb/>as a whole? If thIs is so, it is submitted that section 2(b) of Bill of <lb/>Rights will have an overriding effect on provincial enactments abridg-<lb/>ing or infringing it. This is true whether the section is characterized <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>97 1947, c. 35 (Sask.). <lb/>981954, c. 157 (Ont.); and see generally Bowker, Protection of Basic <lb/>Rights and Liberties (1954-7), 2 U.B.C. Legal Notes, 281 at 302. <lb/>99 [19511 S.C.R. 887 at pp. 918-9; and c.f. Reference re Alberta Statutes, <lb/>[19381 S.C.R. 100 at p. 149 per Cannon J. <lb/>100 Ibid., at p. 920. <lb/>101 Price, Mr. Justice Rand and Canadian Citizenship (1958), 16 Fac. of <lb/>L.R. 16; and see Roncarefli v. Duplessis, [1959] S.C.R. per Rand J. (unre-<lb/>ported as yet). <lb/>lo2 Ibid., at p. 20. <lb/>1 <lb/>0 3 Ibid., at p. 24. <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>separately as an incident of citizenship or on a broader application <lb/>under the residuary power of section 91 of the British North America <lb/>Act. <lb/>Laws against discrimination by private persons obviously create <lb/>extensive problems of enforcement. Even the most ardent advocates <lb/>of explicit protection for civil liberties are opposed to such laws on the <lb/>ground that prejudice and discrimination cannot be preirented by laws, <lb/>as morality cannot be legislated. One important consideration should <lb/>be pointed out. Civil liberties generally are negative in character, <lb/>aimed at securing freedom from something. Therefore, positive legi-<lb/>slation should first promote social justice by ensuring certain minima <lb/>of well-being below which people should not be allowed to fall. In <lb/>this way, racial and religious discrimination Will be mitigated by pro-<lb/>tecting the individual from outside restraints and at the same time <lb/>providing equality of opportunity.&apos; 0 4 <lb/>(3) Section 3 of the Bill of Bights <lb/>This section for the most part spells out the legal protections that <lb/>exist under the common law respecting arrest, trial and detention. 105 <lb/>Much of this part of the Bill of Rights is codified by the Criminal Code. <lb/>The salient features of the section are the provisions for the general <lb/>right to counsel in section 3 (b) (ii) and the right to counsel when <lb/>appearing before an administrative tribunal in section 3 (c). Although <lb/>the Criminal Code and the various voluntary legal aid systems enable <lb/>the indigent to be represented by counsel, this does not compel the <lb/>court to provide counsel. The Sixth Amendment of the U.S. Bill of <lb/>Rights enables the appointment of counsel for an accused in all federal <lb/>cases, capital cases in state courts and lesser state crimes. 1 06 In fact, <lb/>the right to aid of counsel in federal criminal proceedings under the <lb/>Sixth Amendment extends to every phase of appeal, including the pre-<lb/>liminary phase of obtaining permission to appeal. Perhaps section <lb/>3 (b) (Ii) will be interpreted so that our courts must provide counsel <lb/>in all criminal matters?1 07 <lb/>D. The Value of a Statutory Enactment on Civil Liberties <lb/>Part II of the Bill of Rights deals with civil liberties in the event <lb/>of &quot;real or apprehended war, invasion or insurrection.&quot; As it stands <lb/>now the War Measures&apos; 0 8 Act gives to the federal cabinet power to <lb/>authorize whatever may be thought necessary in the interests of <lb/>security. Among the powers specified are &quot;censorship and control <lb/>of publications and writing, communications&quot; and &quot;arrest, detention, <lb/>exclusion and deportation.&quot; All of this would be done by orders-in-<lb/>council with the force of law and if any of them were violated the <lb/>Cabinet could without reference to any court, prescribe its own penal-<lb/>ties up to five years or five thousand dollars, or both. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>104 For a survey of other discriminatory statutes, see Ryan, More About <lb/>a Bill of Rights (1958), 1 Can. Bar J. 74 at p. 75. <lb/>10 5 See generally, Bowker, ante at p. 313. <lb/>10 6 Anderson v. Heinze (1958), 258 F. 2d. 479. <lb/>107 For the protections under the Criminal Code, see Ryan, ante at p. 76. <lb/>108 R.S.C. c. 288. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">[VOL. I <lb/>Civil Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>Section 6 of the War Measures Act is to be repealed so that the <lb/>proclamation declaring a state of war can be debated and if both <lb/>Houses of Parliament resolve that the Proclamation be revoked the <lb/>Bill of Rights cannot be abrogated by the government. It seems to <lb/>me that these provisions might be inherently dangerous to their in-<lb/>fluence on civil liberties in time of peace. Implicit in section 6 is the <lb/>idea that the government can supervise the use of civil liberties. What <lb/>then is to prevent a government in time of peace from making other <lb/>insidious inroads on the use of civil liberties under the guise of <lb/>protective legislation. The essence of civil liberties is that govern-<lb/>ment agrees to keep its hands strictly off them-to preserve them <lb/>rather than supervise their use. While they must be reserved to <lb/>people, they cannot be left subject to the whims of majority opinion. <lb/>Individual rights can best be protected against the vagaries of public <lb/>opinion only through the courts. But in the light of the confused <lb/>judicial interpretation of the constitutional basis of civil liberties, <lb/>it is obvious that the courts themselves need guidance. The best form <lb/>for this to take is as a Bill of Rights imbedded in the Constitution and <lb/>thus made part of our national birth certificate. <lb/>Even if the Bill of Rights were specially buttressed as part of the <lb/>British North America Act, there are still those who would oppose <lb/>any codification of our fundamental freedoms. 09 It is better in Pro-<lb/>fessor Clokie&apos;s opinion to view civil liberty &quot;as flowing from numerous <lb/>aspects of a well-balanced constitutional system of government.&quot; In <lb/>his view &quot;it is also better to have parliament draft appropriate laws <lb/>now, even if misconceived and ill-judged, and establish the requisite <lb/>procedural machinery, no matter how defective, than have these in-<lb/>troduced, as they have been and will be in a haphazard, hasty and <lb/>perhaps violent manner when necessity requires their speedy adoption. <lb/>This is the way of constitutional wisdom and the guarantee of the con-<lb/>tinuance of our liberties.&quot;&quot; 0 <lb/>Implicit in these observations is the feeling that the only effective <lb/>guarantee of freedom is a vigilant public opinion. For that reason, so <lb/>the argument runs, civil liberties are better protected in Britain than <lb/>in the United States. It should be remembered, however, that Canada <lb/>and the United States lack the homogeneity and traditions of the <lb/>British people. The existence of a federal system makes the situation <lb/>more complex, especially in Canada where it is still uncertain what the <lb/>distribution of legislative power is between the federal and provincial <lb/>governments in respect to our baic freedoms. Although civil liberties <lb/>have been traditionally better guarded in Britain, it is also true that <lb/>civil liberties would have suffered severer abridgment in the United <lb/>States,&quot; without Bills of Rights in the federal and state constitutions. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>109 McD. Clokie, The Preservation of Civil Liberties (1947), 12 Can. J. <lb/>Ec. Pol. Sci. at p. 394. <lb/>10McD. Clokie, Emergency Powers and Civil Liberties (1947), 13 Can. <lb/>J. Ec. Pol. Sci. 334 at p. 394. <lb/>II See generally, Corry Democratic Government and Politics (1952), and <lb/>McCloskey, Essays in Constitutional Law (1957). <lb/></listBibl>

	<note place="headnote">19591 <lb/>OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

			<body>The prime advantage of a written Bill of Rights is its educational <lb/>value. This is especially true in a young country like Canada to <lb/>which are gravitating large numbers &apos;of persons of diverse origins and <lb/>of little or no tradition of effective civil liberties. A Charter of basic <lb/>liberties would be useful in teaching mutual respect and tolerance. In <lb/>this regard, the proposed Bill of Rights is open to criticism. If a <lb/>Charter of Liberties is to be of truly educational value, its language <lb/>should be simple yet imaginative. It should contain salient phrases <lb/>which are easily comprehended and catch the imagination of young <lb/>and old alike. Unfortunately, the proposed Bill falls short of this ideal. <lb/>It is set out like an elaborate blueprint, lacking even a decent preamble. <lb/>This is one area where amendments might improve the language of <lb/>the Bill and thus enhance its educational value. In addition, surely <lb/>both the educational value and practical value of the proposed statute <lb/>would have been greater if provision for some sort of sanctions had <lb/>been made. Personal remedies in the form of injunctions and damages <lb/>would certainly not be out of place. Finally, the content of the Bill <lb/>might be criticized for its failure to take note of the change, in most <lb/>Western countries, from laissez-faire to a more collectivist organiza-<lb/>tion of society based on the principles of the Welfare State. 1 -2 This <lb/>omission is even more shameful when one remembers that Canada <lb/>was a signatory to the United Nation&apos;s Declaration of Human Rights. <lb/>Actual protection of civil liberties in practice is essentially a <lb/>judicial function. To often basic values are lost sight of by the courts <lb/>in their reliance on Austinian formalism and the canons of constitu-<lb/>tional interpretation. Codification of fundamental freedoms would <lb/>render the necessary recognition, provided it is in its proper con-<lb/>stitutional form, of those &quot;preferred freedoms&quot; which are necessary <lb/>for the working of the &quot;body politic of the Dominion.&quot; 3 Large policy <lb/>considerations confront the Supreme Court, particularly in the dis-<lb/>charge of its task to protect the fundamental rights of the individual. <lb/>For this reason, the Supreme Court if it is to maintain its role in a <lb/>democratic society, cannot divorce itself from the climate of thinking <lb/>that determines the trends in Canadian political, social and economic <lb/>life, although the Court itself is an important influence on these trends. <lb/>The Supreme Court is now in a favourable position since the final <lb/>abolition of the appeal from Canadian courts to the Privy Council to <lb/>reappraise the hierarchy of constitutional values by departing from <lb/>formalistic doctrinal concepts embodied in prior decisions especially <lb/>in the field of public law. 11 4 The court has open to it a variety of <lb/>means to care for those interests which in its opinion demand special <lb/>judicial protection. Surely those &quot;preferred freedoms&quot; enumerated <lb/>in the proposed Bill are worthy of the vigilant protection of the <lb/>Supreme Court, especially if they are violated by those provinces <lb/>which have in the past done so much to undermine civil liberties. <lb/>If the proposed Bill is questioned either in part or in toto would this <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>12See McWhinney, A Bill of Rights (1958), 5 McGill L.J. 36 at p. 46. <lb/>113 Saumur v. The City of Quebec, ante, at p. 386. <lb/>11 4 See generally McWhinney, Judicial Review In the English Speaking <lb/>World (1956), chapter 1. <lb/>N.B. This article was completed before the March, 1959, issue of the <lb/>Can. Bar Rev. was available. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  should be <note place="headnote">[VOL. I <lb/>CiviZ Liberties and the Canadian Constitution <lb/></note>

			<body>not be a splendid opportunity for the Supreme Court of Canada to <lb/>ensure a uniform standard of freedom to all by upholding the Bill of <lb/>Rights as a valid federal enactment? It is in the area of Public law, <lb/>then, that judicial determination of the interests to be served and the <lb/>objectives to be attained can play its paramount role. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <div type="annex">APPENDIX &quot;&apos;A&quot; <lb/>BILL 0-60 <lb/>An Act for the Recognition and Protection of Human Rights and <lb/>Fundamental Freedoms. <lb/>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and <lb/>House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows: <lb/>PART I <lb/>BILL OF RIGHTS <lb/>1. This Part may be cited as the Canadian Bill of Rights. <lb/>2. It is hereby recognized and declared that in Canada there <lb/>have always existed and shall continue to exist the following human <lb/>rights and fundamental freedoms, namely, <lb/>(a) the right of the individual to life, liberty, security of the <lb/>person and enjoyment of property, and the right not to be <lb/>deprived thereof except by due process of law; <lb/>(b) the right of the individual to protection of the law without <lb/>discrimination by reason of race, national origin, colour, <lb/>religion or sex; <lb/>(c) freedom of religion; <lb/>(d) freedom of speech; <lb/>(f) freedom of assembly and association; and <lb/>(f) freedom of the press. <lb/>3. All the Acts of the Parliament of Canada enacted before or <lb/>after the commencement of this Part, all orders, rules and regulations <lb/>thereunder, and all laws in force in Canada or in any part of Canada <lb/>at the commencement of this Part that are subject to be repealed, <lb/>abolished or altered by the Parliament of Canada, shall be so con-<lb/>strued and applied as not to abrogate, abridge or infringe or to author-<lb/>ize the abrogation, abridgement or infringement of any of the rights <lb/>or freedoms recognized by this Part, and, without limiting the gener-<lb/>ality of the foregoing, no such Act, order, rule, regulation or law <lb/>shall be construed or applied so as to, <lb/>(a) impose or authorize the imposition of torture, or cruel, in-<lb/>human or degrading treatment or punishment; <lb/>(b) deprive a person who has been arrested or detained <lb/></div>

	<note place="headnote">1959] <lb/>OSGOODE HALL LAW JOURNAL <lb/></note>

	<div type="annex">(i) of the right to be informed promptly of the reason for <lb/>his arrest or detention, <lb/>(ii) of the right to retain and instruct counsel without <lb/>delay, or <lb/>(iii) of the remedy by way of habeas corpus for the deter-<lb/>mination of the validity of his detention and for his <lb/>release if the detention is not lawful; <lb/>(c) authorize a court, tribunal, commission, board or other <lb/>authority to compel a person to give evidence if he is denied <lb/>counsel or other constitutional safeguards; <lb/>(d) deprive a person of the right to a fair hearing in accordance <lb/>with the principles of fundamental justice for the determina-<lb/>tion of his rights and obligations; or <lb/>(e) deprive a person of the right to a fair and public hearing by <lb/>an independent and impartial tribunal for the determination <lb/>of any criminal charge against him. <lb/>4. The Minister of Justice shall, in accordance with such regula-<lb/>tions as may be prescribed by the Governor in Council, examine every <lb/>proposed regulation submitted in draft form to the Clerk of the Privy <lb/>Council pursuant to the Regulations Act and every Bill introduced in <lb/>the House of Commons, to ensure that the purposes and provisions of <lb/>this Part in relation thereto are fully carried out. <lb/>PART II <lb/>5. Nothing in Part I shall be construed to abrogate or abridge <lb/>any human right or fundamental freedom not enumerated therein <lb/>that may have existed in Canada at the commencement of this Act. <lb/>6. Section 6 of the War Measures Act is repealed and the follow-<lb/>ing substituted therefor: <lb/>&quot;6.(1) Sections 3, 4 ai~d 5 shall come into force only upon the issue <lb/>of a proclamation of the Governor in Council declaring that war, In-<lb/>vasion or insurrection, real or apprehended, exists. <lb/>(2) A proclamation declaring that war, invasion or insurrection, real <lb/>or apprehended, exists shall be laid before Parliament forthwith after Its <lb/>issue, or, if Parliament is then not sitting, within the first fifteen days <lb/>next thereafter that Parliament is sitting. <lb/>(3) Where a proclamation has been laid before Parliament pursuant <lb/>to subsection (2), a notice of motion in either House signed by ten mem-<lb/>bers thereof and made in accordance with the rules of that House within <lb/>ten days of the day the proclamation was laid before Parliament, praying <lb/>that the proclamation be revoked, shall be debated in that House at the <lb/>first convenient opportunity within the four sitting days next after the <lb/>day the motion in that House was made. <lb/>(4) If both Houses of Parliament resolve that the proclamation be <lb/>revoked, it shall cease to have effect, and sections 3, 4 and 5 shall cease <lb/>to be in force until those sections are again brought into force by a <lb/>further proclamation but without prejudice to the previous operation of <lb/>those sections or anything duly done or suffered thereunder or any offence <lb/>committed or any penalty or forfeiture or punishment incurred <lb/>(5) Any act or thing done or authorized or any order or regulation <lb/>made under the authority of this Act, shall be deemed not to be an abro-<lb/>gation, abridgement or infringement of any right or freedom recognized <lb/>by the Canadian Bill of Rights.&quot; <lb/>Section 6 of the War Measures Act now reads as follows: <lb/>&quot;6. The provisions of the three sections last preceding shall only be <lb/>in force during war, invasion, or insurrection, real or apprehended.&quot; <lb/></div>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">[VOL. I </note>


	</text>

</TEI>